<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39289443</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>17</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>20</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2045-2322</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>14</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>17</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Scientific reports</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Sci Rep</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Faster ciguatoxin extraction methods for toxicity screening.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>21715</StartPage><MedlinePgn>21715</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">21715</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1038/s41598-024-72708-1</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Ciguatera poisoning (CP) is a severe global public health problem caused by the consumption of seafood products contaminated with ciguatoxins (CTXs). The growing demand for seafood products requires high-throughput testing for CTX-susceptible seafood, however complex extraction and slow cleanup methods inhibit this goal. Herein, several methods for extracting CTXs from fish tissue were established and compared; these methods are sensitive, specific, and valid while achieving higher sample extraction throughput than currently established protocols. The trial fish material was generated from multiple species, with different physical conditions (wet and freeze-dried tissue), and naturally contaminated with various CTXs (i.e., CTX-1B, CTX-3C, and C-CTX-1), thus ensuring these methods are robust and broadly applicable. The extraction methods used were based on mechanical maceration with acetone or methanol or enzymatic digestion followed by acetone and ethyl acetate extraction. Crude extracts were investigated for CTX-like toxicity using an in vitro mouse neuroblastoma (N2a) cell-based assay (CBA). Among the three methods, there was no significant difference in toxin estimates (p = 0.219, two-way ANOVA), indicating their interchangeability. For speed (&gt; 16 samples/day), accuracy (100%), and CTX analog retention confirmation by liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry (LC‒MS/MS), the preferred extraction methods were both methanol and enzyme-based. All extraction methods post hoc confirmation of CTX analogs successfully met international seafood market-based CTX contaminant guidance. These methods can drastically increase global CTX screening capabilities and subsequently relieve sample processing bottlenecks, inhibiting environmental and human health-based CTX analysis.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Loeffler</LastName><ForeName>Christopher R</ForeName><Initials>CR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Safety in the Food Chain, National Reference Laboratory for the Monitoring of Marine Biotoxins, German Federal Institute for Risk Assessment, Max-Dohrn-Str. 8-10, 10589, Berlin, Germany. Christopher.loeffler@bfr.bund.de.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Spielmeyer</LastName><ForeName>Astrid</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Safety in the Food Chain, National Reference Laboratory for the Monitoring of Marine Biotoxins, German Federal Institute for Risk Assessment, Max-Dohrn-Str. 8-10, 10589, Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Sci Rep</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101563288</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2045-2322</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>11050-21-8</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D002922">Ciguatoxins</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002922" MajorTopicYN="Y">Ciguatoxins</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000633" MajorTopicYN="N">toxicity</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017747" MajorTopicYN="N">Seafood</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D036841" MajorTopicYN="N">Ciguatera Poisoning</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005399" MajorTopicYN="N">Fishes</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D051379" MajorTopicYN="N">Mice</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D053719" MajorTopicYN="N">Tandem Mass Spectrometry</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D045744" MajorTopicYN="N">Cell Line, Tumor</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018675" MajorTopicYN="N">Toxicity Tests</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">(max. 6, American spelling): marine biotoxins</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Ciguatera</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Extraction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Fish poisoning</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mass spectrometry</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Neuro-2a bioassay</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>32</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39289443</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11408646</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-72708-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1038/s41598-024-72708-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>FAO and WHO. Report of the expert meeting on ciguatera poisoning. Rome, 19–23 November 2018 Food Safety and Quality No. 9. Rome. 10.4060/ca8817en (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larsson, M. E., Laczka, O. F., Suthers, I. M., Ajani, P. A. &amp; Doblin, M. A. Hitchhiking in the east Australian current: Rafting as a dispersal mechanism for harmful epibenthic dinoflagellates. Mar. Ecol. Prog. Ser.596, 49–60 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Masó, M., Garcés, E., Pagès, F. &amp; Camp, J. Drifting plastic debris as a potential vector for dispersing Harmful Algal Bloom (HAB) species. Scientia Mar.67, 107–111 (2003).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loeffler, C. R., Spielmeyer, A., Blaschke, V., Bodi, D. &amp; Kappenstein, O. Ciguatera poisoning in Europe: A traceback to Indian ocean sourced snapper fish (Lutjanus bohar). Food Control151, 109799. 10.1016/j.foodcont.2023.109799 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loeffler, C. R. et al. Food safety risk in Germany from mislabeled imported fish: Ciguatera outbreak trace-back, toxin elucidation, and public health implications. Front. Mar. Sci.10.3389/fmars.2022.849857 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kusche, H. &amp; Hanel, R. Consumers of mislabeled tropical fish exhibit increased risks of ciguatera intoxication: A report on substitution patterns in fish imported at Frankfurt Airport, Germany. Food Control121, 107647. 10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107647 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Friedemann, M. Ciguatera fish poisoning outbreaks from 2012 to 2017 in Germany caused by snappers from India, Indonesia, and Vietnam. J. Consum. Prot. Food Saf.14, 71–80. 10.1007/s00003-018-1191-8 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Epelboin, L. et al. Two clusters of ciguatera fish poisoning in Paris, France, related to tropical fish imported from the French Caribbean by Travelers. J. Travel Med.21, 397–402. 10.1111/jtm.12161 (2014).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25345983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loeffler, C. R. et al. Ciguatoxin prevalence in 4 commercial fish species along an oceanic exposure gradient in the US Virgin Islands. Environ. Toxicol. Chem.37, 1852–1863. 10.1002/etc.4137 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29710376</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loeffler, C. R. et al. Ciguatoxin in Hawai’i: Fisheries forecasting using geospatial and environmental analyses for the invasive Cephalopholis argus (Epinephelidae). Environ. Res.207, 112164. 10.1016/j.envres.2021.112164 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34627798</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yogi, K. et al. LC-MS/MS analysis of ciguatoxins revealing distinct regional and species characteristics in fish and causative alga from the Pacific. Anal. Chem.83, 8886–8891. 10.1021/ac200799j (2011).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22010820</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chinain, M., Gatti, C. M., i., Darius, H. T., Quod, J. P. &amp; Tester, P. A. Ciguatera poisonings: A global review of occurrences and trends. Harmful Algae10.1016/j.hal.2020.101873 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33875186</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holmes, M. J., Venables, B. &amp; Lewis, R. J. Critical review and conceptual and quantitative models for the transfer and depuration of ciguatoxins in fishes. Toxins13, 515 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8402393</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34437386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramos-Sosa, M. J. et al. Ciguatoxin detection in flesh and liver of relevant fish species from the Canary Islands. Toxins14, 46 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8781511</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35051023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oshiro, N. et al. Characteristic distribution of ciguatoxins in the edible parts of a grouper, Variola louti. Toxins13, 218 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8002984</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33803043</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clausing, R. J. et al. Tissue distribution and metabolization of ciguatoxins in an herbivorous fish following experimental dietary exposure to gambierdiscus polynesiensis. Mar. Drugs22, 14 (2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10817614</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38248639</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Colman, J. R., Dechraoui, M. Y. B., Dickey, R. W. &amp; Ramsdell, J. S. Characterization of the developmental toxicity of Caribbean ciguatoxins in finfish embryos. Toxicon Off. J. Int. Soc. Toxinol.44, 59–66. 10.1016/j.toxicon.2004.04.007 (2004).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15225563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>US Food and Drug Administration. Fish and Fishery Products Hazards and Controls Guidance (June 2022 Edition) (Food and Drug Administration, Center for Food Safety and Applied Nutrition, Office of Seafood, 2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Isabel Falcón Garcia. Control of ciguatera poisoning in Canary Islands, Spain. https://climate-adapt.eea.europa.eu/en/metadata/case-studies/control-of-ciguatera-poisoning-in-canary-islands-spain/#legal_aspects (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morihara, C. et al. Clinicoepidemiological profile of ciguatera cardiotoxicity: A systematic review. Am. J. Trop. Med. Hyg.10.4269/ajtmh.24-0207 (2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11376153</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38981507</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Varela Martínez, C. et al. Incidence and epidemiological characteristics of ciguatera cases in Europe. EFSA Support. Publ.18, 6650E. 10.2903/sp.efsa.2021.EN-6650 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Friedman, M. A. et al. An updated review of ciguatera fish poisoning: Clinical, epidemiological, environmental, and public health management. Mar. Drugs15, 72. 10.3390/md15030072 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5367029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28335428</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chinain, M., Gatti, C., Darius, H., Quod, J. P. &amp; Tester, P. Ciguatera poisonings: A global review of occurrences and trends. Harmful Algae102, 101873 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33875186</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Skinner, M. P., Brewer, T. D., Johnstone, R., Fleming, L. E. &amp; Lewis, R. J. Ciguatera fish poisoning in the Pacific Islands (1998 to 2008). PLoS Negl. Trop. Dis.5, e1416. 10.1371/journal.pntd.0001416 (2011).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3236724</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22180797</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soliño, L. &amp; Costa, P. R. Global impact of ciguatoxins and ciguatera fish poisoning on fish, fisheries and consumers. Environ. Res.182, 109111 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31927300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Canals, A. et al. Risk characterisation of ciguatera poisoning in Europe. EFSA Support. Publ.18, 6647E. 10.2903/sp.efsa.2021.EN-6647 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dickey, R. W. Ciguatera Toxins: Chemistry, Toxicology, and Detection 2nd edn, 479–500 (CRC Press, 2008).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lewis, R. J. et al. Purification and characterization of ciguatoxins from Moray eel (Lycodontis javanicus, Muraenidae). Toxicon29, 1115–1127. 10.1016/0041-0101(91)90209-A (1991).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1665604</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campàs, M. et al. A smartphone-controlled amperometric immunosensor for the detection of Pacific ciguatoxins in fish. Food Chem.374, 131687. 10.1016/j.foodchem.2021.131687 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34891085</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hardison, D. R. et al. Fluorescent receptor binding assay for detecting ciguatoxins in Fish. PLoS ONE11, e0153348. 10.1371/journal.pone.0153348 (2016).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4830512</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27073998</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Inserra, M., Lavrukhina, Y., Jones, A., Lewis, J. &amp; Vetter, I. Ciguatoxin detection methods and high-throughput assays. Anal. Food Toxins Toxic. 469–488 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loeffler, C. R., Handy, S. M., Quintana, F. &amp; Deeds, J. R. Fish hybridization leads to uncertainty regarding ciguatera fish poisoning risk: Confirmation of hybridization and ciguatoxin accumulation with implications for stakeholders. J. Mar. Sci. Eng.7, 105 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abraham, A., Jester, E. L. E., Granade, H. R., Plakas, S. M. &amp; Dickey, R. W. Caribbean ciguatoxin profile in raw and cooked fish implicated in ciguatera. Food Chem.131, 192–198. 10.1016/j.foodchem.2011.08.059 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan, T. Y. K. Regional variations in the risk and severity of ciguatera caused by eating Moray Eels. Toxins (Basel). 10.3390/toxins9070201 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5535148</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28672845</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dao, H. V. et al. Ciguatoxin in moray eels raising the risk for seafood safety in Viet Nam. Fish. Sci.88, 821–830. 10.1007/s12562-022-01638-6 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barrett, K. A., Nakao, J. H., Taylor, E. V., Eggers, C. &amp; Gould, L. H. Fish-associated foodborne disease outbreaks: United States, 1998–2015. Foodborne Pathog. Dis.14, 537–543. 10.1089/fpd.2017.2286 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28682115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perkins, R. A. &amp; Morgan, S. S. Poisoning, envenomation, and trauma from marine creatures. Am. Fam. Physician69, 885–890 (2004).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14989575</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Estevez, P. et al. Implementation of liquid chromatography tandem mass spectrometry for the analysis of ciguatera fish poisoning in contaminated fish samples from Atlantic coasts. Food Chem.280, 8–14. 10.1016/j.foodchem.2018.12.038 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30642510</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Darius, H. T. et al. Evaluating age and growth relationship to ciguatoxicity in five coral reef fish species from French Polynesia. Mar. Drugs20, 251 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9027493</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35447924</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oshiro, N. et al. Ciguatera incidence and fish toxicity in Okinawa, Japan. Toxicon56, 656–661. 10.1016/j.toxicon.2009.05.036 (2010).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19520098</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dickey, R. W., Plakas, S. M. &amp; Ciguatera,. A public health perspective. Toxicon56, 123–136. 10.1016/j.toxicon.2009.09.008 (2010).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19782098</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kilcoyne, J., Bogan, Y., Duffy, C. &amp; Hollowell, T. Reducing environmental impacts of marine biotoxin monitoring: A laboratory report. PLOS Sustain. Transform.1, e0000001. 10.1371/journal.pstr.0000001 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holmes, J. CCXXVII.: Contributions to the theory of solutions. The intermiscibility of liquids. J. Chem. Soc. Trans.103, 2147–2166 (1913).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Byrne, F. P. et al. Tools and techniques for solvent selection: Green solvent selection guides. Sustain. Chem. Process.4, 7. 10.1186/s40508-016-0051-z (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spielmeyer, A., Loeffler, C. R. &amp; Bodi, D. Extraction and LC–MS/MS analysis of ciguatoxins: A semi-targeted approach designed for fish of unknown origin. Toxins13, 630 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8473320</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34564634</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lewis, R. J., Yang, A. &amp; Jones, A. Rapid extraction combined with LC-tandem mass spectrometry (CREM-LC/MS/MS) for the determination of ciguatoxins in ciguateric fish flesh. Toxicon54, 62–66. 10.1016/j.toxicon.2009.03.013 (2009).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19303895</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manger, R. L. et al. Detection of sodium channel toxins: Directed cytotoxicity assays of purified ciguatoxins, brevetoxins, saxitoxins, and seafood extracts. J. AOAC Int.78, 521–527 (1995).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7756868</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oshiro, N. et al. LC–MS/MS analysis of ciguatoxins revealing the regional and species distinction of fish in the tropical Western Pacific. J. Mar. Sci. Eng.9, 299 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu, J. et al. The occurrence, distribution, and toxicity of high-risk ciguatera fish species (grouper and snapper) in Kiritimati Island and Marakei Island of the Republic of Kiribati. Toxins14, 208 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8952361</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35324705</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanchez-Henao, A. et al. Presence of CTXs in moray eels and dusky groupers in the marine environment of the Canary Islands. Aquat. Toxicol.221, 105427. 10.1016/j.aquatox.2020.105427 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32044545</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Darius, H. T. et al. Ciguatera risk assessment in two toxic sites of French Polynesia using the receptor-binding assay. Toxicon50, 612–626. 10.1016/j.toxicon.2007.05.007 (2007).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17631928</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nagae, M. et al. Development and validation of an LC–MS/MS method for the ultra-trace analysis of Pacific ciguatoxins in fish. J. AOAC Int.104, 1272–1281. 10.1093/jaoacint/qsab052 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8475085</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33831184</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caillaud, A. et al. Towards the standardisation of the neuroblastoma (neuro-2a) cell-based assay for ciguatoxin-like toxicity detection in fish: Application to fish caught in the Canary Islands. Food Addit. Contam. Part. A29, 1000–1010 (2012).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22394180</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castro, D., Manger, R., Vilariño, O. &amp; Gago-Martínez, A. Evaluation of matrix issues in the applicability of the neuro-2a cell based assay on the detection of CTX in fish samples. Toxins12, 308 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7290336</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32397386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loeffler, C. R., Bodi, D., Tartaglione, L., Dell’Aversano, C. &amp; Preiss-Weigert, A. Improving in vitro ciguatoxin and brevetoxin detection: Selecting neuroblastoma (Neuro-2a) cells with lower sensitivity to ouabain and veratridine (OV-LS). Harmful Algae103, 101994. 10.1016/j.hal.2021.101994 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33980434</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yasumoto, T. Chemistry, etiology, and food chain dynamics of marine toxins. Proc. Jpn. Acad. Ser. B81, 43–51 (2005).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oshiro, N. et al. Analytical studies on ciguateric fish in Okinawa, Japan (II): The grouper Variola albimarginata. J. Mar. Sci. Eng.11, 242 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oshiro, N. &amp; Association, J. F. H. Shigatera Doku (Ciguatera Poison). Shokuhin Eisei Kensa Shishin Rikagaku-Hen (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA. Scientific opinion on marine biotoxins in shellfish – Emerging toxins: Ciguatoxin group. EFSA J.8, 1627. 10.2903/j.efsa.2010.1627 (2010).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Regulation, E. C. No 853/2004. in Official Journal of the European Union. L 139/55 Vol. 47.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Regulation, E. C. No 627/2019. in 02019R0627 — EN — 01.01.2021–001.001 — 1 (ed Council of the European Union European Parlament).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yokozeki, T., Kawabata, M., Fujita, K., Hirama, M. &amp; Tsumuraya, T. Sensitive detection of ciguatoxins using a neuroblastoma cell-based assay with voltage-gated potassium channel inhibitors. Toxins16, 118 (2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10974581</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38535783</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spielmeyer, A., Blaschke, V. &amp; Loeffler, C. R. Fish extract fractionation by solid phase extraction: Investigating co-occurring ciguatoxins by LC–MS/MS and N2a-bioassay. Separations11, 238 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tartaglione, L. et al. Dereplication of gambierdiscus balechii extract by LC-HRMS and in vitro assay: First description of a putative ciguatoxin and confirmation of 44-methylgambierone. Chemosphere319, 137940. 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2023.137940 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36702405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meyer, L., Carter, S. &amp; Capper, A. An updated ciguatoxin extraction method and silica cleanup for use with HPLC–MS/MS for the analysis of P-CTX-1, PCTX-2 and P-CTX-3. Toxicon108, 249–256. 10.1016/j.toxicon.2015.10.021 (2015).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26541571</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Froese, R. &amp; Pauly, D. FishBase. http://www.fishbase.org (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dickey, R. W. in Seafood and Freshwater Toxins: Pharmacology, Physiology, and Detection, 2nd edn (ed. Botana, L. M.) 479–500 (CRC Press, 2008).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manger, R. L., Leja, L. S., Lee, S. Y., Hungerford, J. M. &amp; Wekell, M. M. Tetrazolium-based cell bioassay for neurotoxins active on voltage-sensitive sodium channels: Semiautomated assay for saxitoxins, brevetoxins, and ciguatoxins. Anal. Biochem.214, 190–194. 10.1006/abio.1993.1476 (1993).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8250223</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roué, M. et al. Evidence of the bioaccumulation of ciguatoxins in giant clams (Tridacna maxima) exposed to Gambierdiscus spp. cells. Harmful Algae57(Part A), 78–87. 10.1016/j.hal.2016.05.007 (2016).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30170724</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>