<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39288907</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>17</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1098-9064</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>17</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Seminars in thrombosis and hemostasis</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Semin Thromb Hemost</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Pharmacokinetic and Pharmacodynamic Interactions between Food or Herbal Products and Oral Anticoagulants: Evidence Review, Practical Recommendations, and Knowledge Gaps.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1055/s-0044-1790258</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Interactions between food and oral anticoagulants (OACs), particularly vitamin K antagonists such as warfarin, are widely recognized and may also be clinically relevant for direct OACs. Pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic interactions with food or herbs can lead to anticoagulation potentiation, increased risk of bleeding, or reduced drug efficacy, all compromising patient safety. We conducted a systematic search for randomized controlled trials (RCTs) on PubMed for assessments of interactions between OACs and various ingestants. Since the RCT evidence was slim, we also reviewed prospective longitudinal studies, case series, and case reports to identify possible associations between foods and anticoagulation therapy. We referred to basic or translational studies that shared putative explanations for such interactions, but we failed to identify high-quality evidence in most cases. The limited evidence, small sample size of the studies, conflicting results, and possible heterogeneity in the contents of herbal products prevent a conclusive assessment of these interactions. Existing evidence suggests that (1) cranberry juice consumption (up to 240 mL/d and probably even more) with warfarin is safe; (2) use of green leafy vegetables with a high daily content (more than 250 µg) of vitamin K should be cautioned for patients receiving warfarin, because it may decrease warfarin efficacy. It is also advisable for patients to maintain highly constant intake of green leafy vegetables to ensure stable warfarin effectiveness; (3) ginger, even in small quantities (excluding commercial ginger-flavored beverages, which contain only negligible amounts of ginger), and mango (more than one fruit) can both potentiate warfarin effects; (4) patients taking OACs should avoid St. John's wort due to diminished anticoagulant effect; and (5) consumption of less than 240 mL of grapefruit juice daily is unlikely to interact with OACs. Future longitudinal observational cohort studies and RCTs with larger sample sizes are needed to study specific interactions between food or herbal products and OACs.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Thieme. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Talasaz</LastName><ForeName>Azita H</ForeName><Initials>AH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy Practice, Arnold and Marie Schwartz College of Pharmacy and Health Sciences, Long Island University, New York, New York.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy, New York-Presbyterian Hospital/Columbia University Irving Medical Center, New York, New York.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacotherapy and Outcome Sciences, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Virginia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>McGonagle</LastName><ForeName>Bridget</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Thrombosis Research Group, Brigham and Women's Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Cardiovascular Medicine, Brigham and Women's Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>HajiQasemi</LastName><ForeName>Mohsen</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Medicine, Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ghelichkhan</LastName><ForeName>Zahra A</ForeName><Initials>ZA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Pharmacy, Urmia University of Medical Sciences, Urmia, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sadeghipour</LastName><ForeName>Parham</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Vascular Disease and Thrombosis Research Center, Rajaie Cardiovascular Medical and Research Institute, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rashedi</LastName><ForeName>Sina</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Thrombosis Research Group, Brigham and Women's Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cuker</LastName><ForeName>Adam</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine and Department of Pathology and Laboratory Medicine, Perelman School of Medicine, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lech</LastName><ForeName>Tara</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Cardiovascular Medicine, Department of Medicine, Lahey Hospital and Medical Center, Beth Israel Lahey Health, Burlington, Massachusetts.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Goldhaber</LastName><ForeName>Samuel Z</ForeName><Initials>SZ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Thrombosis Research Group, Brigham and Women's Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Cardiovascular Medicine, Brigham and Women's Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jennings</LastName><ForeName>Douglas L</ForeName><Initials>DL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy Practice, Arnold and Marie Schwartz College of Pharmacy and Health Sciences, Long Island University, New York, New York.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy, New York-Presbyterian Hospital/Columbia University Irving Medical Center, New York, New York.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Piazza</LastName><ForeName>Gregory</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Thrombosis Research Group, Brigham and Women's Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Cardiovascular Medicine, Brigham and Women's Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bikdeli</LastName><ForeName>Behnood</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Thrombosis Research Group, Brigham and Women's Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Cardiovascular Medicine, Brigham and Women's Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Yale New Haven Hospital/Yale Center for Outcomes Research and Evaluation, New Haven, Connecticut.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Semin Thromb Hemost</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0431155</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0094-6176</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CoiStatement>Outside the submitted work, A.C. has served as a consultant for MingSight, Pfizer, Sanofi, and Synergy and has received authorship royalties from UpToDate. G.P. received funding as Research Grants (paid to his institution from BMS/Pfizer, Janssen, Alexion, Bayer, Amgen, BSC, Esperion, 1R01HL164717-01) and has Advisory Roles in BSC, Amgen, BCRI, PERC, NAMSA, BMS, Janssen, Regeneron. Outside the submitted work, B.B. is supported by a Career Development Award from the American Heart Association and VIVA Physicians (#938814). B.B. was supported by the Scott Schoen and Nancy Adams IGNITE Award and is supported by the Mary Ann Tynan Research Scientist award from the Mary Horrigan Connors Center for Women's Health and Gender Biology at the Brigham and Women's Hospital, and the Heart and Vascular Center Junior Faculty Award from the Brigham and Women's Hospital. B.B. reports that he was a consulting expert, on behalf of the plaintiff, for litigation related to two specific brand models of inferior vena cava (IVC) filters. B.B. has not been involved in the litigation in 2022 to 2024 nor has he received any compensation in 2022 to 2024. B.B. reports that he is a member of the Medical Advisory Board for the North American Thrombosis Forum and serves in the Data Safety and Monitory Board of the NAIL-IT trial funded by the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, and Translational Sciences. B.B. is a collaborating consultant with the International Consulting Associates and the U.S. Food and Drug Administration in a study to generate knowledge about utilization, predictors, retrieval, and safety of IVC filters. B.B. receives compensation as an Associated Editor for the New England Journal of Medicine Journal Watch Cardiology, as an Associate Editor for Thrombosis Research, and as an Executive Associate Editor for JACC, and is a Section Editor for Thrombosis and Haemostasis (no compensation).</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39288907</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1055/s-0044-1790258</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>