<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39289791</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1750-3841</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>89</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of food science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Food Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The advantages and trends of lactic acid fermentation in the production of innovative fruit puree: Analysis with PROMETHEE and cluster.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>6481</StartPage><EndPage>6493</EndPage><MedlinePgn>6481-6493</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1750-3841.17344</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The goal of this study was to create a fermented probiotic fruit puree for lactose-intolerant people, vegetarians, and infants over 6 months old. Fermented fruit purees were developed using apples, peaches, and bananas with lactic acid bacteria (LAB) strains: Lactobacillus plantarum subsp. plantarum (S5), Lactobacillus fermentum strain w8 (S10), and Lactobacillus pentosus strain ml104 (S14). Different fruit puree formulations were produced using three strains, two inoculation ratios (4% and 5%), and two fermentation durations (24  and 48 h). The physicochemical parameters (pH, total soluble solids, and color), total phenols content (TPC), total antioxidant capacity, bacterial viability, volatile aroma profile (VAP), and individual phenolic compound profile of fruit puree fermented for both 24  and 48 h were compared with the unfermented (control) purees. The results of VAP were evaluated via PROMETHEE and cluster analysis. Time of fermentation and bacterial cultures at varied concentrations improved color values of samples (L*, a*, and b*) compared to controls. The level of bioactive compounds in several samples (S10 and S14) decreased after fermentation in contrast to S5 samples. The bacterial population in the samples ranged from ∼7.00 to 9.50 log CFU/g after 48-h fermentation. The fruit puree samples exhibited the presence of two different phenolic compounds and a total of 17 distinct volatile aroma compounds. The control sample scored highest for aromatic components in PROMETHEE, while S14-II was the most unique sample in cluster analysis. In conclusion, fermented probiotic fruit puree shown high promise as a carrier for live probiotics, and the fermentation process boosted the nutritional content of the fruit puree.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Journal of Food Science published by Wiley Periodicals LLC on behalf of Institute of Food Technologists.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ucak-Ozkaya</LastName><ForeName>Gulsum</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4207-6797</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Scientific Research Projects Coordination Unit, Mimar Sinan Art Fine University, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Food Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0014052</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-1147</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>33X04XA5AT</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D019344">Lactic Acid</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D010636">Phenols</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D055549">Volatile Organic Compounds</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000975">Antioxidants</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005285" MajorTopicYN="Y">Fermentation</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005638" MajorTopicYN="Y">Fruit</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019936" MajorTopicYN="Y">Probiotics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019344" MajorTopicYN="Y">Lactic Acid</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010636" MajorTopicYN="Y">Phenols</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055549" MajorTopicYN="N">Volatile Organic Compounds</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D048191" MajorTopicYN="N">Lactobacillus plantarum</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005516" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Microbiology</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000975" MajorTopicYN="N">Antioxidants</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016000" MajorTopicYN="N">Cluster Analysis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009812" MajorTopicYN="N">Odorants</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003116" MajorTopicYN="N">Color</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000074421" MajorTopicYN="N">Fermented Foods</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">PROMETHEE</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cluster analysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">fermentation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">fruit puree</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">probiotic</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>20</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39289791</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1750-3841.17344</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Akman, P. K., Ozulku, G., Tornuk, F., &amp; Yetim, H. (2021). Potential probiotic lactic acid bacteria isolated from fermented gilaburu and shalgam beverages. LWT‐Food Science and Technology, 149, 111705. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2021.111705</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alves, J. A., Lima, L. C. de. O., Dias, D. R., Nunes, C. A., &amp; Schwan, R. F. (2010). Effects of spontaneous and inoculated fermentation on the volatile profile of lychee (Litchi chinensis Sonn) fermented beverages. International Journal of Food Science &amp; Technology, 45(11), 2358–2365. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365‐2621.2010.02409.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Apak, R., Güçlü, K., Özyürek, M., &amp; Karademir, S. E. (2004). Novel total antioxidant capacity index for dietary polyphenols and vitamins C and E, using their cupric ion reducing capability in the presence of neocuproine: CUPRAC method. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 52(26), 7970–7981. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf048741x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azadnia, A. H., Ghadimi, P., &amp; Molani‐Aghdam, M. (2011). A hybrid model of data mining and MCDM methods for estimating customer lifetime value. In Proceedings of the 41st International Conference on Computers &amp; Industrial Engineering. pp: 44‐49 ISBN:9781627486835.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bagdat, E. S., Kutlu, G., &amp; Tornuk, F. (2024). The effect of free and encapsulated probiotic bacteria on some physicochemical, microbiological, and textural properties of apricot leather (pestil) during storage. Journal of Food Science, 89, 4688–4703. https://doi.org/10.1111/1750‐3841.17245</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Behzadian, M., Kazemzadeh, R. B., Albadvi, A., &amp; Aghdasi, M. (2010). PROMETHEE: A comprehensive literature review on methodologies and applications. European Journal of Operational Research, 200(1), 198–215. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejor.2009.01.021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brans, J.‐P., &amp; Vincke, P. (1985). Note—A preference ranking organisation method: (The PROMETHEE method for multiple criteria decision‐making). Management Science, 31(6), 647–656. https://doi.org/10.1287/mnsc.31.6.647</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, C., Lu, Y., Yu, H., Chen, Z., &amp; Tian, H. (2019). Influence of 4 lactic acid bacteria on the flavor profile of fermented apple juice. Food Bioscience, 27, 30–36. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fbio.2018.11.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cozzolino, D., Power, A., &amp; Chapman, J. (2019). Interpreting and reporting principal component analysis in food science analysis and beyond. Food Analytical Methods, 12, 2469–2473. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12161‐019‐01605‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Craig, W. J. (2009). Health effects of vegan diets. The American Journal of Clinical Nutrition, 89(5), S1627–S1633. https://doi.org/10.3945/ajcn.2009.26736N</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Assis, B. B. T., Pimentel, T. C., Dantas, A. M., dos Santos Lima, M., da Silva Campelo Borges, G., &amp; Magnani, M. (2021). Biotransformation of the Brazilian Caatinga fruit‐derived phenolics by Lactobacillus acidophilus La‐5 and Lacticaseibacillus casei 01 impacts bioaccessibility and antioxidant activity. Food Research International, 146, 110435. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2021.110435</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Souza, E. L., de Oliveira, K. Á. R., &amp; de Oliveira, M. E. G. (2022). Influence of lactic acid bacteria metabolites on physical and chemical food properties. Current Opinion in Food Science, 49, 100981. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cofs.2022.100981</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dhandevi, P., &amp; Jeewon, R. (2015). Fruit and vegetable intake: Benefits and progress of nutrition education interventions‐narrative review article. Iranian Journal of Public Health, 44(10), 1309.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Di Cagno, R., Filannino, P., Cavoski, I., Lanera, A., Mamdouh, B. M., &amp; Gobbetti, M. (2017). Bioprocessing technology to exploit organic palm date (Phoenix dactylifera L. cultivar Siwi) fruit as a functional dietary supplement. Journal of Functional Foods, 31, 9–19. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jff.2017.01.033</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding, W., &amp; Shah, N. P. (2008). Survival of free and microencapsulated probiotic bacteria in orange and apple juices. International Food Research Journal, 15(2), 219–232.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doriya, K., Kumar, D. S., &amp; Thorat, B. N. (2022). A systematic review on fruit‐based fermented foods as an approach to improve dietary diversity. Journal of Food Processing and Preservation, 46(11), e16994. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfpp.16994</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fellows, P. J. (2022). Food processing technology: Principles and practice. Woodhead Publishing.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Filannino, P., Azzi, L., Cavoski, I., Vincentini, O., Rizzello, C. G., Gobbetti, M., &amp; Di Cagno, R. (2013). Exploitation of the health‐promoting and sensory properties of organic pomegranate (Punica granatum L.) juice through lactic acid fermentation. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 163(2–3), 184–192. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2013.03.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Granato, D., Santos, J. S., Escher, G. B., Ferreira, B. L., &amp; Maggio, R. M. (2018). Use of principal component analysis (PCA) and hierarchical cluster analysis (HCA) for multivariate association between bioactive compounds and functional properties in foods: A critical perspective. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 72, 83–90. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2017.12.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hampton, J., Tang, C., Subhash, J. A., &amp; Serventi, L. (2021). Assessment of pear juice and puree as a fermentation matrix for water kefir. Journal of Food Processing and Preservation, 45(3), e15223. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfpp.15223</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Havermans, R. C., Rutten, G., &amp; Bartelet, D. (2021). Adolescent's willingness to adopt a more plant‐based diet: A theory‐based interview study. Frontiers in Nutrition, 8, 688131. https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2021.688131</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herigstad, B., Hamilton, M., &amp; Heersink, J. (2001). How to optimize the drop plate method for enumerating bacteria. Journal of Microbiological Methods, 44(2), 121–129. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0167‐7012(00)00241‐4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huss, L. R., Dean, J., Lamothe, L. M., Hamaker, B., Reuhs, B., Goran, M. I., &amp; Lê, K.‐A. (2022). Micronutrient profile and carbohydrate microstructure of commercially prepared and home prepared infant fruit and vegetable purees. Nutrients, 15(1), 45. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu15010045</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Inchingolo, F., Inchingolo, A. M., Latini, G., Ferrante, L., de Ruvo, E., Campanelli, M., Longo, M., Palermo, A., Inchingolo, A. D., &amp; Dipalma, G. (2024). Difference in the intestinal microbiota between breastfeed infants and infants fed with artificial milk: A systematic review. Pathogens, 13(7), 533. https://doi.org/10.3390/pathogens13070533</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keșa, A.‐L., Pop, C. R., Mudura, E., Salanță, L. C., Pasqualone, A., Dărab, C., Burja‐Udrea, C., Zhao, H., &amp; Coldea, T. E. (2021). Strategies to improve the potential functionality of fruit‐based fermented beverages. Plants, 10(11), 2263. https://doi.org/10.3390/plants10112263</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar, B. V., Sreedharamurthy, M., &amp; Reddy, O. V. S. (2013). Physico‐chemical analysis of fresh and fermented fruit juices probioticated with Lactobacillus casei. International Journal of Applied Sciences and Biotechnology, 1(3), 127–131. https://doi.org/10.3126/ijasbt.v1i3.8301</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>MacQueen, J. (1967). Some methods for classification and analysis of multivariate observations. In Proceedings of the fifth Berkeley symposium on mathematical statistics and probability.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mashitoa, F. M., Manhivi, V. E., Akinola, S. A., Garcia, C., Remize, F., Shoko, T., &amp; Sivakumar, D. (2021). Changes in phenolics and antioxidant capacity during fermentation and simulated in vitro digestion of mango puree fermented with different lactic acid bacteria. Journal of Food Processing and Preservation, 45(11), e15937. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfpp.15937</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mota‐Rojas, D., Whittaker, A. L., de la Vega, L. T., Ghezzi, M., Lezama‐García, K., Domínguez‐Oliva, A., Falcón, I., Casas‐Alvarado, A., &amp; Alonso‐Spilsbury, M. (2023). Veganism and animal welfare, scientific, ethical, and philosophical arguments. Journal of Animal Behaviour and Biometeorology, 11, e2023015. https://doi.org/10.31893/jabb.23015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muhialdin, B. J., Kadum, H., Zarei, M., &amp; Hussin, A. S. M. (2020). Effects of metabolite changes during lacto‐fermentation on the biological activity and consumer acceptability for dragon fruit juice. LWT‐Food Science and Technology, 121, 108992. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2019.108992</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen, B. T., Bujna, E., Fekete, N., Tran, A. T., Rezessy‐Szabo, J. M., Prasad, R., &amp; Nguyen, Q. D. (2019). Probiotic beverage from pineapple juice fermented with Lactobacillus and Bifidobacterium strains. Frontiers in Nutrition, 6, 54. https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2019.00054</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Organization, W. H. (2020). Healthy diet. https://www.who.int/news‐room/fact‐sheets/detail/healthy‐diet</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ozkaya, G., &amp; Demirhan, A. (2023). Analysis of countries in terms of artificial intelligence technologies: PROMETHEE and GAIA method approach. Sustainability, 15(5), 4604. https://doi.org/10.3390/su15054604</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ozkaya, G., Timor, M., &amp; Erdin, C. (2021). Science, technology and innovation policy indicators and comparisons of countries through a hybrid model of data mining and MCDM methods. Sustainability, 13(2), 694. https://doi.org/10.3390/su13020694</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paramithiotis, S. (2017). Lactic acid fermentation of fruits and vegetables. CRC press. https://doi.org/10.1201/9781315370378</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patra, J. K., Sahoo, S. K., &amp; Swain, M. R. (2017). Nutritional and antioxidant potential of Aegle marmelos fermented fruit juice. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, India Section B: Biological Sciences, 87, 769–775. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40011‐015‐0644‐4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rekhy, R., &amp; McConchie, R. (2014). Promoting consumption of fruit and vegetables for better health. Have campaigns delivered on the goals? Appetite, 79, 113–123. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.appet.2014.04.012</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sajjad, N., Rasool, A., Fazili, A. B. A., &amp; Eijaz Ahmed Bhat, E. (2020). Fermentation of fruits and vegetables. Plant Arch, 20, 1338–1342.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma, R., Garg, P., Kumar, P., Bhatia, S. K., &amp; Kulshrestha, S. (2020). Microbial fermentation and its role in quality improvement of fermented foods. Fermentation, 6(4), 106. https://doi.org/10.3390/fermentation6040106</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh, R., Chidambara Murthy, K., &amp; Jayaprakasha, G. (2002). Studies on the antioxidant activity of pomegranate (Punica granatum) peel and seed extracts using in vitro models. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 50(1), 81–86. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf010865b</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singleton, V. L., Orthofer, R., &amp; Lamuela‐Raventós, R. M. (1999). Analysis of total phenols and other oxidation substrates and antioxidants by means of folin‐ciocalteu reagent. Methods in Enzymology, 299, 152–178. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0076‐6879(99)99017‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sousa‐Gallagher, M., Tank, A., &amp; Sousa, R. (2016). Emerging technologies to extend the shelf life and stability of fruits and vegetables. In The stability and shelf life of food (pp. 399–430). Elsevier. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978‐0‐08‐100435‐7.00014‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Srisuvor, N., Chinprahast, N., Prakitchaiwattana, C., &amp; Subhimaros, S. (2013). Effects of inulin and polydextrose on physicochemical and sensory properties of low‐fat set yoghurt with probiotic‐cultured banana purée. LWT‐Food Science and Technology, 51(1), 30–36. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2012.10.018</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tamang, J. P., Shin, D.‐H., Jung, S.‐J., &amp; Chae, S.‐W. (2016). Functional properties of microorganisms in fermented foods. Frontiers in Microbiology, 7, 578. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2016.00578</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsen, J. H., Lin, Y. P., &amp; King, V. A. E. (2009). Response surface methodology optimisation of immobilised Lactobacillus acidophilus banana puree fermentation. International Journal of Food Science &amp; Technology, 44(1), 120–127. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365‐2621.2007.01681.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yahia, E. M., Maldonado Celis, M. E., &amp; Svendsen, M. (2017). The contribution of fruit and vegetable consumption to human health. Fruit and vegetable phytochemicals: Chemistry and human health (2nd Ed, pp. 1–52). John Wiley &amp; Sons https://doi.org/10.1002/9781119158042.ch1</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>