<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39280228</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>17</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2590-1575</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>23</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>30</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Food chemistry: X</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Food Chem X</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Structural characterization and antioxidant activities of polysaccharides extracted from Polygonati rhizoma pomace.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>101778</StartPage><MedlinePgn>101778</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">101778</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.fochx.2024.101778</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The present study aimed to prepare polysaccharides from the pomace of <i>Polygonatum</i> rhizome and characterize their structural features and biological activities. After hot water extraction and DEAE-52 cellulose fractionation, a neutral polysaccharide (PKP) was obtained with 91.85% sugars and 0.45% proteins. Structural characterization indicated that PKP contained a main fraction with a molecular weight of 4.634 × 10<sup>3</sup> Da and was composed of →1)-<i>β</i>-D-Fru<i>f</i>-(2→ and →6)-<i>β</i>-D-Fru<i>f</i>-(2→ residues. PKP was a semi-crystalline polymer, and the Congo red assay suggested the presence of triple-helix structure in PKP. PKP exhibited moderate radical scavenging activity (including 15.55% inhibition of DPPH, 21.48% inhibition of ABTS, and 22.52% inhibition of ·OH) and could effectively protect MRC-5 cells from H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced oxidative damage at 0.01 mg/mL through inhibiting apoptosis, decreasing SA-<i>β</i>-galactosidase activity, and downregulating the expression levels of p16 and p53. Therefore, PKP could be used in functional foods and pharmaceuticals as an antioxidant. This study provides an attractive method for utilizing polysaccharides from waste materials.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Published by Elsevier Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bu</LastName><ForeName>Yunke</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Agro-products Quality and Safety Control in Storage and Transport Process, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs/Institute of Food Science and Technology, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Beijing 100193, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Food Nutrition and Health in Universities of Shandong, College of Food Science and Engineering, Shandong Agricultural University, 61 Daizong Street, Tai'an, Shandong 271018, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yin</LastName><ForeName>Bangfeng</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Food Nutrition and Health in Universities of Shandong, College of Food Science and Engineering, Shandong Agricultural University, 61 Daizong Street, Tai'an, Shandong 271018, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Qiu</LastName><ForeName>Zhichang</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science, University of Massachusetts, Amherst, MA 01003, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Lingyu</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Food Nutrition and Health in Universities of Shandong, College of Food Science and Engineering, Shandong Agricultural University, 61 Daizong Street, Tai'an, Shandong 271018, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Bin</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Food Nutrition and Health in Universities of Shandong, College of Food Science and Engineering, Shandong Agricultural University, 61 Daizong Street, Tai'an, Shandong 271018, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zheng</LastName><ForeName>Zhenjia</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Food Nutrition and Health in Universities of Shandong, College of Food Science and Engineering, Shandong Agricultural University, 61 Daizong Street, Tai'an, Shandong 271018, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Minmin</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Agro-products Quality and Safety Control in Storage and Transport Process, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs/Institute of Food Science and Technology, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Beijing 100193, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Food Chem X</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101751436</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2590-1575</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Antioxidant activity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Polygonatum rhizome pomace</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Polysaccharide extraction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Structural characterization</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Waste valorization</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39280228</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11402156</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fochx.2024.101778</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2590-1575(24)00666-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Bai J.B., Ge J.C., Zhang W.J., Liu W., Luo J.P., Xu F.Q.…Xie S.Z. Physicochemical, morpho-structural, and biological characterization of polysaccharides from three Polygonatum spp. RSC Advances. 2021;11(60):37952–37965.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9044025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35498116</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bian Z., Li C., Peng D., Wang X., Zhu G. Use of steaming process to improve biochemical activity of Polygonatum sibiricum polysaccharides against D-galactose-induced memory impairment in mice. International Journal of Molecular Sciences. 2022;23(19):11220.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9570032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36232521</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen J., Cheong K.L., Song Z., Shi Y., Huang X. Structure and protective effect on UVB-induced keratinocyte damage of fructan from white garlic. Carbohydrate Polymers. 2013;92(1):200–205.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23218283</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du B., Nie S., Peng F., Yang Y., Xu B. A narrative review on conformational structure characterization of natural polysaccharides. Food Frontiers. 2022;3(4):631–640.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gu J., Zhang H., Yao H., Zhou J., Duan Y., Ma H. Comparison of characterization, antioxidant and immunological activities of three polysaccharides from Sagittaria sagittifolia L. Carbohydrate Polymers. 2020;235</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32122481</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han Q., Wu Z., Huang B., Sun L., Ding C., Yuan S.…Yuan M. Extraction, antioxidant and antibacterial activities of Broussonetia papyrifera fruits polysaccharides. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules. 2016;92:116–124.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27370746</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu Y., Tang Y., Zhang Z., Guo X., Wu Z., Li Z.…Li W. Recent advances in polysaccharides from the genus Polygonatum: Isolation, structures, bioactivities, and application. Food Hydrocolloids. 2023;140</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang S., Ma J., Li Y., Lu B., Du J., Xu J.…Dong C. A polysaccharide from native Curcuma kwangsiensis and its mechanism of reversing MDSC-induced suppressive function. Carbohydrate Polymers. 2022;297</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36184172</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li L., Qiu Z., Dong H., Ma C., Qiao Y., Zheng Z. Structural characterization and antioxidant activities of one neutral polysaccharide and three acid polysaccharides from the roots of Arctium lappa L.: A comparison. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules. 2021;182:187–196.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33836197</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li R., Tao A., Yang R., Fan M., Zhang X., Du Z.…Duan B. Structural characterization, hypoglycemic effects and antidiabetic mechanism of a novel polysaccharides from Polygonatum kingianum Coll. et Hemsl. Biomedicine &amp; Pharmacotherapy. 2020;131</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33152904</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu C., Qiu Z., Gu D., Wang F., Zhang R. A novel anti-inflammatory polysaccharide from blackened jujube: Structural features and protective effect on dextran sulfate sodium-induced colitic mice. Food Chemistry. 2023;405</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu D., Tang W., Huang X.J., Hu J.L., Wang J.Q., Yin J.Y.…Xie M.Y. Structural characteristic of pectin-glucuronoxylan complex from Dolichos lablab L. hull. Carbohydrate Polymers. 2022;298</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36241256</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y., Dong H., Sun-Waterhouse D., Li W., Zhang B., Yu J.…Zheng Z. Three anti-inflammatory polysaccharides from Lonicera japonica Thunb.: Insights into the structure-function relationships. Food Science and Human Wellness. 2023;13(4):2197–2207.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu X. Changes in the structure of polysaccharides under different extraction methods. eFood. 2023;4(2):1–7. e82.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nam S., French A.D., Condon B.D., Concha M. Segal crystallinity index revisited by the simulation of X-ray diffraction patterns of cotton cellulose Iβ and cellulose II. Carbohydrate Polymers. 2016;135:1–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26453844</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan M., Wu Y., Sun C., Ma H., Ye X., Li X. Polygonati Rhizoma: A review on the extraction, purification, structural characterization, biosynthesis of the main secondary metabolites and anti-aging effects. Journal of Ethnopharmacology. 2024;327</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38437890</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qi X., Sun X., Wang M., Wang M., Qi Z., Cui C. Ginseng polysaccharides ameliorate abnormal lipid metabolism caused by acute alcoholic liver injury by promoting autophagy. Food Frontiers. 2023;4(1):394–406.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qi Y., Qiu Z., Li L., Zhao R., Xiang L., Gong X.…Qiao X. Developing garlic polysaccharide-Fe (III) complexes using garlic pomace to provide enhanced iron-supplementing activity in vivo. Food Chemistry. 2024;437</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37922796</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiu Z., Li L., Du H., Chen H., Chen G., Zheng Z., Xiao H. Physicochemical, structural, and functional properties of fructans from single-clove garlic and multiclove garlic: A comparison. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry. 2024;72(14):7818–7831.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38466922</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiu Z., Li L., Zhu W., Qiao X., Zheng Z., Sun-Waterhouse D. Pectins rich in RG-I and galactose extracted from garlic pomace: Physicochemical, structural, emulsifying and antioxidant properties. Food Hydrocolloids. 2024;149</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11311835</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39123530</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiu Z., Qiao Y., Zhang B., Sun-Waterhouse D., Zheng Z. Bioactive polysaccharides and oligosaccharides from garlic (Allium sativum L.): Production, physicochemical and biological properties, and structure-function relationships. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety. 2022;21(4):3033–3095.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35765769</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sha A., Liu Y., Qiu X., Xiong B. Polysaccharide from Paris polyphylla improves learning and memory ability in D-galactose-induced aging model mice based on antioxidation, p19/p53/p21, and Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathways. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules. 2023;251</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37579895</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen L., Fan L., Luo H., Li W., Cao S., Yu S. Cow placenta extract ameliorates d-galactose-induced liver damage by regulating BAX/CASP3 and p53/p21/p16 pathways. Journal of Ethnopharmacology. 2024;323</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38171467</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song S., Qiu Z., Sun-Waterhouse D., Bai X., Xiang L., Zheng Z., Qiao X. Garlic polysaccharide-Cr (III) complexes with enhanced in vitro and in vivo hypoglycemic activities. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules. 2023;237</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36990417</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang W., Li M., Ritzoulis C., Liu Y., Ding Y., Liu W., Liu J. Chemical and thermodynamic characterization of antioxidant emulsifiers: The case of complex of sodium caseinate with EGCG. Food Frontiers. 2023;4(3):1382–1394.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang S., Li G., Zhang X., Wang Y., Qiang Y., Wang B.…Wang Z. Structural characterization and antioxidant activity of Polygonatum sibiricum polysaccharides. Carbohydrate Polymers. 2022;291</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35698327</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu Y., Ye Y., Liu C., Chen B., Ji J., Sun J.…Sun X. Positive effects of steamed Polygonatum sibiricum polysaccharides including a glucofructan on fatty acids and intestinal microflora. Food Chemistry. 2023;402</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36126570</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang J.J., Zhang X., Dai J.F., Ma Y.G., Jiang J.G. Effect of fermentation modification on the physicochemical characteristics and anti-aging related activities of Polygonatum kingianum polysaccharides. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules. 2023;235</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36796559</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Y., Qiu Z., Li L., Vidyarthi S.K., Zheng Z., Zhang R. Structural characterization and antioxidant activities of one neutral polysaccharide and three acid polysaccharides from Ziziphus jujuba cv. Hamidazao: A comparison. Carbohydrate Polymers. 2021;261</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33766366</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu J., Zhao L., Wang Z., Yue T., Wang X., Liu W. Correlations between the structure and anti-diabetic activity of novel polysaccharides from raw and “Nine Steaming Nine Sun-Drying” Polygonti rhizome. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules. 2024;260</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38171437</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuan L., Qiu Z., Yang Y., Liu C., Zhang R. Preparation, structural characterization and antioxidant activity of water-soluble polysaccharides and purified fractions from blackened jujube by an activity-oriented approach. Food Chemistry. 2022;385</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35278736</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuan Q., Liu W., Huang L., Wang L., Yu J., Wang Y.…Wang S. Quality evaluation of immunomodulatory polysaccharides from Agaricus bisporus by an integrated fingerprint technique. Food Frontiers. 2023;4(1):474–490.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng P., Li J., Chen Y., Zhang L. The structures and biological functions of polysaccharides from traditional Chinese herbs. Progress in Molecular Biology and Translational Science. 2019;163:423–444.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7102684</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31030757</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang J., Chen H., Luo L., Zhou Z., Wang Y., Gao T.…Wu M. Structures of fructan and galactan from Polygonatum cyrtonema and their utilization by probiotic bacteria. Carbohydrate Polymers. 2021;267</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34119173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao P., Zhou H., Zhao C., Li X., Wang Y., Huang L., Gao W. Purification, characterization and immunomodulatory activity of fructans from Polygonatum odoratum and P. cyrtonema. Carbohydrate Polymers. 2019;214:44–52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30926006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu M., Huang R., Wen P., Song Y., He B., Tan J.…Wang H. Structural characterization and immunological activity of pectin polysaccharide from kiwano (Cucumis metuliferus) peels. Carbohydrate Polymers. 2021;254</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33357887</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu S., Qiu Z., Qiao X., Waterhouse G.I., Zhu W., Zhao W.…Zheng Z. Creating burdock polysaccharide-oleanolic acid-ursolic acid nanoparticles to deliver enhanced anti-inflammatory effects: Fabrication, structural characterization and property evaluation. Food Science and Human Wellness. 2023;12(2):454–466.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>