<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39287632</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>17</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>17</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1432-0991</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>81</Volume><Issue>11</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>17</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Current microbiology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Curr Microbiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Isolation of Pathogenic Cronobacter Species as Bacteriological Risks Indicator in Powdered Infant Formula Available to Deprived Infants in Lagos Metropolis, Nigeria.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>360</StartPage><MedlinePgn>360</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s00284-024-03850-2</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Powdered infant formula (PIF) is rich in nutrients that support the survival and growth of bacteria that trigger food safety disorders in deprived infants through life-threatening illnesses. The study aims to examine and identify the incidence of pathogenic bacteria of concern in PIF upon reconstitution in lukewarm water. A total of 172 samples consisting of 38 brands of PIF available in the Lagos metropolis were sampled, suspended in water (10 g in 100 mL), and bacteria strains were isolated using combinational enrichment and selective culture techniques. Pure bacterial strains were characterized and identified based on their physiology and 16S rRNA gene sequence homology. While 85 bacterial strains were isolated from the enriched culture system, 20 strains were selectively isolated based on tolerance to sodium deoxycholate. Approximately 13% of the selected bacteria were identified as Cronobacter spp., exhibiting virulence traits including extracellular protease production, coagulation and proteolysis of casein, haem-agglutination, and β-haemolysis of human blood. Approximately 82% of the Cronobacter strains tolerated NaCl (10%) and bile salt; and exhibited resistance to cefotaxime, ceftriaxone, gentamicin, and Amoxicillin-clavulanic acid antibiotics. The presence of Cronobacter spp. in 13% of the PIF brands available to infants calls for concern about the safety of deprived infants that might be fed with such PIF. Consequently, PIF safety alerts need to be activate while further studies on critical points at which the pathogens get introduced to the PIFs need to be identified.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer Science+Business Media, LLC, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Oyetibo</LastName><ForeName>Olubukola Blessing</ForeName><Initials>OB</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2580-1640</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, College of Bioscience, Federal University of Agriculture, Abeokuta, 110212, Ogun State, Nigeria. olubukola.oyetibo@lasu.edu.ng.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Faculty of Science, Lagos State University, Ojoo, Lagos State, Nigeria. olubukola.oyetibo@lasu.edu.ng.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shittu</LastName><ForeName>Olufunke Bolatito</ForeName><Initials>OB</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5000-0015</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, College of Bioscience, Federal University of Agriculture, Abeokuta, 110212, Ogun State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Omemu</LastName><ForeName>Adebukunola Mobolaji</ForeName><Initials>AM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8297-4823</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Hospitality and Tourism, College of Food Science and Human Ecology, Federal University of Agriculture, Abeokuta, 110212, Ogun State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Curr Microbiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7808448</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0343-8651</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000900">Anti-Bacterial Agents</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D012336">RNA, Ribosomal, 16S</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009549" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Nigeria</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D041943" MajorTopicYN="Y">Infant Formula</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D059126" MajorTopicYN="Y">Cronobacter</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="N">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000145" MajorTopicYN="N">classification</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000187" MajorTopicYN="N">drug effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007223" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005516" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Microbiology</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000900" MajorTopicYN="N">Anti-Bacterial Agents</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000494" MajorTopicYN="N">pharmacology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012336" MajorTopicYN="N">RNA, Ribosomal, 16S</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008826" MajorTopicYN="N">Microbial Sensitivity Tests</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D059022" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Safety</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D024881" MajorTopicYN="N">Drug Resistance, Bacterial</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>21</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39287632</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00284-024-03850-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s00284-024-03850-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Okafor PI, Olatona FA, Olufemi OA (2014) Breastfeeding practices of mothers of young children in Lagos, Nigeria. Niger J peadriatr 41:43–47</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peterside O, Kunle-Oluwo OE, Duru CO (2013) Knowledge and practice of exclusive breastfeeding among mothers in Gbarantoru community. J Dental Med Sci 12(6):34–40</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The DHS Program (2019). Nigeria Demographic and Health Survey 2018, Key Findings. https://www.dhsprogram.com/pubs/pdf/SR264/SR264.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Otaigbe BE, Alikor AD, Nkanginieme OE (2005) Growth pattern of exclusively breastfeed infants. Niger J Med 14:137–145</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16083235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Global Health Observatory (Accessed in October 2022). Infants exclusively breastfed for the first six months of life (%). Appears in: WHO Infants less than 6 months who are fed exclusively with breast milk. Infants exclusively breastfed for the first six months of life (%) (who.int)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAO/WHO (2008). Enterobacter sakazakii (Cronobacter spp.) in powdered follow-up formulae. Microbiological Risk Assessment Series no. 15. Available at:  http://www.who.int/foodsafety/publications/micro/mra_followup/en/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meer RR, Baker J, Bodyfelt FW, Griffiths MW (1999) Pschrotrophic Bacillus spp. in fluid milk product. A rev J Food Prod 54:969–979</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rowan NJ, Anderson JG (1998) Diarrhoeal enterotoxin production by psychrotrophic Bacillus cereus present in reconstituted milk—based infant formula (MIF). Lett Appl Microbiol 26:165–165</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Estuningsih S, Kress C, Hassan AA, Akineden O, Schneider E, Usleber E (2006) Enterobacteriaceae in dehydrated powdered infant formula manufactured in Indonesia and Malaysia. J Food Prot 69(12):3013–3017. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362-028X-69.12.3013</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17186672</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giammanco GM, Aleo A, Guida I, Mannina C (2011) Molecular Epidemiological Survey of Citrobacter freundii Misidentified as Cronobacter spp. (Enterobacter sakazakii) and Enterobacter hormaechei Isolated from Powdered Infant Milk Formula. Foodborne Pathog Dis. https://doi.org/10.1089/fpd.2010.0719</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21204699</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jones G, de la Gandara MP, Herrera-Leon L, Herrera-Leon S, Martinez CV, Hureaux-Roy R, Abdallah Y, Nisavanh A, Fabre L, Renaudat C, Mossong J, Mattheus W, Huard C, Le Borge C, de Valk H, Weill F-X, Jourdan-Da Silva N (2019) Outbreak of Salmonella enterica serotype Poona in infants linked to persistent Salmonella contamination in an infant formula manufacturing facility, France, August 2018 to February 2019. Eurosurveillance 24:1900161</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30940315</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6446512</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Henry M, Fouladkhah A (2019) Outbreak history, biofilm formation, and preventive measures for control of Cronobacter sakazakii in infant formula and infant care settings. Microorganisms 7:77. https://doi.org/10.3390/microorganisms7030077</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30870985</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6463179</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nazarowec-White M, Farber JM (1997) Incidence, survival, and growth of Enterobacter sakazakii in infant formula. J Food Prot 60(3):226–230</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31195476</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holy O, Cruz-Cordova A, Xicohtencatl-Cortes J, Hochel I, Parra-Flores J, Petrzelova J, Facevivicova K, Forsythe S, Alsonosi A (2019) Occurrence of virulence factors in Cronobacter sakazakii and Cronobacter malonaticus originated from clinical samples. Microb Pathog 127:250–256. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.micpath.2018.12.011</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30550840</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ling N, Forsythe S, Wu Q, Ding Y, Zhang J, Zeng H (2020) Insights into Cronobacter sakazakii biofilm formation and control strategies in the food industry. Engineering 6:393–405. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eng.2020.02.007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pei X, Li Y, Zhang H, Zhan L, Yu X, Lan G, Jia H, Li N, Yang D, Mei L (2019) Surveillance and characterisation of Cronobacter in powdered infant formula processing factories. Food Control 96:328–323. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2018.09.009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iversen C, Druggan P, Schumacher S, Lehner A, Feer C, Gschwend K, Joosten H, Stephan R (2008) Development of a novel screening method for the isolation of ‘‘Cronobacter’’ spp. (Enterobacter sakazakii). Appl Environ Microbiol 74:2550–2553</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18310415</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2293158</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weisburg WG, Barns SM, Pelletier DA, Lane DJ (1991) 16S ribosomal DNA amplification for phylogenetic study. J Bacteriol 173:697–703</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1987160</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">207061</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fakruddin MD, Mizanur-Rahaman MD, Monzur MA, Mahfuzul HM (2014) Antimicrobial resistance and virulence factors of enterobacteriaceae isolated from food samples of Bangladesh. Int J Microbiol Immunol Res 3(1):12–21</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mansouri S, Norouzi F, Moradi M, Nakhaee N (2001) Comparison of virulence factors among clinical isolates of Pseudomonas aeruginosa producing and non-producing extended spectrum beta lactamases. Curr Res Bacteriol 4:85–93</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Checinska A, Paszcznski A, Burbank M (2015) Bacillus and other spore forming genera: variations in response and mechanism for survival. Annual Rev Food Sci Technol 6:351–369</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barash JR, Hsia JK, Arnon SS (2010) Presence of soil-dwelling Clostridia in commercial powdered infant formulas. J Paediatr 156:402–408</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang L, Bao H, Wei C, Zhang H, Zhou Y, Wang R (2015) Characterization and partial genomic analysis of a lytic Myoviridae bacteriophage against Staphylococcus aureus isolated from dairy cows with mastitis in Mid-east of China. Virus Genes 50:111–117</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25328045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muytjens HL, Roelofs-Willemse H, Jasper GH (1988) Quality of Powdered substitutes for breast milk with regards to members of the family Enterobacteriaceae. J Clin Microbiol 26:743–746</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3284901</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">266435</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Forsythe SJ (2005) Enterobacter sakazakii and other bacteria in powdered infant milk formula. Matern Child Nutr 1:44–45</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16881878</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holy O, Forsythe SJ (2014) Cronobacter species as emerging causes of healthcare associated infection. J Hosp 86:169–177</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iversen C, Forsythe S (2003) Risk profile of Enterobacter sakazakii, an emergent pathogen associated with infant milk formula. Trends Food Sci Technol 14(11):443–454</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Umeda NS, de Filippis I, Forsthe SJ, Brandao MLL (2017) Phenotypic characterization of Cronobacter spp. strains isolated from foods and clinical specimens in Brazil. Food Res Int 102:61–67</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29195992</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iversen C, Lane M, Forsythe SJ (2004) The growth profile, thermotolerance and biofilm formation of Enterobacter sakazakii grown in infant formula milk. Lett Appl Microbiol 38:378–382</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15059207</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu Y, Liu P, Li C, Sha M, Fang J, Gao J, Xu X, Matthews KR (2019) Prevalence and genetic diversity of cronobacter species isolated from four infant formula production factories in China. Front Microbiol. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2019.01938</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32038587</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6930231</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Friedemann M (2009) Epidemiology of invasive neonatal Cronobacter (Enterobacter sakazakii) infections. Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis 28:1297–1304</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19662446</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muytjens HL, van der Rosvander Repe J (1983) Comparative studies of β-lactams antibiotics. Antimicrob Agents Chemother 21(6):6925–934</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Block C, Peleg O, Minister N, Bar-Oz B, Simhon A, Arad I, Shapira M (2002) Cluster of neonatal infections in Jerusalem due to unusual biochemical variant of Enterobacter sakazakii. Eur J Clinl Microbiol Infect Dis 21:613–661</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bar-Oz B, Preminger A, Peleg O, Block C, Arad I (2001) Enterobacter sakazakii infection in the newborn. Acta of Paediatr 90:356–358</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kandhai MC, Reij MW, Gorris LGM, Guillaume-Gentil O, van Schothorst M (2004) Occurrence of Enterobacter sakazakii in food production environments and households. Lancet 363:39–40</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14723994</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Nabulsi AA, Osaili TM, Zain Elabedeen NA, Jaradat ZW, Shaker RR, Kheirallah KA, Tarazi YH, Holley RA (2011) Impact of environmental stress desiccation, acidity, alkalinity, heat or cold on antibiotic susceptibility of Cronobacter sakazakii. Int J Food Microbiol 146:137–143</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21402424</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brandao MLL, Umeda NS, Jackson E, Forsythe SJ, de Filippis I (2017) Isolation, molecular and phenotypic characterisation, and antibiotic susceptibility of Cronobacter spp. from Brazilian retail foods. Food Microbiol 63:129–138</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28040160</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu X, Li C, Wu Q, Zhang J, Huang J, Yang G (2015) Prevalence, molecular characterization, and antibiotic susceptibility of Cronobacter spp. in Chinese ready-to-eat foods. Int J Food Microbiol 204:17–23</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25828706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lai KK (2001) Enterobacter sakazakii infections among neonates, infants, children, and adults. Case reports and a review of the literature. Medicine (Baltimore) 80:113–122</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11307587</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Obasi A, Nwachukwu SC, Ugoji E (2018) First detection of Augmentin and colistin resistant Cronobacter sakazakii from a pharmaceutical wastewater in South-Western Nigeria. Am J Chem Biochem Eng 2(1):1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banu A, Kabbin M, Anand I (2011) Extra-intestinal infections due to Escherichia coli: an emerging issue. J Clinl Diagn Res 5:486–490</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pagotto FJ, Nazarowec-White M, Bidawid S, Farber JM (2003) Enterobacter sakazakii: infectivity and enterotoxin production in vitro and in vivo. J Food Prot 66:370–375</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12636287</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kothary MH, McCardell BA, Frazar CD, Deer D, Tall BD (2007) Characterization of the zinc-containing metalloprotease encoded by zpx and development of a species-specific detection method for Enterobacter sakazakii. Appl Environ Microbiol 73:4142–4151</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17483271</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">1932767</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kucerova E, Clifton SW, Xia XQ, Long F, Porwollik S, Fulton L, Fronick C, Minx P, Kyung K et al (2010) Genome sequence of Cronobacter sakazakii BAA-894 and comparative genomic hybridization analysis with other Cronobacter species. PLoS ONE 5:e9556</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20221447</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2833190</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Epstein EA, Chapman MR (2008) Polymerizing the fibre between bacteria and host cells: the biogenesis of functional amyloid fibres. Cell Microbiol 10:1413–1420</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18373633</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2674401</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>