<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39289890</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1863-2378</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>17</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Zoonoses and public health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Zoonoses Public Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>ESBL Producing E. coli in Chickens and Poultry Farms Environment in Selangor, Malaysia: A Cross-Sectional Study on Their Occurrence and Associated Risk Factors With Environment and Public Health Importance.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/zph.13179</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Extended-spectrum β-lactamase-producing Escherichia coli (ESBL-EC) are widespread multidrug-resistant zoonotic bacteria that threaten animal production, food safety and antimicrobial therapy worldwide including Malaysia. Poultry has been reported as one of the pathways for human exposure to ESBL-EC. There has been little research on the occurrence of ESBL-EC within the Malaysian poultry food chain. Hence, the objectives of the study were to determine the occurrence of ESBL-EC in chickens and to identify the potential risk factors associated with their occurrence in poultry farms.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A cross-sectional study was conducted on 400 samples, consisting of 240 cloacal swabs from chickens and 160 from poultry farms environments in eight districts in Selangor, Malaysia using culture and disk combination methods and multiple polymerase chain reaction assays. In the determination of possible factors associated with the presence of ESBL-EC at poultry farms, a questionnaire was used to obtain the information and data.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The findings demonstrated the wide distribution of ESBL-EC in all the farms with an overall occurrence of 37.2%. Farms in Gombak, Klang and Hulu Selangor had the highest occurrence rates at 62%, 50% and 50%, respectively, followed by farms in Petaling 38%, Sepang at 34%, Kuala Langat at 26% and Kuala Selangor at 24%, and the lowest was in Hulu Langat 14%. Among the study samples, chickens had the highest occurrence rate at 45.4%, followed by chicken house floors at 40% and flies at 30%, while feed and water samples at 17.5% and 12.5%, respectively. The present study indicated the high occurrence and wide dissemination of ESBL-EC in chickens and poultry farms environment. The ESBL-EC occurrence was associated with several factors including imprudent use of antibiotics, poor husbandry, management and biosecurity practices at the farms.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Our study showed the presence and spread of ESBL EC among chickens in the farms and their environment; this may lead to being spread to outside of farm environment by flies, vermins, flying birds, litter and farm wastes and possibly to humans upon contact with the contaminated environment and by poultry meat. Thus, the findings of the study can assist to serve as a piece of useful information to veterinary authority in designing evidence-based mitigation strategies for the control of ESBL-EC in poultry farms.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Wiley‐VCH GmbH. Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Aliyu</LastName><ForeName>Abdulrasheed Bello</ForeName><Initials>AB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Pathology and Microbiology, Universiti Putra Malaysia, Serdang, Selangor, Malaysia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jalila</LastName><ForeName>Abu</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Clinical Studies, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Universiti Putra Malaysia, Serdang, Selangor, Malaysia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Saleha</LastName><ForeName>Abdul Aziz</ForeName><Initials>AA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Pathology and Microbiology, Universiti Putra Malaysia, Serdang, Selangor, Malaysia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zunita</LastName><ForeName>Zakaria</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6574-0841</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Pathology and Microbiology, Universiti Putra Malaysia, Serdang, Selangor, Malaysia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Universiti Putra Malaysia</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Zoonoses Public Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101300786</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1863-1959</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ESBL‐producing E. coli</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Malaysia</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">chickens</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">farm environment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">risk factors</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39289890</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/zph.13179</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>Abubakar, U., T. Balamurugan, M. H. Elnaem, S. A. Syed Sulaiman, and F. U. Khan. 2022. “Mortality and Its Predictors Among Hospitalized Patients With Infections Due to Extended Spectrum Beta‐Lactamase (ESBL) Enterobacteriaceae in Malaysia: A Retrospective Observational Study.” Future Journal of Pharmaceutical Sciences 8: 17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aliyu, A. B., A. A. Saleha, A. Jalila, and Z. Zunita. 2016. “Risk Factors and Spatial Distribution of Extended‐Spectrum β‐Lactamase‐Producing Escherichia coli at Retail Poultry Meat Markets in Malaysia: A Cross‐Sectional Study.” BMC Public Health 16: 699.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bengtsson, B., and C. Greko. 2014. “Antibiotic Resistance‐Consequences for Animal Health, Welfare, and Food Production.” Upsala Journal of Medical Sciences 119, no. 2: 96–102.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blaak, H., A. H. van Hoek, R. A. Hamidjaja, et al. 2015. “Distribution, Numbers, and Diversity of ESBL‐Producing E. Coli in the Poultry Farm Environment.” PLoS One 10, no. 8: e0135402.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bouamamaa, L., A. Sorlozano, A. Laglaoui, M. Lebbadi, A. Aarab, and J. Gutierrez. 2010. “Antibiotic Resistance Patterns of Bacterial Strains Isolated From Periplaneta americana and Musca domestica in Tangier, Morocco.” Journal of Infection in Developing Countries 4, no. 4: 194–201.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonnedahl, J., P. Drobni, A. Johansson, et al. 2010. “Characterization, and Comparison, of Human Clinical and Black‐Headed Gull (Larus ridibundus) Extended‐Spectrum b‐Lactamase‐Producing Bacterial Isolates From Kalmar, on the Southeast Coast of Sweden.” Journal of Antimicrobial Chemotherapy 65: 1939–1944.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chai, M. H., M. Z. Sakiman, N. Jasmy, et al. 2022. “Molecular Detection and Antibiogram ESBL‐Producing and Carbapenem Resistant Escherichia coli From Rabbit, Swine and Poultry in Malaysia.” Tropical Animal Science Journal 45, no. 1: 16–23.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute. 2010. Performance Standards for Antimicrobial Disk Susceptibility Tests. 10th ed. M02‐A10. Wayne, PA: CLSI.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Costa, D., L. Vinué, P. Poeta, et al. 2009. “Prevalence of Extended‐Spectrum Beta‐Lactamase‐Producing Escherichia coli Isolates in Faecal Samples of Broilers.” Veterinary Microbiology 138, no. 3: 339–344.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diarra, M. S., H. Rempel, J. Champagne, L. Masson, J. Pritchard, and E. Topp. 2010. “Distribution of Antimicrobial Resistance and Virulence Genes in Enterococcus spp. and Characterization of Isolates From Broiler Chickens.” Applied and Environmental Microbiology 76, no. 24: 8033–8043.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dierikx, C., J. van der Goot, T. Fabri, A. van Essen‐Zandbergen, H. Smith, and D. Mevius. 2013. “Extended‐Spectrum‐β‐Lactamase‐and AmpC‐β‐Lactamase‐Producing Escherichia coli in Dutch Broilers and Broiler Farmers.” Journal of Antimicrobial Chemotherapy 68, no. 1: 60–67.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAO. 2023. “FAO's Role in Addressing Antimicrobial Resistance.” http://www.fao.org/antimicrobial‐resistance/en/. Accessed 1 November 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Franz, E., J. Schijven, A. M. de Roda Husman, and H. Blaak. 2014. “Meta‐Regression Analysis of Commensal and Pathogenic Escherichia Coli Survival in Soil and Water.” Environmental Science &amp; Technology 48, no. 12: 6763–6771.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hasan, B., L. Sandegren, Å. Melhus, et al. 2012. “Antimicrobial Drug‐Resistant Escherichia coli in Wild Birds and Free‐Range Poultry, Bangladesh.” Emerging Infectious Diseases 18, no. 12: 2055–2058.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hernandez, J., J. Bonnedahl, I. Eliasson, et al. 2010. “Globally Disseminated Human Pathogenic Escherichia coli of O25b‐ST131 Clone, Harbouring blaCTX‐M‐15, Found in Glaucous‐Winged Gull at Remote Commander Islands, Russia.” Environmental Microbiology 2: 329–332.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ho, W. S., G. Balan, S. Puthucheary, et al. 2012. “Prevalence and Characterization of Multidrug‐Resistant and Extended‐Spectrum Beta‐Lactamase‐Producing Escherichia coli From Pediatric Wards of a Malaysian Hospital.” Microbial Drug Resistance 18, no. 4: 408–416.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Islam, M. S., T. A. M. M. Rahman, J. Hassan, and M. T. Rahman. 2023. “Extended‐Spectrum Beta‐Lactamase in Escherichia coli Isolated From Humans, Animals, and Environments in Bangladesh: A One Health Perspective Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis.” One Health 16: 100526.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamaruzzaman, E. A., A. A. Saleha, A. A. Bitrus, Z. Zunita, and A. Jalila. 2020. “Occurrence and Characteristics of Extended‐Spectrum β‐Lactamase‐Producing Escherichia coli From Dairy Cattle, Milk and Farm Environments in Peninsular Malaysia.” Pathogens 9, no. 12: 1007. https://doi.org/10.3390/pathogens9121007.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kilonzo‐Nthenge, A., E. Rotich, and S. N. Nahashon. 2013. “Evaluation of Drug‐Resistant Enterobacteriaceae in Retail Poultry and Beef.” Poultry Science 92, no. 4: 1098–1107.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laube, H., A. Friese, C. von Salviati, B. Guerra, and U. Rösler. 2014. “Transmission of ESBL/AmpC‐Producing Escherichia coli From Broiler Chicken Farms to Surrounding Areas.” Veterinary Microbiology 172, no. 3: 519–527.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee, E., S. Radu, N. N. Jambari, and N. A. Abdul‐Mutalib. 2021. “Prevalence and Antibiogram Profiling of Extended‐Spectrum Beta‐Lactamase (ESBL) Producing Escherichia coli in Raw Vegetables in Malaysia.” Biology Life Science Forum 6: 44. https://doi.org/10.3390/Foods2021‐10960.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lemlen, M., E. Aklilu, M. Mohammed, et al. 2023. “Molecular Characterization and Antimicrobial Resistant Profiles of Extended‐Spectrum Beta‐Lactamase (ESBL) Producing Escherichia coli in Broiler Chicken Farms in Malaysia.” PLoS One 18, no. 5: e0285743.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lim, K. T., R. Yasin, C. C. Yeo, S. Puthucheary, and K. L. Thong. 2009. “Characterization of Multidrug Resistant ESBL‐Producing Escherichia coli Isolates From Hospitals in Malaysia.” Journal of Biomedicine and Biotechnology 2009: 165637. https://doi.org/10.1155/2009/165637.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Livermore, D. M. 2008. “Defining an Extended‐Spectrum β‐Lactamase.” Clinical Microbiology and Infection 14, no. s1: 3–10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mughini‐Gras, L., A. Dorado‐García, E. van Duijkeren, et al. 2019. “Attributable Sources of Community‐Acquired Carriage of Escherichia coli Containing β‐Lactam Antibiotic Resistance Genes: A Population‐Based Modelling Study.” Lancet Planetary Health 3: 357–369.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nadimpalli, M., Y. Vuthy, A. de Lauzanne, et al. 2019. “Meat and Fish as Sources of Extended‐Spectrum β‐Lactamase–Producing Escherichia coli, Cambodia.” Emerging Infectious Diseases 25: 126–131.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramatla, T., T. Mafokwane, K. Lekota, et al. 2023. ““One Health” Perspective on Prevalence of Co‐Existing Extended‐Spectrum β‐Lactamase (ESBL)–Producing Escherichia coli and Klebsiella pneumoniae: A Comprehensive Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis.” Annals of Clinical Microbiology and Antimicrobials 22: 88.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roess, A. A., P. J. Winch, N. A. Ali, et al. 2013. “Animal Husbandry Practices in Rural Bangladesh: Potential Risk Factors for Antimicrobial Drug Resistance and Emerging Diseases.” American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene 89, no. 5: 965–970.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanderson, M. W., J. M. Sargeant, D. G. Renter, D. D. Griffin, and R. A. Smith. 2005. “Factors Associated With the Presence of Coliforms in the Feed and Water of Feedlot Cattle.” Applied and Environmental Microbiology 71, no. 10: 6026–6032.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sekawi, Z., R. Yusof, and M. N. Shamsudin. 2008. “Extended‐Spectrum ß‐Lactamases‐Producing Escherichia coli From a Tertiary Hospital in Malaysia: Emergence of CTX‐M‐Type ß‐Lactamases Variation.” Research Journal of Microbiology 3, no. 6: 489–493.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Solà‐Ginés, M., J. J. González‐López, K. Cameron‐Veas, N. Piedra‐Carrasco, M. Cerdà‐Cuéllar, and L. Migura‐Garcia. 2015. “Houseflies (Musca domestica) as Vectors for Extended‐Spectrum β‐Lactamase‐Producing Escherichia coli on Spanish Broiler Farms.” Applied and Environmental Microbiology 81, no. 11: 3604–3611.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Samanta, I., S. N. Joardar, P. K. Das, and T. K. Sar. 2015. “Comparative Possession of Shiga Toxin, Intimin, Enterohaemolysin and Major Extended Spectrum Beta Lactamase (ESBL) Genes in Escherichia coli Isolated From Backyard and Farmed Poultry.” Iranian Journal of Veterinary Research 16, no. 1: 90–93.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Subramaniam, G., S. Palasubramaniam, and P. Navaratnam. 2006. “SHV‐5 Extended‐Spectrum Beta‐Lactamases in Clinical Isolates of Escherichia coli in Malaysia.” Indian Journal of Medical Microbiology 24, no. 3: 205–207.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suryadevara, N., B. Y. Kai, B. Ganapathy, et al. 2020. “Molecular Characterisation of Escherichia coli From Chickens in Poultry Farms of Malaysia.” Research Journal of Biotechnology 15, no. 10: 1–10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan, H.‐S., P. Yan, H. A. Agustie, H.‐S. Loh, N. Rayamajhi, and C.‐M. Fang. 2023. “Characterisation of ESBL/AmpC‐Producing Enterobacteriaceae Isolated From Poultry Farms in Peninsular Malaysia.” Letters in Applied Microbiology 76: 1–10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tansawai, U., T. R. Walsh, and P. R. Niumsup. 2019. “Extended Spectrum β‐Lactamase‐Producing Escherichia coli Among Backyard Poultry Farms, Farmers and Environments in Thailand.” Poultry Science 98: 2622–2631.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wittum, T. E. 2012. “The Challenge of Regulating Agricultural Ceftiofur Use to Slow the Emergence of Resistance to Extended‐Spectrum Cephalosporins.” Applied and Environmental Microbiology 78, no. 22: 7819–7821.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan, J. J., C. Y. Hong, W. C. Ko, et al. 2004. “Dissemination of blaCMY‐2 Among Escherichia coli Isolates From Food Animals, Retail Ground Meats, and Humans in Southern Taiwan.” Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy 48: 1353–1356.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuan, L., J. H. Liu, G. Z. Hu, et al. 2009. “Molecular Characterization of Extended‐Spectrum β‐Lactamase‐Producing Escherichia coli Isolates From Chickens in Henan Province, China.” Journal of Medical Microbiology 58, no. 11: 1449–1453.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, L., Y. H. Dong, and H. Wang. 2010. “Residues of Veterinary Antibiotics in Manures From Feedlot Livestock in Eight Provinces of China.” Science of the Total Environment 408, no. 5: 1069–1075.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>