<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39289703</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>21</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1757-4749</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>17</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Gut pathogens</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Gut Pathog</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Structured multicellular intestinal spheroids (SMIS) as a standardized model for infection biology.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>47</StartPage><MedlinePgn>47</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">47</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s13099-024-00644-6</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">3D cell culture models have recently garnered increasing attention for replicating organ microarchitecture and eliciting in vivo-like responses, holding significant promise across various biological disciplines. Broadly, 3D cell culture encompasses organoids as well as single- and multicellular spheroids. While the latter have found successful applications in tumor research, there is a notable scarcity of standardized intestinal models for infection biology that mimic the microarchitecture of the intestine. Hence, this study aimed to develop structured multicellular intestinal spheroids (SMIS) specifically tailored for studying molecular basis of infection by intestinal pathogens.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">We have successfully engineered human SMIS comprising four relevant cell types, featuring a fibroblast core enveloped by an outer monolayer of enterocytes and goblet cells along with monocytic cells. These SMIS effectively emulate the in vivo architecture of the intestinal mucosal surface and manifest differentiated morphological characteristics, including the presence of microvilli, within a mere two days of culture. Through analysis of various differentiation factors, we have illustrated that these spheroids attain heightened levels of differentiation compared to 2D monolayers. Moreover, SMIS serve as an optimized intestinal infection model, surpassing the capabilities of traditional 2D cultures, and exhibit a regulatory pattern of immunological markers similar to in vivo infections after Campylobacter jejuni infection. Notably, our protocol extends beyond human spheroids, demonstrating adaptability to other species such as mice and pigs.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Based on the rapid attainment of enhanced differentiation states, coupled with the emergence of functional brush border features, increased cellular complexity, and replication of the intestinal mucosal microarchitecture, which allows for exposure studies via the medium, we are confident that our innovative SMIS model surpasses conventional cell culture methods as a superior model. Moreover, it offers advantages over stem cell-derived organoids due to scalability and standardization capabilities of the protocol. By showcasing differentiated morphological attributes, our model provides an optimal platform for diverse applications. Furthermore, the investigated differences of several immunological factors compared to monotypic monolayers after Campylobacter jejuni infection underline the refinement of our spheroid model, which closely mimics important features of in vivo infections.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kraski</LastName><ForeName>Angelina</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Veterinary Biochemistry, Freie Universität Berlin, Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Migdał</LastName><ForeName>Paweł</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Animal Husbandry and Breeding, Wrocław University of Environmental and Life Sciences, Wrocław, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Klopfleisch</LastName><ForeName>Robert</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Veterinary Pathology, Freie Universität Berlin, Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Räckel</LastName><ForeName>Clara</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Veterinary Biochemistry, Freie Universität Berlin, Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sharbati</LastName><ForeName>Jutta</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Science, OSZ Lise Meitner, Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Heimesaat</LastName><ForeName>Markus M</ForeName><Initials>MM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Microbiology, Infectious Diseases and Immunology, Charité, Universitätsmedizin Berlin, Corporate Member of Freie Universität Berlin, Humboldt-Universität Zu Berlin, and Berlin Institute of Health, Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alter</LastName><ForeName>Thomas</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Food Safety and Food Hygiene, Freie Universität Berlin, Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hanisch</LastName><ForeName>Carlos</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>SGS INSTITUT FRESENIUS GmbH, Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gölz</LastName><ForeName>Greta</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Food Safety and Food Hygiene, Freie Universität Berlin, Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Einspanier</LastName><ForeName>Ralf</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Veterinary Biochemistry, Freie Universität Berlin, Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sharbati</LastName><ForeName>Soroush</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Veterinary Biochemistry, Freie Universität Berlin, Berlin, Germany. soroush.sharbati@fu-berlin.de.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Gut Pathog</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101474263</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1757-4749</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">3D cell culture</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Infection model</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Intestinal mucosa</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Multilayered spheroid</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39289703</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11406839</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13099-024-00644-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s13099-024-00644-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Kapałczyńska M, Kolenda T, Przybyła W, Zajączkowska M, Teresiak A, Filas V, Ibbs M, Bliźniak R, Łuczewski Ł, Lamperska K. 2D and 3D cell cultures—a comparison of different types of cancer cell cultures. AMS. 2018;14(4):910–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6040128</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30002710</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Preksha G, Yesheswini R, Srikanth CV. Cell culture techniques in gastrointestinal research: methods, possibilities and challenges. Indian J Pathol Microbiol. 2021;64(Supplement):S52-s57.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34135138</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biju TS, Priya VV, Francis AP. Role of three-dimensional cell culture in therapeutics and diagnostics: an updated review. Drug Deliv Transl Res. 2023;13(9):2239–53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10042111</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36971997</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Achilli TM, Meyer J, Morgan JR. Advances in the formation, use and understanding of multi-cellular spheroids. Expert Opin Biol Ther. 2012;12(10):1347–60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4295205</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22784238</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryan S-L, Baird A-M, Vaz G, Urquhart AJ, et al. Drug discovery approaches utilizing three-dimensional cell culture. Assay Drug Dev Technol. 2016;14(1):19–28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26866750</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jensen C, Teng Y. Is it time to start transitioning from 2D to 3D cell culture? Front Mol Biosci. 2020. 10.3389/fmolb.2020.00033.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7067892</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32211418</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klingelhutz AJ, Gourronc FA, Chaly A, Wadkins DA, Burand AJ, Markan KR, Idiga SO, Wu M, Potthoff MJ, Ankrum JA. Scaffold-free generation of uniform adipose spheroids for metabolism research and drug discovery. Sci Rep. 2018;8(1):523.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5765134</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29323267</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shanks N, Greek R, Greek J. Are animal models predictive for humans? Philos Ethics Humanit Med. 2009;4:2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2642860</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19146696</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koledova Z. 3D cell culture: an introduction. Methods Mol Biol. 2017;1612:1–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28634931</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clevers H. Modeling development and disease with organoids. Cell. 2016;165(7):1586–97.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27315476</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pleguezuelos-Manzano C, Puschhof J, van den Brink S, Geurts V, Beumer J, Clevers H. Establishment and culture of human intestinal organoids derived from adult stem cells. Curr Protoc Immunol. 2020;130(1): e106.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9285512</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32940424</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Serra D, Mayr U, Boni A, Lukonin I, Rempfler M, Challet Meylan L, Stadler MB, Strnad P, Papasaikas P, Vischi D, et al. Self-organization and symmetry breaking in intestinal organoid development. Nature. 2019;569(7754):66–72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6544541</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31019299</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almeqdadi M, Mana MD, Roper J, Yilmaz ÖH. Gut organoids: mini-tissues in culture to study intestinal physiology and disease. Am J Physiol Cell Physiol. 2019;317(3):C405-c419.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6766612</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31216420</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim J, Koo B-K, Knoblich JA. Human organoids: model systems for human biology and medicine. Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol. 2020;21(10):571–84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7339799</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32636524</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Co JY, Margalef-Català M, Li X, Mah AT, Kuo CJ, Monack DM, Amieva MR. Controlling epithelial polarity: a human enteroid model for host-pathogen interactions. Cell Rep. 2019;26(9):2509-2520.e2504.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6391775</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30811997</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kakni P, López-Iglesias C, Truckenmüller R, Habibović P, Giselbrecht S. PSC-derived intestinal organoids with apical-out orientation as a tool to study nutrient uptake, drug absorption and metabolism. Front Mol Biosci. 2023. 10.3389/fmolb.2023.1102209.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9889654</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36743212</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li L, Jiao L, Feng D, Yuan Y, Yang X, Li J, Jiang D, Chen H, Meng Q, Chen R, et al. Human apical-out nasal organoids reveal an essential role of matrix metalloproteinases in airway epithelial differentiation. Nat Commun. 2024;15(1):143.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10762242</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38168066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stroulios G, Brown T, Moreni G, Kondro D, Dei A, Eaves A, Louis S, Hou J, Chang W, Pajkrt D, et al. Apical-out airway organoids as a platform for studying viral infections and screening for antiviral drugs. Sci Rep. 2022;12(1):7673.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9089294</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35538146</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hofmann S, Cohen-Harazi R, Maizels Y, Koman I. Patient-derived tumor spheroid cultures as a promising tool to assist personalized therapeutic decisions in breast cancer. Transl Cancer Res. 2021;11(1):134–47.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8841497</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35261891</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Białkowska K, Komorowski P, Bryszewska M, Miłowska K. Spheroids as a type of three-dimensional cell cultures-examples of methods of preparation and the most important application. Int J Mol Sci. 2020;21(17):6225.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7503223</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32872135</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo L, Zhang W, Wang J, Zhao M, Shen K, Jia Y, Li Y, Zhang J, Cai W, Xiao D, et al. A novel 3D culture model of human ascs reduces cell death in spheroid cores and maintains inner cell proliferation compared with a nonadherent 3D culture. Front Cell Dev Biol. 2021. 10.3389/fcell.2021.737275.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8632442</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34858974</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gunti S, Hoke ATK, Vu KP, London NR. Organoid and spheroid tumor models: techniques and applications. Cancers. 2021;13(4):874.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7922036</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33669619</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weiswald L-B, Bellet D, Dangles-Marie V. Spherical cancer models in tumor biology. Neoplasia. 2015;17(1):1–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4309685</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25622895</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shield K, Ackland ML, Ahmed N, Rice GE. Multicellular spheroids in ovarian cancer metastases: biology and pathology. Gynecol Oncol. 2009;113(1):143–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19135710</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tutty MA, Prina-Mello A. Three-dimensional spheroids for cancer research. Methods Mol Biol. 2023;2645:65–103.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37202612</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosa RB, Dantas WM, do Nascimento JCF, da Silva MV, de Oliveira RN, Pena LJ. In vitro and in vivo models for studying sars-cov-2, the etiological agent responsible for COVID-19 pandemic. Viruses 2021;13(3):379</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7997194</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33673614</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>da Silva da Costa FA, Soares MR, Malagutti-Ferreira MJ, da Silva GR, Lívero F, Ribeiro-Paes JT. Three-dimensional cell cultures as a research platform in lung diseases and COVID-19. Tissue Eng Regen Med 2021, 18(5):735-745.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8172328</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34080133</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tetteh PW, Basak O, Farin HF, Wiebrands K, Kretzschmar K, Begthel H, van den Born M, Korving J, de Sauvage F, van Es JH, et al. Replacement of lost Lgr5-positive stem cells through plasticity of their enterocyte-lineage daughters. Cell Stem Cell. 2016;18(2):203–13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26831517</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krug SM. Von 3D zu 2D: organoid-basierte monolayer als modell der Darmbarriere. BIOspektrum. 2023;29(7):745–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abud HE, Chan WH, Jardé T. Source and impact of the EGF family of ligands on intestinal stem cells. Front Cell Dev Biol. 2021;9: 685665.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8327171</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34350179</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perez White BE, Getsios S. Eph receptor and ephrin function in breast, gut, and skin epithelia. Cell Adh Migr. 2014;8(4):327–38.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4594571</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25482622</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holmberg J, Genander M, Halford MM, Annerén C, Sondell M, Chumley MJ, Silvany RE, Henkemeyer M, Frisén J. EphB receptors coordinate migration and proliferation in the intestinal stem cell niche. Cell. 2006;125(6):1151–63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16777604</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lisabeth EM, Falivelli G, Pasquale EB. Eph receptor signaling and ephrins. Cold Spring Harb Perspect Biol. 2013. 10.1101/cshperspect.a009159.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3753714</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24003208</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weiß F, Holthaus D, Kraft M, Klotz C, Schneemann M, Schulzke JD, Krug SM. Human duodenal organoid-derived monolayers serve as a suitable barrier model for duodenal tissue. Ann N Y Acad Sci. 2022;1515(1):155–67.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35666953</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lehmann A, Hornby PJ. Intestinal SGLT1 in metabolic health and disease. Am J Physiol Gastrointest Liver Physiol. 2016;310(11):G887-898.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27012770</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spanier B, Rohm F. Proton coupled oligopeptide transporter 1 (PepT1) function, regulation, and influence on the intestinal homeostasis. Compr Physiol. 2018;8(2):843–69.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29687907</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El Harane S, Zidi B, El Harane N, Krause KH, Matthes T, Preynat-Seauve O. Cancer spheroids and organoids as novel tools for research and therapy: state of the art and challenges to guide precision medicine. Cells. 2023;12(7):1001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10093533</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37048073</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gheytanchi E, Naseri M, Karimi-Busheri F, Atyabi F, Mirsharif ES, Bozorgmehr M, Ghods R, Madjd Z. Morphological and molecular characteristics of spheroid formation in HT-29 and Caco-2 colorectal cancer cell lines. Cancer Cell Int. 2021;21(1):204.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8042991</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33849536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xue Y, Wang M, Han H. Interaction between alveolar macrophages and epithelial cells during Mycoplasma pneumoniae infection. Front Cell Infect Microbiol. 2023;13:1052020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10126420</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37113130</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Philpott DJ, Girardin SE, Sansonetti PJ. Innate immune responses of epithelial cells following infection with bacterial pathogens. Curr Opin Immunol. 2001;13(4):410–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11498296</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crawley SW, Mooseker MS, Tyska MJ. Shaping the intestinal brush border. J Cell Biol. 2014;207(4):441–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4242837</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25422372</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaunitz JD, Akiba Y. Control of intestinal epithelial proliferation and differentiation: the microbiome, enteroendocrine L cells, telocytes, enteric nerves, and GLP. Too Dig Dis Sci. 2019;64(10):2709–16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7211432</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31435858</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suzuki A, Sekiya S, Gunshima E, Fujii S, Taniguchi H. EGF signaling activates proliferation and blocks apoptosis of mouse and human intestinal stem/progenitor cells in long-term monolayer cell culture. Lab Invest. 2010;90(10):1425–36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20714325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duckworth CA. Identifying key regulators of the intestinal stem cell niche. Biochem Soc Trans. 2021;49(5):2163–76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8589435</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34665221</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Genander M, Halford MM, Xu NJ, Eriksson M, Yu Z, Qiu Z, Martling A, Greicius G, Thakar S, Catchpole T, et al. Dissociation of EphB2 signaling pathways mediating progenitor cell proliferation and tumor suppression. Cell. 2009;139(4):679–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2786256</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19914164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hanisch C, Sharbati J, Kutz-Lohroff B, Huber O, Einspanier R, Sharbati S. Trefoil factor 3 mediates resistance to apoptosis in colon carcinoma cells by a regulatory RNA axis. Cell Death Dis. 2017;8(3): e2660.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5386576</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28277538</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharbati J, Lewin A, Kutz-Lohroff B, Kamal E, Einspanier R, Sharbati S. Integrated microRNA-mRNA-analysis of human monocyte derived macrophages upon Mycobacterium avium subsp. hominissuis infection. PLoS ONE. 2011;6(5):e20258.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3101234</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21629653</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xi D, Hofmann L, Alter T, Einspanier R, Bereswill S, Heimesaat MM, Gölz G, Sharbati S. The glycosyltransferase ST3GAL2 is regulated by miR-615-3p in the intestinal tract of Campylobacter jejuni infected mice. Gut Pathogens. 2021;13(1):42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8240225</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34183045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kraski A, Mousavi S, Heimesaat MM, Bereswill S, Einspanier R, Alter T, Gölz G, Sharbati S. miR-125a-5p regulates the sialyltransferase ST3GAL1 in murine model of human intestinal campylobacteriosis. Gut Pathogens. 2023;15(1):48.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10583435</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37848994</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharbati J, Hanisch C, Pieper R, Einspanier R, Sharbati S. Small molecule and RNAi induced phenotype transition of expanded and primary colonic epithelial cells. Sci Rep. 2015;5:12681.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4519788</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26223582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tevlek A, Keçili S, Ozcelik O, Kulah H, Tekin H: Spheroid Engineering in Microfluidic Devices. ACS Omega 2023, 8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9893254</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36743071</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sant S, Johnston PA. The production of 3D tumor spheroids for cancer drug discovery. Drug Discov Today Technol. 2017;23:27–36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5497458</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28647083</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pinto B, Henriques AC, Silva PMA, Bousbaa H. Three-dimensional spheroids as in vitro preclinical models for cancer research. Pharmaceutics. 2020;12(12):1186.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7762220</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33291351</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dolznig H, Walzl A, Kramer N, Rosner M, Garin-Chesa P, Hengstschläger M. Organotypic spheroid cultures to study tumor–stroma interaction during cancer development. Drug Discov Today Dis Model. 2011;8(2):113–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herter S, Morra L, Schlenker R, Sulcova J, Fahrni L, Waldhauer I, Lehmann S, Reisländer T, Agarkova I, Kelm J, et al. A novel three-dimensional heterotypic spheroid model for the assessment of the activity of cancer immunotherapy agents. Cancer Immunol Immunother. 2017. 10.1007/s00262-016-1927-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5222939</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27858101</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schimpel C, Passegger C, Egger S, Tam-Amersdorfer C, Strobl H. A novel 3D cell culture model to study the human small intestinal immune landscape. Eur J Immunol. 2023;53(3):2250131.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36527196</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sambuy Y, De Angelis I, Ranaldi G, Scarino ML, Stammati A, Zucco F. The Caco-2 cell line as a model of the intestinal barrier: influence of cell and culture-related factors on Caco-2 cell functional characteristics. Cell Biol Toxicol. 2005;21(1):1–26.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15868485</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding X, Hu X, Chen Y, Xie J, Ying M, Wang Y, Yu Q. Differentiated Caco-2 cell models in food-intestine interaction study: current applications and future trends. Trends Food Sci Technol. 2021;107:455–65.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lea T. Caco-2 Cell Line. In: Verhoeckx K, Cotter P, López-Expósito I, Kleiveland C, Lea T, Mackie A, Requena T, Swiatecka D, Wichers H, editors. The Impact of food bioactives on health: in vitro and ex vivo models. Cham: Springer International Publishing; 2015. p. 103–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29787039</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Däster S, Amatruda N, Calabrese D, Ivanek R, Turrini E, Droeser RA, Zajac P, Fimognari C, Spagnoli GC, Iezzi G, et al. Induction of hypoxia and necrosis in multicellular tumor spheroids is associated with resistance to chemotherapy treatment. Oncotarget. 2017;8(1):1725–36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5352092</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27965457</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barisam M, Saidi MS, Kashaninejad N, Nguyen NT. Prediction of necrotic core and hypoxic zone of multicellular spheroids in a microbioreactor with a U-shaped barrier. Micromachines (Basel). 2018;9(3):94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6187679</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30424028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dini S, Binder BJ, Fischer SC, Mattheyer C, Schmitz A, Stelzer EH, Bean NG, Green JE. Identifying the necrotic zone boundary in tumour spheroids with pair-correlation functions. J R Soc Interface. 2016. 10.1098/rsif.2016.0649.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5095222</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27733696</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antfolk M, Jensen KB. A bioengineering perspective on modelling the intestinal epithelial physiology in vitro. Nat Commun. 2020;11(1):6244.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7721730</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33288759</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scoville D, Sato T, He XC, Li L. Current view: intestinal stem cells and signaling. Gastroenterology. 2008;134:849–64.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18325394</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papadakos S, Petrogiannopoulos L, Pergaris A, Theocharis S. The EPH/Ephrin system in colorectal cancer. Int J Mol Sci. 2022;23:2761.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8910949</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35269901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kania A, Klein R. Mechanisms of ephrin-Eph signalling in development, physiology and disease. Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol. 2016;17(4):240–56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26790531</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Wang J, Yang L, Qiu L, Hua Y, Wu S, Zeng S, Yu L, Zheng X. Epigenetic regulation of intestinal peptide transporter PEPT1 as a potential strategy for colorectal cancer sensitization. Cell Death Dis. 2021;12(6):532.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8144210</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34031358</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Merino B, Fernández-Díaz CM, Cózar-Castellano I, Perdomo G. Intestinal fructose and glucose metabolism in health and disease. Nutrients. 2020;12(1):94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7019254</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31905727</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang CY, Liu S, Xie XN, Tan ZR. Regulation profile of the intestinal peptide transporter 1 (PepT1). Drug Des Devel Ther. 2017;11:3511–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5726373</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29263649</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nielsen CU, Amstrup J, Steffansen B, Frokjaer S, Brodin B. Epidermal growth factor inhibits glycylsarcosine transport and hPepT1 expression in a human intestinal cell line. Am J Physiol Gastrointest Liver Physiol. 2001;281(1):G191-199.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11408272</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brugger MD, Valenta T, Fazilaty H, Hausmann G, Basler K. Distinct populations of crypt-associated fibroblasts act as signaling hubs to control colon homeostasis. PLoS Biol. 2020;18(12): e3001032.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7758045</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33306673</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allaire JM, Crowley SM, Law HT, Chang S-Y, Ko H-J, Vallance BA. The intestinal epithelium: central coordinator of mucosal immunity. Trends Immunol. 2018;39(9):677–96.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29716793</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iftekhar A, Sigal M. Defence and adaptation mechanisms of the intestinal epithelium upon infection. Int J Med Microbiol. 2021;311(3): 151486.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33684844</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roulis M, Flavell RA. Fibroblasts and myofibroblasts of the intestinal lamina propria in physiology and disease. Differentiation. 2016;92(3):116–31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27165847</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bain CC, Mowat AM. The monocyte-macrophage axis in the intestine. Cell Immunol. 2014;291(1–2):41–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4217150</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24726741</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xi D, Alter T, Einspanier R, Sharbati S, Golz G. Campylobacter jejuni genes Cj1492c and Cj1507c are involved in host cell adhesion and invasion. Gut Pathog. 2020;12:8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7011364</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32064001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang JM, An J. Cytokines, inflammation, and pain. Int Anesthesiol Clin. 2007;45(2):27–37.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2785020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17426506</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turner MD, Nedjai B, Hurst T, Pennington DJ. Cytokines and chemokines: at the crossroads of cell signalling and inflammatory disease. Biochim Biophys Acta Mol Cell Res. 2014;1843(11):2563–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24892271</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siegesmund AM, Konkel ME, Klena JD, Mixter PF. Campylobacter jejuni infection of differentiated THP-1 macrophages results in interleukin 1 beta release and caspase-1-independent apoptosis. Microbiology (Reading). 2004;150(Pt 3):561–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14993305</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Banna NA, Cyprian F, Albert MJ. Cytokine responses in campylobacteriosis: linking pathogenesis to immunity. Cytokine Growth Factor Rev. 2018;41:75–87.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29550265</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bücker R, Krug SM, Moos V, Bojarski C, Schweiger MR, Kerick M, Fromm A, Janßen S, Fromm M, Hering NA, et al. Campylobacter jejuni impairs sodium transport and epithelial barrier function via cytokine release in human colon. Mucosal Immunol. 2018;11(2):474–85.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28766554</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu L, Bray MD, Osorio M, Kopecko DJ. Campylobacter jejuni induces maturation and cytokine production in human dendritic cells. Infect Immun. 2006;74(5):2697–705.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1459697</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16622206</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larson CL, Samuelson DR, Eucker TP, O’Loughlin JL, Konkel ME. The fibronectin-binding motif within FlpA facilitates Campylobacter jejuni adherence to host cell and activation of host cell signaling. Emerg Microbes Infect. 2013;2(10): e65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3826066</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26038437</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krause-Gruszczynska M, Boehm M, Rohde M, Tegtmeyer N, Takahashi S, Buday L, Oyarzabal OA, Backert S. The signaling pathway of Campylobacter jejuni-induced Cdc42 activation: Role of fibronectin, integrin beta1, tyrosine kinases and guanine exchange factor Vav2. Cell Commun Signal. 2011;9:32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3286397</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22204307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Higuchi Y, Kojima M, Ishii G, Aoyagi K, Sasaki H, Ochiai A. Gastrointestinal fibroblasts have specialized, diverse transcriptional phenotypes: a comprehensive gene expression analysis of human fibroblasts. PLoS ONE. 2015;10(6): e0129241.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4457624</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26046848</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gonzalez LM, Moeser AJ, Blikslager AT. Porcine models of digestive disease: the future of large animal translational research. Transl Res. 2015;166(1):12–27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4458388</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25655839</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tominaga T, Suzuki M, Saeki H, Matsuno S, Tachibana T, Kudo T. Establishment of an activated macrophage cell line, A-THP-1, and its properties. Tohoku J Exp Med. 1998;186(2):99–119.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10223614</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krzyżek P, Migdał P, Grande R, Gościniak G. Biofilm formation of helicobacter pylori in both static and microfluidic conditions is associated with resistance to clarithromycin. Front Cell Infect Microbiol. 2022;12:868905.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8990135</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35402304</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vandesompele J, De Preter K, Pattyn F, Poppe B, Van Roy N, De Paepe A, Speleman F. Accurate normalization of real-time quantitative RT-PCR data by geometric averaging of multiple internal control genes. Genome Biol. 2002;3(7):Research0034.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC126239</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12184808</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>