<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39282659</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2405-6766</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>36</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Food and waterborne parasitology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Food Waterborne Parasitol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Foodborne concerns of <i>Blastocystis</i> spp. in marine animals (fish, bivalves, and sponges): A systematic review and meta-analysis of global prevalence and subtypes distribution.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e00242</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e00242</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e00242</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.fawpar.2024.e00242</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText><i>Blastocystis</i> spp. is a common intestinal parasite found in humans and various animals, including marine species like fish, bivalves, and sponges. While traditionally considered non-pathogenic, emerging evidence suggests potential foodborne concerns, especially for vulnerable populations. The present systematic review and meta-analysis reviewed four electronic databases (PubMed, Scopus, Google Scholar, and Web of Science) until June 13, 2024, for studies reporting the prevalence and subtypes (STs) distribution of <i>Blastocystis</i> spp. in marine animals, including fish, bivalves, and sponges, to assess foodborne concern and zoonotic importance. In the analysis of 11 studies involving 1329 marine animals from nine countries, five studies/datasets (742 samples) focused on fish, five studies/datasets (567 samples) on bivalves, and one (20 samples) on sponges. This review found that 12.4 % (95 % CI: 4.3-31 %) of marine animals globally were infected by <i>Blastocystis</i> spp., with bivalves showing the highest infection rate at 32 % (95 % CI: 13-59.7 %), exceeding sponges with a single study at 10 % (95 % CI: 2.5-32.4 %), and fish at 4.4 % (95 % CI: 2-9.3 %). Sensitivity analysis assessed changes in weighted prevalence after excluding certain studies. A subgroup analysis of <i>Blastocystis</i> spp. prevalence was conducted based on publication years, countries, continents, WHO regions, and sample sizes. The data collected indicated that marine animals serve as suitable reservoirs for various <i>Blastocystis</i> spp. STs (ST1-ST4, ST7, ST8, ST10, ST14, ST23, ST26, and ST44), with most (except for ST26 and ST44) having the potential for zoonotic transmission. Overall, the findings emphasize the potential for foodborne risk posed by <i>Blastocystis</i> spp. in marine animals and highlight the need for improved monitoring and control measures to ensure food safety.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ghafari-Cherati</LastName><ForeName>Mohammad</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Metabolic Diseases Research Center, Research Institute for Prevention of Non-Communicable Diseases, Qazvin University of Medical Sciences, Qazvin, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Karampour</LastName><ForeName>Amin</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Metabolic Diseases Research Center, Research Institute for Prevention of Non-Communicable Diseases, Qazvin University of Medical Sciences, Qazvin, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nazem-Sadati</LastName><ForeName>Seyedeh-Sara</ForeName><Initials>SS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medical Microbiology Research Center, Qazvin University of Medical Sciences, Qazvin, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Asghari</LastName><ForeName>Ali</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Social Determinants of Health Research Center, Research Institute for Prevention of Non-Communicable Diseases, Qazvin University of Medical Sciences, Qazvin, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Food Waterborne Parasitol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101762332</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2405-6766</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Blastocystis spp.</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Marine animals</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Prevalence</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Subtypes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Systematic review</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>31</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39282659</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11399649</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fawpar.2024.e00242</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2405-6766(24)00024-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Abedi S.H., Fazlzadeh A., Mollalo A., Sartip B., Mahjour S., Bahadory S., Taghipour A., Rostami A. The neglected role of Blastocystis sp. and Giardia lamblia in development of irritable bowel syndrome: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Microb. Pathog. 2022;162</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34592369</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asghari A., Sadeghipour Z., Hassanipour S., Abbasali Z., Ebrahimzadeh-Parikhani H., Hashemzaei M., Alimardani V., Hatam G. Association between Blastocystis sp. infection and immunocompromised patients: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res. 2021;28:60308–60328.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34528202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asghari A., Sadrebazzaz A., Shamsi L., Shams M. Global prevalence, subtypes distribution, zoonotic potential, and associated risk factors of Blastocystis sp. in domestic pigs (Sus domesticus) and wild boars (Sus scrofa): a systematic review and meta-analysis. Microb. Pathog. 2021;160</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34517066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asghari A., Banavand S., Akhlaghzadeh M., Shamsi L., Hatam G. First molecular identification and subtyping of Blastocystis sp. in the most consumed edible marine fish of Iran: a foodborne concern. Acta Parasitol. 2024;1–7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38183610</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asghari A., Yousefi A., Badali R., Mohammadi M.R., Shamsi L., Maleki F., Bahrami A.M. First molecular subtyping and zoonotic significance of Blastocystis sp. in dromedary (C. dromedarius) and Bactrian (C. bactrianus) camels in Iran: a molecular epidemiology and review of available literature. Vet. Med. Sci. 2024;10:e1442.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10996919</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38578271</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asghari A., Yousefi A., Mohammadi M.R., Badali R., Shamsi L., Köseoğlu A.E., Abbaszadeh A., Shams M., Mohammadi-Ghalehbin B. Comparative molecular epidemiology, subtype distribution, and zoonotic potential of Blastocystis sp. in Equus animals (horses, donkeys, and mules) in northwestern Iran. Comp. Immunol. Microbiol. Infect. Dis. 2024:102124.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38262257</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Badparva E., Ezatpour B., Mahmoudvand H., Behzadifar Masoud, Behzadifar Meysam, Kheirandish F. Prevalence and genotype analysis of blastocystis hominis in Iran: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Arch. Clin. Infect. Dis. 2017;12:1–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barati M., KarimiPour A., Rahmanian V., Bahadory S., Abdoli A., Rezanezhad H., Solhjoo K., Taghipour A. Global prevalence and subtype distribution of blastocystis sp. in rodents, birds, and water supplies: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Prev. Vet. Med. 2022:105770.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36181747</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bastaminejad S., Eskandari P., Mohammadi M.R., Shamsi L., Asghari A., Shahabi S., Omidian M., Pouryousef A., Shahriari B. Identification of Blastocystis spp. in urban rodents of different districts in southwestern Iran: subtype distribution and possible zoonotic potential. Acta Parasitol. 2024:1–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38489010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boughattas S., Al-Khater A., Albatesh D., Giraldes B.W., Abu-Madi M., Althani A.A., Benslimane F.M. Molecular investigation of waterborne protozoan contamination using marine Demospongiae. Ecol. Indic. 2024;158</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Compean J.M.C., Bustos-Martínez J., Barbabosa I., del Martínez M., Hamdan-Partida A. 2018. Detection and typing of Blastocystis spp. in oysters (Crassostrea virginica) Collected in Actopan River, Chachalacas, Veracruz.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>dos Zanetti A.S., Malheiros A.F., De Matos T.A., Longhi F.G., Moreira L.M., Silva S.L., Castrillon S.K.I., Ferreira S.M.B., Ignotti E., Espinosa O.A. Prevalence of Blastocystis sp. infection in several hosts in Brazil: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Parasit. Vectors. 2020;13:1–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6961275</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31937366</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fusaro C., Bernal J.E., Baldiris-Ávila R., González-Cuello R., Cisneros-Lorduy J., Reales-Ruiz A., Castro-Orozco R., Sarria-Guzmán Y. Molecular prevalence and subtypes distribution of Blastocystis spp. in humans of Latin America: a systematic review. Trop. Med. Infect. Dis. 2024;9:38.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10893338</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38393127</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gantois N., Lamot A., Seesao Y., Creusy C., Li L.-L., Monchy S., Benamrouz-Vanneste S., Karpouzopoulos J., Bourgain J.-L., Rault C. First report on the prevalence and subtype distribution of Blastocystis sp. in edible marine fish and marine mammals: a large scale-study conducted in Atlantic northeast and on the coasts of northern France. Microorganisms. 2020;8:460.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7144014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32213897</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guilavogui T., Gantois N., Even G., Desramaut J., Dautel E., Denoyelle C., Cissé F.I., Touré S.C., Kourouma B.L., Sawant M. Detection, molecular identification and transmission of the intestinal protozoa Blastocystis sp. in Guinea from a large-scale epidemiological study conducted in the Conakry area. Microorganisms. 2022;10:446.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8876712</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35208899</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Konig G., Müller H.E. Blastocystis hominis in animals: incidence of four serogroups. Zentralblatt für Bakteriol. 1997;286:435–440.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9361389</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumarasamy V., Rajamanikam A., Anbazhagan D., Atroosh W.M., Azzani M., Subramaniyan V., Abdullah S.R. Systematic review and Meta-analysis: epidemiology of human Blastocystis spp. infection in Malaysia. Trop. Med. Infect. Dis. 2023;8:415.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10457748</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37624353</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martínez-Barbabosa I., Gutiérrez-Cárdenas E.M., Hamdan-Partida A., Bustos-Martínez J., Shea M. Presencia de Blastocystis spp. en el molusco Crassostrea virginica, en la Ciudad de México. Rev. Salud Anim. 2018;40</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohammad N.A., Al-Mekhlafi H.M., Moktar N., Anuar T.S. Prevalence and risk factors of Blastocystis infection among underprivileged communities in rural Malaysia. Asian Pac J Trop Med. 2017;10:491–497.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28647187</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohammad N.A., Al-Mekhlafi H.M., Anuar T.S. 2018. Subtype Distribution of Blastocystis Isolated from Humans and Associated Animals in an Indigenous Community with Poor Hygiene in Peninsular Malaysia.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33601835</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moher D., Shamseer L., Clarke M., Ghersi D., Liberati A., Petticrew M., Shekelle P., Stewart L.A., Group, P.-P Preferred reporting items for systematic review and meta-analysis protocols (PRISMA-P) 2015 statement. Syst. Rev. 2015;4:1–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4320440</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25554246</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munn Z., Moola S., Riitano D., Lisy K. The development of a critical appraisal tool for use in systematic reviews addressing questions of prevalence. Int. J. Health Policy Manag. 2014;3:123.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4154549</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25197676</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murtaugh M.P., Steer C.J., Sreevatsan S., Patterson N., Kennedy S., Sriramarao P. Wiley Online Library; 2017. The Science behind One Health: At the Interface of Humans, Animals, and the Environment.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28505393</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rauff-Adedotun A.A., Syafyqah S.N., Soleha R.N., Shahida S.N., Haziqah M.T.F. Prevalence of Blastocystis sp. in freshwater fishes, poultry, and caprine from Penang, Malaysia. Vet. Parasitol. Reg. Stud. Reports. 2022;33</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35820721</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roberts T., Stark D., Harkness J., Ellis J. Update on the pathogenic potential and treatment options for Blastocystis sp. Gut Pathog. 2014;6:1–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4039988</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24883113</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rostami A., Riahi S.M., Haghighi A., Saber V., Armon B., Seyyedtabaei S.J. The role of Blastocystis sp. and Dientamoeba fragilis in irritable bowel syndrome: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Parasitol. Res. 2017;116:2361–2371.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28668983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryckman M., Gantois N., Dominguez R.G., Desramaut J., Li L.-L., Even G., Audebert C., Devos D.P., Chabé M., Certad G. Molecular identification and subtype analysis of Blastocystis sp. isolates from wild mussels (Mytilus edulis) in northern France. Microorganisms. 2024;12:710.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11051716</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38674653</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salvador F., Sulleiro E., Sánchez-Montalvá A., Alonso C., Santos J., Fuentes I., Molina I. Epidemiological and clinical profile of adult patients with Blastocystis sp. infection in Barcelona, Spain. Parasit. Vectors. 2016;9:1–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5064914</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27741951</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santin M., Figueiredo A., Molokin A., George N.S., Köster P.C., Dashti A., González-Barrio D., Carmena D., Maloney J.G. Division of Blastocystis ST10 into three new subtypes: ST42-ST44. J. Eukaryot. Microbiol. 2024;71</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37658622</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shams M., Shamsi L., Sadrebazzaz A., Asghari A., Badali R., Omidian M., Hassanipour S. A systematic review and meta-analysis on the global prevalence and subtypes distribution of Blastocystis sp. infection in cattle: a zoonotic concern. Comp. Immunol. Microbiol. Infect. Dis. 2021;76</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33930630</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shams M., Asghari A., Baniasad M., Shamsi L., Sadrebazzaz A. Blastocystis sp. in small ruminants: a universal systematic review and meta-analysis. Acta Parasitol. 2022;67:1073–1085.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35834160</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shams M., Shamsi L., Yousefi A., Sadrebazzaz A., Asghari A., Mohammadi-Ghalehbin B., Shahabi S., Hatam G. Current global status, subtype distribution and zoonotic significance of Blastocystis in dogs and cats: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Parasit. Vectors. 2022;15:225.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9215001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35733146</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shams M., Bahrami A.M., Mousivand A., Shamsi L., Asghari A., Shahabi S., Sadrebazzaz A. First molecular characterization of Blastocystis subtypes from domestic animals (sheep and cattle) and their animal-keepers in Ilam, western Iran: A zoonotic concern. J. Eukaryot. Microbiol. 2024:e13019.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38225853</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Słodkowicz-Kowalska A., Majewska A.C., Rzymski P., Skrzypczak Ł., Werner A. Human waterborne protozoan parasites in freshwater bivalves (Anodonta anatina and Unio tumidus) as potential indicators of fecal pollution in urban reservoir. Limnologica. 2015;51:32–36.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suarez P., Vallejos-Almirall A., Fernández I., Gonzalez-Chavarria I., Alonso J.L., Vidal G. Identification of Cryptosporidium parvum and Blastocystis hominis subtype ST3 in Cholga mussel and treated sewage: preliminary evidence of fecal contamination in harvesting area. Food Waterborne Parasitol. 2024;34</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10770711</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38188968</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vassalos C.M., Vakalis N., Papadopoulou C. Blastocystis and its pathogenic potential: latest aspects. Rev. Res. Med. Microbiol. 2008;19:87–97.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y., Zhang C., Nan H., Yin S., Cao M., An R., Ma L. 2024. Molecular Detection and Subtype Distribution of Blastocystis sp. in Cold-water Fish and Cultured Water.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>