<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39297357</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1097-0010</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>19</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of the science of food and agriculture</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Sci Food Agric</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Contribution of ultrasound-assisted protein structural changes in marinated beef to the improved binding ability of spices and flavor enhancement.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jsfa.13914</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Marination is an important part of air-dried beef processing, and traditional methods are inefficient and produce inconsistent results. Ultrasound, as a novel technology, can be combined with traditional marination methods. The study aimed to investigate the improvement of beef flavor by ultrasound-assisted marination. At the same time, the potential relationship between the alteration of meat protein and flavor quality by ultrasound-assisted marinating was further investigated to enable better flavor modulation and research.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Headspace solid-phase microextraction-gas chromatography-mass spectrometry revealed that the spice flavor of beef was significantly enhanced by 500 W ultrasound-assisted marination. Meanwhile, the experimental results demonstrated that the ultrasound-assisted marination promoted the unfolding of beef myofibrillar protein structure, which increased the number of hydrophobic and hydrogen bonding sites, enhanced the electrostatic effect and improved the functional properties of the protein. Ultrasound-assisted marination significantly enhanced the binding ability of beef myofibrillar proteins to flavor compounds compared with conventional marination. An electronic nose confirmed that this resulted in a significant increase in the flavor of the marinated meat.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Ultrasound-assisted marination effectively enhanced the flavor of marinated meat, which was closely related to the development of protein conformation. The results of this study have important implications for the food industry and the role of protein unfolding processes in flavor modulation. In particular, the findings can be practically applied to improving meat flavor under ultrasound-assisted marination. © 2024 Society of Chemical Industry.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Society of Chemical Industry.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Chukai</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Zhejiang Key Laboratory of Intelligent Food Logistic and Processing, State Key Laboratory for Managing Biotic and Chemical Threats to the Quality and Safety of Agro-products, Zhejiang-Malaysia Joint Research Laboratory for Agricultural Product Processing and Nutrition, College of Food Science and Engineering, Ningbo University, Ningbo, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sun</LastName><ForeName>Yangying</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7284-3558</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Zhejiang Key Laboratory of Intelligent Food Logistic and Processing, State Key Laboratory for Managing Biotic and Chemical Threats to the Quality and Safety of Agro-products, Zhejiang-Malaysia Joint Research Laboratory for Agricultural Product Processing and Nutrition, College of Food Science and Engineering, Ningbo University, Ningbo, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pan</LastName><ForeName>Daodong</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1834-7267</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Zhejiang Key Laboratory of Intelligent Food Logistic and Processing, State Key Laboratory for Managing Biotic and Chemical Threats to the Quality and Safety of Agro-products, Zhejiang-Malaysia Joint Research Laboratory for Agricultural Product Processing and Nutrition, College of Food Science and Engineering, Ningbo University, Ningbo, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Changyu</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7638-8609</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Zhejiang Key Laboratory of Intelligent Food Logistic and Processing, State Key Laboratory for Managing Biotic and Chemical Threats to the Quality and Safety of Agro-products, Zhejiang-Malaysia Joint Research Laboratory for Agricultural Product Processing and Nutrition, College of Food Science and Engineering, Ningbo University, Ningbo, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>He</LastName><ForeName>Jun</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Zhejiang Key Laboratory of Intelligent Food Logistic and Processing, State Key Laboratory for Managing Biotic and Chemical Threats to the Quality and Safety of Agro-products, Zhejiang-Malaysia Joint Research Laboratory for Agricultural Product Processing and Nutrition, College of Food Science and Engineering, Ningbo University, Ningbo, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Du</LastName><ForeName>Lihui</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Zhejiang Key Laboratory of Intelligent Food Logistic and Processing, State Key Laboratory for Managing Biotic and Chemical Threats to the Quality and Safety of Agro-products, Zhejiang-Malaysia Joint Research Laboratory for Agricultural Product Processing and Nutrition, College of Food Science and Engineering, Ningbo University, Ningbo, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>2021YFD2100103</GrantID><Agency>National Key R &amp; D Program of China</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>19</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Sci Food Agric</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0376334</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-5142</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">combining ability</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">marinating process</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">protein structure</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">spice flavor</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ultrasonic treatment</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>20</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>20</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39297357</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jsfa.13914</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Guo L, Zhang X, Guo Y, Chen Z and Ma H, Evaluation of ultrasonic‐assisted pickling with different frequencies on NaCl transport, impedance properties, and microstructure in pork. Food Chem 430:137003 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng Z, Tian M, Liao G, Chen G, Zhong Y, Yang Y et al., Evaluation of the effects of compound curing agents on the lipid profiles and volatile flavors in Nuodeng ham based on lipidomics and GC‐IMS analysis. Food Res Int 176:113810 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu Z, Yu M, Zhang J and Zhang W, Effects of ultrasonic‐assisted curing on the eating quality of lamb. J Food Eng 361:111756 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fariñas MD, Sanchez‐Jimenez V, Benedito J and Garcia‐Perez JV, Monitoring physicochemical modifications in beef steaks during dry salting using contact and non‐contact ultrasonic techniques. Meat Sci 204:109275 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Motoyama M, Sasaki K and Watanabe A, Wagyu and the factors contributing to its beef quality: a Japanese industry overview. Meat Sci 120:10–18 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duppeti H, Manjabhatta SN and Kempaiah BB, Physicochemical, structural, functional and flavor adsorption properties of white shrimp (Penaeus vannamei) proteins as affected by processing methods. Food Res Int 163:112296 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun X, Saleh ASM, Wang Z, Yu Y, Li W and Zhang D, Insights into the interactions between etheric compounds and myofibrillar proteins using multi‐spectroscopy, molecular docking, and molecular dynamics simulation. Food Res Int 175:113787 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang Q, Ren X, Qu W, Zhang X, Cheng Y and Ma H, The impact of ultrasound duration on the structure of β‐lactoglobulin. J Food Eng 292:110365 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han C, Zheng Y, Wang L, Zhou C, Wang J, He J et al., Contribution of process‐induced molten‐globule state formation in duck liver protein to the enhanced binding ability of (E, E)‐2,4‐heptadienal. J Sci Food Agric 103:3334–3345 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun X, Yu Y, Saleh ASM, Yang X, Ma J, Gao Z et al., Structural changes induced by ultrasound improve the ability of the myofibrillar protein to bind flavor compounds from spices. Ultrason Sonochem 98:106510 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xue C, You J, Zhang H, Xiong S, Yin T and Huang Q, Capacity of myofibrillar protein to adsorb characteristic fishy‐odor compounds: effects of concentration, temperature, ionic strength, pH and yeast glucan addition. Food Chem 363:130304 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin G, Liu Y, Zhang Y, Li C, He L, Zhang Y et al., Underlying formation mechanisms of ultrasound‐assisted brined porcine meat: the role of physicochemical modification, myofiber fragmentation and histological organization. Ultrason Sonochem 94:106318 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang L, Li J, Teng S, Zhang W, Purslow PP and Zhang R, Changes in collagen properties and cathepsin activity of beef M. semitendinosus by the application of ultrasound during post‐mortem aging. Meat Sci 185:108718 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li B, Zhong M, Sun Y, Liang Q, Shen L, Qayum A et al., Recent advancements in the utilization of ultrasonic technology for the curing of processed meat products: a comprehensive review. Ultrason Sonochem 103:106796 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kang D, Gao X, Ge Q, Zhou G and Zhang W, Effects of ultrasound on the beef structure and water distribution during curing through protein degradation and modification. Ultrason Sonochem 38:317–325 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu L, Xia Q, Cao J, He J, Zhou C, Guo Y et al., Ultrasonic effects on the headspace volatilome and protein isolate microstructure of duck liver, as well as their potential correlation mechanism. Ultrason Sonochem 71:105358 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>He S, Li M, Sun Y, Pan D, Zhou C and Lan H, Effects of limited enzymatic hydrolysis and polysaccharide addition on the physicochemical properties of emulsions stabilized with duck myofibrillar protein under low‐salt conditions. Food Chem 430:137053 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao K, Rao J and Chen B, Unraveling the mechanism by which high intensity ultrasound improves the solubility of commercial pea protein isolates. Food Hydrocoll 131:107823 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitra B, Rinnan Å and Ruiz‐Carrascal J, Tracking hydrophobicity state, aggregation behaviour and structural modifications of pork proteins under the influence of assorted heat treatments. Food Res Int 101:266–273 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu X, Sun X, Wei Y, Ma Y, Sun P and Li X, Effects of ultrasonic treatment on physico‐chemical properties and structure of tuna (Thunnus tonggol) myofibrillar proteins. J Food Compos Anal 108:104438 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ren X, Hou T, Liang Q, Zhang X, Hu D, Xu B et al., Effects of frequency ultrasound on the properties of zein‐chitosan complex coacervation for resveratrol encapsulation. Food Chem 279:223–230 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin W, Zhu J, Sun Y, Pan D, Xia Q, Zhou C et al., Effects of ultrasonic‐assisted marinating on degradation of beef protein and formation of flavor precursors. J Food Compos Anal 133:106407 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y, Wang B, Zhang W, Xu W and Hu Z, Effects and mechanism of dilute acid soaking with ultrasound pretreatment on rice bran protein extraction. J Cereal Sci 87:318–324 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Z, Wang Y, Pan D, Geng F, Zhou C and Cao J, Insight into the relationship between microorganism communities and flavor quality of Chinese dry‐cured boneless ham with different quality grades. Food Biosci 50:102174 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen X, Zhao H, Wang H, Xu P, Chen M, Xu Z et al., Preparation of high‐solubility rice protein using an ultrasound‐assisted glycation reaction. Food Res Int 161:111737 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang S, Zhang M, Liu H, Li Q, Xue D, Nian Y et al., Ultrasound treatment can increase digestibility of myofibrillar protein of pork with modified atmosphere packaging. Food Chem 377:131811 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun Y, Ma L, Fu Y, Dai H and Zhang Y, The improvement of gel and physicochemical properties of porcine myosin under low salt concentrations by pulsed ultrasound treatment and its mechanism. Food Res Int 141:110056 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi Z, Zhong S, Yan W, Liu M, Yang Z and Qiao X, The effects of ultrasonic treatment on the freezing rate, physicochemical quality, and microstructure of the back muscle of grass carp (Ctenopharyngodon idella). LWT 111:301–308 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deng X, Ni X, Han J, Yao W, Fang Y, Zhu Q et al., High‐intensity ultrasound modified the functional properties of Neosalanx taihuensis myofibrillar protein and improved its emulsion stability. Ultrason Sonochem 97:106458 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheng L, Wang Y, Chen J, Zou J, Wang Q and Ma M, Influence of high‐intensity ultrasound on foaming and structural properties of egg white. Food Res Int 108:604–610 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao X, Qi J, Fan C, Wang B, Yang C and Liu D, Ultrasound treatment enhanced the ability of the porcine myofibrillar protein to bind furan compounds: investigation of underlying mechanisms. Food Chem 384:132472 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu Z, Zhu W, Yi J, Liu N, Cao Y, Lu J et al., Effects of sonication on the physicochemical and functional properties of walnut protein isolate. Food Res Int 106:853–861 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao Y, Hao X, Hu Y, Zhou N, Ma Q, Zou L et al., Modification of the functional properties of chickpea proteins by ultrasonication treatment and alleviation of malnutrition in rat. Food Funct 14:1773–1784 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang J, Huang F, Huang Q, Ma D, Chen Y, Peng D et al., Physical and emulsifying properties of pea protein: influence of combined physical modification by flaxseed gum and ultrasonic treatment. Food Sci Human Wellness 12:431–441 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu Y, Yang Y, Ma C, Bian X, Ren LK, Liu B et al., The improvement of the oxidative oat (Avena sativa L.) protein based on ultrasound treatment: study of structural, emulsifying, and rheological properties. Food Hydrocoll 144:109047 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rawat R and Saini CS, High‐intensity ultrasound (HIUS) treatment of Sunnhemp protein isolate (Crotalaria juncea L.): modification of functional, structural, and microstructural properties. Food Bioprocess Technol 16:1464–1477 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang T, Han D, Zhao L, Huang F, Yang P and Zhang C, Binding of selected aroma compounds to myofibrillar protein, sarcoplasmic protein, and collagen during thermal treatment: role of conformational changes and degradation of proteins. J Agric Food Chem 71:17860–17873 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu Y, Vanga SK, Wang J and Raghavan V, Effects of ultrasonic and microwave processing on Avidin assay and secondary structures of egg white protein. Food Bioprocess Technol 11:1974–1984 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Z, Yang T, Wang Y, Liu J, Shi W, Hu H et al., Influence of multi‐frequency ultrasound treatment on conformational characteristics of beef myofibrillar proteins with different degrees of doneness. Foods 12:2926 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du J, Cao J, Zhou C, Pan D, Geng F and Wang Y, Insight into the mechanism of myosin‐fibrin gelation induced by non‐disulfide covalent cross‐linking. Food Res Int 156:111168 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Das D, Panesar PS and Saini CS, pH shifting treatment of ultrasonically extracted soybean meal protein isolate: effect on functional, structural, morphological and thermal properties. Process Biochem 120:227–238 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu L, Zheng Y, Zhou C, Pan D, Geng F, Cao J et al., Kinetic response of conformational variation of duck liver globular protein to ultrasonic stimulation and its impact on the binding behavior of n‐alkenals. LWT 150:111890 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>He Y, Zhou C, Li C and Zhou G, Effect of incubation temperature on the binding capacity of flavor compounds to myosin. Food Chem 346:128976 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang P, Wang Z, Feng X and Kan J, Promotion of fishy odor release by phenolic compounds through interactions with myofibrillar protein. Food Chem 387:132852 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu Y, Fan C, Qi J, Zhao X, Yang H, Ye G et al., Effect of ultrasound treatment on porcine myofibrillar protein binding furan flavor compounds at different salt concentrations. Food Chem 443:138427 (2024).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>