<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39296064</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>20</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2405-8440</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>17</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>15</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Heliyon</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Heliyon</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Berberine-loaded nanoemulsions as a natural food preservative; the impact of femtosecond laser irradiation on the antibacterial activity.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e37283</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e37283</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e37283</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e37283</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>There is a growing concern among food safety regulators, the food industry, and consumers about foodborne illnesses. To improve food safety and increase shelf life, it is necessary to use natural preservatives. Natural antimicrobials are safer than artificial preservatives because they can prevent microbial resistance while also meeting consumers' demands for healthier food. This study used Berberine to enhance the antibacterial activity of <i>Satureja Khuzistanica</i> essential oil nanoemulsions (SKEO NE) against <i>Staphylococcus aureus</i> (<i>S. aureus</i>) bacteria, making them a promising option as preservatives. Response Surface Methodology (RSM) was employed to determine the optimized Berberine loaded SKEO NE (Berberine/SKEO NE), resulting in a mean droplet size of 88.60 nm at 6.91, 3.21, and 0.08% w/w of surfactant, essential oil, and Berberine, respectively. Berberine utilization in SKEO NE has led to an increase in antibacterial activity. The nanoemulsion samples significantly ruptured the <i>S. aureus</i> bacterial cell membrane, rapidly discharging cell contents. The use of a microfluidic system in tandem based on the conventional approach significantly accelerated this process. Enhancing the interaction between nanodroplets and the bacterial membrane can be achieved through the nanoemulsification process of EOs, which involves modifying their surface characteristics. This enhancement is particularly pronounced when employing microfluidic systems due to their substantial contact surface area. We investigated the potential of using femtosecond laser irradiation at a wavelength of 1040 nm to augment the antibacterial action of nanoemulsions. The combined treatment of laser and nanoemulsions significantly increased the antibacterial effect of nanoemulsions by approximately 15% for each bacterium, suggesting the potential utility of this treatment to bolster the antibacterial activity of nanoemulsions. Bacteria were trapped using optical tweezers for up to 20 min, with bacterial destruction observed starting at 3 min and exhaustive destruction evident after 20 min.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Parseghian</LastName><ForeName>Liana</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Phytochemistry, Medicinal Plants and Drugs Research Institute, Shahid Beheshti University, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmaceutical Engineering, Medicinal Plants and Drugs Research Institute, Shahid Beheshti University, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kahrarian</LastName><ForeName>Nastaran</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Laser and Plasma Research Institute, Shahid Beheshti University, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Arabanian</LastName><ForeName>Atoosa Sadat</ForeName><Initials>AS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Laser and Plasma Research Institute, Shahid Beheshti University, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Moradi Alvand</LastName><ForeName>Zinab</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Phytochemistry, Medicinal Plants and Drugs Research Institute, Shahid Beheshti University, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmaceutical Engineering, Medicinal Plants and Drugs Research Institute, Shahid Beheshti University, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Massudi</LastName><ForeName>Reza</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Laser and Plasma Research Institute, Shahid Beheshti University, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rahimi</LastName><ForeName>Masoud</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmaceutical Engineering, Medicinal Plants and Drugs Research Institute, Shahid Beheshti University, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rafati</LastName><ForeName>Hasan</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmaceutical Engineering, Medicinal Plants and Drugs Research Institute, Shahid Beheshti University, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>03</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Heliyon</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101672560</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2405-8440</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Antibacterial activity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Berberine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Femtosecond laser pulses</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Nanoemulsion</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Surface modification</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39296064</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11409146</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e37283</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2405-8440(24)13314-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Amit S.K., Uddin M.M., Rahman R., Islam S.M.R., Khan M.S. A review on mechanisms and commercial aspects of food preservation and processing. Agric. Food Secur. 2017;6:1–22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maho T., Binois R., Brulé-Morabito F., Demasure M., Douat C., Dozias S., Bocanegra P.E., Goard I., Hocqueloux L., Le Helloco C., Orel I., Pouvesle J.M., Prazuck T., Stancampiano A., Tocaben C., Robert E. Anti-bacterial action of plasma multi-jets in the context of chronic wound healing. Appl. Sci. 2021;11 doi: 10.3390/app11209598.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/app11209598</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bondi M., Lauková A., de Niederhausern S., Messi P., Papadopoulou C. vol. 2017. J Food Qual; 2017. pp. 1–3. (Natural Preservatives to Improve Food Quality and Safety).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herdiana Y. Functional food in relation to gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD) Nutrients. 2023;15:3583.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10458865</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37630773</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teshome E., Forsido S.F., Rupasinghe H.P.V., Olika Keyata E. Potentials of natural preservatives to enhance food safety and shelf life: a review. Sci. World J. 2022;2022</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9525789</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36193042</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Geerlofs L., He Z., Xiao S., Xiao Z.-C. Efficacy of berberine as a preservative against mold and yeast in poultry feed, Approaches in Poultry. Dairy &amp; Veterinary Sciences. 2019;6:601–605.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mączka W., Twardawska M., Grabarczyk M., Wińska K. Carvacrol—a natural phenolic compound with antimicrobial properties. Antibiotics. 2023;12:824.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10215463</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37237727</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dai ChunMei D.C., Peng Cheng P.C., Wang JiaBo W.J., Xiao XiaoHe X.X. 2010. Dose-effect Relationship of Berberine and Analogues on Antibacterial Metabolism of Bacillus Shigae by Microcalorimetry.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shang X., Yang C., Morris‐Natschke S.L., Li J., Yin X., Liu Y., Guo X., Peng J., Goto M., Zhang J. Biologically active isoquinoline alkaloids covering 2014–2018. Med. Res. Rev. 2020;40:2212–2289.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7554109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32729169</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu S., Yang K., Hong Y., Gong Y., Ni J., Yang N., Ding W. A new perspective on the antimicrobial mechanism of berberine hydrochloride against Staphylococcus aureus revealed by untargeted metabolomic studies. Front. Microbiol. 2022;13</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9328669</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35910599</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salehi B., Selamoglu Z., Sener B., Kilic M., Kumar Jugran A., de Tommasi N., Sinisgalli C., Milella L., Rajkovic J., Morais-Braga M. Flaviana B. Berberis plants—drifting from farm to food applications, phytotherapy, and phytopharmacology. Foods. 2019;8:522.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6836240</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31652576</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaya M., Ravikumar P., Ilk S., Mujtaba M., Akyuz L., Labidi J., Salaberria A.M., Cakmak Y.S., Erkul S.K. Production and characterization of chitosan based edible films from Berberis crataegina's fruit extract and seed oil. Innovat. Food Sci. Emerg. Technol. 2018;45:287–297.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu X., Chen L., Kang Y., He D., Yang B., Wu K. Cinnamon essential oil nanoemulsions by high-pressure homogenization: formulation, stability, and antimicrobial activity. Lwt. 2021;147</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xia S., Ma L., Wang G., Yang J., Zhang M., Wang X., Su J., Xie M. In vitro antimicrobial activity and the mechanism of berberine against methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus isolated from bloodstream infection patients. Infect. Drug Resist. 2022:1933–1944.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9034846</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35469308</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Z., Chen Y., Deng J., Jia X., Zhou J., Lv H. Solid dispersion of berberine–phospholipid complex/TPGS 1000/SiO2: preparation, characterization and in vivo studies. Int J Pharm. 2014;465:306–316.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24456672</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu W., Ling P., Zhang T. Polymeric micelles, a promising drug delivery system to enhance bioavailability of poorly water‐soluble drugs. J Drug Deliv. 2013;2013</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3712247</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23936656</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taouzinet L., Djaoudene O., Fatmi S., Bouiche C., Amrane-Abider M., Bougherra H., Rezgui F., Madani K. Trends of nanoencapsulation strategy for natural compounds in the food industry. Processes. 2023;11:1459.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan Y., Sadia H., Ali Shah S.Z., Khan M.N., Shah A.A., Ullah N., Ullah M.F., Bibi H., Bafakeeh O.T., Ben Khedher N. Classification, synthetic, and characterization approaches to nanoparticles, and their applications in various fields of nanotechnology: a review. Catalysts. 2022;12:1386.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang H., Yang J., Sun R., Han S., Yang Z., Teng L. Microfluidics for nano-drug delivery systems: from fundamentals to industrialization. Acta Pharm. Sin. B. 2023;13:3277–3299.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10466004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37655333</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arbore C., Perego L., Sergides M., Capitanio M. Probing force in living cells with optical tweezers: from single-molecule mechanics to cell mechanotransduction. Biophys Rev. 2019;11:765–782.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6815294</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31612379</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Z., Kimkes T.E.P., Heinemann M. Manipulating rod-shaped bacteria with optical tweezers. Sci. Rep. 2019;9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6911073</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31836805</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang H., Liu K.-K. Optical tweezers for single cells. J R Soc Interface. 2008;5:671–690.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2408388</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18381254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Min T.L., Mears P.J., Chubiz L.M., V Rao C., Golding I., Chemla Y.R. High-resolution, long-term characterization of bacterial motility using optical tweezers. Nat. Methods. 2009;6:831–835.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2784139</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19801991</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kishimoto T., Masui K., Minoshima W., Hosokawa C. Recent advances in optical manipulation of cells and molecules for biological science. J. Photochem. Photobiol. C Photochem. Rev. 2022;53</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lele P.P., Hosu B.G., Berg H.C. Dynamics of mechanosensing in the bacterial flagellar motor. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA. 2013;110:11839–11844.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3718179</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23818629</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malyshev D., Robinson N.F., Öberg R., Dahlberg T., Andersson M. Reactive oxygen species generated by infrared laser light in optical tweezers inhibits the germination of bacterial spores. J Biophotonics. 2022;15</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35538633</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keloth A., Anderson O., Risbridger D., Paterson L. Single cell isolation using optical tweezers. Micromachines. 2018;9:434.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6187562</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30424367</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banavath H.N., Allam S.R., Valathati S.S., Sharan A., Rajasekaran B. Femtosecond laser pulse assisted photoporation for drug delivery in Chronic myelogenous leukemia cells. J. Photochem. Photobiol., B. 2018;187:35–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30098520</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goswami D. Intense femtosecond optical pulse shaping approaches to spatiotemporal control. Front. Chem. 2023;10</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9878401</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36712993</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alvand Z.M., Rahimi M., Rafati H. A microfluidic chip for visual investigation of the interaction of nanoemulsion of Satureja Khuzistanica essential oil and a model gram-negative bacteria. Int J Pharm. 2021;607</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34419590</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jafarı-sales A., Jafari B., Khaneshpour H., Pashazadeh M. Antibacterial effect of methanolic extract of rosa damascena on standard bacteria Staphylococcus aureus, Bacillus cereus, Escherichia coli and Pseudomonas aeruginosa in vitro. International Journal of Nature and Life Sciences. 2020;4:40–46.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parvekar P., Palaskar J., Metgud S., Maria R., Dutta S. The minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) and minimum bactericidal concentration (MBC) of silver nanoparticles against Staphylococcus aureus. Biomater Investig Dent. 2020;7:105–109.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7470068</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32939454</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sepahvand S., Amiri S., Radi M., Akhavan H.-R. Antimicrobial activity of thymol and thymol-nanoemulsion against three food-borne pathogens inoculated in a sausage model. Food Bioproc Tech. 2021;14:1936–1945.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang H., Song L., Sun P., Su R., Wang S., Cheng S., Zhan X., Lü X., Xia X., Shi C. Synergistic bactericidal effect of ultrasound combined with citral nanoemulsion on Salmonella and its application in the preservation of purple kale. Ultrason. Sonochem. 2023;92</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9800203</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36571884</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu M., Pan Y., Feng M., Guo W., Fan X., Feng L., Huang J., Cao Y. Garlic essential oil in water nanoemulsion prepared by high-power ultrasound: properties, stability and its antibacterial mechanism against MRSA isolated from pork. Ultrason. Sonochem. 2022;90</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9579707</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36244094</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nejabatdoust A., Baghaei Daemi H., Salehzadeh A., Azimi S.C., Darafkan S., Fallah Digsara F., Pourebrahim M., Seighalani R. Comparing of effects of hydro-alcoholic, ethanolic, and methanolic extracts of the Frangula alnus: chemical composition, antimicrobial, and synergism. Journal of Genetic Resources. 2020;6:20–33.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu P.F., Liu Z.H., Duan Y.H., Sun Q., Wang D., Zeng X.F., Wang J.X. Microfluidic controllable synthesis of monodispersed sulfur nanoparticles with enhanced antibacterial activities. Chem. Eng. J. 2020;398 doi: 10.1016/j.cej.2020.125293.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cej.2020.125293</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang D., Feng B., Li N., Su L., Wang Z., Kong F., Bi Y. Preparation, characterization, and biological activity of Cinnamomum cassia essential oil nano-emulsion. Ultrason. Sonochem. 2022;86</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9058955</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35472756</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alvand Z.M., Rahimi M., Rafati H. Interaction of a natural compound nanoemulsion with Gram negative and Gram positive bacterial membrane; a mechanism based study using a microfluidic chip and DESI technique. Int J Pharm. 2022;626</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36087628</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>V Ilina I., Sitnikov D.S. Photonics. MDPI; 2022. Application of ultrashort lasers in developmental biology: a review; p. 914.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8534476</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34679594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu X., Chen L., Kang Y., He D., Yang B., Wu K. Cinnamon essential oil nanoemulsions by high-pressure homogenization: formulation, stability, and antimicrobial activity. Lwt. 2021;147</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen C.Z., Cooper S.L. Interactions between dendrimer biocides and bacterial membranes. Biomaterials. 2002;23:3359–3368.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12099278</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woo I.-S., Rhee I.-K., Park H.-D. Differential damage in bacterial cells by microwave radiation on the basis of cell wall structure. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 2000;66:2243–2247.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC101483</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10788410</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bajpai V.K., Sharma A., Baek K. Antibacterial mechanism of action of T axus cuspidata stem essential oil against selected foodborne pathogens. J. Food Saf. 2013;33:348–359.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>