<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39293236</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-0341</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>600</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>11</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Virology</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Whole genome sequence analysis of turkey orthoreovirus isolates reveals a strong viral host-specificity and naturally occurring co-infections in commercial turkeys.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>110216</StartPage><MedlinePgn>110216</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.virol.2024.110216</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0042-6822(24)00237-X</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Avian orthoreoviruses (ARV) are an emerging threat for the poultry industry, both in the United States (US) and globally. ARV infections in turkeys have been associated with arthritis, lameness and neurological disorders, and cost the US economy approximately USD 33 million per year. There is not a commercial vaccine available and the shortage of turkey ARV (TRV) genomic data hinders the efforts to explore the molecular epidemiology of this virus, although several studies suggest a close relationship between European TRVs and TRVs present in the US. This study shows a snapshot of the genomic diversity of Avian orthoreoviruses (ARV) circulating in Germany in the mid-2000s. Through a deep genomic analysis of 18 ARV isolates recovered from sick turkeys, we observed that co-infection was a common condition. 80% of the samples showed signs of a simultaneous infection with a TRV and a chicken ARV (CRV). We believe this is the first reported evidence of CRV and TRV naturally occurring co-infections in commercial turkeys. These co-infection events were identified due to the significant genomic diversity observed among ARV infecting various production bird species. Our phylogenetic analysis revealed a consistent host-associated ARV clustering, with three main clades: (i) a TRV clade, (ii) a CRV clade, and (iii) a Duck ARV (DRV)/Goose ARV (GRV) clade. Furthermore, our findings indicate that German TRVs have interacted with their European and American counterparts, suggesting active mobilization of the virus, likely through the commercial trading of live animals. However, we also consider the potential role of migratory birds in the international movement of ARV.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024. Published by Elsevier Inc.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alvarez Narvaez</LastName><ForeName>Sonsiray</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Southeast Poultry Research Laboratories, United States Department of Agriculture, Athens, GA, USA; Department of Infectious Diseases, University of Georgia, Athens, GA, USA. Electronic address: sonsiray.alvarez@uga.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Harrell</LastName><ForeName>Telvin L</ForeName><Initials>TL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Southeast Poultry Research Laboratories, United States Department of Agriculture, Athens, GA, USA. Electronic address: Telvin.Harrell@usda.gov.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Day</LastName><ForeName>J Michael</ForeName><Initials>JM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>US Department of Agriculture, Office of Public Health Science, Laboratory Quality Assurance, Response and Coordination, Food Safety and Inspection Service, Athens, GA, USA. Electronic address: Michael.day@ars.usda.gov.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Conrad</LastName><ForeName>Steven J</ForeName><Initials>SJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Southeast Poultry Research Laboratories, United States Department of Agriculture, 934 College Station Rd, Athens, GA, 30605, USA. Electronic address: Steven.Conrad@usda.gov.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Virology</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0110674</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0042-6822</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Avian orthoreovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Chicken</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Co-infection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Host specificity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Turkey</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>48</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>48</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39293236</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.virol.2024.110216</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0042-6822(24)00237-X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>