<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39296060</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>20</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2405-8440</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>17</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>15</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Heliyon</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Heliyon</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Phenolic components from carrot (<i>Daucus carota</i> L.) pomace: Optimizing the extraction and assessing its potential antioxidant and antimicrobial activities.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e36971</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e36971</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e36971</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e36971</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Carrot pomace is a significant agricultural byproduct. Obtained during carrot juice processing. This residue is an appropriate reservoir of constituents with bioactive properties that could be investigated in the development of food constituents and nutritional supplements and in improving the quality and safety of foods. For this purpose, the objective of the present investigation was to extract the polyphenols from carrot pomace utilizing maceration and ultrasound-based extraction (UAE) procedures and to evaluate the antioxidant properties of phenolic constituents. To maximize the extraction of carrot pomace, a response surface approach was used. The optimal mixture of extraction time (A, min), ultrasonication power (B, w), and solvent type (C, v/v) for the highest yield of carrot pomace was found using a three-variable composite rotatable design (CRD). In order to assess different functional groups, Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy was utilized to investigate the extract collected under optimal circumstances. The highest polyphenols (26.53 %) were extracted by ethanol 70 % at 10 min with a sonication power of 250 w. The optimized extract also exhibited significant antioxidant and antimicrobial functions. The total phenolic compounds and scavenging of the DPPH radical were 85 mg GAE/gr and EC<sub>50</sub>: 55 ± 1 μg/mL, respectively. Together with <i>Staphylococcus aureus</i>, the highest zone of inhibition (12 mm) was identified. Our finding revealed that carrot pomace is an appropriate source of bioactive phenolic constituents, exhibiting antioxidant and antibacterial attributes, and could be applied as a natural preserver for promoting safety and quality properties in food products on an industrial scale.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sabahi</LastName><ForeName>Sahar</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science &amp; Technology, Faculty of Agriculture, Ferdowsi University of Mashhad, Mashhad, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nutrition, School of Allied Medical Sciences, Ahvaz Jundishapur University of Medical Sciences, Ahvaz, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abbasi</LastName><ForeName>Amin</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Technology, National Nutrition and Food Technology Research Institute, Faculty of Nutrition Science and Food Technology, Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mortazavi</LastName><ForeName>Seyed Ali</ForeName><Initials>SA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science &amp; Technology, Faculty of Agriculture, Ferdowsi University of Mashhad, Mashhad, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Heliyon</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101672560</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2405-8440</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Antimicrobial activity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Antioxidant activity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Carrot pomace</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Food safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Maceration</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Optimization</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Ultrasound-assisted extraction</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39296060</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11408792</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e36971</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2405-8440(24)13002-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Polat S., Guclu G., Kelebek H., Keskin M., Selli S. Comparative elucidation of colour, volatile and phenolic profiles of black carrot (Daucus carota L.) pomace and powders prepared by five different drying methods. Food Chem. 2022;369</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34479009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Panzella L., Moccia F., Nasti R., Marzorati S., Verotta L., Napolitano A. Bioactive phenolic compounds from agri-food wastes: an update on green and sustainable extraction methodologies. Front. Nutr. 2020;7:60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7221145</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32457916</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guaita M., Bosso A. Polyphenolic characterization of grape skins and seeds of four Italian red cultivars at harvest and after fermentative maceration. Foods. 2019;8(9):395.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6770923</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31500205</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iqbal A., Schulz P., Rizvi S.S. Valorization of bioactive compounds in fruit pomace from agro-fruit industries: present Insights and future challenges. Food Biosci. 2021;44</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu D.-P., Li Y., Meng X., Zhou T., Zhou Y., Zheng J., Zhang J.-J., Li H.-B. Natural antioxidants in foods and medicinal plants: extraction, assessment and resources. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 2017;18(1):96.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5297730</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28067795</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar N., Goel N. Phenolic acids: natural versatile molecules with promising therapeutic applications. Biotechnology Reports. 2019;24</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6734135</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31516850</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pang S.F., Yusoff M., Gimbun J. Extraction and microencapsulation of polyphenols from Orthosiphon stamineus leaves. J. Mech. Eng. Sci. 2014;7:1033–1041.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saini A., Panesar P.S., Bera M.B. Valorization of fruits and vegetables waste through green extraction of bioactive compounds and their nanoemulsions-based delivery system. Bioresources and Bioprocessing. 2019;6(1):1–12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nastić N., Borrás-Linares I., Lozano-Sánchez J., Švarc-Gajić J., Segura-Carretero A. Comparative assessment of phytochemical profiles of comfrey (Symphytum officinale L.) root extracts obtained by different extraction techniques. Molecules. 2020;25(4):837.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7070662</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32075048</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agcam E., Akyıldız A., Kamat S., Balasubramaniam V. Bioactive compounds extraction from the black carrot pomace with assistance of high pressure processing: an optimization study. Waste and Biomass Valorization. 2021:1–19.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Safdar M.N., Kausar T., Jabbar S., Mumtaz A., Ahad K., Saddozai A.A. Extraction and quantification of polyphenols from kinnow (Citrus reticulate L.) peel using ultrasound and maceration techniques. J. Food Drug Anal. 2017;25(3):488–500.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9328816</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28911634</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abbasi A., Hashemi M., Kafil H.S., Astamal M.A., Lahouty M., Tajani A.G., Hosseini H., Nasirifar S.Z. A critical review on the bioavailability promotion of the food bioactive compounds: nano lipid carriers perspective. Pharmaceut. Sci. 2024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ranjha M.M.A.N., Amjad S., Ashraf S., Khawar L., Safdar M.N., Jabbar S., Nadeem M., Mahmood S., Murtaza M.A. Extraction of polyphenols from apple and pomegranate peels employing different extraction techniques for the development of functional date bars. Int. J. Fruit Sci. 2020;20(sup3):S1201–S1221.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar K., Srivastav S., Sharanagat V.S. Ultrasound assisted extraction (UAE) of bioactive compounds from fruit and vegetable processing by-products: a review. Ultrason. Sonochem. 2021;70</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7786612</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32920300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abbasi A., Rad A.H., Maleki L.A., Kafil H.S., Baghbanzadeh A. Antigenotoxicity and cytotoxic potentials of cell-free supernatants derived from Saccharomyces cerevisiae var. boulardii on HT-29 human colon cancer cell lines. Probiotics and Antimicrobial Proteins. 2023;15(6):1583–1595.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36588138</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perussello C.A., Zhang Z., Marzocchella A., Tiwari B.K. Valorization of apple pomace by extraction of valuable compounds. Compr. Rev. Food Sci. Food Saf. 2017;16(5):776–796.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33371603</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sánchez-Rangel J.C., Benavides J., Jacobo-Velázquez D.A. Valorization of carrot pomace: UVC induced accumulation of antioxidant phenolic compounds. Appl. Sci. 2021;11(22)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bamba B.S.B., Shi J., Tranchant C.C., Xue S.J., Forney C.F., Lim L.-T. Influence of extraction conditions on ultrasound-assisted recovery of bioactive phenolics from blueberry pomace and their antioxidant activity. Molecules. 2018;23(7):1685.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6099992</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29997308</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vorobyova V., Vasyliev G., Skiba M. Eco-friendly “green” synthesis of silver nanoparticles with the black currant pomace extract and its antibacterial, electrochemical, and antioxidant activity. Appl. Nanosci. 2020;10:4523–4534.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Szymańska-Chargot M., Chylińska M., Pieczywek P.M., Walkiewicz A., Pertile G., Frąc M., Cieślak K.J., Zdunek A. Evaluation of nanocomposite made of polylactic acid and nanocellulose from carrot pomace modified with silver nanoparticles. Polymers. 2020;12(4):812.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7240409</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32260337</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu Y., Burton S., Kim C., Sismour E. Phenolic compounds, antioxidant, and antibacterial properties of pomace extracts from four Virginia‐grown grape varieties. Food Sci. Nutr. 2016;4(1):125–133.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4708636</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26788319</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabahi S., Abbasi A., Mortazavi S.A. Characterization of cinnamon essential oil and its application in Malva sylvestris seed mucilage edible coating to the enhancement of the microbiological, physicochemical and sensory properties of lamb meat during storage. J. Appl. Microbiol. 2022;133(2):488–502.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35429123</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abbasi A., Sabahi S., Bazzaz S., Tajani A.G., Lahouty M., Aslani R., Hosseini H. An edible coating utilizing Malva sylvestris seed polysaccharide mucilage and postbiotic from Saccharomyces cerevisiae var. boulardii for the preservation of lamb meat. Int. J. Biol. Macromol. 2023;246</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37399877</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaur S., Panesar P.S., Chopra H.K. Standardization of ultrasound-assisted extraction of bioactive compounds from kinnow Mandarin peel. Biomass Conversion and Biorefinery. 2021:1–11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dent M., Dragović-Uzelac V., Penić M., Bosiljkov T., Levaj B. The effect of extraction solvents, temperature and time on the composition and mass fraction of polyphenols in Dalmatian wild sage (Salvia officinalis L.) extracts. Food Technol. Biotechnol. 2013;51(1):84–91.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma Y., Ye X., Hao Y., Xu G., Xu G., Liu D. Ultrasound-assisted extraction of hesperidin from Penggan (Citrus reticulata) peel. Ultrason. Sonochem. 2008;15(3):227–232.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17584518</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yingngam B., Monschein M., Brantner A. Ultrasound-assisted extraction of phenolic compounds from Cratoxylum formosum ssp. formosum leaves using central composite design and evaluation of its protective ability against H2O2-induced cell death. Asian Pac. J. Tropical Med. 2014;7:S497–S505.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25312174</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan Z., Qu W., Ma H., Atungulu G.G., McHugh T.H. Continuous and pulsed ultrasound-assisted extractions of antioxidants from pomegranate peel. Ultrason. Sonochem. 2011;18(5):1249–1257.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21317015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martino E., Ramaiola I., Urbano M., Bracco F., Collina S. Microwave-assisted extraction of coumarin and related compounds from Melilotus officinalis (L.) Pallas as an alternative to Soxhlet and ultrasound-assisted extraction. J. Chromatogr., A. 2006;1125(2):147–151.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16769080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al Jitan S., Alkhoori S.A., Yousef L.F. Phenolic acids from plants: extraction and application to human health. Stud. Nat. Prod. Chem. 2018;58:389–417.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bubalo M.C., Ćurko N., Tomašević M., Ganić K.K., Redovniković I.R. Green extraction of grape skin phenolics by using deep eutectic solvents. Food Chem. 2016;200:159–166.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26830574</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharmila G., Nikitha V., Ilaiyarasi S., Dhivya K., Rajasekar V., Kumar N.M., Muthukumaran K., Muthukumaran C. Ultrasound assisted extraction of total phenolics from Cassia auriculata leaves and evaluation of its antioxidant activities. Ind. Crop. Prod. 2016;84:13–21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu Z., Guan Q., Koubaa M., Barba F.J., Roohinejad S., Cravotto G., Yang X., Li S., He J. HPLC-DAD-ESI-MS2 analytical profile of extracts obtained from purple sweet potato after green ultrasound-assisted extraction. Food Chem. 2017;215:391–400.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27542491</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Skіba М., Pivovarov О., Makarova A., Vorobyova V. Plasmochemical preparation of silver nanoparticles: thermodynamics and kinetics analysis of the process, Восточно-Европейский журнал передовых технологий. 2018;2(6):4–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang T., Guo N., Wang S.-X., Kou P., Zhao C.-J., Fu Y.-J. Ultrasound-negative pressure cavitation extraction of phenolic compounds from blueberry leaves and evaluation of its DPPH radical scavenging activity. Food Bioprod. Process. 2018;108:69–80.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khoshdouni Farahani Z., H Mousavi M.A. The effect of extraction conditions using ultrasonic and maceration methods on the extraction rate of phenolic compounds and the extraction efficiency of jujube fruit (Ziziphus spp.) Applied Biology. 2021;11(41):23–40.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moeini A., Mortazavi S.A., Sharifi A. Extraction of phenolic compounds from Agrimonia eupatoria using microwave and ultrasound-assisted extraction methods. Journal of Food and Bioprocess Engineering. 2022</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amin S., Jung S., Kang I., Duval A. Valorization of baby carrot processing waste. J. Culin. Sci. Technol. 2021:1–17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamiloglu S., Capanoglu E., Bilen F.D., Gonzales G.B., Grootaert C., Van de Wiele T., Van Camp J. Bioaccessibility of polyphenols from plant-processing byproducts of black carrot (Daucus carota L.) J. Agric. Food Chem. 2016;64(12):2450–2458.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26262673</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gulsunoglu Z., Karbancioglu-Guler F., Raes K., Kilic-Akyilmaz M. Soluble and insoluble-bound phenolics and antioxidant activity of various industrial plant wastes. Int. J. Food Prop. 2019;22(1):1501–1510.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tiwari S., Upadhyay N., Singh A.K., Meena G.S., Arora S. Organic solvent-free extraction of carotenoids from carrot bio-waste and its physico-chemical properties. J. Food Sci. Technol. 2019;56:4678–4687.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6801288</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31686699</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Čanadanović-Brunet J.M., Savatović S.S., Ćetković G.S., Vulić J.J., Djilas S.M., Markov S.L., Cvetković D.D. Antioxidant and antimicrobial activities of beet root pomace extracts. Czech J. Food Sci. 2011;29(6):575–585.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar T., Jain V. Appraisal of total phenol, flavonoid contents, and antioxidant potential of folkloric Lannea coromandelica using in vitro and in vivo assays. Sci. Tech. Rep. 2015;2015</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4589636</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26457224</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tumbas Šaponjac V., Čanadanović-Brunet J., Ćetković G., Jakišić M., Djilas S., Vulić J., Stajčić S. Encapsulation of beetroot pomace extract: RSM optimization, storage and gastrointestinal stability. Molecules. 2016;21(5):584.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6273385</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27144556</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vasyliev G.S., Vorobyova V.I., Linyucheva O.V. Evaluation of reducing ability and antioxidant activity of fruit pomace extracts by spectrophotometric and electrochemical methods. Journal of Analytical Methods in Chemistry. 2020;2020:1–16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7787820</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33489417</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaur N., Aggarwal P. Development and characterisation of packing, microstructural, physico‐and phytochemical attributes of potential functional jamun (Syzygium cumini L.) pomace powder for direct compression: high antioxidant nutraceutical tablets. Int. J. Food Sci. Technol. 2022</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vasyliev G.S., Vorobyova V.I., Linyucheva O.V. Evaluation of reducing ability and antioxidant activity of fruit pomace extracts by spectrophotometric and electrochemical methods. Journal of Analytical Methods in Chemistry. 2020;2020(1)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7787820</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33489417</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silva V., Igrejas G., Falco V., Santos T.P., Torres C., Oliveira A.M., Pereira J.E., Amaral J.S., Poeta P. Chemical composition, antioxidant and antimicrobial activity of phenolic compounds extracted from wine industry by-products. Food Control. 2018;92:516–522.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vodnar D.C., Călinoiu L.F., Dulf F.V., Ştefănescu B.E., Crişan G., Socaciu C. Identification of the bioactive compounds and antioxidant, antimutagenic and antimicrobial activities of thermally processed agro-industrial waste. Food Chem. 2017;231:131–140.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28449989</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheaib D., Raafat K., El Darra N. Evaluation of phenolic content, antiradical and antibacterial activities of orange and carrot pomace extracts. BAU Journal-Health and Wellbeing. 2019;1(2):1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nirmala J.G., Narendhirakannan R. In vitro antioxidant and antimicrobial activities of grapes (Vitis vinifera L) seed and skin extracts–Muscat variety. Int. J. Pharm. Pharmaceut. Sci. 2011;3(4):242–249.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng V.J., Bekhit A.E.-D.A., McConnell M., Mros S., Zhao J. Effect of extraction solvent, waste fraction and grape variety on the antimicrobial and antioxidant activities of extracts from wine residue from cool climate. Food Chem. 2012;134(1):474–482.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vorobyova V., Vasyliev G., Uschapovskiy D., Lyudmyla K., Skiba M. Green synthesis, characterization of silver nanoparticals for biomedical application and environmental remediation. J. Microbiol. Methods. 2022;193</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34826520</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Behbahani B.A., Yazdi F.T., Mortazavi A., Gholian M.M., Zendeboodi F., Vasiee A. Antimicrobial effect of Carboxy Methyl Cellulose (CMC) containing aqueous and ethanolic Eucalyptus camaldulensis L. leaves extract against Streptococcus pyogenes, Pseudomonas aeruginosa and Staphylococcus epidermidis. Archives of Advances in Biosciences. 2014;5(2)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gnanamani A., Hariharan P., Paul-Satyaseela M. Staphylococcus aureus: overview of bacteriology, clinical diseases, epidemiology, antibiotic resistance and therapeutic approach. Frontiers in Staphylococcus aureus. 2017;4(28):10.5772.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barcella L., Barbaro A.P., Rogolino S.B. Colonial morphology of Escherichia coli: impact of detection in clinical specimens. Microbiologia Medica. 2016;31(2)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee M.-W., Hung C.-L., Cheng J.-C., Wang Y.-J. A new anti-adhesion film synthesized from polygalacturonic acid with 1-ethyl-3-(3-dimethylaminopropyl) carbodiimide crosslinker. Biomaterials. 2005;26(18):3793–3799.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15626427</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>