<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39296292</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>20</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1664-302X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>15</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Frontiers in microbiology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Front Microbiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Quantitative assessment and genomic profiling of <i>Campylobacter</i> dynamics in poultry processing: a case study in the United Arab Emirates integrated abattoir system.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1439424</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1439424</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1439424</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3389/fmicb.2024.1439424</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>In the United Arab Emirates, no previous research has investigated the dynamics of the foodborne pathogen <i>Campylobacter</i> in broiler abattoir processing. This study conducted in one of the largest poultry producers in the UAE, following each key slaughter stage-defeathering, evisceration, and final chilling-five broiler carcasses were collected from 10 slaughter batches over a year. Additionally, one caecum was obtained from 15 chickens in each slaughter batch to evaluate the flock colonization. In total, 300 samples (150 carcasses and 150 caeca) were collected and enumerated for <i>Campylobacter</i> using standard methods. <i>Campylobacter</i> was pervasive in caecal samples from all slaughter batches, with 86% of carcasses post-defeathering and evisceration stages and 94% post-chilling tested positive for <i>Campylobacter</i>. <i>Campylobacter coli</i> predominates in 55.2% of positive samples, followed by <i>Campylobacter jejuni</i> in 21%, with both species co-existing in 23.8% of the samples. <i>Campylobacter</i> counts in caecal contents ranged from 6.7 to 8.5 log<sub>10</sub> CFU/g, decreasing post-defeathering and evisceration to 3.5 log<sub>10</sub> CFU/g of neck skin and further to 3.2 log<sub>10</sub> CFU/g of neck skin post-evisceration. After chilling, 70% of carcasses exceeded 3 log<sub>10</sub> CFU/g of neck skin. Whole-genome sequencing (WGS) of 48 isolates unveiled diverse sequence types and clusters, with isolates sharing the same clusters (less than 20 single nucleotide polymorphisms) between different farms, different flocks within the same farm, as well as in consecutive slaughter batches, indicating cross-contamination. Multiple antimicrobial resistance genes and mutations in <i>gyrA</i> T86I (conferring fluoroquinolone resistance) and an RNA mutation (23S r.2075; conferring macrolide resistance) were widespread, with variations between <i>C. coli</i> and <i>C. jejuni</i>. WGS results revealed that selected virulence genes (<i>pglG, pseD, pseI, flaA, flaB, cdtA,</i> and <i>cdtC</i>) were significantly present in <i>C. jejuni</i> compared to <i>C. coli</i> isolates. This study offers the first insights into <i>Campylobacter</i> dynamics in poultry processing in the UAE. This work provides a base for future research to explore additional contributors to <i>Campylobacter</i> contamination in primary production. In conclusion, effective <i>Campylobacter</i> management demands a comprehensive approach addressing potential contamination sources at every production and processing stage, guided by continued microbiological surveillance and genomic analysis to safeguard public health and food safety.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Habib, Mohamed, Lakshmi, Al Marzooqi, Afifi, Shehata, Khan, Ghazawi, Abdalla and Anes.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Habib</LastName><ForeName>Ihab</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Veterinary Public Health Research Laboratory, Department of Veterinary Medicine, College of Agriculture and Veterinary Medicine, United Arab Emirates University, Al Ain, United Arab Emirates.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>ASPIRE Research Institute for Food Security in the Drylands (ARIFSID), United Arab Emirates University, Al Ain, United Arab Emirates.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Mohamed</LastName><ForeName>Mohamed-Yousif Ibrahim</ForeName><Initials>MI</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Veterinary Public Health Research Laboratory, Department of Veterinary Medicine, College of Agriculture and Veterinary Medicine, United Arab Emirates University, Al Ain, United Arab Emirates.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lakshmi</LastName><ForeName>Glindya Bhagya</ForeName><Initials>GB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Veterinary Public Health Research Laboratory, Department of Veterinary Medicine, College of Agriculture and Veterinary Medicine, United Arab Emirates University, Al Ain, United Arab Emirates.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Al Marzooqi</LastName><ForeName>Hassan Mohamed</ForeName><Initials>HM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Research Section, Applied Research and Capacity Building Division, Agriculture and Food Safety Authority (ADAFSA), Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Afifi</LastName><ForeName>Hanan Sobhy</ForeName><Initials>HS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Research Section, Applied Research and Capacity Building Division, Agriculture and Food Safety Authority (ADAFSA), Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shehata</LastName><ForeName>Mohamed Gamal</ForeName><Initials>MG</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Research Section, Applied Research and Capacity Building Division, Agriculture and Food Safety Authority (ADAFSA), Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Technology Department, Arid Lands Cultivation Research Institute (ALCRI), City of Scientific Research and Technological Applications (SRTACITY), Alexandria, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khan</LastName><ForeName>Mushtaq</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Microbiology and Immunology, College of Medicine and Health Sciences, United Arab Emirates University, Al Ain, United Arab Emirates.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ghazawi</LastName><ForeName>Akela</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Microbiology and Immunology, College of Medicine and Health Sciences, United Arab Emirates University, Al Ain, United Arab Emirates.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abdalla</LastName><ForeName>Afra</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Veterinary Public Health Research Laboratory, Department of Veterinary Medicine, College of Agriculture and Veterinary Medicine, United Arab Emirates University, Al Ain, United Arab Emirates.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Anes</LastName><ForeName>Febin</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Veterinary Public Health Research Laboratory, Department of Veterinary Medicine, College of Agriculture and Veterinary Medicine, United Arab Emirates University, Al Ain, United Arab Emirates.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Front Microbiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101548977</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1664-302X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Campylobacter</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">United Arab Emirates</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">chicken meat</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">enumeration</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">slaughterhouse</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">whole genome sequencing</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest. The author(s) declared that they were an editorial board member of Frontiers, at the time of submission. This had no impact on the peer review process and the final decision.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>55</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39296292</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11408311</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2024.1439424</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Allen V. M., Bull S. A., Corry J. E., Domingue G., Jørgensen F., Frost J. A., et al. . (2007). Campylobacter spp. contamination of chicken carcasses during processing in relation to flock colonisation. Int. J. Food Microbiol. 113, 54–61. doi: 10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2006.07.011, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2006.07.011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17007949</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asuming-Bediako N., Parry-Hanson Kunadu A., Abraham S., Habib I. (2019). Campylobacter at the human-food Interface: the African perspective. Pathogens 8:87. doi: 10.3390/pathogens8020087, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/pathogens8020087</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6631673</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31242594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Awad A., Yeh H. Y., Ramadan H., Rothrock M. J. (2023). Genotypic characterization, antimicrobial susceptibility and virulence determinants of Campylobacter jejuni and Campylobacter coli isolated from pastured poultry farms. Front. Microbiol. 14:1271551. doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2023.1271551, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2023.1271551</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10668334</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38029099</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>CDC  (2019). Preliminary incidence and trends of infections with pathogens transmitted commonly through food — foodborne diseases active surveillance network, 10 U.S. sites, 2016–2019 MMWR Morb mortal. Available at: https://www.cdc.gov/foodnet/reports/prelim-data-intro-2019.html (Accessed March 30, 2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7206985</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32352955</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dahl L. G., Joensen K. G., Østerlund M. T., Kiil K., Nielsen E. M. (2021). Prediction of antimicrobial resistance in clinical Campylobacter jejuni isolates from whole-genome sequencing data. Eur. J. Clin. Microbiol. Infect. Dis. 40, 673–682. doi: 10.1007/s10096-020-04043-y, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10096-020-04043-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7979593</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32974772</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duarte A. S., Nauta M. J. (2015). Impact of microbial count distributions on human health risk estimates. Int. J. Food Microbiol. 195, 48–57. doi: 10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2014.11.024, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2014.11.024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25506750</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA  (2020). Update and review of control options for Campylobacter in broilers at primary production. Available at: https://www.efsa.europa.eu/en/efsajournal/pub/6090 (Accessed March 20, 2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7448041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32874298</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feldgarden M., Brover V., Gonzalez-Escalona N., Frye J. G., Haendiges J., Haft D. H., et al. . (2021). AMRFinderPlus and the reference gene catalog facilitate examination of the genomic links among antimicrobial resistance, stress response, and virulence. Sci. Rep. 11:12728. doi: 10.1038/s41598-021-91456-0, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-91456-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8208984</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34135355</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Foddai A., Takeuchi-Storm N., Høg B. B., Kjeldgaard J. S., Andersen J. K., Ellis-Iversen J. (2022). Assessing Campylobacter cross-contamination of Danish broiler flocks at slaughterhouses considering true flock prevalence estimates and ad-hoc sampling. Microb. Risk Anal. 21:100214. doi: 10.1016/j.mran.2022.100214</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.mran.2022.100214</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fourment M., Gibbs M. J. (2006). PATRISTIC: a program for calculating patristic distances and graphically comparing the components of genetic change. BMC Evol. Biol. 6:1. doi: 10.1186/1471-2148-6-1, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1471-2148-6-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1352388</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16388682</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Habib I., Coles J., Fallows M., Goodchild S. (2019). A baseline quantitative survey of Campylobacter spp. on retail chicken portions and carcasses in metropolitan Perth, Western Australia. Foodborne Pathog. Dis. 16, 180–186. doi: 10.1089/fpd.2018.2554, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/fpd.2018.2554</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30457884</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Habib I., Ibrahim Mohamed M. Y., Ghazawi A., Lakshmi G. B., Khan M., Li D., et al. . (2023). Genomic characterization of molecular markers associated with antimicrobial resistance and virulence of the prevalent Campylobacter coli isolated from retail chicken meat in the United Arab Emirates. Curr. Res. Food Sci. 6:100434. doi: 10.1016/j.crfs.2023.100434, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.crfs.2023.100434</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9850066</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36687171</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Habib I., Mohamed M. I., Khan M. (2021). Current state of Salmonella, Campylobacter and Listeria in the food chain across the Arab countries: a descriptive review. Foods 10:2369. doi: 10.3390/foods10102369, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods10102369</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8535026</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34681418</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Habib I., Mohamed M. Y. I., Lakshmi G. B., Khan M., Li D. (2022). Quantification of Campylobacter contamination on chicken carcasses sold in retail markets in the United Arab Emirates. Food Contaminat. 9:95. doi: 10.1186/s40550-022-00095-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40550-022-00095-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hakeem M. J., Lu X. (2021). Survival and control of Campylobacter in poultry production environment. Front. Cell. Infect. Microbiol. 10:615049. doi: 10.3389/fcimb.2020.615049, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2020.615049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7879573</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33585282</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hansson I., Sandberg M., Habib I., Lowman R., Engvall E. O. (2018). Knowledge gaps in control of Campylobacter for prevention of campylobacteriosis. Transbound. Emerg. Dis. 65, 30–48. doi: 10.1111/tbed.12870, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/tbed.12870</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29663680</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hasan N. A., Davidson R. M., Epperson L. E., Kammlade S. M., Beagle S., Levin A. R., et al. . (2021). Population genomics and inference of Mycobacterium avium complex clusters in cystic fibrosis care centers, United States. Emerg. Infect. Dis. 27, 2836–2846. doi: 10.3201/eid2711.210124, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3201/eid2711.210124</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8544995</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34670648</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ISO  (2017). Microbiology of food and animal feeding stuffs – horizontal method for detection and enumeration of Campylobacter spp. – part 1: detection method (ISO 10272-1, 2006). Available at: https://www.iso.org/standard/63228.html (Accessed May 5, 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keener K. M., Bashor M. P., Curtis P. A., Sheldon B. W., Kathariou S. (2004). Comprehensive review of Campylobacter and poultry processing. Compr. Rev. Food Sci. Food Saf. 3, 105–116. doi: 10.1111/j.1541-4337.2004.tb00060.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1541-4337.2004.tb00060.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33430546</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lassen B., Takeuchi-Storm N., Henri C., Hald T., Sandberg M., Ellis-Iversen J. (2023). Analysis of reservoir sources of Campylobacter isolates to free-range broilers in Denmark. Poult. Sci. 102:103025. doi: 10.1016/j.psj.2023.103025, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2023.103025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10485630</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37672837</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leone C., Xu X., Mishra A., Thippareddi H., Singh M. (2024). Interventions to reduce Salmonella and Campylobacter during chilling and post-chilling stages of poultry processing: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Poult. Sci. 103:103492. doi: 10.1016/j.psj.2024.103492, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2024.103492</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10864810</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38335673</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moilanen T., Lehtinen J., Visuri K., Sihvonen S. (2024). Solu – a cloud platform for real-time genomic pathogen surveillance. BioRxiv. doi: 10.1101/2024.05.30.596434</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/2024.05.30.596434</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nagel G. M., Bauermeister L. J., Bratcher C. L., Singh M., McKee S. R. (2013). Salmonella and Campylobacter reduction and quality characteristics of poultry carcasses treated with various antimicrobials in a post-chill immersion tank. Int. J. Food Microbiol. 165, 281–286. doi: 10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2013.05.016, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2013.05.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23800739</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nelson J. M., Chiller T. M., Powers J. H., Angulo F. J. (2007). Fluoroquinolone-resistant Campylobacter species and the withdrawal of fluoroquinolones from use in poultry: a public health success story. Clin. Infect. Dis. 44, 977–980. doi: 10.1086/512369, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1086/512369</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17342653</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Normand V., Boulianne M., Quessy S. (2008). Evidence of cross-contamination by Campylobacter spp. of broiler carcasses using genetic characterization of isolates. Canad. J. Vet. Res.
72, 396–402. Available at: https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2568043/
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2568043</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19086371</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pacholewicz E., Dame-Korevaar A., van der Most M., Ellen H., Bokma M. H., Koene M. G. J. (2024). Campylobacter presence on Dutch broiler farms and associated risk factors. Poult. Sci. 103:103568. doi: 10.1016/j.psj.2024.103568, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2024.103568</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11067780</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38447312</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pacholewicz E., Swart A., Schipper M., Gortemaker B. G., Wagenaar J. A., Havelaar A. H., et al. . (2015). A comparison of fluctuations of Campylobacter and Escherichia coli concentrations on broiler chicken carcasses during processing in two slaughterhouses. Int. J. Food Microbiol. 205, 119–127. doi: 10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2015.04.006, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2015.04.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25950748</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prendergast D. M., Lynch H., Whyte P., Golden O., Murphy D., Gutierrez M., et al. . (2022). Genomic diversity, virulence and source of Campylobacter jejuni contamination in Irish poultry slaughterhouses by whole genome sequencing. J. Appl. Microbiol. 133, 3150–3160. doi: 10.1111/jam.15753, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jam.15753</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9804324</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35993276</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rasschaert G., De Zutter L., Herman L., Heyndrickx M. (2020). Campylobacter contamination of broilers: the role of transport and slaughterhouse. Int. J. Food Microbiol. 322:108564. doi: 10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2020.108564, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2020.108564</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32163798</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robyn J., Rasschaert G., Pasmans F., Heyndrickx M. (2015). Thermotolerant Campylobacter during broiler rearing: risk factors and intervention. Compr. Rev. Food Sci. Food Saf. 14, 81–105. doi: 10.1111/1541-4337.12124, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.12124</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33401809</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenquist H., Boysen L., Krogh A. L., Jensen A. N., Nauta M. (2013). Campylobacter contamination and the relative risk of illness from organic broiler meat in comparison with conventional broiler meat. Int. J. Food Microbiol. 162, 226–230. doi: 10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2013.01.022</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2013.01.022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23454812</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rossler E., Olivero C., Soto L. P., Frizzo L. S., Zimmermann J., Rosmini M. R., et al. . (2020). Prevalence, genotypic diversity and detection of virulence genes in thermotolerant Campylobacter at different stages of the poultry meat supply chain. Int. J. Food Microbiol. 326:108641. doi: 10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2020.108641, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2020.108641</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32371295</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seliwiorstow T., Baré J., Van Damme I., Uyttendaele M., De Zutter L. (2015). Campylobacter carcass contamination throughout the slaughter process of Campylobacter-positive broiler batches. Int. J. Food Microbiol. 194, 25–31. doi: 10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2014.11.004, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2014.11.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25461605</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tegtmeyer N., Sharafutdinov I., Harrer A., Soltan Esmaeili D., Linz B., Backert S. (2021). Campylobacter virulence factors and molecular host-pathogen interactions. Curr. Top. Microbiol. Immunol. 431, 169–202. doi: 10.1007/978-3-030-65481-8_7, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-65481-8_7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33620652</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>USDA , (2021). Poultry and products annual. Available at: https://www.fas.usda.gov/data/united-arab-emirates-poultry-and-products-annual-2. (Accessed January 12, 2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vinueza-Burgos C., Cevallos M., Cisneros M., Van Damme I., De Zutter L. (2018). Quantification of the Campylobacter contamination on broiler carcasses during the slaughter of Campylobacter positive flocks in semi-industrialized slaughterhouses. Int. J. Food Microbiol. 269, 75–79. doi: 10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2018.01.021, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2018.01.021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29421361</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vinueza-Burgos C., Wautier M., Martiny D., Cisneros M., Van Damme I., De Zutter L. (2017). Prevalence, antimicrobial resistance and genetic diversity of Campylobacter coli and Campylobacter jejuni in Ecuadorian broilers at slaughter age. Poult. Sci. 96, 2366–2374. doi: 10.3382/ps/pew487, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3382/ps/pew487</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5850218</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28339716</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao J., Cheng Y., Zhang W., Lu Q., Guo Y., Hu Q., et al. . (2023). Genetic characteristics, antimicrobial susceptibility, and virulence genes distribution of Campylobacter isolated from local dual-purpose chickens in Central China. Front. Cell. Infect. Microbiol. 13:1236777. doi: 10.3389/fcimb.2023.1236777, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2023.1236777</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10517862</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37743858</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Q., Lin J., Pereira S. (2003). Fluoroquinolone-resistant Campylobacter in animal reservoirs: dynamics of development, resistance mechanisms and ecological fitness. Anim. Health Res. Rev. 4, 63–71. doi: 10.1079/ahr200356, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1079/ahr200356</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15134291</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang X., Tang M., Zhou Q., Zhang J., Yang X., Gao Y. (2018). Prevalence and characteristics of Campylobacter throughout the slaughter process of different broiler batches. Front. Microbiol. 9:2092. doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2018.02092, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.02092</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6131577</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30233556</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao S., Tyson G. H., Chen Y., Li C., Mukherjee S., Young S., et al. . (2015). Whole-genome sequencing analysis accurately predicts antimicrobial resistance phenotypes in Campylobacter spp. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 82, 459–466. doi: 10.1128/AEM.02873-15, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.02873-15</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4711122</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26519386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>