<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39295431</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1750-3841</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>19</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of food science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Food Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Relationship between consumer acceptance, sensory characteristics, and physicochemical characteristics of "Fuji" apples from different origins.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1750-3841.17296</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>This study examines the acceptance of young Chinese consumers for different "Fuji" apples, focusing on their sensory characteristics and physicochemical foundations. The sensory attributes of the samples were evaluated using a combination of static descriptive analysis (DA) and temporal check-all-that-apply fading (TCATA-fading) methods. Furthermore, the volatile compounds, soluble sugars, organic acids, and textural parameters of the samples were analyzed. The findings revealed that participants favored apples that were perceived as "sweet," "crunchy," "juicy," and "aromatic." The results from the DA indicated that certain sensory attributes, such as "sweet," "vanilla," "honey," and "pear" positively influenced acceptance, while attributes like "sour," "hard," and "grass" had a negative impact. The findings from both the DA and TCATA-fading methods were consistent with each other. In terms of dynamic evaluation, sweetness, and sourness were the initial perceptions, followed by a range of other flavors. Notably, our data suggested that sweetness perception could be enhanced by attributes such as "honey" and "banana." Additionally, the sugar-acid ratio and specific volatile compounds, including hexanal, (E)-2-hexenal, β-damascenone, butyl acetate, and propyl 2-methylbutyrate, were found to influence the perception of sweetness in apples. PRACTICAL APPLICATION: This study helps to understand the effect of different origins on the acceptance of "Fuji" apples and to know the sensory and material basis for the emergence of such differences. It is beneficial for growers and marketers to improve 'Fuji' apples.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Institute of Food Technologists.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhu</LastName><ForeName>Yuxuan</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Beijing Key Laboratory of Forestry Food Processing and Safety, Department of Food Science, College of Biological Sciences and Biotechnology, Beijing Forestry University, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Shuying</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Beijing Key Laboratory of Forestry Food Processing and Safety, Department of Food Science, College of Biological Sciences and Biotechnology, Beijing Forestry University, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhu</LastName><ForeName>Baoqing</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7815-8655</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Beijing Key Laboratory of Forestry Food Processing and Safety, Department of Food Science, College of Biological Sciences and Biotechnology, Beijing Forestry University, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Chunguang</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Beijing Key Laboratory of Forestry Food Processing and Safety, Department of Food Science, College of Biological Sciences and Biotechnology, Beijing Forestry University, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Junlong</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Beijing Key Laboratory of Forestry Food Processing and Safety, Department of Food Science, College of Biological Sciences and Biotechnology, Beijing Forestry University, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Yuchao</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science and Engineering, South Xinjiang Special Agricultural Products Deep Processing Crops Key Laboratory, Tarim University, Aral, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jia</LastName><ForeName>Yiming</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science and Engineering, South Xinjiang Special Agricultural Products Deep Processing Crops Key Laboratory, Tarim University, Aral, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhu</LastName><ForeName>Lixia</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science and Engineering, South Xinjiang Special Agricultural Products Deep Processing Crops Key Laboratory, Tarim University, Aral, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>2018AB042</GrantID><Agency>Xinjiang Production and Construction Corps</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>31960503</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>19</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Food Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0014052</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-1147</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">TCATA‐fading</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">dynamic perception</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">flavor</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">origin identification</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">static descriptive analysis</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39295431</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1750-3841.17296</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Agorastos, G., van Halsema, E., Bast, A., &amp; Klosse, P. (2023). On the importance of saliva in mouthfeel sensations. International Journal of Gastronomy and Food Science, 31, 100667. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijgfs.2023.100667</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ai, Y., &amp; Han, P. (2022). Neurocognitive mechanisms of odor‐induced taste enhancement: A systematic review. International Journal of Gastronomy and Food Science, 28, 100535. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijgfs.2022.100535</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alcaire, F., Antúnez, L., Vidal, L., Giménez, A., &amp; Ares, G. (2017). Aroma‐related cross‐modal interactions for sugar reduction in milk desserts: Influence on consumer perception. Food Research International, 97, 45–50. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2017.02.019</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alcaire, F., Antúnez, L., Vidal, L., Zorn, S., Giménez, A., Castura, J. C., &amp; Ares, G. (2017). Comparison of static and dynamic sensory product characterizations based on check‐all‐that‐apply questions with consumers. Food Research International, 97, 215–222. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2017.04.012</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aprea, E., Charles, M., Endrizzi, I., Laura Corollaro, M., Betta, E., Biasioli, F., &amp; Gasperi, F. (2017). Sweet taste in apple: The role of sorbitol, individual sugars, organic acids and volatile compounds. Scientific Reports, 7(1), 44950. https://doi.org/10.1038/srep44950</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ares, G., Castura, J. C., Antúnez, L., Vidal, L., Giménez, A., Coste, B., Picallo, A., Beresford, M. K., Chheang, S. L., &amp; Jaeger, S. R. (2016). Comparison of two TCATA variants for dynamic sensory characterization of food products. Food Quality and Preference, 54, 160–172. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodqual.2016.07.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barba, C., Beno, N., Guichard, E., &amp; Thomas‐Danguin, T. (2018). Selecting odorant compounds to enhance sweet flavor perception by gas chromatography/olfactometry‐associated taste (GC/O‐AT). Food Chemistry, 257, 172–181. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2018.02.152</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barker, S., &amp; McSweeney, M. B. (2022). Sensory characterization of yellow pea and ground chicken hybrid meat burgers using static and dynamic methodologies. Journal of Food Science, 87(12), 5390–5401. https://doi.org/10.1111/1750‐3841.16380</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bat, K. B., Vodopivec, B. M., Eler, K., Ogrinc, N., Mulič, I., Masuero, D., &amp; Vrhovšek, U. (2018). Primary and secondary metabolites as a tool for differentiation of apple juice according to cultivar and geographical origin. LWT, 90, 238–245. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2017.12.026</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bertelsen, A. S., Mielby, L. A., Alexi, N., Byrne, D. V., &amp; Kidmose, U. (2020). Sweetness enhancement by aromas: Measured by descriptive sensory analysis and relative to reference scaling. Chemical Senses, 45(4), 293–301. https://doi.org/10.1093/chemse/bjaa012</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bowen, A. J., Blake, A., Tureček, J., &amp; Amyotte, B. (2019). External preference mapping: A guide for a consumer‐driven approach to apple breeding. Journal of Sensory Studies, 34(1), e12472. https://doi.org/10.1111/joss.12472</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao, Y., Wang, H., Zhou, Z., Li, Z., &amp; Li, X. (2022). Production region significantly influences the main volatiles of ‘Fuji’ apple. Journal of Food Measurement and Characterization, 16(2), 1000–1011. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11694‐021‐01226‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castura, J. C., Antúnez, L., Giménez, A., &amp; Ares, G. (2016). Temporal check‐all‐that‐apply (TCATA): A novel dynamic method for characterizing products. Food Quality and Preference, 47, 79–90. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodqual.2015.06.017</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Charles, M., Aprea, E., &amp; Gasperi, F. (2018). Factors influencing sweet taste in apple bioactive molecules in food. Springer. https://doi.org/10.1007/978‐3‐319‐78030‐6_80</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Charles, M., Endrizzi, I., Aprea, E., Zambanini, J., Betta, E., &amp; Gasperi, F. (2017). Dynamic and static sensory methods to study the role of aroma on taste and texture: A multisensory approach to apple perception. Food Quality and Preference, 62, 17–30. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodqual.2017.06.014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chauvin, M. A., Ross, C. F., Pitts, M., Kupferman, E., &amp; Swanson, B. (2010). Relationship between instrumental and sensory determination of apple and pear texture. Journal of Food Quality, 33(2), 181–198. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1745‐4557.2010.00292.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, T., Ji, D., Zhang, Z., Li, B., Qin, G., &amp; Tian, S. (2021). Advances and strategies for controlling the quality and safety of postharvest fruit. Engineering, 7(8), 1177–1184. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eng.2020.07.029</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>China, N. B. O. S. (2022). China statistical yearbook. China Statistics Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cliff, M. A., Stanich, K., Lu, R., &amp; Hampson, C. R. (2016). Use of descriptive analysis and preference mapping for early‐stage assessment of new and established apples. Journal of the Science of Food and Agriculture, 96(6), 2170–2183. https://doi.org/10.1002/jsfa.7334</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Commisso, M., Bianconi, M., Poletti, S., Negri, S., Munari, F., Ceoldo, S., &amp; Guzzo, F. (2021). Metabolomic profiling and antioxidant activity of fruits representing diverse apple and pear cultivars. Biology, 10(5), 380. https://doi.org/10.3390/biology10050380</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Egea, M. B., Bertolo, M. R. V., Oliveira Filho, J. G. D., &amp; Lemes, A. C. (2021). A narrative review of the current knowledge on fruit active aroma using gas chromatography‐olfactometry (GC‐O) analysis. Molecules (Basel, Switzerland), 26(17), 5181. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules26175181</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Endrizzi, I., Torri, L., Corollaro, M. L., Demattè, M. L., Aprea, E., Charles, M., Biasioli, F., &amp; Gasperi, F. (2015). A conjoint study on apple acceptability: Sensory characteristics and nutritional information. Food Quality &amp; Preference, 40, 39–48. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodqual.2014.08.007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galmarini, M. V., Symoneaux, R., Chollet, S., &amp; Zamora, M. C. (2013). Understanding apple consumers' expectations in terms of likes and dislikes. Use of comment analysis in a cross‐cultural study. Appetite, 62, 27–36. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.appet.2012.11.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giné Bordonaba, J., &amp; Terry, L. A. (2010). Manipulating the taste‐related composition of strawberry fruits (Fragaria×ananassa) from different cultivars using deficit irrigation. Food Chemistry, 122(4), 1020–1026. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2010.03.060</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kortesniemi, M., Rosenvald, S., Laaksonen, O., Vanag, A., Ollikka, T., Vene, K., &amp; Yang, B. (2018). Sensory and chemical profiles of Finnish honeys of different botanical origins and consumer preferences. Food Chemistry, 246, 351–359. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2017.10.069</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Král, M., Ošťádalová, M., &amp; Tremlová, B. (2017). Effect of storage on textural and sensory properties of Czech apple cultivars. Erwerbs‐Obstbau, 59(1), 39–43. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10341‐016‐0294‐6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laaksonen, O., Knaapila, A., Niva, T., Deegan, K. C., &amp; Sandell, M. (2016). Sensory properties and consumer characteristics contributing to liking of berries. Food Quality and Preference, 53, 117–126. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodqual.2016.06.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, J., Zhang, C., Liu, H., Liu, J., &amp; Jiao, Z. (2020). Profiles of sugar and organic acid of fruit juices: A comparative study and implication for authentication. Journal of Food Quality, 2020, 1–11. https://doi.org/10.1155/2020/7236534</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, X., Huang, J., Xiong, Y., Zhou, J., Tan, X., &amp; Zhang, B. (2018). Determination of soluble solid content in multi‐origin ‘Fuji’ apples by using FT‐NIR spectroscopy and an origin discriminant strategy. Computers and Electronics in Agriculture, 155, 23–31. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.compag.2018.10.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang, S., Liu, Y., Yuan, S., Liu, Y., Zhu, B., &amp; Zhang, M. (2022). Study of consumer liking of six Chinese vinegar products and the correlation between these likings and the volatile profile. Foods, 11(15), 2224. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods11152224</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, Y., Gu, P., Laaksonen, O., Wei, B., Zhu, Y., Zhang, B., Zhu, B., &amp; Li, H. (2022). Lactic acid bacteria incubation and aging drives flavor enhancement of goji berry juice. Journal of Food Composition and Analysis, 105, 104202. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfca.2021.104202</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, Y., Wang, S., Ren, J., Yuan, G., Li, Y., Zhang, B., &amp; Zhu, B. (2018). Characterization of free and bound volatile compounds in six Ribes nigrum L. blackcurrant cultivars. Food Research International, 103, 301–315. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2017.10.038</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>MacKenzie, J. R., Duizer, L. M., &amp; Bowen, A. J. (2022). Apple flavor and its effects on sensory characteristics and consumer preference. Journal of Sensory Studies, 28, e12735. https://doi.org/10.1111/joss.12735</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McMahon, K. M., Culver, C., Castura, J. C., &amp; Ross, C. F. (2017). Perception of carbonation in sparkling wines using descriptive analysis (DA) and temporal check‐all‐that‐apply (TCATA). Food Quality and Preference, 59, 14–26. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodqual.2017.01.017</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehinagic, E., Royer, G., Symoneaux, R., Jourjon, F., &amp; Prost, C. (2006). Characterization of odor‐active volatiles in apples:  Influence of cultivars and maturity stage. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 54(7), 2678–2687. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf052288n</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mignard, P., Beguería, S., Giménez, R., Font I Forcada, C., Reig, G., &amp; Moreno, M. Á. (2022). Effect of genetics and climate on apple sugars and organic acids profiles. Agronomy, 12(4), 827. https://doi.org/10.3390/agronomy12040827</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nie, W., Abler, D., &amp; Li, T. (2021). Grading attribute selection of China's grading system for agricultural products: What attributes benefit consumers more? Journal of Behavioral and Experimental Economics, 93, 101707. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socec.2021.101707</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nikfardjam, M. P., &amp; Maier, D. (2011). Development of a headspace trap HRGC/MS method for the assessment of the relevance of certain aroma compounds on the sensorial characteristics of commercial apple juice. Food Chemistry, 126(4), 1926–1933. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2010.12.021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niu, Y., Wang, R., Xiao, Z., Zhu, J., Sun, X., &amp; Wang, P. (2019). Characterization of ester odorants of apple juice by gas chromatography‐olfactometry, quantitative measurements, odour threshold, aroma intensity and electronic nose. Food Research International, 120, 92–101. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2019.01.064</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oliveira, A. A. A., Andrade, A. C., Bastos, S. C., Condino, J. P. F., Curzi Júnior, A., &amp; Pinheiro, A. C. M. (2021). Use of strawberry and vanilla natural flavors for sugar reduction: A dynamic sensory study with yogurt. Food Research International, 139, 109972. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2020.109972</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pickup, W., Bremer, P., &amp; Peng, M. (2018). Comparing conventional descriptive analysis and napping‐UFP against physiochemical measurements: A case study using apples. Journal of the Science of Food and Agriculture, 98(4), 1476–1484. https://doi.org/10.1002/jsfa.8616</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tanaka, F., Miyazawa, T., Okazaki, K., Tatsuki, M., &amp; Ito, T. (2015). Sensory and metabolic profiles of “Fuji” apples (Malus domestica Borkh.) grown without synthetic agrochemicals: The role of ethylene production. Bioscience Biotechnology and Biochemistry, 79(12), 2034–2043. https://doi.org/10.1080/09168451.2015.1062713</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ting, V. J. L., Romano, A., Silcock, P., Bremer, P., Corollaro, M., Soukoulis, C., Cappellin, L., Gasperi, F., &amp; Biasioli, F. (2015). Apple flavor: Linking sensory perception to volatile release and textural properties. Journal of Sensory Studies, 30, 195–210. https://doi.org/10.1111/joss.12151</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Visalli, M., Béno, N., Nicolle, L., &amp; Schlich, P. (2023). Assessment of the validity and reliability of temporal sensory evaluation methods used with consumers on controlled stimuli delivered by a gustometer. Food Quality and Preference, 110, 104942. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodqual.2023.104942</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, H., Feng, X., Suo, H., Yuan, X., Zhou, S., Ren, H., Jiang, Y., &amp; Kan, J. (2022). Comparison of the performance of the same panel with different training levels: Flash profile versus descriptive analysis. Food Quality and Preference, 99, 104582. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodqual.2022.104582</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Q. J., Mielby, L. A., Thybo, A. K., Bertelsen, A. S., Kidmose, U., Spence, C., &amp; Byrne, D. V. (2019). Sweeter together? Assessing the combined influence of product‐related and contextual factors on perceived sweetness of fruit beverages. Journal of Sensory Studies, 34(3), e12492. https://doi.org/10.1111/joss.12492</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, X., Fauconnier, M., &amp; Bi, J. (2022). Characterization and discrimination of apples by flash GC E‐nose: Geographical regions and botanical origins studies in China. Foods, 11(11), 1631. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods11111631</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao, Z., Chen, H., Niu, Y., &amp; Zhu, J. (2021). Characterization of the aroma‐active compounds in banana (Musa AAA Red green) and their contributions to the enhancement of sweetness perception. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 69(50), 15301–15313. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jafc.1c06434</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, W., Fang, Y., Zhang, Q., Guo, Y., Gao, G., &amp; Yi, X. (2017). Correlation analysis between chemical or texture attributes and stress relaxation properties of ‘Fuji’ apple. Postharvest Biology and Technology, 129, 45–51. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.postharvbio.2017.03.010</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>