<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39296503</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>20</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2296-861X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>11</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Frontiers in nutrition</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Front Nutr</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Effect of ultrasound treatment on quality parameters and health promoting activity of fish protein hydrolysates extracted from side streams of Atlantic mackerel (<i>Scomber scombrus</i>).</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1446485</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1446485</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1446485</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3389/fnut.2024.1446485</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Fish protein hydrolysates (FPH) obtained by enzymatic hydrolysis allows for smart valorization of fish side streams. However, further treatments are normally needed to enhance bioactive and functional properties of the obtained FPH. At present, the commonly used methods to improve functional properties of FPH include chemical and enzymatic modification. Chemical treatments often cause environmental problems, while the enzymatic modification method requires the use of quite expensive enzymes. In recent years, emerging technologies such as ultrasound treatment (US-treatment) have shown great potential in protein modification with high efficiency and safety, low energy consumption, and low nutritional destructiveness. In this study, high-power ultrasound treatments were applied to fish protein hydrolysates (FPH) extracted from Atlantic mackerel (<i>Scomber scombrus</i>) side streams to improve their quality parameters. The effect of three different treatments of 300 W, 450 W and 600 W at the operating frequency of 20 kHz for 10 min on the physicochemical, structural, and functional characteristics of FPH, were examined. The results have shown that with an increase in ultrasound power, the protein solubility of FPH increased linearly, and the changes were significant for all US-treated samples compared to control (untreated) samples. US-treatment significantly increased the degree of hydrolysis of FPH samples treated with 450 W and 600 W compared to control samples. The carbonyl content of FPH increased (significantly for 450 W and 600 W), while thiol groups decreased (significantly for 300 W and 450 W). This indicated that some US-treatments induced oxidation of FPH, however the values of the protein oxidation were low. Amino acid composition of FPH revealed that US-treatment increased the proportion of essential amino acids in the sample treated with 300 W and 450 W, but the increase was not significant. After the US-treatment, all FPH samples became lighter and less yellowish and reddish, which suggest potentially higher attractiveness to consumers. In addition, the <i>in vitro</i> antioxidant activity was assessed using the DPPH, FRAP, and ABTS assays and the cell-free dipeptidyl peptidase IV (DPP-IV) inhibitory activity was also measured. Moreover, these biological activities were measured at cellular level utilizing human intestinal Caco-2 cells. Specifically, the FPH capacity to lower H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced reactive oxygen species (ROS) and lipid peroxidation levels was used to measure its antioxidant activity. The findings suggest that <i>Scomber scombrus</i> hydrolysates could find use as ingredients for promoting health.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Cropotova, Kvangarsnes, Rustad, Stangeland, Roda, Fanzaga, Bartolomei and Lammi.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cropotova</LastName><ForeName>Janna</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biological Sciences Ålesund, Norwegian University of Science and Technology, Ålesund, Norway.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kvangarsnes</LastName><ForeName>Kristine</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biological Sciences Ålesund, Norwegian University of Science and Technology, Ålesund, Norway.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rustad</LastName><ForeName>Turid</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biotechnology and Food Science, Norwegian University of Science and Technology, Trondheim, Norway.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Stangeland</LastName><ForeName>Janne</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Møreforsking AS, Ålesund, Norway.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Roda</LastName><ForeName>Gabriella</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Università degli Studi di Milano, Milano, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fanzaga</LastName><ForeName>Melissa</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Università degli Studi di Milano, Milano, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bartolomei</LastName><ForeName>Martina</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Università degli Studi di Milano, Milano, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lammi</LastName><ForeName>Carmen</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Università degli Studi di Milano, Milano, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Front Nutr</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101642264</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2296-861X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Atlantic mackerel</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">FPH</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">functional properties</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">quality parameters</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ultrasound treatment</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39296503</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11408299</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fnut.2024.1446485</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Venugopal V, Sasidharan A. Functional proteins through green refining of seafood side streams. Front Nutr. (2022) 9:1896. doi: 10.3389/fnut.2022.974447</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fnut.2022.974447</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9454818</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36091241</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siddiqui SA, Schulte H, Pleissner D, Schönfelder S, Kvangarsnes K, Dauksas E, et al. . Transformation of seafood side-streams and residuals into valuable products. Foods. (2023) 12:422. doi: 10.3390/foods12020422, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods12020422</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9857928</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36673514</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venugopal V. Valorization of seafood processing discards: bioconversion and bio-refinery approaches. Front Sustain Food Syst. (2021) 5:611835. doi: 10.3389/fsufs.2021.611835</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fsufs.2021.611835</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nirmal NP, Maqsood S. Seafood waste utilization: isolation, characterization, functional and bio-active properties, and their application in food and nutrition. Front Nutr. (2022) 9:948624. doi: 10.3389/FNUT.2022.948624</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/FNUT.2022.948624</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9332191</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35911102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kvangarsnes K, Dauksas E, Tolstorebrov I, Rustad T, Bartolomei M, Xu R, et al. . Physicochemical and functional properties of rainbow trout (Oncorhynchus mykiss) hydrolysate. Heliyon. (2023) 9:e17979. doi: 10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e17979</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e17979</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10336833</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37449127</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li N, Zhang KX, Du JY, Tan ZF, Xu YP, Liu XY, et al. . High-intensity ultrasound improved the physicochemical and gelling properties of Litopenaeus vannamei myofibrillar protein. Ultrason Sonochem. (2022) 90:106217. doi: 10.1016/j.ultsonch.2022.106217, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ultsonch.2022.106217</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9643580</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36347155</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bartolomei M, Cropotova J, Bollati C, Kvangarsnes K, d’Adduzio L, Li J, et al. . Rainbow trout (Oncorhynchus mykiss) as source of multifunctional peptides with antioxidant, ACE and DPP-IV inhibitory activities. Nutrients. (2023) 15:829. doi: 10.3390/nu15040829, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu15040829</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9960528</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36839187</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu D, Tu ML, Wang Z, Wu C, Yu C, Battino M, et al. . Biological and conventional food processing modifications on food proteins: structure, functionality, and bioactivity. Biotechnol Adv. (2020) 40:107491. doi: 10.1016/j.biotechadv.2019.107491, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.biotechadv.2019.107491</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31756373</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassoun A, Cropotova J, Trollman H, Jagtap S, Garcia-Garcia G, Parra-López C, et al. . Use of industry 4.0 technologies to reduce and valorize seafood waste and by-products: a narrative review on current knowledge. Curr Res Food Sci. (2023) 6:100505. doi: 10.1016/j.crfs.2023.100505, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.crfs.2023.100505</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10160358</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37151380</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Su J, Cavaco-Paulo A. Effect of ultrasound on protein functionality. Ultrason Sonochem. (2021) 76:105653. doi: 10.1016/j.ultsonch.2021.105653</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ultsonch.2021.105653</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8253904</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34198127</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dinakarkumar Y, Krishnamoorthy S, Margavelu G, Ramakrishnan G, Chandran M. Production and characterization of fish protein hydrolysate: effective utilization of trawl by-catch. Food Chem Adv. (2022) 1:100138. doi: 10.1016/j.focha.2022.100138</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.focha.2022.100138</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng Q, Sun DW. Factors affecting the water holding capacity of red meat products: a review of recent research advances. Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr. (2008) 48:137–59. doi: 10.1080/10408390601177647, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408390601177647</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18274969</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adler-Nissen J. Determination of the degree of hydrolysis of food protein hydrolysates by trinitrobenzenesulfonic acid. J Agric Food Chem. (1976) 27:1256–62. doi: 10.1021/jf60226a042</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/jf60226a042</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">544653</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siddik MAB, Chaklader MR, Foysal MJ, Howieson J, Fotedar R, Gupta SK. Influence of fish protein hydrolysate produced from industrial residues on antioxidant activity, cytokine expression and gut microbial communities in juvenile barramundi Lates calcarifer. Fish Shellfish Immunol. (2020) 97:465–73. doi: 10.1016/j.fsi.2019.12.057</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fsi.2019.12.057</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31866445</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Majumder K, Mine Y, Wu J. The potential of food protein-derived anti-inflammatory peptides against various chronic inflammatory diseases. J Sci Food Agric. (2016) 96:2303–11. doi: 10.1002/jsfa.7600</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jsfa.7600</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26711001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maneesai P, Wattanathorn J, Potue P, Khamseekaew J, Rattanakanokchai S, Thukham-Mee W, et al. . Cardiovascular complications are resolved by tuna protein hydrolysate supplementation in rats fed with a high-fat diet. Sci Rep. (2023) 13:12280. doi: 10.1038/s41598-023-39538-z, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-023-39538-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10382531</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37507421</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Penggalih MHST, Praditya GN, Rizqiansyah CY, Setyawardani A, Purnomo AF, Maulana RA, et al. . Marine-derived protein: peptide bioresources for the development of nutraceuticals for improved athletic performance. Front Sports Act Living. (2023) 5:1281397. doi: 10.3389/fspor.2023.1281397</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fspor.2023.1281397</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10642366</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37964773</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ISO 5983-2:2009 . Determination of nitrogen content and calculation of crude protein content—part 2: block digestion and steam distillation method. Geneva, Switzerland: International Organization for Standardization; (2009).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>AOAC . Official methods of analysis: official method for ash. Method No. 936.03. Washington, DC: Association of Official Analytical Chemists; (2000).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lowry OH, Rosebrough NJ, Lewis FA, Randall RJ. Protein measurement with the folin phenol reagent. J Biol Chem. (1951) 193:265–75. doi: 10.1016/S0021-9258(19)52451-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0021-9258(19)52451-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14907713</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buss H, Chan TP, Sluis KB, Domigan NM, Winterbourn CC. Protein carbonyl measurement by a sensitive ELISA method. Free Radic Biol Med. (1997) 23:361–6. doi: 10.1016/S0891-5849(97)00104-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0891-5849(97)00104-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9214571</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ellman GL. Tissue sulfhydryl groups. Arch Biochem Biophys. (1959) 82:70–7. doi: 10.1016/0003-9861(59)90090-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0003-9861(59)90090-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">13650640</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Commission Internationale de l’Éclairage . Improvement to industrial color-difference evaluation. Wien, Austria: CIE Central Bureau; (2001).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aiello G, Xu R, Pugliese R, Bartolomei M, Li J, Bollati C, et al. . Quality assessment of the protein ingredients recovered by ultrasound-assisted extraction from the press cakes of coconut and almond beverage preparation. Foods. (2022) 11:3693. doi: 10.3390/foods11223693</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods11223693</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9689247</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36429285</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Groleau PE, Morin P, Gauthier SF, Pouliot Y. Effect of physicochemical conditions on peptide-peptide interactions in a tryptic hydrolysate of β-lactoglobulin and identification of aggregating peptides. J Agric Food Chem. (2003) 51:4370–5. doi: 10.1021/jf0259720</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/jf0259720</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12848512</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bartolomei M, Capriotti AL, Li Y, Bollati C, Li J, Cerrato A, et al. . Exploitation of olive (Olea europaea L.) seed proteins as upgraded source of bioactive peptides with multifunctional properties: focus on antioxidant and dipeptidyl-dipeptidase—IV inhibitory activities, and glucagon-like peptide 1 improved modulation. Antioxidants. (2022) 11:1730. doi: 10.3390/antiox11091730, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/antiox11091730</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9495363</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36139804</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bollati C, Cruz-Chamorro I, Aiello G, Li J, Bartolomei M, Santos-Sánchez G, et al. . Investigation of the intestinal trans-epithelial transport and antioxidant activity of two hempseed peptides WVSPLAGRT (H2) and IGFLIIWV (H3). Food Res Int. (2022) 152:110720. doi: 10.1016/j.foodres.2021.110720</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2021.110720</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35181114</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Režek JA, Mason TJ, Lelas V, Paniwnyk L, Herceg Z. Effect of ultrasound treatment on particle size and molecular weight of whey proteins. J Food Eng. (2014) 121:15–23. doi: 10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2013.08.012</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2013.08.012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bagarinao NC, Kaur L, Boland M. Effects of ultrasound treatments on tenderness and in vitro protein digestibility of New Zealand abalone, Haliotis iris. Foods. (2020) 9:1122. doi: 10.3390/foods9081122, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods9081122</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7466270</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32824048</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Misir GB, Koral S. Effects of ultrasound treatment on structural, chemical and functional properties of protein hydrolysate of rainbow trout (Oncorhynchus mykiss) by-products. Ital J Food Sci. (2019) 31:205–23. doi: 10.14674/IJFS-1218</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.14674/IJFS-1218</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kadam SU, Tiwari BK, Álvarez C, O’Donnell CP. Ultrasound applications for the extraction, identification and delivery of food proteins and bioactive peptides. Trends Food Sci Technol. (2015) 46:60–7. doi: 10.1016/j.tifs.2015.07.012</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2015.07.012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tian R, Feng J, Huang G, Tian B, Zhang Y, Jiang L, et al. . Ultrasound driven conformational and physicochemical changes of soy protein hydrolysates. Ultrason Sonochem. (2020) 68:105202. doi: 10.1016/j.ultsonch.2020.105202</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ultsonch.2020.105202</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32593148</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y, Zhou F, Zhao M, Lin L, Ning Z, Sun B. Soy peptide nanoparticles by ultrasound-induced self-assembly of large peptide aggregates and their role on emulsion stability. Food Hydrocoll. (2018) 74:62–71. doi: 10.1016/j.foodhyd.2017.07.021</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodhyd.2017.07.021</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang B, Atungulu GG, Khir R, Geng J, Ma H, Li Y, et al. . Ultrasonic treatment effect on enzymolysis kinetics and activities of ACE-inhibitory peptides from oat-isolated protein. Food Biophysics. (2015) 10:244–52. doi: 10.1007/s11483-014-9375-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11483-014-9375-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rajapakse N, Mendis E, Jung W-K, Je J-Y, Kim S-K. Purification of a radical scavenging peptide from fermented mussel sauce and its antioxidant properties. Food Res Int. (2005) 38:175–82. doi: 10.1016/j.foodres.2004.10.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2004.10.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Linde GA, Laverde JA, Vaz de Faria E, Barros CN, Faria de Moraes F, Zanin GM. Taste modification of amino acids and protein hydrolysate by α-cyclodextrin. Food Res Int. (2009) 42:814–8. doi: 10.1016/j.foodres.2009.03.016</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2009.03.016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pathak R, Bhangu SK, Martin GJO, Separovic F, Ashokkumar M. Ultrasound-induced protein restructuring and ordered aggregation to form amyloid crystals. Eur Biophys J. (2022) 51:335–52. doi: 10.1007/s00249-022-01601-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00249-022-01601-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9233657</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35576075</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Liu J, Zhang Z, Meng X, Yang T, Shi W, et al. . Insights into ultrasonication treatment on the characteristics of cereal proteins: functionality, conformational and physicochemical characteristics. Foods. (2023) 12:971. doi: 10.3390/foods12050971, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods12050971</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10000784</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36900488</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fadimu GJ, Gill H, Farahnaky A, Truong T. Investigating the impact of ultrasound pretreatment on the physicochemical, structural, and antioxidant properties of lupin protein hydrolysates. Food Bioprocess Technol. (2021) 14:2004–19. doi: 10.1007/s11947-021-02700-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11947-021-02700-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen HT, Bao HND, Dang HTT, Tómasson T, Arason S, Gudjónsdóttir M. Protein characteristics and bioactivity of fish protein hydrolysates from Tra catfish (Pangasius hypophthalmus) side stream isolates. Foods. (2022) 11:4102. doi: 10.3390/foods11244102</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods11244102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9778320</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36553843</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giménez B, Alemán A, Montero P, Gómez-Guillén MC. Antioxidant and functional properties of gelatin hydrolysates obtained from skin of sole and squid. Food Chem. (2009) 114:976–83. doi: 10.1016/j.foodchem.2008.10.050</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2008.10.050</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thiansilakul Y, Benjakul S, Shahidi F. Compositions, functional properties and antioxidative activity of protein hydrolysates prepared from round scad (Decapterus maruadsi). Food Chem. (2007) 103:1385–94. doi: 10.1016/j.foodchem.2006.10.055</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2006.10.055</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Groleau PE, Gauthier SF, Pouliot Y. Effect of residual chymotryptic activity in a trypsin preparation on peptide aggregation in a β-lactoglobulin hydrolysate. Int Dairy J. (2003) 13:887–95. doi: 10.1016/S0958-6946(03)00112-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0958-6946(03)00112-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun K-L, Gao M, Wang Y-Z, Li X-R, Wang P, Wang B. Antioxidant peptides from protein hydrolysate of marine red algae Eucheuma cottonii: preparation, identification, and cytoprotective mechanisms on H2O2 oxidative damaged HUVECs. Front Microbiol. (2022) 13:791248. doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2022.791248, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2022.791248</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9069057</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35531284</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bordbar S, Ebrahimpour A, Zarei M, Abdul HA, Saari N. Alcalase-generated proteolysates of stone fish (Actinopyga lecanora) flesh as a new source of antioxidant peptides. Int J Food Prop. (2018) 21:1541–59. doi: 10.1080/10942912.2018.1497060</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10942912.2018.1497060</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nazeer RA, Sampath Kumar NS, Jai GR. In vitro and in vivo studies on the antioxidant activity of fish peptide isolated from the croaker (Otolithes ruber) muscle protein hydrolysate. Peptides. (2012) 35:261–8. doi: 10.1016/j.peptides.2012.03.028</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.peptides.2012.03.028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22504498</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>González-Serrano DJ, Hadidi M, Varcheh M, Jelyani AZ, Moreno A, Lorenzo JM. Bioactive peptide fractions from collagen hydrolysate of common carp fish byproduct: antioxidant and functional properties. Antioxidants. (2022) 11:509. doi: 10.3390/antiox11030509</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/antiox11030509</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8944790</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35326159</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He L, Wang X, Wang Y, Luo J, Zhao Y, Han G, et al. . Production and identification of dipeptidyl peptidase IV (DPP-IV) inhibitory peptides from discarded cowhide collagen. Food Chem. (2023) 405:134793. doi: 10.1016/j.foodchem.2022.134793, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2022.134793</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36335727</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galanakis CM. Emerging technologies for the production of nutraceuticals from agricultural by-products: a viewpoint of opportunities and challenges. Food Bioprod Process. (2013) 91:575–9. doi: 10.1016/j.fbp.2013.01.004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fbp.2013.01.004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin H-M, Deng S-G, Huang S-B. Antioxidant activities of ferrous-chelating peptides isolated from five types of low-value fish protein hydrolysates. J Food Biochem. (2014) 38:627–33. doi: 10.1111/jfbc.12103</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jfbc.12103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Subhan F, Kang HY, Lim Y, Ikram M, Baek SY, Jin S, et al. . Fish scale collagen peptides protect against CoCl2/TNF-α-induced cytotoxicity and inflammation via inhibition of ROS, MAPK, and NF-κB pathways in HaCaT cells. Oxidative Med Cell Longev. (2017) 2017:9703609. doi: 10.1155/2017/9703609, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2017/9703609</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5498912</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28717410</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang W-Y, Zhao Y-Q, Zhao G-X, Chi C-F, Wang B. Antioxidant peptides from collagen hydrolysate of redlip croaker (Pseudosciaena polyactis) scales: preparation, characterization, and cytoprotective effects on H2O2-damaged HepG2 cells. Mar Drugs. (2020) 18:156. doi: 10.3390/md18030156</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/md18030156</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7142964</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32168851</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brieger K, Schiavone S, Miller FJ, Jr, Krause K-H. Reactive oxygen species: from health to disease. Swiss Med Wkly. (2012) 142:w13659. doi: 10.4414/smw.2012.13659</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4414/smw.2012.13659</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22903797</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>