<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39295953</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>20</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2214-7500</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>13</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Dec</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Toxicology reports</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Toxicol Rep</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Analysis of 3-MCPD and 1,3-DCP occurrence in mayonnaise: A probabilistic risk assessment of dietary exposure for Iranians.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>101725</StartPage><MedlinePgn>101725</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">101725</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.toxrep.2024.101725</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Mayonnaise is a commonly used oil-in-water emulsion food product. Due to their toxicological properties/genotoxicity and carcinogenicity, chloropropanols' oral exposure has raised concerns over the past decade. The present study reports the occurrence level of free forms of 3-chloropropane-1,2-diol (3-MCPD) and 1,3-dichloro-2-propanol (1,3-DCP) in mayonnaise samples and the risk of oral exposure to these chemicals through consumption of the analyzed samples. Mayonnaise (low- and high-fat, from 6 brands, totally 120 samples) were analyzed for 1,3-DCP and 3-MCPD by gas chromatography-mass spectrometry. The mean level of chemicals was higher in the high-fat samples, with no significant difference among the brands. Generally, 1,3-DCP level was significantly lower in both high-fat and low-fat samples compared to 3-MCPD. Hazard Index (HI) values calculated for oral exposure to 3-MCPD for Iranian adults using probabilistic methods, were less than 1.0, reflecting no major risk<i>.</i> In the Margin of Exposure scenario, low- and high-fat mayonnaise samples were of <i>de minimis</i> health concern at the 50th, 80th, and 95th centiles. Nevertheless, in order to safeguard consumer interests, it is imperative to implement online real-time methodologies for monitoring reactions that result in generation of thermal process contaminants such as 3-MCPD and 1,3-DCP, and to innovate novel technologies to minimize the occurrence of such chemicals while preserving both safety and sensory attributes.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Taghizadeh</LastName><ForeName>Seyedeh Faezeh</ForeName><Initials>SF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Applied Biomedical Research Center, Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Mashhad, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tsitsimpikou</LastName><ForeName>Christina</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>General Chemical State Laboratory of Greece, Athens 11512, Greece.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tsatsakis</LastName><ForeName>Aristidis</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Toxicology, Medical School, University of Crete, Heraklion, Crete, Greece.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Haghparast</LastName><ForeName>Hadi</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Student Research Committee, Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Mashhad, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tabriznia Tabrizi</LastName><ForeName>Ghazaleh</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Student Research Committee, Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Mashhad, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Velayati</LastName><ForeName>Mahin</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Applied Biomedical Research Center, Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Mashhad, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Student Research Committee, Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Mashhad, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Karimi</LastName><ForeName>Gholamreza</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacodynamics and Toxicology, School of Pharmacy, Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Mashhad, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rezaee</LastName><ForeName>Ramin</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Applied Biomedical Research Center, Mashhad University of Medical Sciences, Mashhad, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>31</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Ireland</Country><MedlineTA>Toxicol Rep</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101630272</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2214-7500</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Chloropropanols</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Chronic oral exposure</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">High fat mayonnaise</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Low fat mayonnaise</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Regular daily intake</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>48</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39295953</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11408863</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.toxrep.2024.101725</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2214-7500(24)00108-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Ahmad Tarmizi A.H., Kuntom A. The occurrence of 3-monochloropropane-1, 2-diol esters and glycidyl esters in vegetable oils during frying. Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2022;62:3403–3419.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33397128</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmadpourmir H., Velayati M., Tsitsimpikou C., Tsatsakis A., Tzatzarakis M., Sahranavard T., Taghizadeh S.F., Rezaee R. 3-Monochloropropane-1, 2-diol (3-MCPD)(free and esterified) in edible oil, soy sauce and infant formula: A systematic review of the occurrence and employed analytical approaches. Microchem. J. 2024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alu'datt M.H., Rababah T., Gammoh S., Ereifej K., Al-Mahasneh M., Kubow S., Tawalbeh D. Emulsions. Elsevier; 2016. Emulsified protein filaments: types, preparation, nutritional, functional, and biological properties of mayonnaise; pp. 557–572.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andres S., Appel K.E., Lampen A. Toxicology, occurrence and risk characterisation of the chloropropanols in food: 2-monochloro-1, 3-propanediol, 1, 3-dichloro-2-propanol and 2, 3-dichloro-1-propanol. Food Chem. Toxicol. 2013;58:467–478.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23712097</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arisseto A.P., Silva W.C., Scaranelo G.R., Vicente E. 3-MCPD and glycidyl esters in infant formulas from the Brazilian market: occurrence and risk assessment. Food Control. 2017;77:76–81.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arisseto A.P., Vicente E., Furlani R.P.Z., Toledo M.Cd.F. Estimate of dietary intake of chloropropanols (3-MCPD and 1, 3-DCP) and health risk assessment. Food Sci. Technol. 2013;33:125–133.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calta P., Velíšek J., Doležal M., Hasnip S., Crews C., Réblová Z. Formation of 3-chloropropane-1, 2-diol in systems simulating processed foods. Eur. Food Res. Technol. 2004;218:501–506.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng Ww, Liu Gq, Wang Lq, Liu Zs. Glycidyl fatty acid esters in refined edible oils: a review on formation, occurrence, analysis, and elimination methods. Compr. Rev. Food Sci. Food Saf. 2017;16:263–281.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33371535</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Custodio-Mendoza J., Carro A., Lage-Yusty M., Herrero A., Valente I., Rodrigues J., Lorenzo R. Occurrence and exposure of 3-monochloropropanediol diesters in edible oils and oil-based foodstuffs from the Spanish market. Food Chem. 2019;270:214–222.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30174037</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Menezes R.C.F., de Carvalho Gomes Q.C., de Almeida B.S., de Matos M.F.R., Pinto L.C. Plant-based mayonnaise: Trending ingredients for innovative products. Int. J. Gastron. Food Sci. 2022</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA Update of the risk assessment on 3-monochloropropane diol and its fatty acid esters. EFSA J. Jan. 2018;16</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7009698</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32625654</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA Human risk assessment of multiple chemicals using component-based approaches: a horizontal perspective. EFSA J. 2020 doi: 10.2903/sp.efsa.2020.EN-1759.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2903/sp.efsa.2020.EN-1759</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>FSANZ Chloropropanols in Food, an Analysis of the Public Health Risk, Technical Report Series No. 15. Food Stand. Aust. N. Z. (FSANZ) 2003 &lt;http://www.foodstandards.gov.au/_srcfiles/Chloropropanol%20Report%20%28no%20appendices%29-%2011%20Sep%2003b-2.pdf&gt;.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gonzalez N., Marques M., Calderon J., Collantes R., Corraliza L., Timoner I., Bosch J., Castell V., Domingo J.L., Nadal M. Occurrence and dietary intake of food processing contaminants (FPCs) in Catalonia, Spain. J. Food Compos. Anal. 2022;106</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heshmati A., Ghadimi S., Khaneghah A.M., Barba F.J., Lorenzo J.M., Nazemi F., Fakhri Y. Risk assessment of benzene in food samples of Iran's market. Food Chem. Toxicol. 2018;114:278–284.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29471007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang M., Liu T., Fan F., Sun B., Tian H., Zhang Y. Research progress of chloropropanols esters in foods. J. Food Saf. Qual. 2014;5:3962–3970.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang Z., Xie D., Cao Z., Guo Z., Chen L., Jiang L., Sui X., Wang Z. The effects of chloride and the antioxidant capacity of fried foods on 3-chloro-1, 2-propanediol esters and glycidyl esters during long-term deep-frying. Lwt. 2021;145</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>IARC Agents Classif. IARC Monogr. 2017;1:123.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim W., Jeong Y.A., On J., Choi A., Lee J.-y, Lee J.G., Lee K.-G., Pyo H. Analysis of 3-MCPD and 1, 3-DCP in various foodstuffs using GC-MS. Toxicol. Res. 2015;31:313–319.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4609979</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26483891</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuhlmann J. Analysis and occurrence of dichloropropanol fatty acid esters and related process-induced contaminants in edible oils and fats. Eur. J. Lipid Sci. Technol. 2016;118:382–395.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee B.Q., Mohamed C.W.J.B.W., Khor S.M. A simultaneous derivatization of 3-monochloropropanediol and 1, 3-dichloropropane with hexamethyldisilazane–trimethylsilyl trifluoromethanesulfonate at room temperature for efficient analysis of food sample analysis. J. Chromatogr. A. 2016;1432:101–110.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26792449</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li S., Li J., Feng S., Bian L., Liu Z., Ping Y., Wang X., Van Schepdael A. Headspace solid-phase microextraction and on-fiber derivatization for the determination of 3-/2-MCPDE and GE in breast milk and infant formula by gas chromatography tandem mass spectrometry. Lwt. 2022;154</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahmoud Y., Abo-Zied F., Salem S. Effects of subacute 3-monochloropropane-1, 2-diol treatment on the kidney of male albino rats. Biotech. Histochem. 2019;94:199–203.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30449186</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin A.A., Fodjo E.K., Marc G.B.I., Albert T., Kong C. Simple and rapid detection of free 3-monochloropropane-1, 2-diol based on cysteine modified silver nanoparticles. Food Chem. 2021;338</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32827901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oey S.B., van der Fels-Klerx H., Fogliano V., van Leeuwen S.P. Chemical refining methods effectively mitigate 2-MCPD esters, 3-MCPD esters, and glycidyl esters formation in refined vegetable oils. Food Res. Int. 2022;156</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35651009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Özdikicierler O., Yemişçioğlu F., Saygın Gümüşkesen A. Effects of process parameters on 3-MCPD and glycidyl ester formation during steam distillation of olive oil and olive pomace oil. Eur. Food Res. Technol. 2016;242:805–813.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sulin S., Mokhtar M., Mohammed M., Baharuddin A. Review on palm oil contaminants related to 3-monochloropropane-1, 2-diol (3-MCPD) and glycidyl esters (GE) Food Res. 2020;4:11–18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Svejkovska B., Novotný O., Divinova V., Réblová Z., Doležal M., Velíšek J. Esters of 3-chloropropane-1, 2-diol in foodstuffs. Czech J. Food Sci. 2004;22:190.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Syed Putra S.S., Basirun W.J., Elgharbawy A.A., Hayyan M., Al Abdulmonem W., Aljohani A.S., Hayyan A. 3-Monochloropropane-1, 2-diol (3-MCPD): a review on properties, occurrence, mechanism of formation, toxicity, analytical approach and mitigation strategy. J. Food Meas. Charact. 2023:1–24.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taghizadeh S.F., Azizi M., Hassanpourfard G., Rezaee R., Karimi G. Assessment of carcinogenic and non-carcinogenic risk of exposure to metals via consumption of coffee, tea, and herbal tea in Iranians. Biol. Trace Elem. Res. 2022:1–18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35462590</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taghizadeh S.F., Badibostan H., Hayes A.W., Giesy J.P., Karimi G. Residues levels of pesticides in walnuts of Iran and associated health risks. Hum. Ecol. Risk Assess.: Int. J. 2021;27:191–204.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taghizadeh S.F., Iranmanesh O., Tsitsimpikou C., Tsatsakis A., Karimi G., Rezaee R. Determination of 3 monochloropropane-1, 2-diol (3-MCPD) level in chocolate: a probabilistic health risk assessment for Iranian consumers. J. Food Compos. Anal. 2024;125</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taghizadeh S.F., Karimi G., Tzatzarakis M., Tsakiris I., Ahmadpourmir H., Azizi M., Afshari A., Ghorani V., Yarmohammadi F., Tsatsakis A. Probabilistic risk assessment of exposure to multiple metals and pesticides through consumption of fruit juice samples collected from Iranian market. Food Chem. Toxicol. 2022;170</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36326503</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taghizadeh S.F., Naseri M., Ahmadpourmir H., Azizi M., Rezaee R., Karimi G. Determination of 3 monochloropropane-1, 2-diol (3-MCPD) and 1, 3-Dichloropropan-2-ol (1, 3-DCP) levels in edible vegetable oils: a health risk assessment for Iranian consumers. Microchem. J. 2023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taghizadeh S.F., Rezaee R., Azizi M., Hayes A.W., Karimi G. Occurrence of 3-monochloropropane-1, 2-Diol (3-MCPD) in canned vegetables: a probabilistic assessment of health risk for Iranian consumers. J. Food Compos. Anal. 2023;115</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taghizadeh S.F., Rezaee R., Badiebostan H., Giesy J.P., Karimi G. Occurrence of mycotoxins in rice consumed by Iranians: a probabilistic assessment of risk to health. Food Addit. Contam.: Part A. 2020;37:342–354.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31810432</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taghizadeh S.F., Rezaee R., Boskabady M., Mashayekhi Sardoo H., Karimi G. Exploring the carcinogenic and non-carcinogenic risk of chemicals present in vegetable oils. Int. J. Environ. Anal. Chem. 2022;102:5756–5784.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams G., Leblanc J.-C., Setzer R.W. Application of the margin of exposure (MoE) approach to substances in food that are genotoxic and carcinogenic: example:(CAS No. 96-23-1) 1, 3-dichloro-2-propanol (DCP) Food Chem. Toxicol. 2010;48:S57–S62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20113855</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong S.F., Lee B.Q., Low K.H., Jenatabadi H.S., Mohamed C.W.J.B.W., Khor S.M. Estimation of the dietary intake and risk assessment of food carcinogens (3-MCPD and 1, 3-DCP) in soy sauces by Monte Carlo simulation. Food Chem. 2020;311</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31869642</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong Y.H., Muhamad H., Abas F., Lai O.M., Nyam K.L., Tan C.P. Effects of temperature and NaCl on the formation of 3-MCPD esters and glycidyl esters in refined, bleached and deodorized palm olein during deep-fat frying of potato chips. Food Chem. 2017;219:126–130.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27765207</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie Y., van der Fels-Klerx H., van Leeuwen S.P., Fogliano V. Dietary advanced glycation end-products, 2-monochloropropane-1, 3-diol esters and 3-monochloropropane-1, 2-diol esters and glycidyl esters in infant formulas: Occurrence, formulation and processing effects, mitigation strategies. Compr. Rev. Food Sci. Food Saf. 2021;20:5489–5515.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34626078</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yau J., Kwong K., Chung S., Ho Y., Xiao Y. Dietary exposure to chloropropanols of secondary school students in Hong Kong. Food Addit. Contam. B. 2008;1:93–99.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24784804</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng X., Fu W., Zheng K., Gao B., Lin L., Liu W., Lin Z., Fang Q. A novel method for the simultaneous determination of esterified 2-/3-MCPD and glycidol in foods by GC-MS/MS. Food Control. 2021;123</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>