<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39318305</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1473-5830</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>35</Volume><Issue>7</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Coronary artery disease</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Coron Artery Dis</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Effectiveness of low-dose rivaroxaban in preventing recurrent major adverse cardiovascular events in coronary artery disease: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>614</StartPage><EndPage>621</EndPage><MedlinePgn>614-621</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/MCA.0000000000001381</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Despite advancements in coronary artery disease (CAD) management, major adverse cardiovascular events persist. Vitamin K antagonists and direct oral anticoagulants present bleeding risks. Low-dose rivaroxaban (2.5 mg) is approved by the European Society of Cardiology and the US Food and Drug Administration for CAD. The survival advantage and risk-benefit profile of combining low-dose rivaroxaban with aspirin for CAD patients remain uncertain. This meta-analysis aims to compare the efficacy of low-dose rivaroxaban plus aspirin versus aspirin monotherapy in CAD patients.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">We systematically searched databases for randomized controlled trials exploring low-dose rivaroxaban with aspirin in CAD patients. Of the 6220 studies screened, five met the inclusion criteria. Primary outcomes included myocardial infarction, stroke, major bleeding events, and all-cause mortality. The analysis employed a fixed-effects model, calculating hazard ratios (HRs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Five randomized controlled trials involving 41,351 participants were included. Rivaroxaban (2.5 mg) significantly reduced all-cause mortality (HR, 0.88; 95% CI, 0.81-0.95; P = 0.002), myocardial infarction (HR, 0.81; 95% CI, 0.70-0.94; P = 0.006), and stroke (HR, 0.61; 95% CI, 0.49-0.76; P &lt; 0.00001) compared to aspirin alone. However, it increased major bleeding risk (HR, 1.66; 95% CI, 1.40-1.97; P &lt; 0.01). Meta-regression revealed no dose-dependent impact on all-cause mortality.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Low-dose rivaroxaban demonstrates survival benefits and reduces myocardial infarction and stroke risks in CAD patients, albeit with an increased risk of major bleeding. Consideration of patient bleeding risk is crucial when adding rivaroxaban to antiplatelet therapy. Further research is warranted to compare its effectiveness and safety with dual antiplatelet therapy or P2Y12 inhibitors.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Al Hennawi</LastName><ForeName>Hussam</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Jefferson Abington Hospital, Pennsylvania, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khan</LastName><ForeName>Muhammad Khuzzaim</ForeName><Initials>MK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Dow University of Health Sciences, Karachi.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rasheed</LastName><ForeName>Faisal</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Allama Iqbal Medical College, Lahore.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rathi</LastName><ForeName>Sushma</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Dow University of Health Sciences, Karachi.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ali</LastName><ForeName>Mirha</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Jinnah Sindh Medical University.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ali</LastName><ForeName>Abraish</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Dow University of Health Sciences, Karachi.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Asghar</LastName><ForeName>Zoha</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Ziauddin University, Karachi, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pasha</LastName><ForeName>Khadija</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Dow University of Health Sciences, Karachi.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ashraf</LastName><ForeName>Muhammad Talal</ForeName><Initials>MT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Dow University of Health Sciences, Karachi.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Klugherz</LastName><ForeName>Bruce</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiology, Jefferson Abington Hospital, Pennsylvania, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D000078182">Systematic Review</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D017418">Meta-Analysis</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Coron Artery Dis</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9011445</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0954-6928</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>9NDF7JZ4M3</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000069552">Rivaroxaban</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D065427">Factor Xa Inhibitors</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>R16CO5Y76E</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D001241">Aspirin</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D010975">Platelet Aggregation Inhibitors</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000069552" MajorTopicYN="Y">Rivaroxaban</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000008" MajorTopicYN="N">administration &amp; dosage</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000009" MajorTopicYN="N">adverse effects</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000627" MajorTopicYN="N">therapeutic use</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003324" MajorTopicYN="Y">Coronary Artery Disease</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000401" MajorTopicYN="N">mortality</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016032" MajorTopicYN="Y">Randomized Controlled Trials as Topic</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D065427" MajorTopicYN="Y">Factor Xa Inhibitors</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000008" MajorTopicYN="N">administration &amp; dosage</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000009" MajorTopicYN="N">adverse effects</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000627" MajorTopicYN="N">therapeutic use</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001241" MajorTopicYN="Y">Aspirin</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000009" MajorTopicYN="N">adverse effects</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000627" MajorTopicYN="N">therapeutic use</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000008" MajorTopicYN="N">administration &amp; dosage</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006470" MajorTopicYN="Y">Hemorrhage</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000139" MajorTopicYN="N">chemically induced</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010975" MajorTopicYN="N">Platelet Aggregation Inhibitors</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000009" MajorTopicYN="N">adverse effects</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000627" MajorTopicYN="N">therapeutic use</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000008" MajorTopicYN="N">administration &amp; dosage</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004359" MajorTopicYN="N">Drug Therapy, Combination</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009203" MajorTopicYN="N">Myocardial Infarction</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D020521" MajorTopicYN="N">Stroke</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000209" MajorTopicYN="N">etiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016896" MajorTopicYN="N">Treatment Outcome</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39318305</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MCA.0000000000001381</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00019501-202411000-00011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Olie RH, van der Meijden PEJ, Ten Cate H. The coagulation system in atherothrombosis: implications for new therapeutic strategies. Res Pract Thromb Haemost 2018; 2:188–198.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wallentin L, Wilcox RG, Weaver WD, Emanuelsson H, Goodvin A, Nyström P, et al.; ESTEEM Investigators. Oral ximelagatran for secondary prophylaxis after myocardial infarction: the ESTEEM randomised controlled trial. Lancet 2003; 362:789–797.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oldgren J, Budaj A, Granger CB, Khder Y, Roberts J, Siegbahn A, et al.; RE-DEEM Investigators. Dabigatran vs. placebo in patients with acute coronary syndromes on dual antiplatelet therapy: a randomized, double-blind, phase II trial. Eur Heart J 2011; 32:2781–2789.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alexander JH, Lopes RD, James S, Kilaru R, He Y, Mohan P, et al.; APPRAISE-2 Investigators. Apixaban with antiplatelet therapy after acute coronary syndrome. N Engl J Med 2011; 365:699–708.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonaca MP, Bhatt DL, Cohen M, Steg PG, Storey RF, Jensen EC, et al.; PEGASUS-TIMI 54 Steering Committee and Investigators. Long-term use of ticagrelor in patients with prior myocardial infarction. N Engl J Med 2015; 372:1791–1800.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Es RF, Jonker JJ, Verheugt FW, Deckers JW, Grobbee DE; Antithrombotics in the Secondary Prevention of Events in Coronary Thrombosis-2 (ASPECT-2) Research Group. Aspirin and coumadin after acute coronary syndromes (the ASPECT-2 study): a randomised controlled trial. Lancet 2002; 360:109–113.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wooten JM. Comparing new anticoagulants. South Med J 2012; 105:665–669.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan SU, Khan MZ, Asad ZUA, Valavoor S, Khan MU, Khan MS, et al. Efficacy and safety of low dose rivaroxaban in patients with coronary heart disease: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Thromb Thrombolysis 2020; 50:913–920.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie C, Hang Y, Zhu J, Li C, Jiang B, Zhang Y, et al. Benefit and risk of adding rivaroxaban in patients with coronary artery disease: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Clin Cardiol 2021; 44:20–26.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Page MJ, McKenzie JE, Bossuyt PM, Boutron I, Hoffmann TC, Mulrow CD, et al. The PRISMA 2020 statement: an updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews. Syst Rev 2021; 10:89.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sterne JAC, Savović J, Page MJ, Elbers RG, Blencowe NS, Boutron I, et al. RoB 2: a revised tool for assessing risk of bias in randomised trials. BMJ 2019; 366:l4898.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Higgins JP, Thompson SG, Deeks JJ, Altman DG. Measuring inconsistency in meta-analyses. BMJ 2003; 327:557–560.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee YH. An overview of meta-analysis for clinicians. Korean J Intern Med 2018; 33:277–283.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Connolly SJ, Eikelboom JW, Bosch J, Dagenais G, Dyal L, Lanas F, et al.; COMPASS investigators. Rivaroxaban with or without aspirin in patients with stable coronary artery disease: an international, randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial [published correction appears in Lancet. 2017 Dec 21;:]. Lancet 2018; 391:205–218.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zannad F, Anker SD, Byra WM, Cleland JGF, Fu M, Gheorghiade M, et al.; COMMANDER HF Investigators. Rivaroxaban in patients with heart failure, sinus rhythm, and coronary disease. N Engl J Med 2018; 379:1332–1342.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mega JL, Braunwald E, Wiviott SD, Bassand J-P, Bhatt DL, Bode C, et al.; ATLAS ACS 2–TIMI 51 Investigators. Rivaroxaban in patients with a recent acute coronary syndrome. N Engl J Med 2012; 366:9–19.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mega JL, Braunwald E, Mohanavelu S, Burton P, Poulter R, Misselwitz F, et al.; ATLAS ACS-TIMI 46 study group. Rivaroxaban versus placebo in patients with acute coronary syndromes (ATLAS ACS-TIMI 46): a randomised, double-blind, phase II trial. Lancet 2009; 374:29–38.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gibson William J, Gibson CM, Yee Megan K, Korjian S, Daaboul Y, Plotnikov Alexei N, et al. Safety and efficacy of rivaroxaban when added to aspirin monotherapy among stabilized post-acute coronary syndrome patients: a pooled analysis study of ATLAS ACS-TIMI 46 and ATLAS ACS 2-TIMI 51. J Am Heart Assoc 2019; 8:e009451.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eikelboom JW, Bhatt DL, Fox KAA, Bosch J, Connolly SJ, Anand SS, et al. Mortality benefit of rivaroxaban plus aspirin in patients with chronic coronary or peripheral artery disease. J Am Coll Cardiol 2021; 78:14–23.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Layne K, Ferro A. Antiplatelet therapy in acute coronary syndrome. Eur Cardiol 2017; 12:33–37.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roffi M, Patrono C, Collet JP, Mueller C, Valgimigli M, Andreotti F, et al.; ESC Scientific Document Group. 2015 ESC Guidelines for the management of acute coronary syndromes in patients presenting without persistent ST-segment elevation: Task Force for the Management of Acute Coronary Syndromes in Patients Presenting without Persistent ST-Segment Elevation of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC). Eur Heart J 2016; 37:267–315.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shireman TI, Howard PA, Kresowik TF, Ellerbeck EF. Combined anticoagulant-antiplatelet use and major bleeding events in elderly atrial fibrillation patients. Stroke 2004; 35:2362–2367.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mann KG, Brummel K, Butenas S. What is all that thrombin for? J Thromb Haemost 2003; 1:1504–1514.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oldgren J, Wallentin L, Siegbahn A, et al. Biomarkers in relation to the effects of ticagrelor in comparison with clopidogrel in non-ST-elevation acute coronary syndrome patients managed with or without in-hospital revascularization: a substudy from the Prospective Randomized Platelet Inhibition and Patient Outcomes (PLATO) trial. Circulation 2011; 123:62–73.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gibson CM, Chakrabarti AK, Mega J, Bode C, Bassand J-P, Verheugt FWA, et al.; ATLAS-ACS 2 TIMI 51 Investigators. Reduction of stent thrombosis in patients with acute coronary syndromes treated with rivaroxaban in ATLAS-ACS 2 TIMI 51. J Am Coll Cardiol 2013; 62:286–290.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patrono C, García Rodríguez LA, Landolfi R, Baigent C. Low-dose aspirin for the prevention of atherothrombosis. N Engl J Med 2005; 353:2373–2383.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lopes RD, Leonardi S, Wojdyla DM, et al. Stent thrombosis in patients with acute coronary syndromes treated with rivaroxaban or placebo in addition to antiplatelet therapy: a pooled analysis of the ATLAS ACS 2-TIMI 51 and ATLAS ACS 2-TIMI 46 trials. JACC Cardiovasc Interv 2014; 7:1346–1356.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gurbel PA, Bliden KP, Butler K, Tantry US, Gesheff T, Wei C, et al. Randomized double-blind assessment of the ONSET and OFFSET of the antiplatelet effects of ticagrelor versus clopidogrel in patients with stable coronary artery disease: the ONSET/OFFSET study. Circulation 2009; 120:2577–2585.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>