<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39316975</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1873-3778</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>1736</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>20</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of chromatography. A</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Chromatogr A</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Two-dimensional metal-organic framework nanosheets coated solid-phase microextraction Arrow coupled with UPLC-Q-ToF-MS for the determination of three veterinary residues in milk and pork.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>465373</StartPage><MedlinePgn>465373</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.chroma.2024.465373</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0021-9673(24)00747-7</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>This study presents a method utilizing solid-phase microextraction Arrow (SPME Arrow) combined with ultra-performance liquid chromatography-quadrupole time-of-flight mass spectrometry (UPLC-Q-TOF-MS) for the selective detection of three veterinary drugs-thiabendazole, sulfamethazine, and clenbuterol-in milk and pork. Two-dimensional metal-organic framework nanosheets (2D-MOFs) were employed as coating materials for the SPME Arrow. Three types of 2D-MOFs (Ni, Mn, and Co based) were synthesized and characterized using Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy, scanning electron microscopy, transmission electron microscopy, and a physical adsorption analyzer. The 2D-MOF coatings were fabricated using the electrospinning technique, with polyacrylonitrile (PAN) serving as the binder. Comparative analysis of the three 2D-MOF coatings revealed that 2D-Ni-MOF was the optimal coating material for the SPME Arrow. Optimization of the coating preparation conditions and SPME procedures included determining the optimal mass ratio of 2D-Ni-MOF to PAN, electrospinning time, and extraction and desorption parameters. Equilibrium extraction was achieved within 60 min, and desorption was completed within 30 min. Subsequently, the 2D-Ni-MOF-SPME Arrow-UPLC-Q-TOF-MS method was established and validated under optimal conditions, demonstrating high precision with inter-day precision ranging from 3.8 % to 9.5 % and intra-day precision ranging from 5.1 % to 11.5 %. The reusability study indicated that the extraction performance of the new SPME Arrow remained consistent after 90 adsorption-desorption cycles. The method exhibited linearity in milk and pork over the ranges of 0.002-5 μg L<sup>-1</sup> and 0.01-5 μg L<sup>-1</sup>, respectively. The detection limits in milk and pork were 0.001-0.004 μg L<sup>-1</sup> and 0.003-0.007 μg L<sup>-1</sup>, respectively. This method demonstrated excellent applicability for determining residues of the three veterinary drugs in milk and pork.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Du</LastName><ForeName>Xuanhua</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory for Managing Biotic and Chemical Threats to the Quality and Safety of Agro-products, Zhejiang Key Laboratory of Intelligent Food Logistic and Processing, Zhejiang-Malaysia Joint Research Laboratory for Agricultural Product Processing and Nutrition and College of Food Science and Engineering, Ningbo University, Ningbo 315800, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lan</LastName><ForeName>Hangzhen</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory for Managing Biotic and Chemical Threats to the Quality and Safety of Agro-products, Zhejiang Key Laboratory of Intelligent Food Logistic and Processing, Zhejiang-Malaysia Joint Research Laboratory for Agricultural Product Processing and Nutrition and College of Food Science and Engineering, Ningbo University, Ningbo 315800, China. Electronic address: lanhangzhen@nbu.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wu</LastName><ForeName>Zhen</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory for Managing Biotic and Chemical Threats to the Quality and Safety of Agro-products, Zhejiang Key Laboratory of Intelligent Food Logistic and Processing, Zhejiang-Malaysia Joint Research Laboratory for Agricultural Product Processing and Nutrition and College of Food Science and Engineering, Ningbo University, Ningbo 315800, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pan</LastName><ForeName>Daodong</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory for Managing Biotic and Chemical Threats to the Quality and Safety of Agro-products, Zhejiang Key Laboratory of Intelligent Food Logistic and Processing, Zhejiang-Malaysia Joint Research Laboratory for Agricultural Product Processing and Nutrition and College of Food Science and Engineering, Ningbo University, Ningbo 315800, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wu</LastName><ForeName>Yichun</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Zhoushan Institute for Food and Drug Control, Zhoushan 316012, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>20</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>J Chromatogr A</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9318488</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0021-9673</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Electrospinning</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Solid phase microextraction Arrow</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Two-dimensional metal-organic framework nanosheets</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">UPLC-Q-TOF-MS</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Veterinary drug residues</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare the following financial interests/personal relationships which may be considered as potential competing interests: Hangzhen Lan reports financial support was provided by Ningbo University. Hangzhen Lan reports financial support was provided by One Health Interdisciplinary Research Project of Ningbo University. Hangzhen Lan reports financial support was provided by J National Natural Science Foundation of China. Hangzhen Lan reports financial support was provided by Key R&amp;D Program of Zhejiang. Hangzhen Lan reports financial support was provided by Natural Science Foundation of Zhejiang Province. Hangzhen Lan reports financial support was provided by Science and Technology Programs of Ningbo.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39316975</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chroma.2024.465373</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0021-9673(24)00747-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>