<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39322972</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1750-3841</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>25</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of food science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Food Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Electrolyzed water combined with ozone treatment for efficient removal of mancozeb residues from grapes.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1750-3841.17374</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Existing cleaning methods mainly focus on removing free-state pesticides. However, mancozeb can bind to the wax layer of grapes, forming bound-state residues that are difficult to remove. This study aims to develop an effective cleaning strategy to eliminate both free and bound mancozeb residues from grapes. Compared with the untreated mancozeb aqueous solution, the concentration of free mancozeb significantly decreased (p &lt; 0.05) after treatment with ozonated water (OW), electrolyzed water (EW), and their combination (OW+EW) for 60 min. The combined treatment synergistically promoted mancozeb degradation, thus reducing its half-life to 38% and 75% of that observed when OW and EW were used alone, respectively. To investigate the effect of the waxy layer on mancozeb removal, oleanolic acid (OLA) was selected as a representative component. The binding effect of OLA limited the degradation of mancozeb in OW and EW, extending its half-life by 1.27 and 1.20 times, respectively. Density functional theory elucidated the mechanism by which the binding of OLA affects the degradation of mancozeb. Interestingly, the decomposition of mancozeb in OW + EW was almost unaffected by the introduction of OLA, indicating that the combined treatment could effectively remove bound-state mancozeb. The combined treatment was then successfully applied to remove mancozeb from grapes. After exposure to OW + EW for 10 min, the removal efficiency of mancozeb reached up to 80.61% with minimal risks of ethylene thiourea formation. There was no obvious change in the surface color of grapes after treatment. The findings provide valuable guidance for removing mancozeb from fresh fruits rich in waxy coatings.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Institute of Food Technologists.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wen</LastName><ForeName>Aying</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Food Science and Resources, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Food Science and Technology, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Collaborative Innovation Center of Food Safety and Quality Control in Jiangsu Province, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gao</LastName><ForeName>Fang</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of Agro-product Safety and Quality, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Guo</LastName><ForeName>Boru</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Food Science and Resources, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Food Science and Technology, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Collaborative Innovation Center of Food Safety and Quality Control in Jiangsu Province, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Linquan</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Food Science and Resources, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Food Science and Technology, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Collaborative Innovation Center of Food Safety and Quality Control in Jiangsu Province, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yuan</LastName><ForeName>Shaofeng</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Food Science and Resources, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Food Science and Technology, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Collaborative Innovation Center of Food Safety and Quality Control in Jiangsu Province, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yu</LastName><ForeName>Hang</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Food Science and Resources, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Food Science and Technology, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Collaborative Innovation Center of Food Safety and Quality Control in Jiangsu Province, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Guo</LastName><ForeName>Yahui</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6512-355X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Food Science and Resources, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Food Science and Technology, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Collaborative Innovation Center of Food Safety and Quality Control in Jiangsu Province, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cheng</LastName><ForeName>Yuliang</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9616-7133</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Food Science and Resources, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Food Science and Technology, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Collaborative Innovation Center of Food Safety and Quality Control in Jiangsu Province, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Ling</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Xinjiang Agricultural Products Quality and Safety Center, Urumchi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yao</LastName><ForeName>Weirong</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4730-3976</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Food Science and Resources, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Food Science and Technology, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Collaborative Innovation Center of Food Safety and Quality Control in Jiangsu Province, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Food Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0014052</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-1147</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Combined treatment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Electrolyzed water</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mancozeb</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Ozonated water</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pesticide removal</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39322972</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1750-3841.17374</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Bai, F. Y., Ni, S., Ren, Y., Tang, Y. Z., Zhao, Z., &amp; Pan, X. M. (2020). DFT analysis on the removal of dimethylbenzoquinones in atmosphere and water environments:. •OH‐initiated oxidation and captured by (TiO2)n clusters (n = 1‐6). Journal of Hazardous Materials, 386, 121636. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhazmat.2019.121636</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bianchi, S., Nottola, S. A., Torge, D., Palmerini, M. G., Necozione, S., &amp; Macchiarelli, G. (2020). Association between female reproductive health and mancozeb: Systematic review of experimental models. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, 17(7), 2580. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph17072580</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cabrera, L. C., Di Piazza, G., Dujardin, B., &amp; Pastor, P. M. (2023). The 2021 European Union report on pesticide residues in food. Efsa Journal, 21(4), 7939. https://doi.org/10.2903/j.efsa.2023.7939</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cap, M., Rojas, D., Fernandez, M., Fulco, M., Rodriguez, A., Soteras, T., Cristos, D., &amp; Mozgovoj, M. (2020). Effectiveness of short exposure times to electrolyzed water in reducing Salmonella spp and Imidacloprid in lettuce. Lwt‐Food Science and Technology, 128, 109496. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2020.109496</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cengiz, M. F., &amp; Certel, M. (2014). Effects of chlorine, hydrogen peroxide, and ozone on the reduction of mancozeb residues on tomatoes. Turkish Journal of Agriculture and Forestry, 38(3), 371–376. https://doi.org/10.3906/tar‐1307‐14</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cocco, P. (2022). Time for re‐evaluating the human carcinogenicity of ethylenedithiocarbamate fungicides? A systematic review. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, 19(5), 2632. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph19052632</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fadriquela, A., Sajo, M. E. J., Bajgai, J., Kim, D. H., Kim, C. S., Kim, S. K., &amp; Lee, K. J. (2020). Effects of strong acidic electrolyzed water in wound healing via inflammatory and oxidative stress response. Oxidative Medicine and Cellular Longevity, 2020, 2459826. https://doi.org/10.1155/2020/2459826</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu, X. Y., Yuan, S. F., Yang, F. W., Yu, H., Xie, Y. F., Guo, Y. H., &amp; Yao, W. R. (2023). Characterization of the interaction between boscalid and tannic acid and its effect on the antioxidant properties of tannic acid. Journal of Food Science, 88(4), 1325–1335. https://doi.org/10.1111/1750‐3841.16488</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo, B., Wen, A., Yu, H., Guo, Y., Cheng, Y., Xie, Y., Qian, H., &amp; Yao, W. (2023). Interaction between six waxy components in summer black grapes (Vitis vinifera) and mancozeb and its effect on the residue of mancozeb. International Journal of Molecular Sciences, 24(9), 7705. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms24097705</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han, Q., Dong, W., Wang, H., Ma, H., Liu, P., Gu, Y., Fan, H., &amp; Song, X. (2019). Degradation of tetrabromobisphenol a by ozonation: Performance, products, mechanism and toxicity. Chemosphere, 235, 701–712. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2019.06.204</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hayama, T., &amp; Takada, M. (2008). Simple and rapid method for the determination of ethylenebisdithiocarbamate fungicides in fruits and vegetables using liquid chromatography with tandem mass spectrometry. Analytical and Bioanalytical Chemistry, 392(5), 969–976. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00216‐008‐2346‐8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang, Z., Wang, P., Pu, Z., Lu, L., Chen, G., Hu, X., Fayyaz, A., &amp; Gai, Y. (2021). Effects of mancozeb on citrus rhizosphere bacterial community. Microbial Pathogenesis, 154, 104845. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.micpath.2021.104845</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hwang, E., Cash, J. N., &amp; Zabik, M. J. (2002). Chlorine and chlorine dioxide treatment to reduce or remove EBDCs and ETU residues in a solution. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 50(16), 4734–4742. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf020307c</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hwang, E. S., Cash, J. N., &amp; Zabik, M. J. (2001). Ozone and hydrogen peroxyacetic acid treatment to reduce or remove EBDCs and ETU residues in a solution. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 49(11), 5689–5694. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf0106650</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hwang, E. S., Cash, J. N., &amp; Zabik, M. J. (2003). Determination of degradation products and pathways of mancozeb and ethylenethiourea (ETU) in solutions due to ozone and chlorine dioxide treatments. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 51(5), 1341–1346. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf020764t</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, S. W., Abd El‐Aty, A. M., Choi, J. H., Lee, Y. J., Lieu, T. T. B., Chung, H. S., Rahman, M. M., Choi, O. J., Shin, H. C., Rhee, G. S., Chang, M. I., Kim, H. J., &amp; Shim, J. H. (2016). Contributing effect of various washing procedures and additives on the decline pattern of diethofencarb in crown daisy, a model of leafy vegetables. Food Chemistry, 201, 153–159. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2016.01.064</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kishimoto, N., Morita, Y., Tsuno, H., Oomura, T., &amp; Mizutani, H. (2005). Advanced oxidation effect of ozonation combined with electrolysis. Water Research, 39(19), 4661–4672. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.watres.2005.09.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar, Y. B., Shabeer, T. P. A., Jadhav, M., Banerjee, K., Hingmire, S., Saha, S., &amp; Rai, A. B. (2020). Analytical method validation, dissipation and safety evaluation of combination fungicides fenamidone plus mancozeb and iprovalicarb plus propineb in/on tomato. Journal of Food Science and Technology‐Mysore, 57(6), 2061–2069. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13197‐020‐04240‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, C. J., Xie, Y. F., Guo, Y. H., Cheng, Y. L., Yu, H., Qian, H., &amp; Yao, W. R. (2021). Effects of ozone‐microbubble treatment on the removal of residual pesticides and the adsorption mechanism of pesticides onto the apple matrix. Food Control, 120, 00–00. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2020.107548</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, Y., Wang, J., Zhu, X. R., Liu, Y., Cheng, M., Xing, W. H., Wan, Y., Li, N., Yang, L., &amp; Song, P. F. (2021). Effects of electrolyzed water treatment on pesticide removal and texture quality in fresh‐cut cabbage, broccoli, and color pepper. Food Chemistry, 353, 129408. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2021.129408</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>López‐Fernández, O., Pose‐Juan, E., Rial‐Otero, R., &amp; Simal‐Gándara, J. (2017). Effects of hydrochemistry variables on the half‐life of mancozeb and on the hazard index associated to the sum of mancozeb and ethylenethiourea. Environmental Research, 154, 253–260. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envres.2017.01.016</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>López‐Fernández, O., Rial‐Otero, R., &amp; Simal‐Gándara, J. (2013). Factors governing the removal of mancozeb residues from lettuces with washing solutions. Food Control, 34(2), 530–538. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2013.05.022</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu, L., Guo, H. Y., Kang, N. B., He, X. G., Liu, G. S., Li, J., He, X., Yan, X., &amp; Yu, H. (2022). Application of electrolysed water in the quality and safety control of fruits and vegetables: A review. International Journal of Food Science and Technology, 57(9), 5698–5711. https://doi.org/10.1111/ijfs.15916</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs, National Health Commission, &amp; State Administration for Market Regulation. (2021). GB 2763‐2021: National food safety standard maximum residue limits for pesticides in foods. ChemLinked.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petha, N. H., Lokhande, R. S., Seshadri, D. T., Patil, R. M., Bhagat, T. S., &amp; Patil, J. G. (2017). A simple pre‐column derivatization method for the determination of mancozeb technical (fungicide) by reverse phase HPLC‐UV. Analytical Methods, 9(32), 4702–4708. https://doi.org/10.1039/c7ay00830a</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qi, H., Huang, Q., &amp; Hung, Y.‐C. (2018). Effectiveness of electrolyzed oxidizing water treatment in removing pesticide residues and its effect on produce quality. Food Chemistry, 239, 561–568. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2017.06.144</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Runkle, J., Flocks, J., Economos, J., &amp; Dunlop, A. L. (2017). A systematic review of mancozeb as a reproductive and developmental hazard. Environment International, 99, 29–42. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2016.11.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Studziński, W., Narloch, I., &amp; Dąbrowski, Ł. (2024). Determination of the efficiency of electrolyzed water devices for the removal of pesticides in aqueous solutions and the characteristics of the pesticide residues and their transformation products. Journal of Water Process Engineering, 61, 105372. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jwpe.2024.105372</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thind, T. S., &amp; Hollomon, D. W. (2018). Thiocarbamate fungicides: Reliable tools in resistance management and future outlook. Pest Management Science, 74(7), 1547–1551. https://doi.org/10.1002/ps.4844</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wen, A. Y., Yuan, S. F., Wang, H. H., Mi, S. N., Yu, H., Guo, Y. H., Xie, Y., Qian, H., &amp; Yao, W. R. (2024). Molecular insights on the binding of chlortetracycline to bovine casein and its effect on the thermostability of chlortetracycline. Food Chemistry, 432, 137104. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2023.137104</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, D., Zhang, R., Lu, G., Lin, Q., Liu, F., &amp; Li, Y. (2017). Degradation of octocrylene using combined ozonation and electrolysis process: Optimization by response surface methodology. CLEAN—Soil, Air, Water, 45(2), 1500664. https://doi.org/10.1002/clen.201500664</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu, G. F., Nie, J. Y., Li, H. F., Yan, Z., &amp; Cheng, Y. (2017). Determination of mancozeb residue in fruit by derivatization and a modified QuEChERS method using ultraperformance liquid chromatography‐tandem mass spectrometry. Analytical and Bioanalytical Chemistry, 409(21), 5057–5063. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00216‐017‐0451‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, B., Cheng, X., Zhang, Y. L., Li, W., Wang, J. Q., &amp; Guo, H. G. (2021). Insight into the role of binding interaction in the transformation of tetracycline and toxicity distribution. Environmental Science and Ecotechnology, 8, 100127. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ese.2021.100127</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, B., Wang, C. J., Cheng, X., Zhang, Y. L., Li, W., Wang, J. Q., Tian, Z., Chu, W., Korshin, G. V., &amp; Guo, H. G. (2021). Interactions between the antibiotic tetracycline and humic acid: Examination of the binding sites, and effects of complexation on the oxidation of tetracycline. Water Research, 202, 117379. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.watres.2021.117379</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yigit, N., &amp; Velioglu, Y. S. (2020). Effects of processing and storage on pesticide residues in foods. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 60(21), 3622–3641. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2019.1702501</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>