<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39323638</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1663-9812</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>15</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Frontiers in pharmacology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Front Pharmacol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>From sugar binders to diabetes fighters: the lectin saga of antihyperglycemic activity through systematic review and meta-analysis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1382876</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1382876</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1382876</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3389/fphar.2024.1382876</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Lectins are carbohydrate-binding proteins that are extremely selective for sugar groups in the other molecules. As a result, they perform a variety of roles in biological processes involving cell, carbohydrate, and protein recognition at the cellular and molecular levels. Because lectins can bind to carbohydrates, they may play a role in determining the rate of carbohydrate digestion. They also bind to some proteins involved in diabetes mellitus (DM) pathophysiology. The present review aims to summarize the efficiency of lectins from different sources as potential antihyperglycemic agents.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) guidelines were employed for the drafting. In this regard, published scientific articles on the effects of different lectins on blood glucose (BG), glucose tolerance, hormonal effects, carbohydrate-digesting enzymes, oxidative stress, and insulin production process were collected from reputed journals using electronic databases. Furthermore, the toxicity effects of lectins from different sources were collected. A specific keyword search was completed to collect numerous articles with unique experimental designs and significant results. This was followed by the selection of the requisite articles based on the criteria designed by the authors. Data extraction was based on the common research elements included in the articles.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS AND DISCUSSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Of 13 identified studies, 11 studies were considered after double screening based on the inclusion criteria. All 11 pharmacological investigations were considered for review. Subsequent studies reflected on the pharmacological properties of lectins on the levels of BG, oxidative stress, β-cell proliferation, insulin resistance, inhibition of carbohydrate digesting enzymes, body weight, food and water intake, lipid profile, and other parameters. This review highlights lectins as potential anti-diabetic agents.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">However, due to limited research, systematic evaluation is recommended for their development and promotion as effective potential antihyperglycemic agents. The clinical efficacy and safety of lectins against diabetes mellitus must also be evaluated.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Simha N., Patil, M. K., N., Wong, Kijsomporn, Raj and Ramu.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Simha N</LastName><ForeName>Akshaya</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biotechnology and Bioinformatics, JSS Academy of Higher Education and Research, Mysuru, Karnataka, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Patil</LastName><ForeName>Shashank M</ForeName><Initials>SM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biotechnology and Bioinformatics, JSS Academy of Higher Education and Research, Mysuru, Karnataka, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>M K</LastName><ForeName>Jayanthi</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacology, JSS Medical College, JSS Academy of Higher Education and Research, Mysuru, Karnataka, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>N</LastName><ForeName>Chaitra</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Medical Statistics, School of Life Sciences, JSS Academy of Higher Education and Research, Mysuru, Karnataka, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wong</LastName><ForeName>Ling Shing</ForeName><Initials>LS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Health and Life Sciences, INTI International University, Nilai, Malaysia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kijsomporn</LastName><ForeName>Jureerat</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nursing School, Metharath University, Bangtoey, Pathum Thani, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Raj</LastName><ForeName>Ranjith</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacology, JSS Medical College, JSS Academy of Higher Education and Research, Mysuru, Karnataka, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ramu</LastName><ForeName>Ramith</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biotechnology and Bioinformatics, JSS Academy of Higher Education and Research, Mysuru, Karnataka, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D000078182">Systematic Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Front Pharmacol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101548923</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1663-9812</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antihyperglycemic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">carbohydrate-digesting enzymes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">diabetes mellitus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">hormonal effects</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">insulin production process</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">lectins</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">oxidative stress</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">toxicity</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39323638</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11422237</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fphar.2024.1382876</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">1382876</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Ahmed H., Khan M. A., Kahlert U. D., Niemelä M., Hänggi D., Chaudhry S. R., et al. (2021). Role of adaptor protein myeloid differentiation 88 (MyD88) in post-subarachnoid hemorrhage inflammation: a systematic review. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 22 (8), 4185. PMID: 33919485; PMCID: PMC8073517. 10.3390/ijms22084185</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms22084185</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8073517</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33919485</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahrén B. (2000). Autonomic regulation of islet hormone secretion--implications for health and disease. Diabetologia 43, 393–410. 10.1007/S001250051322</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/S001250051322</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10819232</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akash M. S. H., Shen Q., Rehman K., Chen S. (2012). Interleukin-1 receptor antagonist: a new therapy for type 2 diabetes mellitus. J. Pharm. Sci. 101, 1647–1658. 10.1002/JPS.23057</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/JPS.23057</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22271340</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alves M. F. de A., Barreto F. K. de A., Vasconcelos M. A. de, Nascimento Neto L. G. do, Carneiro R. F., Silva L. T. da, et al. (2020). Antihyperglycemic and antioxidant activities of a lectin from the marine red algae, Bryothamnion seaforthii, in rats with streptozotocin-induced diabetes. Int. J. Biol. Macromol. 158, 773–780. 10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2020.04.238</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2020.04.238</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32360963</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arafat H. A., Katakam A. K., Chipitsyna G., Gong Q., Vancha A. R., Gabbeta J., et al. (2007). Osteopontin protects the islets and beta-cells from interleukin-1 beta-mediated cytotoxicity through negative feedback regulation of nitric oxide. Endocrinology 148, 575–584. 10.1210/EN.2006-0970</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1210/EN.2006-0970</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17110428</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Atkinson M. A., Eisenbarth G. S., Michels A. W. (2014). Type 1 diabetes. Lancet 383, 69–82. 10.1016/S0140-6736(13)60591-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(13)60591-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4380133</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23890997</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balzarini J. (2006). Inhibition of HIV entry by carbohydrate-binding proteins. Antivir. Res. 71 (2-3), 237–247. 10.1016/j.antiviral.2006.02.004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.antiviral.2006.02.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16569440</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bari A. U., Silva H. C., Silva M. T., Pereira Junior F. N., Cajazeiras J. B., Sampaio A. H., et al. (2013). Purification and partial characterization of a new mannose/glucose‐specific lectin from Dialium guineense Willd seeds that exhibits toxic effect. Journal of Molecular Recognition 26 (8), 351–356.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23784991</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhutia S. K., Mallick S. K., Maiti S., Maiti T. K. (2008). Antitumor and proapoptotic effect of Abrus agglutinin derived peptide in Dalton’s lymphoma tumor model. Chem. Biol. Interact. 174, 11–18. 10.1016/j.cbi.2008.04.043</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cbi.2008.04.043</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18550041</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Birck C., Damian L., Marty-Detraves C., Lougarre A., Schulze-Briese C., Koehl P., et al. (2004). A new lectin family with structure similarity to actinoporins revealed by the crystal structure of Xerocomus chrysenteron lectin XCL. J. Mol. Biol. 344 (5), 1409–1420. 10.1016/j.jmb.2004.10.007</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2004.10.007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15561152</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bodaghi A. B., Ebadi E., Gholami M. J., Azizi R., Shariati A. (2023). A decreased level of high-density lipoprotein is a possible risk factor for type 2 diabetes mellitus: a review. Health Sci. Rep. 6 (12), e1779. PMID: 38125279; PMCID: PMC10731824. 10.1002/hsr2.1779</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/hsr2.1779</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10731824</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38125279</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Böni-Schnetzler M., Boller S., Debray S., Bouzakri K., Meier D. T., Prazak R., et al. (2009). Free fatty acids induce a proinflammatory response in islets via the abundantly expressed interleukin-1 receptor I. Endocrinology 150, 5218–5229. 10.1210/EN.2009-0543</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1210/EN.2009-0543</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19819943</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Böni-Schnetzler M., Thorne J., Parnaud G., Marselli L., Ehses J. A., Kerr-Conte J., et al. (2008). Increased interleukin (IL)-1beta messenger ribonucleic acid expression in beta -cells of individuals with type 2 diabetes and regulation of IL-1beta in human islets by glucose and autostimulation. J. Clin. Endocrinol. Metab. 93, 4065–4074. 10.1210/JC.2008-0396</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1210/JC.2008-0396</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2579638</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18664535</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonner C., Kerr-Conte J., Gmyr V., Queniat G., Moerman E., Thévenet J., et al. (2015). Inhibition of the glucose transporter SGLT2 with dapagliflozin in pancreatic alpha cells triggers glucagon secretion. Nat. Med. 21, 512–517. 10.1038/NM.3828</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/NM.3828</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25894829</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bovi M., Carrizo M. E., Capaldi S., Perduca M., Chiarelli L. R., Galliano M., et al. (2011). Structure of a lectin with antitumoral properties in king bolete (Boletus edulis) mushrooms. Glycobiology 21 (8), 1000–1009. 10.1093/glycob/cwr012</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/glycob/cwr012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21303815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braga A. A., Rodrigues e Lacerda R., Medeiros G. K. V. de V., Gonçalves G. F., Pessoa H. de L. F., Cardoso J. D., et al. (2015). Antibacterial and hemolytic activity of a new lectin purified from the seeds of Sterculia foetida L. Appl. Biochem. Biotechnol. 175, 1689–1699. 10.1007/s12010-014-1390-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12010-014-1390-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25422058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Butschi A., Titz A., Wälti M. A., Olieric V., Paschinger K., Nöbauer K., et al. (2010). Caenorhabditis elegans N-glycan core beta-galactoside confers sensitivity towards nematotoxic fungal galectin CGL2. PLoS Pathog. 6 (1), e1000717. 10.1371/journal.ppat.1000717</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000717</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2798750</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20062796</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carrizo M. E., Capaldi S., Perduca M., Irazoqui F. J., Nores G. A., Monaco H. L. (2005). The antineoplastic lectin of the common edible mushroom (Agaricus bisporus) has two binding sites, each specific for a different configuration at a single epimeric hydroxyl. J. Biol. Chem. 280 (11), 10614–10623. 10.1074/jbc.M411989200</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1074/jbc.M411989200</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15596442</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng H. Y., Ning M. X., Chen D. K., Ma W. T. (2019). Interactions between the gut microbiota and the host innate immune response against pathogens. Front. Immunol. 10, 607. 10.3389/fimmu.2019.00607</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2019.00607</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6449424</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30984184</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheung A. H. K., Wong J. H., Ng T. B. (2009). Musa acuminata (Del Monte banana) lectin is a fructose-binding lectin with cytokine-inducing activity. Phytomedicine 16, 594–600. 10.1016/j.phymed.2008.12.016</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.phymed.2008.12.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19195858</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dedon P. C., Tannenbaum S. R. (2004). Reactive nitrogen species in the chemical biology of inflammation. Arch. Biochem. Biophys. 423, 12–22. 10.1016/J.ABB.2003.12.017</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/J.ABB.2003.12.017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14989259</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doliba N. M., Qin W., Najafi H., Liu C., Buettger C. W., Sotiris J., et al. (2012). Glucokinase activation repairs defective bioenergetics of islets of Langerhans isolated from type 2 diabetics. Am. J. Physiol. Endocrinol. Metab. 302, E87-E102. 10.1152/AJPENDO.00218.2011</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1152/AJPENDO.00218.2011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3328091</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21952036</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ehses J. A., Perren A., Eppler E., Ribaux P., Pospisilik J. A., Maor-Cahn R., et al. (2007). Increased number of islet-associated macrophages in type 2 diabetes. Diabetes 56, 2356–2370. 10.2337/DB06-1650</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/DB06-1650</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17579207</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fang E. F., Lin P., Wong J. H., Tsao S. W., Ng T. B. (2010). A lectin with anti-HIV-1 reverse transcriptase, antitumor, and nitric oxide inducing activities from seeds of Phaseolus vulgaris cv. extralong autumn purple bean. J. Agric. Food Chem. 58, 2221–2229. 10.1021/jf903964u</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/jf903964u</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20095617</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng L., Sun H., Zhang Y., Li D. F., Wang D. C. (2010). Structural insights into the recognition mechanism between an antitumor galectin AAL and the Thomsen-Friedenreich antigen. FASEB J. 24 (10), 3861–3868. 10.1096/fj.10-159111</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1096/fj.10-159111</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3229422</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20530247</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Firdose N., Raj R., Gangadharappa B. S., N S. R., Ishika G. V., Ramu R. (2023). Effect of selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors on blood glucose in euglycemic and streptozotocin-induced diabetic albino Wistar rats. Int. J. Health Allied Sci. 12. 10.55691/2278-344X.1057</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.55691/2278-344X.1057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fitches E., Wiles D., Douglas A. E., Hinchliffe G., Audsley N., Gatehouse J. A. (2008). The insecticidal activity of recombinant garlic lectins towards aphids. Insect Biochem. Mol. Biol. 38, 905–915. 10.1016/j.ibmb.2008.07.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ibmb.2008.07.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18707000</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freed D. L. (1999). Do dietary lectins cause disease? BMJ 318 (7190), 1023–1024. PMID: 10205084; PMCID: PMC1115436. 10.1136/bmj.318.7190.1023</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.318.7190.1023</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1115436</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10205084</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gabius H. J. (1997). Animal lectins. Eur. J. Biochem. 243 (3), 543–576. 10.1111/j.1432-1033.1997.t01-1-00543.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1432-1033.1997.t01-1-00543.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9057819</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gadgoli C., Sali L., Abhyankar M., Pathak P. (2015). “Complex of zinc and lectins from seeds of Vigna radiata as potential anti-diabetic agent,” in Complex of zinc and lectins from seeds of Vigna radiata as potential anti-diabetic agent.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giacco F., Brownlee M. (2010). Oxidative stress and diabetic complications. Circ. Res. 107, 1058–1070. 10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.110.223545</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.110.223545</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2996922</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21030723</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Govindappa M., Sadananda T. S., Channabasava C. C. P., Ramachandra Y. L., Chandrappa C. P., Padmalatha R. S., et al. (2015). Materials and methods Collection of endophytic fungi, Alternaria species and mass production Isolation and purification of lectin from endophytic fungi Alternaria species. Integr. Obes. Diabetes 1, 11–19. 10.15761/IOD.1000104</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15761/IOD.1000104</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grácio M., Rocha J., Pinto R., Boavida Ferreira R., Solas J., Eduardo-Figueira M., et al. (2021). A proposed lectin-mediated mechanism to explain the in vivo antihyperglycemic activity of γ-conglutin from Lupinus albus seeds. Food Sci. Nutr. 9, 5980–5996. 10.1002/fsn3.2520</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/fsn3.2520</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8565248</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34760231</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gutierrez R. M. P., Gómez Y. G. Y., Guzman M. D. (2011). Attenuation of nonenzymatic glycation, hyperglycemia, and hyperlipidemia in streptozotocin-induced diabetic rats by chloroform leaf extract of Azadirachta indica . Pharmacogn. Mag. 7, 254–259. 10.4103/0973-1296.84243</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/0973-1296.84243</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3173902</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21969798</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heimberg H., de Vos A., Pipeleers D., Thorens B., Schuit F. (1995). Differences in glucose transporter gene expression between rat pancreatic alpha- and beta-cells are correlated to differences in glucose transport but not in glucose utilization. J. Biol. Chem. 270, 8971–8975. 10.1074/JBC.270.15.8971</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1074/JBC.270.15.8971</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7721807</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu R., Li J., Yao K., Miao M., Zhu K., Liu Z. (2013). Listeria septicemia accompanied by central nervous system involvement in a patient with multiple myeloma and secondary diabetes. Am. J. Case Rep. 14, 226–229. PMID: 23847709; PMCID: PMC3702689. 10.12659/AJCR.889168</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.12659/AJCR.889168</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3702689</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23847709</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huligere S. S., Chandana Kumari V. B., Alqadi T., Kumar S., Cull C. A., Amachawadi R. G., et al. (2023). Isolation and characterization of lactic acid bacteria with potential probiotic activity and further investigation of their activity by α-amylase and α-glucosidase inhibitions of fermented batters. Front. Microbiol. 13, 1042263. 10.3389/fmicb.2022.1042263</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2022.1042263</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9901530</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36756202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hutchings P., Rosen H., O’Reilly L., Simpson E., Gordon S., Cooke A. (1990). Transfer of diabetes in mice prevented by blockade of adhesion-promoting receptor on macrophages. Nature 348, 639–642. 10.1038/348639A0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/348639A0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2250718</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ighodaro O. M., Adeosun A. M., Akinloye O. A. (2017). Alloxan-induced diabetes, a common model for evaluating the glycemic-control potential of therapeutic compounds and plants extracts in experimental studies. Medicina 53, 365–374. 10.1016/j.medici.2018.02.001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.medici.2018.02.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29548636</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iliev I. D., Funari V. A., Taylor K. D., Nguyen Q., Reyes C. N., Strom S. P., et al. (2012). Interactions between commensal fungi and the C-type lectin receptor Dectin-1 influence colitis. Science 336 (6086), 1314–1317. Epub 2012 Jun 6. PMID: 22674328; PMCID: PMC3432565. 10.1126/science.1221789</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.1221789</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3432565</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22674328</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaber K., Francis F., Paquereau L., Fournier D., Haubruge E. (2007). Effect of a fungal lectin from Xerocomus chrysenteron (XCL) on the biological parameters of aphids. Commun. Agric. Appl. Biol. Sci. 72, 629–638.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18399496</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jimbo M., Usui R., Sakai R., Muramoto K., Kamiya H. (2007). Purification, cloning and characterization of egg lectins from the teleost Tribolodon brandti. Comp. Biochem. Physiology Part B Biochem. Mol. Biol. 147 (2), 164–171. 10.1016/j.cbpb.2007.01.014</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cbpb.2007.01.014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17331772</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnson E. C., Bardis C. N., Jansen L. T., Adams J. D., Kirkland T. W., Kavouras S. A. (2017). Reduced water intake deteriorates glucose regulation in patients with type 2 diabetes. Nutr. Res. 43, 25–32. 10.1016/J.NUTRES.2017.05.004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/J.NUTRES.2017.05.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28739050</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Karnchanatat A., Sangvanich P. (2014). A glucose/mannose-specific lectin with alpha-glucosidase inhibitory activity from Sterculia monosperma Vent seeds. Phuket, Thailand: Awanwee petchkongkaew, 75–82. Available at: www.natpro5.psu.ac.th.
</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaur M., Singh K., Rup P. J., Kamboj S. S., Singh J. (2009). Anti-insect potential of lectins from Arisaema species towards Bactrocera cucurbitae. J. Environ. Biol. 30, 1019–1023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20329399</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kavalali G., Tuncel H., Gö Ksel C S., Hatemi H. H. (2002). Hypoglycemic activity of Urtica pilulifera in streptozotocin-diabetic rats. Int. J. Ethnopharmacol. 84, 241–245. 10.1016/S0378-8741(02)00315-X</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0378-8741(02)00315-X</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12648821</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kojima M., Hosoda H., Date Y., Nakazato M., Matsuo H., Kangawa K. (1999). Ghrelin is a growth-hormone-releasing acylated peptide from stomach. Nature 402, 656–660. 10.1038/45230</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/45230</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10604470</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Konidala P., Niemeyer B. (2007). Molecular dynamics simulations of pea (Pisum sativum) lectin structure with octyl glucoside detergents: The ligand interactions and dynamics. Biophysical chemistry 128 (2–3), 215–230.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17532552</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar V., Ramu R., Shirahatti P. S., Kumari V. B. C., Sushma P., Mandal S. P., et al. (2021). α-Glucosidase, α-amylase inhibition, kinetics and docking studies of novel (2-chloro-6-(trifluoromethyl benzyloxy)arylidene) based rhodanine and rhodanine acetic acid derivatives. ChemistrySelect 6, 9637–9644. 10.1002/slct.202101954</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/slct.202101954</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumari V. B. C., Huligere S. S., Ramu R., Naik Bajpe S., Sreenivasa M. Y., Silina E., et al. (2022). Evaluation of probiotic and antidiabetic attributes of lactobacillus strains isolated from fermented beetroot. Front. Microbiol. 13, 911243. 10.3389/fmicb.2022.911243</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2022.911243</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9237538</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35774469</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lam S. K., Ng T. B. (2010). First report of a haemagglutinin-induced apoptotic pathway in breast cancer cells. Biosci. Rep. 30, 307–317. 10.1042/BSR20090059</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1042/BSR20090059</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19689432</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leonidas D. D., Swamy B. M., Hatzopoulos G. N., Gonchigar S. J., Chachadi V. B., Inamdar S. R., et al. (2007). Structural basis for the carbohydrate recognition of the Sclerotium rolfsii lectin. J. Mol. Biol. 368 (4), 1145–1161. 10.1016/j.jmb.2007.02.092</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2007.02.092</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17391699</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y. R., Liu Q. H., Wang H. X., Ng T. B. (2008). A novel lectin with potent antitumor, mitogenic and HIV-1 reverse transcriptase inhibitory activities from the edible mushroom Pleurotus citrinopileatus. Biochimica Biophysica Acta (BBA) - General Subj. 1780, 51–57. 10.1016/J.BBAGEN.2007.09.004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/J.BBAGEN.2007.09.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17961926</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Z., Stirling K., Yang J., Zhang L. (2020). Gut microbiota and diabetes: from correlation to causality and mechanism. World J. Diabetes 11 (7), 293–308. 10.4239/wjd.v11.i7.293</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4239/wjd.v11.i7.293</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7415231</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32843932</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo W., Wu G., Chen X., Zhang Q., Zou C., Wang J., et al. (2022). Blockage of MyD88 in cardiomyocytes alleviates cardiac inflammation and cardiomyopathy in experimental diabetic mice. Biochem. Pharmacol. 206, 115292. 10.1016/j.bcp.2022.115292</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bcp.2022.115292</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36241098</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maedler K., Oberholzer J., Bucher P., Spinas G. A., Donath M. Y. (2003). Monounsaturated fatty acids prevent the deleterious effects of palmitate and high glucose on human pancreatic beta-cell turnover and function. Diabetes 52, 726–733. 10.2337/DIABETES.52.3.726</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/DIABETES.52.3.726</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12606514</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maradesha T., Patil S. M., Al-Mutairi K. A., Ramu R., Madhunapantula S. V., Alqadi T. (2022). Inhibitory effect of polyphenols from the whole green jackfruit flour against α-glucosidase, α-amylase, aldose reductase and glycation at multiple stages and their interaction: inhibition kinetics and molecular simulations. Molecules 27 (6), 1888. 10.3390/molecules27061888</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules27061888</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8949615</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35335251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marques D. N., Almeida A. S. de, Sousa A. R. de O., Pereira R., Andrade A. L., Chaves R. P., et al. (2018). Antibacterial activity of a new lectin isolated from the marine sponge Chondrilla caribensis. Int. J. Biol. Macromol. 109, 1292–1301. 10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2017.11.140</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2017.11.140</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29175164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martiz R. M., Patil S. M., Abdulaziz M., Babalghith A., Al-Areefi M., Al-Ghorbani M., et al. (2022). Defining the role of isoeugenol from Ocimum tenuiflorum against diabetes mellitus-linked Alzheimer’s disease through network pharmacology and computational methods. Molecules. 27 (8), 2398. 10.3390/molecules27082398</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules27082398</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9025232</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35458596</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCulloch L. J., van de Bunt M., Braun M., Frayn K. N., Clark A., Gloyn A. L. (2011). GLUT2 (SLC2A2) is not the principal glucose transporter in human pancreatic beta cells: implications for understanding genetic association signals at this locus. Mol. Genet. Metab. 104, 648–653. 10.1016/J.YMGME.2011.08.026</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/J.YMGME.2011.08.026</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21920790</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McPherson R. L., Isabella C. R., Walker R. L., Sergio D., Bae S., Gaca T., et al. (2023). Lectin-Seq: a method to profile lectin-microbe interactions in native communities. Sci. Adv. 9 (30), eadd8766. 10.1126/sciadv.add8766</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/sciadv.add8766</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10381928</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37506208</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitra N., Srinivas V. R., Ramya T. N., Ahmad N., Reddy G. B., Surolia A. (2002). Conformational stability of legume lectins reflect their different modes of quaternary association: solvent denaturation studies on concanavalin A and winged bean acidic agglutinin. Biochemistry 41 (29), 9256–9263. 10.1021/bi020240m</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/bi020240m</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12119041</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ngai P. H. K., Ng T. B. (2007). A lectin with antifungal and mitogenic activities from red cluster pepper (Capsicum frutescens) seeds. Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 74, 366–371. 10.1007/s00253-006-0685-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00253-006-0685-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17082928</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patil S. M., Martiz R. M., Satish A. M., Shbeer A. M., Ageel M., Al-Ghorbani M., et al. (2022a). Discovery of novel coumarin derivatives as potential dual inhibitors against α-glucosidase and α-amylase for the management of post-prandial hyperglycemia via molecular modelling approaches. Molecules 27 (12), 3888. 10.3390/molecules27123888</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules27123888</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9227442</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35745030</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patil S. M., Ramu R., Shirahatti P. S., Shivamallu C., Amachawadi R. G. (2021a). A systematic review on ethnopharmacology, phytochemistry and pharmacological aspects of Thymus vulgaris Linn. Heliyon 7, e07054. 10.1016/j.heliyon.2021.e07054</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2021.e07054</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8141878</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34041399</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patil S. M., Shirahatti P. S., Ramu R. (2022b). Azadirachta indica A. Juss (neem) against diabetes mellitus: a critical review on its phytochemistry, pharmacology, and toxicology. J. Pharm. Pharmacol. 74, 681–710. 10.1093/JPP/RGAB098</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/JPP/RGAB098</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34562010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patil S. M., Shirahatti P. S., V b C. K., Ramu R., M n N. P. (2021b). Azadirachta indica A. Juss (neem) as a contraceptive: an evidence-based review on its pharmacological efficiency. Phytomedicine 88, 153596. 10.1016/j.phymed.2021.153596</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.phymed.2021.153596</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34092456</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peumans W. J., Damme E. J. (1998). Plant lectins: versatile proteins with important perspectives in biotechnology. Biotechnol. Genet. Eng. Rev. 15 (1), 199–228. 10.1080/02648725.1998.10647956</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/02648725.1998.10647956</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peumans W. J., Van Damme E. J. (1995). Lectins as plant defense proteins. Plant physiol. 109 (2), 347–352. 10.1104/pp.109.2.347</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1104/pp.109.2.347</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC157596</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7480335</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pham H., Robinson-Cohen C., Biggs M. L., Ix J. H., Mukamal K. J., Fried L. F., et al. (2012). Chronic kidney disease, Insulin resistance, and incident diabetes in older adults. Clin. J. Am. Soc. Nephrol. 7, 588–594. 10.2215/CJN.11861111</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2215/CJN.11861111</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3315343</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22383749</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pusztai A. (1993). Dietary lectins are metabolic signals for the gut and modulate immune and hormone functions. Eur. J. Clin. Nutr. 47 (10), 691–699.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8269884</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramos D. de B. M., Gomes F. S., Napoleão T. H., Paiva P. M. G., da Silva M. D. C., Barroso Coelho L. C. B. (2014). Antimicrobial activity of cladonia verticillaris lichen preparations on bacteria and fungi of medical importance. Chin. J. Biol. 2014, 1–7. 10.1155/2014/219392</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2014/219392</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramu R., Shirahatti P. S., Anilakumar K. R., Nayakavadi S., Zameer F., Dhananjaya B. L., et al. (2017). Assessment of nutritional quality and global antioxidant response of banana (musa sp. CV. Nanjangud rasa bale) pseudostem and flower. Pharmacogn. Res. 9, S74-S83–S83. 10.4103/pr.pr_67_17</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/pr.pr_67_17</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5757331</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29333047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramu R., Shirahatti P. S., Nayakavadi S., R V., Zameer F., Dhananjaya B. L., et al. (2016). The effect of a plant extract enriched in stigmasterol and β-sitosterol on glycaemic status and glucose metabolism in alloxan-induced diabetic rats. Food Funct. 7, 3999–4011. 10.1039/C6FO00343E</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C6FO00343E</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27711824</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramu R., Shirahatti P. S., Th D., Bajpe S. N., Sreepathi N., Patil S. M., et al. (2022). Investigating Musa paradisiaca (Var. Nanjangud rasa bale) pseudostem in preventing hyperglycemia along with improvement of diabetic complications. J. App Biol. Biotech. 10, 56–65. 10.7324/JABB.2022.100408</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7324/JABB.2022.100408</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramu R., Shirahatti P. S., Zameer F., Nagendra Prasad M. N. (2015). Investigation of antihyperglycaemic activity of banana (Musa sp. var. Nanjangud rasa bale) pseudostem in normal and diabetic rats. J. Sci. Food Agric. 95, 165–173. 10.1002/jsfa.6698</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jsfa.6698</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24752944</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rocha A. A. da, Araújo T. F. D. S., Fonseca C. S. M. da, Mota D. L. da, Medeiros P. L. de, Paiva P. M. G., et al. (2013). Lectin from Crataeva tapia bark improves tissue damages and plasma hyperglycemia in alloxan-induced diabetic mice. Evidence-based Complementary Altern. Med. 2013, 869305. 10.1155/2013/869305</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2013/869305</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3845403</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24324521</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sajal H., Patil S. M., Raj R., Shbeer A. M., Ageel M., Ramu R. (2022). Computer-aided screening of phytoconstituents from Ocimum tenuiflorum against diabetes mellitus targeting DPP4 inhibition: a combination of molecular docking, molecular dynamics, and pharmacokinetics approaches. Molecules 27 (16), 5133. 10.3390/molecules27165133</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules27165133</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9415412</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36014373</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santos J. V. O., Porto A. L. F., Cavalcanti I. M. F. (2021). Potential application of combined therapy with lectins as a therapeutic strategy for the treatment of bacterial infections. Antibiot. (Basel) 10 (5), 520. PMID: 34063213; PMCID: PMC8147472. 10.3390/antibiotics10050520</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/antibiotics10050520</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8147472</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34063213</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santos A. F. S., Da Silva M. D. C., Napoleão T. H., Paiva P. M. G., Correia M. D. S., Coelho L. C. B. B. (2014). Lectins: Function, structure, biological properties and potential applications. Curr. Top Pept. Protein Res. 15, 41–62.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sawant S. S., Randive V. R., Kulkarni S. R. (2017). Lectins from seeds of Abrus precatorius: evaluation of antidiabetic and antihyperlipidemic potential in diabetic rats. Asian J. Pharm. Res. 7, 71. 10.5958/2231-5691.2017.00013.2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5958/2231-5691.2017.00013.2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharon N. (1993). Lectin-carbohydrate complexes of plants and animals: an atomic view. Trends Biochem. Sci. 18 (6), 221–226. 10.1016/0968-0004(93)90193-q</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0968-0004(93)90193-q</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8346557</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharon N., Lis H. (2002). How proteins bind carbohydrates: lessons from legume lectins. J. Agric. food Chem. 50 (22), 6586–6591. 10.1021/jf020190s</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/jf020190s</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12381156</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siritapetawee J., Limphirat W., Wongviriya W., Maneesan J., Samosornsuk W. (2018). Isolation and characterization of a galactose-specific lectin (EantH) with antimicrobial activity from Euphorbia antiquorum L. latex. Int. J. Biol. Macromol. 120, 1846–1854. 10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2018.09.206</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2018.09.206</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30290251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stanely P., Prince M., Menon V. P. (2000). Hypoglycaemic and other related actions of Tinospora cordifolia roots in alloxan-induced diabetic rats. J. Ethnopharmacol. 70, 9–15. 10.1016/S0378-8741(99)00136-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0378-8741(99)00136-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10720784</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang J., Allen Lee C., Du Y., Sun Y., Pearlman E., Sheibani N., et al. (2013). MyD88-dependent pathways in leukocytes affect the retina in diabetes. PloS one 8 (7), e68871. 10.1371/journal.pone.0068871</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068871</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3708907</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23874797</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thakur A., Rana M., Lakhanpal T. N., Ahmad A., Khan M. I. (2007). Purification and characterization of lectin from fruiting body of Ganoderma lucidum: lectin from Ganoderma lucidum. Biochimica Biophysica Acta (BBA)-General Subj. 1770 (9), 1404–1412. 10.1016/j.bbagen.2007.05.009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bbagen.2007.05.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17629405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The UniProt Consortium (2023). UniProt: the universal protein knowledgebase in 2023. Nucleic acids Res. 51 (D1), D523–D531. 10.1093/nar/gkac1052</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/nar/gkac1052</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9825514</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36408920</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thorens B. (2015). GLUT2, glucose sensing and glucose homeostasis. Diabetologia 58, 221–232. 10.1007/S00125-014-3451-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/S00125-014-3451-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25421524</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tian J., Zhao Y., Wang L., Li L. (2021). Role of TLR4/MyD88/NF-κB signaling in heart and liver-related complications in a rat model of type 2 diabetes mellitus. J. Int. Med. Res. 49 (3), 300060521997590. PMID: 33787393; PMCID: PMC8020098. 10.1177/0300060521997590</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0300060521997590</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8020098</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33787393</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tschop M., Smiley D. L., Heiman M. L. (2000). Ghrelin induces adiposity in rodents. Nature 407, 908–913. 10.1038/35038090</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/35038090</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11057670</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Usha N., Raghavendra Swamy K. N., Meenakshi S., Ganesh S., Ramu R. (2023). Influence of mastication and its relationship with Body Mass Index before and after prosthetic rehabilitation in partially edentulous patients. Int. J. Health Allied Sci. 11. 10.55691/2278-344X.1028</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.55691/2278-344X.1028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vera-Nuñez N., Guirao A. R. Y., da Silva J. D. F., Ramos I. P., Torres M. K. S., Coelho L. C. B. B., et al. (2021). Water-soluble lectin (Wsmol) from moringa oleifera seeds treatment recovers glycemic levels and improves left ventricular ejection fraction on type-2 diabetes mice model. An Acad Bras Cienc 93, e20201596. 10.1590/0001-3765202120201596</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/0001-3765202120201596</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33978069</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Virounbounyapat P. (2012). An alpha-glucosidase inhibitory activity of thermostable lectin protein from Archidendron jiringa Nielsen seeds. Afr. J. Biotechnol. 11. 10.5897/ajb12.401</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5897/ajb12.401</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wälti M. A., Walser P. J., Thore S., Grünler A., Bednar M., Künzler M., et al. (2008). Structural basis for chitotetraose coordination by CGL3, a novel galectin-related protein from Coprinopsis cinerea. J. Mol. Biol. 379 (1), 146–159. 10.1016/j.jmb.2008.03.062</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2008.03.062</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2785874</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18440554</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J.-H., Kong J., Li W., Molchanova V., Chikalovets I., Belogortseva N., et al. (2006). A beta-galactose-specific lectin isolated from the marine worm Chaetopterus variopedatus possesses anti-HIV-1 activity. Comp. Biochem. Physiol. C Toxicol. Pharmacol. 142, 111–117. 10.1016/j.cbpc.2005.10.019</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cbpc.2005.10.019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16316787</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang N., Whang I., Lee J. (2008). A novel C-type lectin from abalone, Haliotis discus discus, agglutinates Vibrio alginolyticus. Dev. and Comp. Immunol. 32, 1034–1040. 10.1016/j.dci.2008.02.001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.dci.2008.02.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18372041</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang W., Wang G., Zhuo X., Liu Y., Tang L., Liu X., et al. (2020). C-type lectin-mediated microbial homeostasis is critical for Helicoverpa armigera larval growth and development. PLoS Pathog. 16 (9), e1008901. 10.1371/journal.ppat.1008901</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1008901</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7549827</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32997722</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y., Liu Y., Wang H., Li C., Qi P., Bao J. (2012). Agaricus bisporus lectins mediates islet β-cell proliferation through regulation of cell cycle proteins. Exp. Biol. Med. 237, 287–296. 10.1258/ebm.2011.011251</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1258/ebm.2011.011251</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22393165</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y., Spatz M., Da Costa G., Michaudel C., Lapiere A., Danne C., et al. (2022). Deletion of both Dectin-1 and Dectin-2 affects the bacterial but not fungal gut microbiota and susceptibility to colitis in mice. Microbiome 10 (1), 91. 10.1186/s40168-022-01273-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40168-022-01273-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9195441</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35698210</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Willcox A., Richardson S. J., Bone A. J., Foulis A. K., Morgan N. G. (2009). Analysis of islet inflammation in human type 1 diabetes. Clin. Exp. Immunol. 155, 173–181. 10.1111/J.1365-2249.2008.03860.X</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/J.1365-2249.2008.03860.X</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2675247</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19128359</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong J. H., Wong C. C., Ng T. B. (2006). Purification and characterization of a galactose-specific lectin with mitogenic activity from pinto beans. Biochimica Biophysica Acta (BBA)-General Subj. 1760 (5), 808–813. 10.1016/j.bbagen.2006.02.015</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bbagen.2006.02.015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16600511</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wren A. M., Small C. J., Ward H. L., Murphy K. G., Dakin C. L., Taheri S., et al. (2000). The novel hypothalamic peptide ghrelin stimulates food intake and growth hormone secretion. Endocrinology 141, 4325–4328. 10.1210/ENDO.141.11.7873</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1210/ENDO.141.11.7873</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11089570</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu L., Bao J.-K. (2013). Anti-tumor and anti-viral activities of Galanthus nivalis agglutinin (GNA)-related lectins. Glycoconj J. 30, 269–279. 10.1007/s10719-012-9440-z</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10719-012-9440-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22893111</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie Y., Bowe B., Li T., Xian H., Yan Y., Al-Aly Z. (2018). Higher blood urea nitrogen is associated with increased risk of incident diabetes mellitus. Kidney Int. 93, 741–752. 10.1016/J.KINT.2017.08.033</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/J.KINT.2017.08.033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29241622</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang S., Cai Y., Meng C., Ding X., Huang J., Luo X., et al. (2021). The role of the microbiome in diabetes mellitus. Diabetes Res. Clin. Pract. 172, 108645. 10.1016/j.diabres.2020.108645</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.diabres.2020.108645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33359751</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao J. K., Wang H. X., Ng T. B. (2009). Purification and characterization of a novel lectin from the toxic wild mushroom Inocybe umbrinella. Toxicon 53, 360–366. 10.1016/j.toxicon.2008.12.009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.toxicon.2008.12.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19111567</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>