<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39328221</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2092-6456</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>33</Volume><Issue>14</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Food science and biotechnology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Food Sci Biotechnol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Development of molecular markers based on real-time PCR to detect flax and sesame in commercial amaranth products.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>3313</StartPage><EndPage>3322</EndPage><MedlinePgn>3313-3322</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s10068-024-01584-2</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="UNLABELLED"><i>Amaranthus</i>, <i>Sesamum indicum</i>, and <i>Linum usitatissimum</i> are the most popular oilseed grains worldwide. Protein-rich <i>Amaranthus</i> contains bioactive peptides, is nutritious, and exhibits anti-allergic properties. <i>Sesamum indicum</i> is a primary trigger of anaphylaxis. <i>Linum usitatissimum</i> also displays allergenic properties. A DNA marker assessable using quantitative real-time PCR was developed to detect <i>S. indicum</i> and <i>L. usitatissimum</i> as allergenic contaminants of anti-allergenic <i>Amaranthus</i>. The efficiency of each primer set ranged from 90-98%, and high linear correlation (R<sup>2</sup> &gt; 0.99) was obtained between crossover values and the log DNA concentration. We established a Ct value of 0.1% of the binary as a cutoff. The practical application of the designed marker was confirmed by analyzing 20 commercial products. The qPCR system developed for detecting flaxseed and sesame can be applied for regulatory monitoring of allergenic substances in commercial amaranth-containing foods, thus contributing to protecting public health and safety.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="SUPPLEMENTARY INFORMATION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1007/s10068-024-01584-2.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Korean Society of Food Science and Technology 2024. Springer Nature or its licensor (e.g. a society or other partner) holds exclusive rights to this article under a publishing agreement with the author(s) or other rightsholder(s); author self-archiving of the accepted manuscript version of this article is solely governed by the terms of such publishing agreement and applicable law.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kim</LastName><ForeName>Yeon Mi</ForeName><Initials>YM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Plant Genomics Laboratory, Interdisciplinary Program in Smart Agriculture, Kangwon National University, Chuncheon, 24341 Republic of Korea.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/01mh5ph17</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.412010.6</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 0707 9039</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jang</LastName><ForeName>Cheol Seong</ForeName><Initials>CS</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6691-4150</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Plant Genomics Laboratory, Interdisciplinary Program in Smart Agriculture, Kangwon National University, Chuncheon, 24341 Republic of Korea.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/01mh5ph17</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.412010.6</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 0707 9039</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>13</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Korea (South)</Country><MedlineTA>Food Sci Biotechnol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9816587</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1226-7708</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Amaranthus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">DNA marker</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Linum usitatissimum</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SYBR® Green real-time PCR</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sesamum indicum</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflict of interestThe authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39328221</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11422535</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10068-024-01584-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">1584</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>1 CPWG, Hollingsworth PM, Forrest LL, Spouge JL, Hajibabaei M, Ratnasingham S, van der Bank M, Chase MW, Cowan RS and Erickson DL. A DNA barcode for land plants. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences. 106: 12794-12797 (2009)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2722355</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19666622</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allmann M, Candrian U, Höfelein C and Lüthy J. Polymerase chain reaction (PCR): a possible alternative to immunochemical methods assuring safety and quality of food. Detection of wheat contamination in non-wheat food products. Zeitschrift fur Lebensmittel-untersuchung und-forschung. 196: 248-251 (1993)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8465611</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alvarez-Perea A, Alzate-Pérez D, Doleo Maldonado A and Baeza ML. Anaphylaxis caused by flaxseed. The Journal of Investigational Allergology and Clinical Immunology. 23: 446-447 (2013)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24459826</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>An J, Moon JC and Jang CS. Markers for distinguishing Orostachys species by SYBR Green-based real-time PCR and verification of their application in commercial O. japonica food products. Applied Biological Chemistry. 61: 499-508 (2018)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arya M, Shergill IS, Williamson M, Gommersall L, Arya N and Patel HRH. Basic principles of real-time quantitative PCR. Expert Review of Molecular Diagnostics. 5: 209-219 (2005)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15833050</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Black WC. Flax hypersensitiveness. Journal of the American Medical Association. 94: 1064-1065 (1930)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bolaños D, Marchevsky EJ and Camiña JM. Elemental analysis of amaranth, chia, sesame, linen, and quinoa seeds by ICP-OES: assessment of classification by chemometrics. Food Analytical Methods. 9: 477-484 (2016)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Broeders S, Huber I, Grohmann L, Berben G, Taverniers I, Mazzara M, Roosens N and Morisset D. Guidelines for validation of qualitative real-time PCR methods. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology. 37: 115-126 (2014)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choi J-Y, Bae S, Kim J, Kim J and Moon K-D. Quality characteristics of sesame oil obtained from imported sesame (Sesamum indicum). Korean Journal of Food Science and Technology. 51: 309-315 (2019)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dalal I, Binson I, Reifen R, Amitai Z, Shohat T, Rahmani S, Levine A, Ballin A and Somekh E. Food allergy is a matter of geography after all: sesame as a major cause of severe IgE-mediated food allergic reactions among infants and young children in Israel. Allergy. 57: 362-365 (2002)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11906370</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gangur V, Kelly C and Navuluri L. Sesame allergy: a growing food allergy of global proportions? Annals of Allergy, Asthma &amp; Immunology. 95: 4-11 (2005)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16095135</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goyal A, Sharma V, Upadhyay N, Gill S and Sihag M. Flax and flaxseed oil: an ancient medicine &amp; modern functional food. Journal of Food Science and Technology. 51: 1633-1653 (2014)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4152533</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25190822</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grant LR. A report of six cases of flaxseed sensitization with review of the literature. Journal of Allergy. 3: 469-477 (1932)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee J-H, Kim S-R, Song J-Y and Shin M-S. Comparison on physicochemical properties of amaranth starch with other waxy cereal starches. Korean Journal of Food Science and Technology. 31: 612-618 (1999)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lezaun A, Fraj J, Colas C, Duce F, Dominguez MA, Cuevas M and Eiras P. Anaphylaxis from linseed. Allergy. 53: 105-106 (1998a)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9491240</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lo Y-T and Shaw P-C. DNA-based techniques for authentication of processed food and food supplements. Food Chemistry. 240: 767-774 (2018)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28946341</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Minas K, McEwan NR, Newbold CJ and Scott KP. Optimization of a high-throughput CTAB-based protocol for the extraction of qPCR-grade DNA from rumen fluid, plant and bacterial pure cultures. FEMS Microbiology Letters. 325: 162-169 (2011)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22029887</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moronta J, Smaldini PL, Fossati CA, Añon MC and Docena GH. The anti-inflammatory SSEDIKE peptide from Amaranth seeds modulates IgE-mediated food allergy. Journal of Functional Foods. 25: 579-587 (2016)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oh SH and Jang CS. Development and validation of a real-time PCR based assay to detect adulteration with corn in commercial turmeric powder products. Foods. 9: 882 (2020)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7404567</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32635672</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park Y-E, Kim B-H, Yoon Y-C, Kim J-K, Lee J-H, Kwon G-S, Hwang HS and Lee J-B. Total polyphenol contents, flavonoid contents, and antioxidant activity of roasted-flaxseed extracts based on lactic-acid bacteria fermentation. Journal of Life Science. 28: 547-554 (2018)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park B-G, Lee S-Y and Lee M-H. Quality and antioxidant properties of sponge cake added with flaxseed powder. Culinary Science and Hospitality Research. 23: 207-215 (2017)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park CB, Sung BR and Chung DH. Variation and correlations of lodging related characters in sesame germplasms. Korean Journal of Breeding (Korea Republic) (1991)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peter K and Gandhi P. Rediscovering the therapeutic potential of Amaranthus species: A review. Egyptian Journal of Basic and Applied Sciences. 4: 196-205 (2017)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silva-Sánchez C, Barba De La Rosa AP, León-Galván MF, De Lumen BO, De León-Rodríguez A and González De Mejía E. Bioactive peptides in amaranth (Amaranthus hypochondriacus) seed. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry. 56: 1233-1240 (2008)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18211015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh KK, Mridula D, Rehal J and Barnwal P. Flaxseed: a potential source of food, feed and fiber. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition. 51: 210-222 (2011)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21390942</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yi M-R, Kang C-H and Bu H-J. Anti-inflammatory and tyrosinase inhibition effects of Amaranth (Amaranthus spp L.) seed extract. Korean Journal of Plant Resources. 30: 144-151 (2017)</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>