<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39328229</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2092-6456</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>33</Volume><Issue>14</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Food science and biotechnology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Food Sci Biotechnol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Development and verification of new reference plasmid (pUC_GM-SB) for the DNA-based detection of genetically modified sugar beet H7-1.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>3291</StartPage><EndPage>3297</EndPage><MedlinePgn>3291-3297</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s10068-024-01572-6</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="UNLABELLED">The sugar beet is the second-largest sugar-producing crop. Genetically modified (GM) sugar beet, which have herbicide-resistant, have been developed to increase production and comprise over 90% of the market share. This study describes qualitative and quantitative PCR methods for the GM sugar beet H7-1 with reference plasmid (pUC_GM-SB) containing an endogenous gene (<i>GS2</i>) and an event-specific gene for H7-1 that served as a positive control for PCR. The detection limit of qualitative PCR was approximately 10 copies of the reference plasmid and 0.05% in spiked samples. In the case of quantitative PCR, the detection limit was five copies of the reference plasmid. Regarding repeatability, the standard deviation and relative standard deviation were found to range from 0.11 to 0.24 and from 0.23% to 0.99%, respectively. This study provides food safety assurance for imported GM sugar beet H7-1 using the reference plasmid and supports efficient detection methods.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="SUPPLEMENTARY INFORMATION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1007/s10068-024-01572-6.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Korean Society of Food Science and Technology 2024. Springer Nature or its licensor (e.g. a society or other partner) holds exclusive rights to this article under a publishing agreement with the author(s) or other rightsholder(s); author self-archiving of the accepted manuscript version of this article is solely governed by the terms of such publishing agreement and applicable law.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Suh</LastName><ForeName>Seung-Man</ForeName><Initials>SM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Life Sciences &amp; Resources and Department of Food Science and Biotechnology, Kyung Hee University, Yongin, 17104 Korea.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/01zqcg218</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.289247.2</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 2171 7818</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kim</LastName><ForeName>Sumin</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Life Sciences &amp; Resources and Department of Food Science and Biotechnology, Kyung Hee University, Yongin, 17104 Korea.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/01zqcg218</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.289247.2</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 2171 7818</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kim</LastName><ForeName>Hyun-Jae</ForeName><Initials>HJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Life Sciences &amp; Resources and Department of Food Science and Biotechnology, Kyung Hee University, Yongin, 17104 Korea.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/01zqcg218</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.289247.2</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 2171 7818</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shin</LastName><ForeName>Min-Ki</ForeName><Initials>MK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Novel Food Division, National Institute of Food and Drug Safety Evaluation, Cheongju, 28159 Korea.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/027k9sa32</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.467691.b</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0004 1773 0675</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kim</LastName><ForeName>Hae-Yeong</ForeName><Initials>HY</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3409-0932</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Life Sciences &amp; Resources and Department of Food Science and Biotechnology, Kyung Hee University, Yongin, 17104 Korea.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/01zqcg218</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.289247.2</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 2171 7818</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Korea (South)</Country><MedlineTA>Food Sci Biotechnol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9816587</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1226-7708</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Event-specific primer</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">GM sugar beet</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Qualitative PCR</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Quantitative PCR</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Reference plasmid</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflict of interestOn behalf of all authors, the corresponding author states that there is no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>6</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39328229</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11422527</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10068-024-01572-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">1572</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Caprioara-Buda M, Meyer W, Jeynov B, Corbisier P, Trapmann S, Emons H. Evaluation of plasmid and genmic DNA calibrants used for the quantification of genetically modified organisms. Analytical and Bioanalytical Chemistry. 404: 29-42 (2012)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22638881</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaouachi M, Alaya A, Ali IBH, Hafsa AB, Nabi N, Berard A, Romaniuk M, Skhiri F, Said K. Development of real-time PCR method for the detection and the quantification of a new endogenous reference gene in sugar beet “Beta vulgaris L.”: GMO application. Plant Cell Reports. 32: 117-128 (2013)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23052591</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Debode F, Janssen E, Berben G. Development of 10 new screening PCR assays for GMO detection targeting promoter (pFMV, pNOS, pSSuAra, pTA29, pUbi, pRice actin) and terminators (t35S, tE9, tOCS, tg7). European Food Research and Technology. 236: 659-669 (2013)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Food Safety Authority (EFSA), Lenzi P, Papadopoulou N, Raffaello T, Risk assessment of new sequencing information for genetically modified sugar beet H7-1. EFSA Journal. 20(6): e07354 (2022)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9175132</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35702696</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>European network of GMO laboratories (ENGL). Definition of minimum performance requirements for analytical methods of GMO testing, Version 25-01-2005, replaced by a new version 18 October 2008 and date of application 13 April 2009. Available from: http://gmo-crl.jre.ec.europa.eu/doc/Min_Perf_Requir_Analyt_methods.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO). Agricultural production statistics 2000–2021. FAOSTAT analytical briefs. No. 60. Rome. (2022) Available from: http://www.fao.org/3/cc3751en/cc3751en.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim JH, Park SB, Roh HJ, Park S, Shin MK, Moon GI, Hong JH, Kim HY. A simplified and accurate detection of the genetically modified wheat MON with one calibrator plasmid. 176: 1–6 (2015)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25624198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Z, Li X, Wang C, Song G, Pi L, Zheng L, Zhang D, Yang L. One novel multiple-target plasmid reference molecule targeting eight genetically modified canola events for genetically modified canola detection. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry. 65(38): 8489-8500 (2017)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28844131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mazzara M, Foti N, Savini C, van Den Eede G. Event-specific method for the quantitation of sugar beet line H7–1 using real-time PCR-validation report and validated method-v.1.01. Publications Office of the European Union. EUR26143 (2013)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meng Y, Liu X, Wang S, Zhang D, Yang L. Applicability of plasmid calibrant pTC1507 in quantification of TC1507 maize: an interlaboratory study. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry. 60: 23-28 (2012)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22148678</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meng Y, Wang S, Guo J, Yang L. Collaborative ring trial of the applicability of a reference plasmid DNA calibrant in the quantitative analysis of GM maize event MON810. Foods. 11(11):1538 (2022)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9180190</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35681288</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nehls R, Kraus J, Matzk A, Jansen R. Transgenic varieties: sugarbeet. Sugar Tech. 12: 194-200. (2010)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Padgette SR, Kolacz KH, Delannay X, Re DB, LaVallee BJ, Tinius CN, Rhodes WK, Otero YI, Barry GF, Eichholtz DA, Peschke VM, Nida DL, Taylor NB, Kishore GM. Development, identification, and characterization of a glyphosate-tolerant soybean line. Crop Science. 35(5):1451–1461 (1995)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pi L, Li X, Cao Y, Wang C, Pan L, Yang L. Development and application of a multi-targeting reference plasmid as calibrator for analysis of five genetically modified soybean events. Analytical and Bioanalytical Chemistry. 407(10): 2877-2886 (2015)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25673245</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shin MK, Jeon SM, Park JS. Quantitative real-time PCR analysis of four genetically modified soybean events using plasmid and genomic DNA calibrators. Food Science and Biotechnology. In press (2023)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10866821</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38371688</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steinrucken H, Armhein N. The herbicide glyphosate is a potent inhibitor of 5-enolpyruvylshikimic acid-3-phosphate synthase. Biochemical Biophysical Research Communications 94(4):1207-1212 (1980)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7396959</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stevanato P, Chiodi C, Broccanello C, Concheri G, Biancardi E, Pavli O, Skaracis G. Sustainability of the sugar beet crops. Sugar Tech. 21: 703-716 (2019)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Subrahmanyeswari T, Gantait S. Advancements and prospectives of sugar beet (Beta vulgaris L.) biotechnology. Applied Microbiology and Biotechnology. 106(22): 7417-7430 (2022)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36241928</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suh SM, Kim HJ, Shin MK, Hong SJ, Cha JE, Kim HY. Multiplex PCR detection method for genetically modified canola event (MON94100, LBFLFK, and NS-B50027-4) combined with capillary electrophoresis. Food Science and Biotechnology. 33: 637-643 (2024)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10805685</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38274186</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang X, Teng D, Xi D, Guan Q, Wang J. Construction of a reference plasmid containing ten targets for the detection of genetically modified crops. Plasmid. 69(1): 108-113 (2013)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23085154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Y, Li J, Wang Y, Li X, Li Y, Zhu L, Li J, Wu G. Development and application of a general plasmid reference material for GMO screening. Plasmid. 87(88): 28-36 (2016)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27497661</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu J, Zhang X, Adil MF, Lei B, Jia M, Zhao H, Yu S, Liu J, Huo Y, Shamsi IH. A new reference plasmid “pGMT27” provides an efficient transgenic detection method for flue-cured tobacco. Journal of Food Quality. 2021: 3220013 (2021)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang N, Xu W, Bai W, Zhai Z, Luo Y, Yan X, He J, Huang K. Event-specific qualitative and quantitative PCR detection of LY038 maize in mixed samples. Food Control. 22(8): 1287-1295 (2011)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang L, Wu Y, Wu G, Cao Y, Lu C. Correction of the lack of commutability between plasmid DNA and genomic DNA for quantification of genetically modified organisms using pBSTopas as a model. Analytical and Bioanalytical Chemistry. 406: 6385-6397 (2014)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25182967</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>