<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39323872</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2297-1769</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>11</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Frontiers in veterinary science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Front Vet Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Aligning valid research outcomes with stakeholder values-what do they need for decision-making?</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1444023</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1444023</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1444023</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3389/fvets.2024.1444023</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>This paper is derived from a presentation given by the first author at the 2024 Symposium for the Calvin Schwabe Award, presented to Dr. Jan Sargeant for Lifetime Achievement in Veterinary Epidemiology and Preventive Medicine. Researchers must work toward ensuring validity throughout the research process, but we also should ensure that our resulting outcomes are specified to appropriately inform and enable decision-making by the end-users. Given the scope and diversity of topics addressed by veterinary researchers, the potential beneficiaries or stakeholders of our research also varies. Stakeholders or end-users may include veterinary practitioners, other researchers, livestock owners, "pet parents," government officials, corporate entities, or the general public in the case of public health or food security and safety issues. Current research in animal agriculture provides an opportunity to consider research outcomes in a sustainability framework which concurrently values social, economic, and environment impacts of animal health and management decisions. In companion animals, contemporary issues of affordability and access to care, quality of life, or compliance effects on efficacy, also extend the spectrum of relevant research outcomes. In these cases, traditional measures of animal health, such as morbidity, mortality, or weight gain, may not be the most relevant for the end-users. Furthermore, if studies are not designed and analyzed with well-defined primary outcomes that are informed by stakeholders' values, but rather post-hoc considerations of these values are made based on indirect or surrogate measures, there is the potential to incorporate error and bias into our conclusions and the end-users' decision-making processes.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Renter, Sargeant, O’Connor and Ruple.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Renter</LastName><ForeName>David G</ForeName><Initials>DG</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Outcomes Research and Epidemiology, College of Veterinary Medicine, Kansas State University, Manhattan, KS, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sargeant</LastName><ForeName>Jan M</ForeName><Initials>JM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Population Medicine, Ontario Veterinary College, University of Guelph, Guelph, ON, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>O'Connor</LastName><ForeName>Annette M</ForeName><Initials>AM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Large Animal Clinical Sciences, College of Veterinary Medicine, Michigan State University, East Lansing, MI, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ruple</LastName><ForeName>Audrey</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Population Health Sciences, VA-MD College of Veterinary Medicine, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, VA, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Front Vet Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101666658</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2297-1769</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">outcomes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">outcomes research</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">research impact</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">validity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">veterinary</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest. The author(s) declared that they were an editorial board member of Frontiers, at the time of submission. This had no impact on the peer review process and the final decision.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>58</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>57</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39323872</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11423354</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fvets.2024.1444023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Sargeant JM, O’Connor AM, LeBlanc SJ, Winder CB. Invited review: maximizing value and minimizing waste in clinical trial research in dairy cattle: selecting interventions and outcomes to build an evidence base. J Dairy Sci. (2022) 105:8594–608. doi: 10.3168/jds.2022-22015, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3168/jds.2022-22015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36055845</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sargeant JM, O’Connor AM, Renter DG, Ruple A. What question are we trying to answer? Embracing causal inference. Front Vet Sci. (2024) 11:1402981. doi: 10.3389/fvets.2024.1402981, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fvets.2024.1402981</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11149352</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38835899</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bello NM, Renter DG. Invited review: reproducible research from noisy data: revisiting key statistical principles for the animal sciences. J Dairy Sci. (2018) 101:5679–701. doi: 10.3168/jds.2017-13978, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3168/jds.2017-13978</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29729923</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sargeant JM, O’Connor AM, O’Sullivan TL, Ramirez A. Maximizing value and minimizing waste in clinical trial research in swine: selecting outcomes to build an evidence base. J Swine Health Prod. (2023) 31:29–35. doi: 10.54846/jshap/1300</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.54846/jshap/1300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cernicchiaro N, Oliveira ARS, Hanthorn C, Renter DG. Outcomes research: origins, relevance, and potential impacts for veterinary medicine. J Am Vet Med Assoc. (2022) 260:714–23. doi: 10.2460/javma.21.06.0318</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2460/javma.21.06.0318</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35092660</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horton LM, Depenbusch BE, Dewsbury DM, McAtee TB, Betts NB, Renter DG. Comprehensive outcomes affected by antimicrobial metaphylaxis of feedlot calves at medium-risk for bovine respiratory disease from a randomized controlled trial. Vet Sci. (2023) 10:67. doi: 10.3390/vetsci10020067, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/vetsci10020067</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9960805</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36851371</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dixon AL, Hanthorn CJ, Pendell DL, Cernicchiaro N, Renter DG. Economic assessments from experimental research trials of feedlot cattle health and performance: a scoping review. Transl Anim Sci. (2022) 6:txac077. doi: 10.1093/tas/txac077, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/tas/txac077</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9280984</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35854971</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Winder CB, Churchill KJ, Sargeant JM, LeBlanc SJ, O’Connor AM, Renaud DL. Invited review: completeness of reporting of experiments: REFLECTing on a year of animal trials in the journal of dairy science. J Dairy Sci. (2019) 102:4759–71. doi: 10.3168/jds.2018-15797</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3168/jds.2018-15797</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31005322</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruple A, Sargeant JM, Selmic LE, O’Connor AM. The standards of reporting randomized trials in pets (PetSORT): methods and development processes. Front Vet Sci. (2023) 10:1137774. doi: 10.3389/fvets.2023.1137774, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fvets.2023.1137774</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10103610</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37065218</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sargeant JM, Ruple A, Selmic LE, O’Connor AM. The standards of reporting trials in pets (PetSORT): explanation and elaboration. Front Vet Sci. (2023) 10:1137781. doi: 10.3389/fvets.2023.1137781, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fvets.2023.1137781</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10103631</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37065227</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sargeant JM, O’Connor AM, Gardner IA, Dickson JS, Torrence ME, Dohoo IR, et al. . The REFLECT statement: reporting guidelines for randomized controlled trials in livestock and food safety: explanation and elaboration. J Food Prot. (2010) 73:579–603. doi: 10.4315/0362-028x-73.3.579, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4315/0362-028x-73.3.579</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20202349</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Connor AM, Sargeant JM, Gardner IA, Dickson JS, Torrence ME, Participants CM, et al. . The REFLECT statement: methods and processes of creating reporting guidelines for randomized controlled trials for livestock and food safety by modifying the CONSORT statement. Zoonoses Public Health. (2010) 57:95–104. doi: 10.1111/j.1863-2378.2009.01311</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1863-2378.2009.01311</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20070653</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Good Practices Reports &amp; More . ISPOR—the professional society for health economics and outcomes research. Available at:
https://www.ispor.org/heor-resources/good-practices (Accessed May 31, 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dewsbury DMA, Renter DG, Bradford BJ, DeDonder KD, Mellencamp M, Cernicchiaro N. The application, value, and impact of outcomes research in animal health and veterinary medicine. Front Vet Sci. (2022) 9:972057. doi: 10.3389/fvets.2022.972057, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fvets.2022.972057</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9744767</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36524226</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>