<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39323262</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1750-3841</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>25</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of food science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Food Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A review on rebaudioside M: The next generation steviol glycoside and noncaloric sweetener.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1750-3841.17401</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>So far, the use of artificial low-calorie sweeteners, like sucralose, saccharin, and so on, to replace the conventional-based sugars has not succeeded due to the long-term adverse health effects, for example, hypertension, and not well-known safety stand. In this review, we discussed the next generation SvGl (rebaudioside M [Reb M]), their biosynthetic pathway in plant, high-yield production via microbial fermentation and enzyme engineering, physicochemical properties, taste modification, kinetic metabolism, application in food and beverages, safety and toxicological evaluation, regulation and dosage recommendation, and health benefits. In stevia, the biosynthesis of stevia glycosides, especially Reb M, is derived from the bifurcation of the pathway leading to gibberellin, followed by subsequent enzymatic modification of rubusoside. Reb M is more economically produced via microbial fermentation of modified yeast Yarrowia lipolytica and enzymatic bioconversion of rebaudioside A (Reb A) or Reb E. Reb M can serve as a suitable alternative to the conventional-based sugars.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Institute of Food Technologists.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Okonkwo</LastName><ForeName>Clinton E</ForeName><Initials>CE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Food and Biological Engineering, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science, College of Food and Agriculture, United Arab Emirates University, Al Ain, UAE.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Adeyanju</LastName><ForeName>Adeyemi A</ForeName><Initials>AA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Microbiology, College of Pure and Applied Science, Landmark University, Omu-Aran, Kwara State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Onyeaka</LastName><ForeName>Helen</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3846-847X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Chemical Engineering, University of Birmingham, Birmingham, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nwonuma</LastName><ForeName>Charles Obiora</ForeName><Initials>CO</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biochemistry, College of Pure and Applied Sciences, Landmark University, Omu-Aran, Kwara State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Olaniran</LastName><ForeName>Abiola F</ForeName><Initials>AF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Microbiology, College of Pure and Applied Science, Landmark University, Omu-Aran, Kwara State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alejolowo</LastName><ForeName>Omokolade Oluwaseyi</ForeName><Initials>OO</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biochemistry, College of Pure and Applied Sciences, Landmark University, Omu-Aran, Kwara State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Inyinbor</LastName><ForeName>Adejumoke A</ForeName><Initials>AA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Physical Sciences Department, Industrial Chemistry Programme, Landmark University, Omu-Aran, Kwara State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Oluyori</LastName><ForeName>Abimbola Peter</ForeName><Initials>AP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Physical Sciences Department, Industrial Chemistry Programme, Landmark University, Omu-Aran, Kwara State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Cunshan</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9119-3941</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Food and Biological Engineering, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>32072174</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>CX (21) 2026</GrantID><Agency>Jiangsu Agricultural Science and Technology Innovation Fund</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>XTCX2019</GrantID><Agency>Open Fund Project of Provincial Ministry Co-operative Innovation Centre for Modern Agricultural Equipment and Technology</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>CE20222011</GrantID><Agency>Changzhou Science and Technology Projects-Agricultural Science and Technology</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>BE2020776</GrantID><Agency>Social Development General Project of Jiangsu</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>BZ2024050</GrantID><Agency>Special Fund for Science and Technology Plan of Jiangsu Province-"the Belt and Road" Innovation Cooperation Project</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Food Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0014052</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-1147</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Stevia rebaudiana</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">microbial fermentation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">rebaudioside M</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">steviol glycosides</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">uridine‐diphosphate glycosyltransferases</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>57</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>57</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39323262</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1750-3841.17401</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Abudula, R., Jeppesen, P. B., Rolfsen, S. E. D., Xiao, J., &amp; Hermansen, K. (2004). Rebaudioside A potently stimulates insulin secretion from isolated mouse islets: Studies on the dose‐, glucose‐, and calcium‐dependency. Metabolism, 53(10), 1378–1381. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.metabol.2004.04.014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Acevedo, W., Ramírez‐Sarmiento, C. A., &amp; Agosin, E. (2018). Identifying the interactions between natural, non‐caloric sweeteners and the human sweet receptor by molecular docking. Food Chemistry, 264, 164–171. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2018.04.113</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmad, J., Khan, I., Blundell, R., Azzopardi, J., &amp; Mahomoodally, M. F. (2020). Stevia rebaudiana Bertoni.: An updated review of its health benefits, industrial applications and safety. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 100, 177–189. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2020.04.030</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ameer, K., Ameer, S., Kim, Y. M., Nadeem, M., Park, M. K., Murtaza, M. A., Khan, M. A., Nasir, M. A., Mueen‐Ud‐din, G., Mahmood, S., Kausar, T., &amp; Abubakar, M. (2022). A hybrid RSM‐ANN‐GA approach on optimization of ultrasound‐assisted extraction conditions for bioactive component‐rich Stevia rebaudiana (Bertoni) leaves extract. Foods, 11(6), 883. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods11060883/s1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ameer, K., Bae, S. W., Jo, Y., Chung, N., Gao, Y., &amp; Kwon, J. H. (2017). Optimization and modeling for heat reflux extraction of total yield, stevioside and rebaudioside‐A from Stevia rebaudiana (Bertoni) leaves. Separation Science and Technology, 52(7), 1193–1205. https://doi.org/10.1080/01496395.2017.1285313</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anderson, J. C., Carlson, T. L., &amp; Fosmer, A. M. (2022). Fermentation methods for producing steviol glycosides with multi‐phase feeding (U.S. Patent No. 11,225,678). U.S. Patent and Trademark Office.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anker, C. C. B., Rafiq, S., &amp; Jeppesen, P. B. (2019). Effect of steviol glycosides on human health with emphasis on type 2 diabetic biomarkers: A systematic review and meta‐analysis of randomized controlled trials. Nutrients, 11(9), 1965.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barriocanal, L. A., Palacios, M., Benitez, G., Benitez, S., Jimenez, J. T., Jimenez, N., &amp; Rojas, V. (2008). Apparent lack of pharmacological effect of steviol glycosides used as sweeteners in humans. A pilot study of repeated exposures in some normotensive and hypotensive individuals and in type 1 and type 2 diabetics. Regulatory Toxicology and Pharmacology, 51(1), 37–41. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.yrtph.2008.02.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bennett, R. D., Lieber, E. R., &amp; Heftmann, E. (1967). Biosynthesis of steviol from (−)‐kaurene. Phytochemistry, 6(8), 1107–1110. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0031‐9422(00)86068‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brewster, E. (2021). Solving for sugar reduction. Food Technology, 75(4), 39–47.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bian, J., Xia, Y., Han, R., Wang, C., He, J., &amp; Zhong, F. (2023). How to determine iso‐sweet concentrations for various sweeteners: Insights from consumers and trained panels. Food Quality and Preference, 107, 104824. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodqual.2023.104824</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bondarev, N. I., Sukhanova, M. A., Reshetnyak, O. V., &amp; Nosov, A. M. (2003). Steviol glycoside content in different organs of Stevia rebaudiana and its dynamics during ontogeny. Biologia Plantarum, 47(2), 261–264. https://doi.org/10.1023/b:biop.0000022261.35259.4f/metrics</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brambilla, E., Cagetti, M. G., Ionescu, A., Campus, G., &amp; Lingström, P. (2014). An in vitro and in vivo comparison of the effect of Stevia rebaudiana extracts on different caries‐related variables: A randomized controlled trial pilot study. Caries Research, 48(1), 19–23. https://doi.org/10.1159/000351650</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brandle, J. E., &amp; Telmer, P. G. (2007). Steviol glycoside biosynthesis. Phytochemistry, 68(14), 1855–1863. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2007.02.010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bursać Kovačević, D., Barba, F. J., Granato, D., Galanakis, C. M., Herceg, Z., Dragović‐Uzelac, V., &amp; Putnik, P. (2018). Pressurized hot water extraction (PHWE) for the green recovery of bioactive compounds and steviol glycosides from Stevia rebaudiana Bertoni leaves. Food Chemistry, 254, 150–157. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2018.01.192</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bursać Kovačević, D., Maras, M., Barba, F. J., Granato, D., Roohinejad, S., Mallikarjunan, K., Montesano, D., Lorenzo, J. M., &amp; Putnik, P. (2018). Innovative technologies for the recovery of phytochemicals from Stevia rebaudiana Bertoni leaves: A review. Food Chemistry, 268, 513–521. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2018.06.091</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carakostas, M. C., Curry, L. L., Boileau, A. C., &amp; Brusick, D. J. (2008). Overview: The history, technical function and safety of rebaudioside A, a naturally occurring steviol glycoside, for use in food and beverages. Food and Chemical Toxicology, 46(7), S1–S10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carbonell‐Capella, J. M., Šic Žlabur, J., Rimac Brnčić, S., Barba, F. J., Grimi, N., Koubaa, M., Brnčić, M., &amp; Vorobiev, E. (2017). Electrotechnologies, microwaves, and ultrasounds combined with binary mixtures of ethanol and water to extract steviol glycosides and antioxidant compounds from Stevia rebaudiana leaves. Journal of Food Processing and Preservation, 41(5), e13179. https://doi.org/10.1111/JFPP.13179</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castro‐Muñoz, R., Correa‐Delgado, M., Córdova‐Almeida, R., Lara‐Nava, D., Chávez‐Muñoz, M., Velásquez‐Chávez, V. F., Hernández‐Torres, C. E., Gontarek‐Castro, E., &amp; Ahmad, M. Z. (2022). Natural sweeteners: Sources, extraction and current uses in foods and food industries. Food Chemistry, 370, 130991. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2021.130991</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ceunen, S., &amp; Geuns, J. M. C. (2013). Steviol glycosides: Chemical diversity, metabolism, and function. Journal of Natural Products, 76(6), 1201–1228.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chakraborty, R., &amp; Roy, S. (2021). Angiotensin‐converting enzyme inhibitors from plants: A review of their diversity, modes of action, prospects, and concerns in the management of diabetes‐centric complications. Journal of Integrative Medicine, 19(6), 478–492. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.joim.2021.09.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, J., Xia, Y., Sui, X., Peng, Q., Zhang, T., Li, J., &amp; Zhang, J. (2018). Steviol, a natural product inhibits proliferation of the gastrointestinal cancer cells intensively. Oncotarget, 9(41), 26299. https://doi.org/10.18632/oncotarget.25233</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, L., Cai, R., Weng, J., Li, Y., Jia, H., Chen, K., Yan, M., &amp; Ouyang, P. (2020). Production of rebaudioside D from stevioside using a UGTSL2 Asn358Phe mutant in a multi‐enzyme system. Microbial Biotechnology, 13(4), 974–983. https://doi.org/10.1111/1751‐7915.13539</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, L., Pan, H., Cai, R., Li, Y., Jia, H., Chen, K., Yan, M., &amp; Ouyang, P. (2021). Bioconversion of stevioside to rebaudioside E using glycosyltransferase UGTSL2. Applied Biochemistry and Biotechnology, 193(3), 637–649. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12010‐020‐03439‐y/metrics</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chéron, J. B., Golebiowski, J., Antonczak, S., &amp; Fiorucci, S. (2017). The anatomy of mammalian sweet taste receptors. Proteins: Structure, Function, and Bioinformatics, 85(2), 332–341.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Darise, M., Mizutani, K., Kasai, R., Tanaka, O., Kitahata, S., Okada, S., Ogawa, S., Murakami, F., &amp; Chen, F. H. (1984). Enzymic transglucosylation of rubusoside and the structure‐sweetness relationship of steviol‐bisglycosides. Agricultural and Biological Chemistry, 48(10), 2483–2488. https://doi.org/10.1080/00021369.1984.10866520</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Díaz‐Montes, E., Gutiérrez‐Macías, P., Orozco‐Álvarez, C., &amp; Castro‐Muñoz, R. (2020). Fractionation of Stevia rebaudiana aqueous extracts via two‐step ultrafiltration process: Towards rebaudioside a extraction. Food and Bioproducts Processing, 123, 111–122. https://doi.org/10.1016/J.FBP.2020.06.010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA Panel on Food Additives and Nutrient Sources added to Food. (2015). Scientific opinion on the safety of the proposed amendment of the specifications for steviol glycosides (E 960) as a food additive. EFSA Journal, 13(12), 4316.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FDA. (2018). GRAS Notice GRN 812 for Rebaudioside M. https://www.fda.gov/media/130891/download. Accessed 1st January 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA Panel on Food Additives and Flavourings (FAF). Younes, M., Aquilina, G., Engel, K. H., Fowler, P., Frutos Fernandez, M. J., Fürst, P., Gürtler, R., Gundert‐Remy, U., Husøy, T., Mennes, W., Moldeus, P., Oskarsson, A., Shah, R., Waalkens‐Berendsen, I., Wölfle, D., Degen, G., Gott, D., Leblanc, J. C., … Castle, L.. (2019). Safety of the proposed amendment of the specifications for steviol glycosides (E 960) as a food additive: Rebaudioside M produced via enzyme‐catalysed bioconversion of purified stevia leaf extract. EFSA Journal, 17(10), e05867.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gallo, M., Vitulano, M., Andolfi, A., DellaGreca, M., Conte, E., Ciaravolo, M., &amp; Naviglio, D. (2017). Rapid solid–liquid dynamic extraction (RSLDE): A new rapid and greener method for extracting two steviol glycosides (stevioside and rebaudioside A) from stevia leaves. Plant Foods for Human Nutrition, 72(2), 141–148. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11130‐017‐0598‐1/metrics</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gelinas, B. S., Liu, Y., Tello, E., &amp; Peterson, D. G. (2022). Untargeted LC–MS based identification of rebaudioside A degradation products impacting flavor perception during storage. Food Chemistry, 373, 131457. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2021.131457</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Geuns, J. M. C., Buyse, J., Vankeirsbilck, A., Temme, E. H. M., Compernolle, F., &amp; Toppet, S. (2006). Identification of steviol glucuronide in human urine. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 54(7), 2794–2798.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>GRAS Notice. (2019). GRAS notification of rebaudioside M (95%) ((GRN) No. 846). GRAS Associates. https://fda.report/media/135172/GRAS‐Notice‐GRN‐846‐Rebaudioside‐M.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gu, W., Rebsdorf, A., Anker, C., Gregersen, S., Hermansen, K., Geuns, J. M. C., &amp; Jeppesen, P. B. (2019). Steviol glucuronide, a metabolite of steviol glycosides, potently stimulates insulin secretion from isolated mouse islets: Studies in vitro. Endocrinology, Diabetes &amp; Metabolism, 2(4), e00093. https://doi.org/10.1002/edm2.93</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guleria, P., &amp; Yadav, S. K. (2013). Agrobacterium mediated transient gene silencing (AMTS) in Stevia rebaudiana: Insights into steviol glycoside biosynthesis pathway. PLoS ONE, 8(9), e74731. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0074731</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo, B., Deng, Z., Meng, F., Wang, Q., Zhang, Y., Yuan, Z., &amp; Rao, Y. (2022). Enhancement of rebaudioside M production by structure‐guided engineering of glycosyltransferase UGT76G1. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 70(16), 5088–5094.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo, M., Yang, K., Zhou, Z., Chen, Y., Zhou, Z., Chen, P., Huang, R., &amp; Wang, X. (2023). Inhibitory effects of stevioside on Streptococcus mutans and Candida albicans dual‐species biofilm. Frontiers in Microbiology, 14, 1128668. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2023.1128668/full</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>He, B., Bai, X., Tan, Y., Xie, W., Feng, Y., &amp; Yang, G. Y. (2022). Glycosyltransferases: Mining, engineering and applications in biosynthesis of glycosylated plant natural products. Synthetic and Systems Biotechnology, 7(1), 602–620.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hedden, P., &amp; Thomas, S. G. (2012). Gibberellin biosynthesis and its regulation. Biochemical Journal, 444(1), 11–25. https://doi.org/10.1042/BJ20120245</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hutapea, A. M., Toskulkao, C., Buddhasukh, D., Wilairat, P., &amp; Glinsukon, T. (1997). Digestion of stevioside, a natural sweetener, by various digestive enzymes. Journal of Clinical Biochemistry and Nutrition, 23(3), 177–186.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iatridis, N., Kougioumtzi, A., Vlataki, K., Papadaki, S., &amp; Magklara, A. (2022). Anti‐cancer properties of Stevia rebaudiana; more than a sweetener. Molecules, 27(4), 1362. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules27041362</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackson, A. U., Tata, A., Wu, C., Perry, R. H., Haas, G., West, L., &amp; Cooks, R. G. (2009). Direct analysis of stevia leaves for diterpene glycosides by desorption electrospray ionization mass spectrometry. Analyst, 134(5), 867–874. https://doi.org/10.1039/b823511b</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jan, S. A., Habib, N., Shinwari, Z. K., Ali, M., &amp; Ali, N. (2021). The anti‐diabetic activities of natural sweetener plant stevia: An updated review. SN Applied Sciences, 3(4), 1–6. https://doi.org/10.1007/s42452‐021‐04519‐2/tables/2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeppesen, P. B., Gregersen, S., Poulsen, C. R., &amp; Hermansen, K. (2000). Stevioside acts directly on pancreatic β cells to secrete insulin: Actions independent of cyclic adenosine monophosphate and adenosine triphosphate—Sensitivie K+‐channel activity. Metabolism, 49(2), 208–214. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0026‐0495(00)91325‐8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jung, J., Kim, S. H., Park, S., &amp; Hong, J. H. (2021). Sweetness profiles of glycosylated rebaudioside A and its binary mixtures with allulose and maltitol. Food Science and Biotechnology, 30(3), 423–432. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10068‐020‐00873‐w/figures/1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalicka, D., Znamirowska, A., Buniowska, M., Esteve Más, M. J., &amp; Frigola Canoves, A. (2017). Effect of stevia addition on selected properties of yoghurt during refrigerated storage. Polish Journal of Natural Sciences, 32(2), 323–334.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kasahara, H., Hanada, A., Kuzuyama, T., Takagi, M., Kamiya, Y., &amp; Yamaguchi, S. (2002). Contribution of the mevalonate and methylerythritol phosphate pathways to the biosynthesis of gibberellins in Arabidopsis. Journal of Biological Chemistry, 277(47), 45188–45194. https://doi.org/10.1074/jbc.m208659200</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keefer, H. R. M., Nishku, S., Gerard, P. D., &amp; Drake, M. A. (2020). Role of sweeteners on temporality and bar hardening of protein bars. Journal of Dairy Science, 103(7), 6032–6053. https://doi.org/10.3168/jds.2019‐17995</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khilar, S., Singh, A. P., Biagi, M., &amp; Sharma, A. (2022). An insight into attributes of Stevia rebaudiana Bertoni: Recent advances in extraction techniques, phytochemistry, food applications and health benefits. Journal of Agriculture and Food Research, 10, 100458. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jafr.2022.100458</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kurek, J. M., &amp; Krejpcio, Z. (2019). The functional and health‐promoting properties of Stevia rebaudiana Bertoni and its glycosides with special focus on the antidiabetic potential—A review. Journal of Functional Foods, 61, 103465. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jff.2019.103465</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laquatra, I., Sollid, K., Edge, M. S., Pelzel, J., &amp; Turner, J. (2015). Including “added sugars” on the nutrition facts panel: How consumers perceive the proposed change. Journal of the Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics, 115(11), 1758–1763.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Le Donne, C., Mistura, L., Goscinny, S., Janvier, S., Cuypers, K., D'Addezio, L., Sette, S., Catasta, G., Ferrari, M., Piccinelli, R., Van Loco, J., &amp; Turrini, A. (2017). Assessment of dietary intake of 10 intense sweeteners by the Italian population. Food and Chemical Toxicology, 102, 186–197. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fct.2017.02.014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee, H. N., Hong, S. J., Kang, H. J., Ju, J. H., Park, B. R., Ko, J. A., &amp; Kim, Y. M. (2021). Effective rebaudioside a separation from stevia extracts by enzymatic bioconversion. Journal of Food Processing and Preservation, 45(3), e15202. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfpp.15202</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lima, Y. C., Kurauti, M. A., daFonseca Alves, G., Ferezini, J., Piovan, S., Malta, A., de Almeida, F. L. A., Gomes, R. M., de Freitas Mathias, P. C., Milani, P. G., daCosta, S. C., &amp; Mareze‐Costa, C. E. (2019). Whey protein sweetened with Stevia rebaudiana Bertoni (Bert.) increases mitochondrial biogenesis markers in the skeletal muscle of resistance‐trained rats. Nutrition &amp; Metabolism, 16(1), 1–11. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12986‐019‐0391‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, X., Hu, Y., Wei, B., Liu, F., Xu, H., Liu, C., Li, Y., &amp; Liang, H. (2022). Immobilized glucosyltransferase and sucrose synthase on Fe3O4@Uio‐66 in cascade catalysis for the one‐pot conversion of rebaudioside D from rebaudioside A. Process Biochemistry, 118, 323–334. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.procbio.2022.05.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moongngarm, A., Sriharboot, N., Loypimai, P., &amp; Moontree, T. (2022). Ohmic heating‐assisted water extraction of steviol glycosides and phytochemicals from Stevia rebaudiana leaves. LWT, 154, 112798. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2021.112798</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muenprasitivej, N., Tao, R., Nardone, S. J., &amp; Cho, S. (2022). The effect of steviol glycosides on sensory properties and acceptability of ice cream. Foods, 11(12), 1745.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nuemket, N., Yasui, N., Kusakabe, Y., Nomura, Y., Atsumi, N., Akiyama, S., … &amp; Yamashita, A. (2017). Structural basis for perception of diverse chemical substances by T1r taste receptors. Nature communications, 8(1), 15530.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olsson, K., Carlsen, S., Semmler, A., Simón, E., Mikkelsen, M. D., &amp; Møller, B. L. (2016). Microbial production of next‐generation stevia sweeteners. Microbial Cell Factories, 15(1), 1–14. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12934‐016‐0609‐1/figures/7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perrier, J. D., Mihalov, J. J., &amp; Carlson, S. J. (2018). FDA regulatory approach to steviol glycosides. Food and Chemical Toxicology, 122, 132–142. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fct.2018.09.062</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ping, Q., Yang, L., Jiang, J., Yuan, J., Ai, S., Sun, S., Ni, Z., Yang, S., Yuan, Z., Rao, Y., &amp; Zhang, Y. (2022). Efficient synthesis of rebaudioside D2 through UGT94D1‐catalyzed regio‐selective glycosylation. Carbohydrate Research, 522, 108687. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.carres.2022.108687</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prakash, I., Chaturvedula, V. S. P., &amp; Markosyan, A. (2013). Isolation, characterisation and sensory evaluation of a hexa β‐d‐glucopyranosyl diterpene from Stevia rebaudiana. Natural Product Communications, 8(11), 1934578X1300801106.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prakash, I., Bunders, C., Devkota, K. P., Charan, R. D., Ramirez, C., Priedemann, C., &amp; Markosyan, A. (2014). Isolation and characterization of a novel rebaudioside M isomer from a bioconversion reaction of rebaudioside A and NMR comparison studies of rebaudioside M isolated from Stevia rebaudiana Bertoni and Stevia rebaudiana morita. Biomolecules, 4(2), 374–389. https://doi.org/10.3390/biom4020374</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prakash, I., Chaturvedula, V. S. P., &amp; Markosyan, A. (2014). Structural characterization of the degradation products of a minor natural sweet diterpene glycoside rebaudioside M under acidic conditions. International Journal of Molecular Sciences, 15(1), 1014–1025. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms15011014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prakash, I., Ma, G., Bunders, C., Devkota, K. P., Charan, R. D., Ramirez, C., Snyder, T. M., &amp; Priedemann, C. (2015). A new diterpene glycoside: 15α‐Hydroxy‐rebaudioside M isolated from Stevia rebaudiana. Natural Product Communications, 10(7), 1159–1161.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prakash, I., Markosyan, A., &amp; Bunders, C. (2014). Development of next generation stevia sweetener: Rebaudioside M. Foods, 3(1), 162–175. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods3010162</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prakash, I., &amp; Chaturvedula, V. S. P. (2018). Steviol glycosides: Natural noncaloric sweeteners. In J. M. Merillon &amp; K Ramawat (Eds.), Reference series in phytochemistry (pp. 101–128). Springer.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Purkayastha, S., &amp; Kwok, D. (2020). Metabolic fate in adult and pediatric population of steviol glycosides produced from stevia leaf extract by different production technologies. Regulatory Toxicology and Pharmacology, 116, 104727. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.yrtph.2020.104727</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Purkayastha, S., Markosyan, A., Prakash, I., Bhusari, S., Pugh, G., Lynch, B., &amp; Roberts, A. (2016). Steviol glycosides in purified stevia leaf extract sharing the same metabolic fate. Regulatory Toxicology and Pharmacology, 77, 125–133. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.yrtph.2016.02.015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Purkayastha, S., Pugh, G., Lynch, B., Roberts, A., Kwok, D., &amp; Tarka, S. M. (2014). In vitro metabolism of rebaudioside B, D, and M under anaerobic conditions: Comparison with rebaudioside A. Regulatory Toxicology and Pharmacology, 68(2), 259–268. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.yrtph.2013.12.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raspe, D. T., daSilva, C., &amp; Cláudio da Costa, S. (2022). Compounds from Stevia rebaudiana Bertoni leaves: An overview of non‐conventional extraction methods and challenges. Food Bioscience, 46, 101593. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fbio.2022.101593</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richman, A., Swanson, A., Humphrey, T., Chapman, R., McGarvey, B., Pocs, R., &amp; Brandle, J. (2005). Functional genomics uncovers three glucosyltransferases involved in the synthesis of the major sweet glucosides of Stevia rebaudiana. The Plant Journal, 41(1), 56–67. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365‐313x.2004.02275.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruddat, M., Heftmann, E., &amp; Lang, A. (1965). Biosynthesis of steviol. Archives of Biochemistry and Biophysics, 110(3), 496–499. https://doi.org/10.1016/0003‐9861(65)90441‐8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Samah, N. A., Hisham, A. D. A., &amp; Rahim, S. A. (2013). Determination of stevioside and rebaudioside A in Stevia rebaudiana leaves via preparative high performance liquid chromatography (prep‐HPLC). International Journal of Chemical and Environmental Engineering, 4(2), 86–89.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Samuel, P., Ayoob, K. T., Magnuson, B. A., Wölwer‐Rieck, U., Jeppesen, P. B., Rogers, P. J., Rowland, I., &amp; Mathews, R. (2018). Stevia leaf to stevia sweetener: Exploring its science, benefits, and future potential. The Journal of Nutrition, 148(7), 1186S–1205S. https://doi.org/10.1093/jn/nxy102</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shivanna, N., Naika, M., Khanum, F., &amp; Kaul, V. K. (2013). Antioxidant, anti‐diabetic and renal protective properties of Stevia rebaudiana. Journal of Diabetes and Its Complications, 27(2), 103–113. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jdiacomp.2012.10.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shu, W., Zheng, H., Fu, X., Zhen, J., Tan, M., Xu, J., Zhao, X., Yang, S., Song, H., &amp; Ma, Y. (2020). Enhanced heterologous production of glycosyltransferase UGT76G1 by co‐expression of endogenous prpD and malK in Escherichia coli and its transglycosylation application in production of rebaudioside. International Journal of Molecular Sciences, 21(16), 5752. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms21165752</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soejarto, D. D., Addo, E. M., &amp; Kinghorn, A. D. (2019). Highly sweet compounds of plant origin: From ethnobotanical observations to wide utilization. Journal of Ethnopharmacology, 243, 112056. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jep.2019.112056</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sponsel, V. M., &amp; Hedden, P. (2010). Gibberellin biosynthesis and inactivation. In Plant hormones: Biosynthesis, signal transduction, action! (pp. 63–94). Springer. https://doi.org/10.1007/978‐1‐4020‐2686‐7_4/cover</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suresh, P. S., Singh, P. P., Sharma, M., &amp; Sharma, U. (2023). Multicomponent natural deep eutectic solvents: Super solvents for the efficient extraction of steviol glycosides (rebaudioside A) from Stevia rebaudiana. Journal of Cleaner Production, 385, 135639. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclepro.2022.135639</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Talevi, A. (2022). Potential medicinal effects and applications of stevia constituents. Phytochemistry Reviews, 21(1), 161–178. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11101‐021‐09753‐5/metrics</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tao, R. (2020). Discrimination and sensory characterization of steviol glycosides (rebaudioside A, D, and M) by consumers and electronic tongue. Michigan State University.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tao, R., &amp; Cho, S. (2020). Consumer‐based sensory characterization of steviol glycosides (rebaudioside A, D, and M). Foods, 9(8), 1026.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tian, X., Zhong, F., &amp; Xia, Y. (2022). Dynamic characteristics of sweetness and bitterness and their correlation with chemical structures for six steviol glycosides. Food Research International, 151, 110848. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2021.110848</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Totté, N., Ende, W. V. D., Van Damme, E. J., Compernolle, F., Baboeuf, I., &amp; Geuns, J. M. (2003). Cloning and heterologous expression of early genes in gibberellin and steviol biosynthesis via the methylerythritol phosphate pathway in Stevia rebaudiana. Canadian Journal of Botany, 81(5), 517–522.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Upreti, M., Dubois, G., &amp; Prakash, I. (2012). Synthetic study on the relationship between structure and sweet taste properties of steviol glycosides. Molecules, 17(4), 4186–4196.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vallejo, V. A., &amp; Warner, R. M. (2021). Identifying quantitative trait loci for steviol glycoside production in Stevia rebaudiana using transcriptome‐derived SSRs. Industrial Crops and Products, 161, 113176. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.indcrop.2020.113176</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vanneste, J., Sotto, A., Courtin, C. M., Van Craeyveld, V., Bernaerts, K., Van Impe, J., Vandeur, J., Taes, S., &amp; Van Der Bruggen, B. (2011). Application of tailor‐made membranes in a multi‐stage process for the purification of sweeteners from Stevia rebaudiana. Journal of Food Engineering, 103(3), 285–293. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2010.10.026</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Velesiotis, C., Kanellakis, M., &amp; Vynios, D. H. (2022). Steviol glycosides affect functional properties and macromolecular expression of breast cancer cells. IUBMB Life, 74(10), 1012–1028. https://doi.org/10.1002/iub.2669</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vogt, T., &amp; Jones, P. (2000). Glycosyltransferases in plant natural product synthesis: Characterization of a supergene family. Trends in Plant Science, 5(9), 380–386. https://doi.org/10.1016/s1360‐1385(00)01720‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Y., Luo, X., Chen, L., Mustapha, A. T., Yu, X., Zhou, C., &amp; Okonkwo, C. E. (2023). Natural and low‐caloric rebaudioside A as a substitute for dietary sugars: A comprehensive review. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 22(1), 615–642. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.13084</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Y., Sun, X., Jia, X., Zhu, L., &amp; Yin, H. (2021). Comparative transcriptomic of Stevia rebaudiana provides insight into rebaudioside D and rebaudioside M biosynthesis. Plant Physiology and Biochemistry, 167, 541–549. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.plaphy.2021.08.028</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Z., Liu, W., Liu, W., Ma, Y., Li, Y., Wang, B., Wei, X., Liu, Z., &amp; Song, H. (2021). Co‐immobilized recombinant glycosyltransferases efficiently convert rebaudioside A to M in cascade. RSC Advances, 11(26), 15785–15794. https://doi.org/10.1039/d0ra10574k</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Z., Yuan, Y., Liu, Y., Zhang, M., &amp; Hua, X. (2022). Modification on the length of glucosyl chain in glucosyl steviol glycosides and its effect on product taste quality. European Food Research and Technology, 248(7), 1703–1713. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00217‐022‐03997‐x/metrics</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, S., Xu, Y., Li, C., Tao, H., Wang, A., Sun, C., … &amp; Wang, Y. (2018). Gambogic acid sensitizes breast cancer cells to TRAIL‐induced apoptosis by promoting the crosstalk of extrinsic and intrinsic apoptotic signalings. Food and Chemical Toxicology, 119, 334–341.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu, Y., Wang, X., Zhang, C., Zhou, X., Xu, X., Han, L., Lv, X., Liu, Y., Liu, S., Li, J., Du, G., Chen, J., Ledesma‐Amaro, R., &amp; Liu, L. (2022). De novo biosynthesis of rubusoside and rebaudiosides in engineered yeasts. Nature Communications, 13(1), 1–12. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467‐022‐30826‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu, Y., Wu, Y., Liu, Y., Li, J., Du, G., Chen, J., Lv, X., &amp; Liu, L. (2022). Sustainable bioproduction of natural sugar substitutes: Strategies and challenges. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 129, 512–527. https://doi.org/10.1016/J.TIFS.2022.11.008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yadav, S. K., &amp; Guleria, P. (2012). Steviol glycosides from stevia: Biosynthesis pathway review and their application in foods and medicine. Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition, 52(11), 988–998.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yildiz‐Ozturk, E., Tag, O., &amp; Yesil‐Celiktas, O. (2014). Subcritical water extraction of steviol glycosides from Stevia rebaudiana leaves and characterization of the raffinate phase. The Journal of Supercritical Fluids, 95, 422–430. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.supflu.2014.10.017</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yılmaz, F. M., Görgüç, A., Uygun, Ö., &amp; Bircan, C. (2021). Steviol glycosides and polyphenols extraction from Stevia rebaudiana Bertoni leaves using maceration, microwave‐, and ultrasound‐assisted techniques. Separation Science and Technology, 56(5), 936–948.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu, J., Tao, Y., Pan, H., Lin, L., Sun, J., Ma, R., Li, Y., &amp; Jia, H. (2022). Mutation of stevia glycosyltransferase UGT76G1 for efficient biotransformation of rebaudioside E into rebaudioside M. Journal of Functional Foods, 92, 105033. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jff.2022.105033</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, J., Tang, M., Chen, Y., Ke, D., Zhou, J., Xu, X., Yang, W., He, J., Dong, H., Wei, Y., Naismith, J. H., Lin, Y., Zhu, X., &amp; Cheng, W. (2021). Catalytic flexibility of rice glycosyltransferase OsUGT91C1 for the production of palatable steviol glycosides. Nature Communications, 12(1), 1–12. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467‐021‐27144‐4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, R., Tang, R., Bi, J., Shen, S., Wu, Q., Chen, Q., &amp; Li, Y. (2023). Efficient bioconversion of stevioside and rebaudioside A to glucosylated steviol glycosides using an alkalihalobacillus oshimesis‐derived cyclodextrin glucanotransferase. Molecules, 28(3), 1245. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules28031245/s1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, S., Liu, Q., Lyu, C., Chen, J., Chen, J., Yang, Y., Zhang, H., Hou, K., &amp; Wu, W. (2020). Characterizing glycosyltransferases by a combination of sequencing platforms applied to the leaf tissues of Stevia rebaudiana. BMC Genomics, 21, 794. https://doi.org/10.21203/rs.3.rs‐24957/v4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, T., Zhang, Y., Sun, Y., Xu, X., Wang, Y., Chong, X., Yang, Y., &amp; Yuan, H. (2023). Isolation and functional analysis of SrMYB1, a direct transcriptional repressor of SrUGT76G1 in Stevia rebaudiana. Journal of Integrative Agriculture, 22(4), 1058–1067. https://doi.org/10.1016/J.JIA.2023.03.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, L., Wang, Y., Li, Z., Wang, X., Chen, Y., &amp; Wu, X. (2020). Enzymatic mosnoglucosylation of rubusoside and the structure‐sweetness/taste relationship of monoglucosyl derivatives. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 68(32), 8702–8709.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou, X., Gong, M., Lv, X., Liu, Y., Li, J., Du, G., &amp; Liu, L. (2021). Metabolic engineering for the synthesis of steviol glycosides: Current status and future prospects. Applied Microbiology and Biotechnology, 105(13), 5367–5381. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00253‐021‐11419‐3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou, Z., Xia, Y., &amp; Hu, X. (2023). Could one stone hit two or three birds on the stevia leaves? Harvesting rebaudioside A with enzymatic producing rubusoside directly from the stevia leaves. Industrial Crops and Products, 192, 116027. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.indcrop.2022.116027</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>