<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39323244</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1750-3841</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>25</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of food science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Food Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Lactiplantibacillus plantarum 299V fermented in microcapsules shows enhanced stability and could improve the microbial quality and safety of oysters through bioaccumulation.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1750-3841.17406</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>In this study, microcapsules of Lactiplantibacillus plantarum 299V were prepared using an emulsification/internal gelation technique. Loads of the probiotics were condensed to 9.86 ± 0.13 log CFU/g after 24 h fermentation of the microcapsules. Physical characterization revealed that L. plantarum 299V cells were uniformly distributed within the core of the microcapsules, with a mean diameter of 109.81 ± 0.39 µm and a span value of 0.36 ± 0.00, which were comparable to those of the unfermented microcapsules (p &gt; 0.05). The viability of L. plantarum 299V in the fermented microcapsules was 2.08 ± 0.15 log higher than that of free cells at the end of 5 h simulated gastrointestinal digestion (p &lt; 0.05). Oysters were able to accumulate the fermented microcapsules through filter feeding, resulting in a load of probiotics exceeding 6.00 log CFU/g. The presence of L. plantarum 299V-carrying microcapsules in oyster tissues significantly suppressed spoilage-causing bacteria during 11 days refrigeration storage, suggested by the tested parameters, including total psychrotrophic bacteria, H<sub>2</sub>S-producing bacteria, and Pseudomonas spp. (p &lt; 0.05). Pathogenic bacteria, including Vibrio parahaemolyticus and Salmonella enterica artificially introduced into oysters, were also significantly suppressed by over 1.00-log within 4 days compared to control samples (p &lt; 0.05). In summary, oysters bioaccumulated with fermented L. plantarum 299V-carrying microcapsules, justified a novel probiotic-carrying product to exsert the health-promoting effect of probiotics. This solution could also enhance the microbial quality and safety of oysters during storage.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Journal of Food Science published by Wiley Periodicals LLC on behalf of Institute of Food Technologists.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hua</LastName><ForeName>Qian</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science &amp; Technology, Faculty of Science, National University of Singapore, Singapore, Singapore.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Dan</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science &amp; Technology, Faculty of Science, National University of Singapore, Singapore, Singapore.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>National University of Singapore</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Food Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0014052</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-1147</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">microbial quality</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">oyster</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">probiotic microencapsulation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">simulated digestion</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>57</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>57</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39323244</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1750-3841.17406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Adilah, R. N., Chiu, S. T., Hu, S. Y., Ballantyne, R., Happy, N., Cheng, A. C., &amp; Liu, C. H. (2022). Improvement in the probiotic efficacy of Bacillus subtilis E20‐stimulates growth and health status of white shrimp, Litopenaeus vannamei via encapsulation in alginate and coated with chitosan. Fish and Shellfish Immunology, 125, 74–83. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fsi.2022.05.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brands, D. A., Inman, A. E., Gerba, C. P., Maré, C. J., Billington, S. J., Saif, L. A., Levine, J. F., &amp; Joens, L. A. (2005). Prevalence of Salmonella spp. in oysters in the United States. Applied and Environmental Microbiology, 71(2), 893–897. https://doi.org/10.1128/AEM.71.2.893‐897.2005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brodkorb, A., Egger, L., Alminger, M., Alvito, P., Assunção, R., Ballance, S., Bohn, T., Bourlieu‐Lacanal, C., Boutrou, R., Carrière, F., Clemente, A., Corredig, M., Dupont, D., Dufour, C., Edwards, C., Golding, M., Karakaya, S., Kirkhus, B., Le Feunteun, S., … Recio, I. (2019). INFOGEST static in vitro simulation of gastrointestinal food digestion. Nature Protocols, 14(4), 991–1014. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41596‐018‐0119‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brumfield, K. D., Chen, A. J., Gangwar, M., Usmani, M., Hasan, N. A., Jutla, A. S., Huq, A., &amp; Colwell, R. R. (2023). Environmental factors influencing occurrence of Vibrio parahaemolyticus and Vibrio vulnificus. Applied and Environmental Microbiology, 89(6), e0030723. https://doi.org/10.1128/aem.00307‐23</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cai, S., Zhao, M., Fang, Y., Nishinari, K., Phillips, G. O., &amp; Jiang, F. (2014). Microencapsulation of Lactobacillus acidophilus CGMCC1.2686 via emulsification/internal gelation of alginate using Ca‐EDTA and CaCO3 as calcium sources. Food Hydrocolloids, 39, 295–300. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodhyd.2014.01.021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cani, P. D., &amp; Van Hul, M. (2015). Novel opportunities for next‐generation probiotics targeting metabolic syndrome. Current Opinion in Biotechnology, 32, 21–27. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.copbio.2014.10.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. (2024). Foodborne diseases active surveillance network (FoodNet). https://wwwn.cdc.gov/foodnetfast/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chauhan, A., &amp; Singh, R. (2018). Probiotics in aquaculture: A promising emerging alternative approach. Symbiosis, 77(2), 99–113. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13199‐018‐0580‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chytiri, S., Paleologos, E., Savvaidis, I., &amp; Kontominas, M. G. (2004). Relation of biogenic amines with microbial and sensory changes of whole and filleted freshwater rainbow trout (Onchorynchus mykiss) stored on ice. Journal of Food Protection, 67(5), 960–965. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028x‐67.5.960</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cuevas‐González, P. F., Liceaga, A. M., &amp; Aguilar‐Toalá, J. E. (2020). Postbiotics and paraprobiotics: From concepts to applications. Food Research International, 136, 109502. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2020.109502</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eshaghi Gorji, M., &amp; Li, D. (2022). Photoinactivation of bacteriophage MS2, Tulane virus and Vibrio parahaemolyticus in oysters by microencapsulated rose bengal. Food Quality and Safety, 6, fyac017. https://doi.org/10.1093/fqsafe/fyac017</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fečkaninová, A., Koščová, J., Mudroňová, D., Popelka, P., &amp; Toropilová, J. (2017). The use of probiotic bacteria against Aeromonas infections in salmonid aquaculture. Aquaculture, 469, 1–8. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aquaculture.2016.11.042</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernández‐Vélez, I., Bidegain, G., &amp; Ben‐Horin, T. (2023). Predicting the growth of Vibrio parahaemolyticus in oysters under varying ambient temperature. Microorganisms, 11(5), 1169. https://doi.org/10.3390/microorganisms11051169</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations/World Health Organization. (2006). Report on joint FAO/WHO expert consultation on evaluation of health and nutritional properties of probiotics in food including powder milk with live lactic acid bacteria. FAO/WHO.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garcia‐Gonzalez, N., Battista, N., Prete, R., &amp; Corsetti, A. (2021). Health‐promoting role of Lactiplantibacillus plantarum isolated from fermented foods. Microorganisms, 9(2), 349. https://doi.org/10.3390/microorganisms9020349</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goatcher, L. J., &amp; Westhoff, D. C. (2006). Repression of Vibrio parahaemolyticus BY Pseudomonas species isolated from processed oysters. Journal of Food Science, 40(3), 533–536. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365‐2621.1975.tb12521.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hai, N. V. (2015). The use of probiotics in aquaculture. Journal of Applied Microbiology, 119(4), 917–935. https://doi.org/10.1111/jam.12886</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hao, Y., Li, J., Wang, J., &amp; Chen, Y. (2024). Mechanisms of health improvement by Lactiplantibacillus plantarum based on animal and human trials: A review. Fermentation, 10(2), 73. https://doi.org/10.3390/fermentation10020073</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Helander, I. M., Nurmiaho‐Lassila, E. L., Ahvenainen, R., Rhoades, J., &amp; Roller, S. (2001). Chitosan disrupts the barrier properties of the outer membrane of Gram‐negative bacteria. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 71(2–3), 235–244. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0168‐1605(01)00609‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hua, Q., Wong, C. H., &amp; Li, D. (2022). Postbiotics enhance the functionality of a probiotic edible coating for salmon fillets and the probiotic stability during simulated digestion. Food Packaging and Shelf Life, 34, 100954. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fpsl.2022.100954</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huq, T., Fraschini, C., Khan, A., Riedl, B., Bouchard, J., &amp; Lacroix, M. (2017). Alginate based nanocomposite for microencapsulation of probiotic: Effect of cellulose nanocrystal (CNC) and lecithin. Carbohydrate Polymers, 168, 61–69. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.carbpol.2017.03.032</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ji, R., Wu, J., Zhang, J., Wang, T., Zhang, X., Shao, L., Chen, D., &amp; Wang, J. (2019). Extending viability of Bifidobacterium longum in chitosan‐coated alginate microcapsules using emulsification and internal gelation encapsulation technology. Frontiers Microbiology, 10, 1389. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2019.01389</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kesika, P., Suganthy, N., Sivamaruthi, B. S., &amp; Chaiyasut, C. (2021). Role of gut‐brain axis, gut microbial composition, and probiotic intervention in Alzheimer's disease. Life Science, 264, 118627. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lfs.2020.118627</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, Y., Ten, M. M. Z., Zwe, Y. H., &amp; Li, D. (2022). Lactiplantibacillus plantarum 299v as starter culture suppresses Enterobacteriaceae more efficiently than spontaneous fermentation of carrots. Food Microbiology, 103, 103952. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fm.2021.103952</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lim, P. L., Toh, M., &amp; Liu, S. Q. (2015). Saccharomyces cerevisiae EC‐1118 enhances the survivability of probiotic Lactobacillus rhamnosus HN001 in an acidic environment. Applied and Microbiology Biotechnology, 99(16), 6803–6811. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00253‐015‐6560‐y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>López‐Caballero, M. E., Pérez‐Mateos, M., Montero, P., &amp; Borderías, A. J. (2000). Oyster preservation by high‐pressure treatment. Journal of Food Protection, 63(2), 196–201. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028x‐63.2.196</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marteau, P. R., Vrese, M. d., Cellier, C. J., &amp; Schrezenmeir, J. (2001). Protection from gastrointestinal diseases with the use of probiotics. The American Journal of Clinical Nutrition, 73(2), 430s–436s. https://doi.org/10.1093/ajcn/73.2.430s</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Minelli, E. B., &amp; Benini, A. (2009). Relationship between number of bacteria and their probiotic effects. Microbial Ecology in Health and Disease, 20(4), 180–183. https://doi.org/10.1080/08910600802408095</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohammadi, R., Moradi, M., Tajik, H., &amp; Molaei, R. (2022). Potential application of postbiotics metabolites from bioprotective culture to fabricate bacterial nanocellulose based antimicrobial packaging material. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 220, 528–536. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2022.08.108</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moradi, M., Kousheh, S. A., Almasi, H., Alizadeh, A., Guimarães, J. T., Yılmaz, N., &amp; Lotfi, A. (2020). Postbiotics produced by lactic acid bacteria: The next frontier in food safety. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 19(6), 3390–3415. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.12613</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakada, Y., &amp; Itoh, Y. (2003). Identification of the putrescine biosynthetic genes in Pseudomonas aeruginosa and characterization of agmatine deiminase and N‐carbamoylputrescine amidohydrolase of the arginine decarboxylase pathway. Microbiology (Reading, England), 149(3), 707–714. https://doi.org/10.1099/mic.0.26009‐0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noguerola, I., &amp; Blanch, A. R. (2008). Identification of Vibrio spp. with a set of dichotomous keys. Journal of Applied Microbiology, 105(1), 175–185. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365‐2672.2008.03730.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nualkaekul, S., Lenton, D., Cook, M. T., Khutoryanskiy, V. V., &amp; Charalampopoulos, D. (2012). Chitosan coated alginate beads for the survival of microencapsulated Lactobacillus plantarum in pomegranate juice. Carbohydrate Polymers, 90(3), 1281–1287. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.carbpol.2012.06.073</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parveen, S., Hettiarachchi, K. A., Bowers, J. C., Jones, J. L., Tamplin, M. L., Mckay, R., Beatty, W., Brohawn, K., Dasilva, L. V., &amp; Depaola, A. (2008). Seasonal distribution of total and pathogenic Vibrio parahaemolyticus in Chesapeake Bay oysters and waters. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 128(2), 354–361. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2008.09.019</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pilet, J. (2023). Oysters harvested in Florida linked to three‐state Salmonella outbreak. https://www.foodsafetynews.com/2023/03/oysters‐harvested‐in‐florida‐linked‐to‐salmonella‐outbreak/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prabhakar, P. K., Vatsa, S., Srivastav, P. P., &amp; Pathak, S. S. (2020). A comprehensive review on freshness of fish and assessment: Analytical methods and recent innovations. Food Research International, 133, 109157. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2020.109157</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roberts, T. A., Baird‐Parker, A. C., &amp; Tompkin, R. B.International Commission on Microbiological Specifications for Foods. (1996). Microorgnisms in Foods 5: Characteristics of Microbial Pathogens. Blackie Academic &amp; Professional, London.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rolfe, R. D. (2000). The role of probiotic cultures in the control of gastrointestinal health. The Journal of Nutrition, 130(2), 396S–402S. https://doi.org/10.1093/jn/130.2.396S</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharafi, H., Alirezalu, A., Liu, S. Q., Karami, A., &amp; Moradi, M. (2024). Postbiotics‐enriched flaxseed mucilage coating: A solution to improving postharvest quality and shelf life of strawberry. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 265(Pt2), 131398. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2024.131398</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singapore Food Agency. (2021). Recall of raw pacific oysters from the SA due to Vibrio parahaemolyticus contamination. https://www.sfa.gov.sg/docs/default‐source/default‐document‐library/sfa‐media‐release‐recall‐of‐raw‐pacific‐oysters‐from‐the‐sa‐due‐to‐vibrio‐parahaemolyticus‐contamination.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ta, L. P., Bujna, E., Antal, O., Ladányi, M., Juhász, R., Szécsi, A., Kun, S., Sudheer, S., Gupta, V. K., &amp; Nguyen, Q. D. (2021). Effects of various polysaccharides (alginate, carrageenan, gums, chitosan) and their combination with prebiotic saccharides (resistant starch, lactosucrose, lactulose) on the encapsulation of probiotic bacteria Lactobacillus casei 01 strain. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 183, 1136–1144. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2021.04.170</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tamber, S., Montgomery, A., Eloranta, K., &amp; Buenaventura, E. (2020). Enumeration and survival of Salmonella enterica in live oyster shellstock harvested from Canadian waters. Journal of Food Protection, 83(1), 6–12. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X.JFP‐19‐318</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor, M., Cheng, J., Sharma, D., Bitzikos, O., Gustafson, R., Fyfe, M., Greve, R., Murti, M., Stone, J., Honish, L., Mah, V., Punja, N., Hexemer, A., Mcintyre, L., Henry, B., Kendall, P., Atkinson, R., Buenaventura, E., Martinez‐Perez, A., … The Outbreak Investigation Team. (2018). Outbreak of Vibrio parahaemolyticus associated with consumption of raw oysters in Canada, 2015. Foodborne Pathogens and Disease, 15(9), 554–559. https://doi.org/10.1089/fpd.2017.2415</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toushik, S. H., Park, J. H., Kim, K., Ashrafudoulla, M., Senakpon Isaie Ulrich, M., Mizan, M. F. R., Roy, P. K., Shim, W. B., Kim, Y. M., Park, S. H., &amp; Ha, S. D. (2022). Antibiofilm efficacy of Leuconostoc mesenteroides J.27‐derived postbiotic and food‐grade essential oils against Vibrio parahaemolyticus, Pseudomonas aeruginosa, and Escherichia coli alone and in combination, and their application as a green preservative in the seafood industry. Food Research International, 156, 111163. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2022.111163</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Food and Drug Administration. (2022). FDA advises consumers to avoid potentially contaminated raw oysters from oyster kings in New Brunswick, Canada. https://www.fda.gov/food/alerts‐advisories‐safety‐information/fda‐advises‐consumers‐avoid‐potentially‐contaminated‐raw‐oysters‐oyster‐kings‐new‐brunswick‐canada</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Food and Drug Administration. (2023a). FDA advises restaurants and retailers not to serve or sell and consumers not to eat certain oysters from fanny bay oysters potentially containing high levels of Vibrio parahaemolyticus. https://www.fda.gov/food/alerts‐advisories‐safety‐information/fda‐advises‐restaurants‐and‐retailers‐not‐serve‐or‐sell‐and‐consumers‐not‐eat‐certain‐oysters‐fanny</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Food and Drug Administration. (2023b). FDA advises restaurants and retailers not to serve or sell and consumers not to eat oysters from Future Seafoods, Inc., potentially contaminated with Salmonella and E. coli. https://www.fda.gov/food/alerts‐advisories‐safety‐information/fda‐advises‐restaurants‐and‐retailers‐not‐serve‐or‐sell‐and‐consumers‐not‐eat‐oysters‐future</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Y., Tan, C., Davachi, S. M., Li, P., Davidowsky, P., &amp; Yan, B. (2021). Development of microcapsules using chitosan and alginate via W/O emulsion for the protection of hydrophilic compounds by comparing with hydrogel beads. International Journal of Biological Macromolecules, 177, 92–99. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2021.02.089</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei, G., Tay, M. Y. F., Kamaja, V. K., &amp; Chan‐Park, M. B. (2024). Synbiotic encapsulation against Vibrio parahaemolyticus infection in whiteleg shrimps. Aquaculture, 590, 741051. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aquaculture.2024.741051</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong, C. H., &amp; Li, D. (2023). Comparison of two strategies enhancing the antagonistic effect of lactic acid bacteria in edible coating against Listeria monocytogenes on fresh‐cut apple slices. LWT—Food Science and Technology, 182, 114923. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2023.114923</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, D., Lewis, E. D., Pae, M., &amp; Meydani, S. N. (2018). Nutritional modulation of immune function: Analysis of evidence, mechanisms, and clinical relevance. Frontiers in Immunology, 9, 3160. https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2018.03160</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yolmeh, M., Xavier‐Santos, D., &amp; Sant'Ana, A. S. (2024). Modulating gut microbiota by paraprobiotics: Mechanisms, advantages, and challenges. Food Bioscience, 60, 104305. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fbio.2024.104305</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>