<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39321168</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1932-6203</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>19</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>PloS one</Title><ISOAbbreviation>PLoS One</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Impact of urban productive safety net program on urban households' asset accumulation and food consumption rate in Dessie City, South Wollo Zone, Amhara Region, Ethiopia.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e0308575</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e0308575</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e0308575</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1371/journal.pone.0308575</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Agriculture is the driver of economic growth in many developing countries like Ethiopia, where it often represents at least 25% of gross domestic product. But the quality and productivity of the land depends on the way agriculture is practiced. Better agricultural techniques are necessarily including Productive Safety net Program. Urban Productive Safety Net Program is designed to support the poor households and establish urban safety net mechanisms. While several studies have examined the effects of rural productive safety net programs, the outcomes of similar programs in urban areas are not well documented. This knowledge gap hinders the ability to effectively design and implement urban productive safety net programs. The main objective of this study was to assess the impact of urban productive safety net program on asset accumulation and consumption rate in Dessie city. Both primary and secondary data sources were used. A total of 112 households were selected randomly among the public work Urban Productive Safety Net Program beneficiary and non-beneficiary households. Descriptive analysis, inferential statistics and econometric models were used for analysis. Based on the econometric estimation results the demographic and socio-economic variables such as education, access to credit, access to extension services and adult male labor force revealed positive relation to public work urban productive safety net program beneficiary and non-beneficiary household's asset accumulation and consumption. The impact of program participation was also found to be positive and significant for both home asset and community asset. While food and non-food consumption even the total consumption and food security status are also positive. Generally, the result indicated that, due to program participation beneficiary households have higher home asset and community asset and better consumption and food security status.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: © 2024 Alem-meta Assefa. This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Assefa</LastName><ForeName>Alem-Meta</ForeName><Initials>AM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1856-2373</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Geography and Environmental Studies, Wollo University, Dessie, Ethiopia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>PLoS One</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101285081</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1932-6203</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005002" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Ethiopia</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005191" MajorTopicYN="Y">Family Characteristics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014505" MajorTopicYN="Y">Urban Population</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005523" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Supply</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012959" MajorTopicYN="N">Socioeconomic Factors</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002947" MajorTopicYN="N">Cities</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000383" MajorTopicYN="N">Agriculture</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39321168</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11423993</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0308575</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">PONE-D-23-24451</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Fekadu N, Mberengwa (2009) Challenges of Productive Safety Net Program Implementation at Local Level. The Cases of Kuyu Woreda, North Shewa Zone, Oromia Region, Ethiopia. Journal of Sustainable Development in Africa, 11(1), 248–267.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Samuel G (2010) Food aid and small householder agriculture in Ethiopia development studies, March 20–22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Bank (2012) Retrieved from; Washington, D.C: 2012. Managing risk, promoting growth: Developing systems for social protection in Africa‐‐the World Bank’s Africa social protection strategy 2012–2022. [Google Scholar]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAO, IFAD, UNICEF, WFP and WHO (2023) The State of Food Security and Nutrition in the World 2023. Urbanization, agrifood systems transformation and healthy diets across the rural–urban continuum. Rome, FAO. 10.4060/cc3017en</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4060/cc3017en</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (2023) The State of Food Security and Nutrition in the World 2023. Rome: FAO. Retrieved from https://www.fao.org/publications/sofi/2023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Africa Center for Strategic Studies (2023) Unresolved Conflicts Continue to Drive Africa’s Food Crisis.
africacenter.org/spotlight/unresolved-conflicts-continue-to-drive-africas-food-crisis/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Development (MOARD) (2010) Concept Note for Establishment of a System of Productive Safety Net in Ethiopia.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berhane G Hoddinott J Kumar H, Alemayehu S, Michael T, Yisehac Y et al.. (2013) ‘Evaluation of Ethiopia’s Food Security Program: Documenting Progress in the Implementation of the Productive Safety Nets Program and the Household Asset Building Programm’. ESSP II–EDRI REPORT, Washington, D.C: International Food Policy Research Institute.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gilligan D.O, Hoddinott J, Seyoum T.A(2008) The impact of Ethiopia’s Productive Safety Net Programme and its linkages. International Food Policy Research Institute (IFPRI).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berhane G, Gilligan D.O., Hoddinott J, Kumar N, Taffesse A.S(2014) Can social protection work in Africa? The impact of Ethiopia’s Productive Safety Net Programme. Economic Development and Cultural Change, 63(1), 1–26.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Federal Democratic Republic of Ethiopia (FDRE) (2006) Productive Safety Net Program: Program Implementation Manual (rev). Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Development (MoARD), Addis Ababa, Ethiopia.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Federal Democratic Republic of Ethiopia (FDRE) (2001) Rural Development Policies, Strategies and Instruments of the Government of the FDRE.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berhane G Hoddinott J, Kumar N, Alemayehu S (2011) The impact of Ethiopia’s Productive Safety Nets and Household Asset Building Programme: 2006–2010. Washington, D.C: International Food Policy Research Institute.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Urban Development and Housing UPSNP (2016) Urban Productive Safety Net Program Implementation Manual, Version xx, Addis Ababa.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dessie City UPSNP Task Force Office (2019) Unpublished Report Document, Ethiopia.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zewdie Y.M (2014) "Food Insecurity and Coping Strategies of Urban Poor Households in Addis Ababa." Journal of Economics and Sustainable Development, 5(20): 20–30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andersson C, Alemu M, Stage J (2010) Impacts of the Productive Safety Net Program in Ethiopia on livestock and tree holdings of rural households Environment for Development Discussion Paper Series 09–05.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Devereux S, Sabates-Wheeler R (2004) Transformative social protection. IDS Working Paper, 232. Institute of Development Studies, Brighton, Sussex Bn1 9RE England.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kataru K (2011) Assessment of the Impact of Productive Safety Net Program on the Lives of the Beneficiaries in Ethiopia: The Case of Dera Malo Woreda, Gamo Gofa Zone, unpublished Master of Arts Degree in Public Management, Addis Ababa University, Ethiopia.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tadele M (2011) Impact of Productive Safety Net Program on the sustainable Land Management Practice in Central Rift value. University of Haramaya, Ethiopia.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andersson C, Alemu M, Jesper S (2011) Impacts of the Productive Safety Net Program in Ethiopia on livestock and tree holdings of rural households. Journal of Development Economics, 94 (2011) 119–126. doi: 10.1016/j.jdeveco.2009.12.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jdeveco.2009.12.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Habitamu A (2011) Impact of Productive Safety Net Program on the Household Welfare and labor supply in rural Ethiopia. Master’s Thesis, Addis Ababa University, Ethiopia.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Central Statistics Authority (CSA) (2007) National Population Statistics. Federal Democratic Republic of Ethiopia, Central Statistical Authority, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kombo DK, Tromp DL (2006) Thesis Writing: An Introduction, Paulines Publications Africa, Nairobi.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Creswell JW (2009) Research Design: Qualitative, Quantitative, and Mixed Methods Approaches. 3rdEdition, SAGE Publications, London, United Kingdom.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kothari CR (2004) Quantitative Techniques. 2ndEdition, New Delhi: Vikas Publishing House Pvt. Ltd. India.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gujarati DN (2004) Basic Econometrics. 4thEdition, the McGraw−Hill Companies.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gilligan DO, Hoddinott J, Alemayehu S (2008) An analysis of Ethiopia’s Productive Safety Net Program and its linkages. International Food Policy Research Institute, Washington, DC.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenbaum PR, Rubin DB (1983) The Central Role of the Propensity Score in Observational Studies for Causal Effects. Biometrika,70, 41–55. 10.1093/biomet/70.1.41</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/biomet/70.1.41</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gebrehiwot T, Castilla C (2019) "The Role of the Productive Safety Net Programme (PSNP) in Improving Consumption and Asset Accumulation in Rural Ethiopia." Journal of Development Studies, 55(5): 685–700.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gilligan Daniel O, Hoddinott John(2007) "Is There Persistence in the Impact of Emergency Food Aid? Evidence on Consumption, Food Security, and Assets in Rural Ethiopia." American Journal of Agricultural Economics, 89(2): 225–242.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gebrehiwot T, Van der Veen A (2015) "Coping with Food Insecurity on a Micro-scale: Evidence from Ethiopian Rural Households." Ecology of Food and Nutrition, 54(2): 187–208.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24564194</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Derso A, Bizuneh H, Keleb A, Ademas A, Adane M (2021) Food insecurity status and determinants among Urban Productive Safety Net Program beneficiary households in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia. PLOS ONE,16(9):e0256634. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0256634</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0256634</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8476016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34570794</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alemseged G, Hailu B (2018) Determinants of rural household food insecurity in Northern Ethiopia: An empirical study. Sustainable Development Africa, 2018; 20(1):32–63.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scho L, Wekesah F, Mohamed S (2014) Vulnerability to food insecurity in urban slums: Experiences from Nairobi, Kenya. Journal of Urban Health, 2014; 91(6):1098–113.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4242851</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25172616</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yibrah H (2010) Impact of Productive Safety Net Program on the Rural Households asset Protection and Consumption. Unpublished MA Thesis, Mekelle University, Ethiopia.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>