<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39328042</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1557-8992</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>27</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of child and adolescent psychopharmacology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Long-Acting Injectable Antipsychotic Medication Use in Youth: A Systematic Review of the Literature Along with MedWatch Safety Data and Prescriber Attitudes.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1089/cap.2024.0050</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText><b><i>Objectives:</i></b> Long-acting injectable (LAI) antipsychotic medications are being prescribed to children and adolescents along a broad age range from 2 to 17 years old. However, there is no U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) approved indication for the use of any LAI in a pediatric population. The goal of this article is to perform a systematic literature review regarding the use of LAIs in a pediatric population, to obtain pediatric LAI safety data, and to survey prescriber attitudes regarding LAI use in youth. <b><i>Methods:</i></b> A search for relevant articles between June 1986 and June 2021 was conducted. Safety data were obtained from FDA MedWatch postmarketing adverse event reports regarding LAI use in children and adolescents. A survey of practicing Child and Adolescent Psychiatrists in Wisconsin was done regarding the use of LAIs in youth. <b><i>Results:</i></b> The predominant reasons for LAI use in youth were illness severity and treatment noncompliance. Twenty-six of 30 identified studies and reports favored LAI use in youth, but were of low to very low quality. Overall, 587 FDA MedWatch reports between June 1986 and June 2021 were identified. Most adverse events occurred in modest numbers. Extrapyramidal symptoms accounted for 18% of all MedWatch reports, neuroleptic malignant syndrome accounted for 3% of all reports, and deaths accounted for 2% of all reports. The concern for safety was reflected in prescriber survey results along with a recognition that LAIs can be helpful to target severe psychiatric symptoms and address treatment noncompliance. <b><i>Conclusions:</i></b> No randomized controlled studies were found. Identified published studies and reports were of low to very low quality. However, it appeared reasonable that the use of LAIs in a select group of pediatric patients can be helpful to target severe psychiatric symptoms and to enhance treatment compliance.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Scharko</LastName><ForeName>Alexander M</ForeName><Initials>AM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5816-3326</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Winnebago Mental Health Institute, Winnebago, Wisconsin, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Medicine, Medical College of Wisconsin, Milwaukee, Wisconsin, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sieracki</LastName><ForeName>Rita</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medical College of Wisconsin Libraries, Milwaukee, Wisconsin, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mireski</LastName><ForeName>Sarah J</ForeName><Initials>SJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Winnebago Mental Health Institute, Winnebago, Wisconsin, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9105358</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1044-5463</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">children and adolescents</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">long-acting injectable antipsychotic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pediatric psychopharmacology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">treatment noncompliance</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>6</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>6</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39328042</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/cap.2024.0050</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>