<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39335899</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>30</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2304-8158</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><Issue>18</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>19</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Foods (Basel, Switzerland)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Foods</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>How Do Socio-Demographic Factors, Health Status, and Knowledge Influence the Acceptability of Probiotics Products in Hong Kong?</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">2971</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3390/foods13182971</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>In recent years, due to growing interest in gut health, the potential benefits of probiotics on the gut have received much attention. Probiotics, now readily available in both dietary supplements and a variety of foods, have become a focal point of consumer health choices. This study aims to explore the impact of consumer-related factors, including socio-demographic profiles, health status, and probiotics knowledge, on the acceptance of probiotics products in Hong Kong. A total of 385 participants engaged in a survey, providing data for an in-depth analysis of how these factors influence attitudes toward probiotics. Findings revealed a general confidence in the safety of probiotics products among respondents; however, there was a noticeable gap in probiotics understanding. The study highlighted a correlation between probiotics knowledge and specific socio-demographic attributes, with higher educational attainment positively linked to greater probiotics awareness. Furthermore, the research indicated that women exhibit higher health consciousness and a greater propensity for probiotics consumption compared to men. Consequently, promoting enhanced probiotics education and fostering increased health awareness are crucial steps to prevent the misuse of probiotics and optimize health outcomes.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Zilin</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Biological Sciences, Faculty of Science, The University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science and Nutrition, The Hong Kong Polytechnic University, Hong Kong, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wu</LastName><ForeName>Nan</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Biological Sciences, Faculty of Science, The University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chan</LastName><ForeName>Shun Wan</ForeName><Initials>SW</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8238-798X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food and Health Sciences, Technological and Higher Education Institute of Hong Kong, Hong Kong, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>19</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Foods</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101670569</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2304-8158</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">health status</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">knowledge</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">probiotics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">socio-demographics</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>8</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39335899</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11431766</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods13182971</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">foods13182971</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Rodriguez-Leyva D., Pierce G.N. The Impact of Nutrition on the COVID-19 Pandemic and the Impact of the COVID-19 Pandemic on Nutrition. Nutrients. 2021;13:1752. doi: 10.3390/nu13061752.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu13061752</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8223988</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34064053</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koirala S., Anal A.K. Probiotics-based foods and beverages as future foods and their overall safety and regulatory claims. Future Foods. 2021;3:100013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nag M., Siddiqua F., Baruah N., Das S., Basumatary B., Deka M., Saikia K.K., Malick P. The Functional Foods. Apple Academic Press; New York, NY, USA: 2024. Functional Foods: Formulation, Fortification, and Combating COVID-19; pp. 117–148.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Temple N.J. A rational definition for functional foods: A perspective. Front. Nutr. 2022;9:957516. doi: 10.3389/fnut.2022.957516.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fnut.2022.957516</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9559824</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36245478</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maftei N.-M., Raileanu C.R., Balta A.A., Ambrose L., Boev M., Marin D.B., Lisa E.L. The Potential Impact of Probiotics on Human Health: An Update on Their Health-Promoting Properties. Microorganisms. 2024;12:234. doi: 10.3390/microorganisms12020234.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/microorganisms12020234</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10891645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38399637</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Obayomi O.V., Olaniran A.F., Owa S.O. Unveiling the role of functional foods with emphasis on prebiotics and probiotics in human health: A review. J. Funct. Foods. 2024;119:106337.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Begum P.S., Madhavi G., Rajagopal S., Viswanath B., Razak M.A., Venkataratnamma V. Probiotics as functional foods: Potential effects on human health and its impact on neurological diseases. Int. J. Nutr. Pharmacol. Neurol. Dis. 2017;7:23–33.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palanivelu J., Thanigaivel S., Vickram S., Dey N., Mihaylova D., Desseva I. Probiotics in functional foods: Survival assessment and approaches for improved viability. Appl. Sci. 2022;12:455. doi: 10.3390/app12010455.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/app12010455</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Syngai G.G., Gopi R., Bharali R., Dey S., Lakshmanan G.A., Ahmed G. Probiotics-the versatile functional food ingredients. J. Food Sci. Technol. 2016;53:921–933.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4837740</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27162372</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Szydłowska A., Sionek B. Probiotics and postbiotics as the functional food components affecting the immune response. Microorganisms. 2022;11:104. doi: 10.3390/microorganisms11010104.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/microorganisms11010104</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9862734</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36677396</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McFarland L.V. From yaks to yogurt: The history, development, and current use of probiotics. Clin. Infect. Dis. 2015;60:S85–S90. doi: 10.1093/cid/civ054.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/civ054</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25922406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ayivi R.D., Gyawali R., Krastanov A., Aljaloud S.O., Worku M., Tahergorabi R., Silva R.C.d., Ibrahim S.A. Lactic acid bacteria: Food safety and human health applications. Dairy. 2020;1:202–232. doi: 10.3390/dairy1030015.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/dairy1030015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hill C., Guarner F., Reid G., Gibson G.R., Merenstein D.J., Pot B., Morelli L., Canani R.B., Flint H.J., Salminen S., et al. The International Scientific Association for Probiotics and Prebiotics consensus statement on the scope and appropriate use of the term probiotic. Nat. Rev. Gastroenterol. Hepatol. 2014;11:506–514. doi: 10.1038/nrgastro.2014.66.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nrgastro.2014.66</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24912386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo X., Long R., Kreuzer M., Ding L., Shang Z., Zhang Y., Yang Y., Cui G. Importance of functional ingredients in yak milk-derived food on health of Tibetan nomads living under high-altitude stress: A review. Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2014;54:292–302. doi: 10.1080/10408398.2011.584134.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2011.584134</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24188303</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO) Guidelines for the Evaluation of Probiotics in Food. FAO; London, ON, Canada: 2002. Report of a Joint FAO/WHO Working Group on Drafting Guidelines for the Evaluation of Probiotics in Food.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martín R., Langella P. Emerging health concepts in the probiotics field: Streamlining the definitions. Front. Microbiol. 2019;10:1047. doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2019.01047.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2019.01047</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6536656</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31164874</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bisht D., Pal D., Shrestha R. Probiotics. CRC Press; Boca Raton, FL, USA: 2024. Introduction to Probiotics, Prebiotics, and Synbiotics: A Holistic Approach; pp. 1–28.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mishra S., Acharya S. A brief overview on probiotics: The health friendly microbes. Biomed. Pharmacol. J. 2021;14:1869–1880. doi: 10.13005/bpj/2285.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.13005/bpj/2285</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tarapatzi G., Filidou E., Kandilogiannakis L., Spathakis M., Gaitanidou M., Arvanitidis K., Drygiannakis I., Valatas V., Kotzampassi K., Manolopoulos V.G., et al. The Probiotic Strains Bifid οbacterium lactis, Lactobacillus acidophilus, Lactiplantibacillus plantarum and Saccharomyces boulardii Regulate Wound Healing and Chemokine Responses in Human Intestinal Subepithelial Myofibroblasts. Pharmaceuticals. 2022;15:1293. doi: 10.3390/ph15101293.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ph15101293</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9611312</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36297405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sahni C., Gupta R.K., Nand P. Insignificant viability of the granules of probiotic and prebiotic with skimmed milk powder. Biomed. Prev. Nutr. 2014;4:603–605. doi: 10.1016/j.bionut.2014.08.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bionut.2014.08.005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang S., Naumovski N., Ajlouni S., Ayyash M., Silva R., Balthazar C.F., Esmerino E.A., Freitas M.Q., da Silva M.C., Sant’Ana A.S., et al. Nonbovine milk and its products as sources of probiotics delivery: An overview of its viability, functionality and product quality characteristics. Int. J. Dairy Technol. 2023;76:482–511. doi: 10.1111/1471-0307.12976.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1471-0307.12976</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tripathi M.K., Giri S.K. Probiotic functional foods: Survival of probiotics during processing and storage. J. Funct. Foods. 2014;9:225–241. doi: 10.1016/j.jff.2014.04.030.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jff.2014.04.030</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang D., Wu F., Zhou D., Tan B., Chen T. Commercial probiotic products in public health: Current status and potential limitations. Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2024;64:6455–6476. doi: 10.1080/10408398.2023.2169858.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2023.2169858</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36688290</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Di Cerbo A., Palmieri B. The market of probiotics. Pak. J. Pharm. Sci. 2015;28:2199–2206.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26639512</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaur H., Kaur G., Ali S.A. Dairy-based probiotic-fermented functional foods: An update on their health-promoting properties. Fermentation. 2022;8:425. doi: 10.3390/fermentation8090425.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/fermentation8090425</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dahiya D., Nigam P.S. Probiotics, prebiotics, synbiotics, and fermented foods as potential biotics in nutrition improving health via microbiome-gut-brain axis. Fermentation. 2022;8:303. doi: 10.3390/fermentation8070303.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/fermentation8070303</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Das T.K., Pradhan S., Chakrabarti S., Mondal K.C., Ghosh K. Current status of probiotic and related health benefits. Appl. Food Res. 2022;2:100185. doi: 10.1016/j.afres.2022.100185.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.afres.2022.100185</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ranjha M.M.A.N., Shafique B., Batool M., Kowalczewski P.Ł., Shehzad Q., Usman M., Manzoor M.F., Zahra S.M., Yaqub S., Aadil R.M. Nutritional and health potential of probiotics: A review. Appl. Sci. 2021;11:11204. doi: 10.3390/app112311204.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/app112311204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>da Silva T.F., Glória R.d.A., Americo M.F., Freitas A.d.S., de Jesus L.C.L., Barroso F.A.L., Laguna J.G., Coelho-Rocha N.D., Tavares L.M., Le Loir Y., et al. Unlocking the potential of probiotics: A comprehensive review on research, production, and regulation of probiotics. Probiotics Antimicrob. Proteins. 2024 doi: 10.1007/s12602-024-10247-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12602-024-10247-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38539008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Behera K.K., Bist R., Mohanty S., Bhattacharya M. Prebiotics, Probiotics and Nutraceuticals. Springer; Berlin/Heidelberg, Germany: 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Di Vincenzo F., Del Gaudio A., Petito V., Lopetuso L.R., Scaldaferri F. Gut microbiota, intestinal permeability, and systemic inflammation: A narrative review. Intern. Emerg. Med. 2024;19:275–293. doi: 10.1007/s11739-023-03374-w.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11739-023-03374-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10954893</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37505311</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marques T.M., Ganda-Mall J.P., Forsgård R., Wall R., Brummer R.J., De Vos W.M. The Gut-Brain Axis. Elsevier; Amsterdam, The Netherlands: 2024. Correlating the gut microbiome to health and disease; pp. 1–36.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fasano A., Matera M. Probiotics and Child Gastrointestinal Health: Advances in Microbiology, Infectious Diseases and Public Health Volume 19. Springer; Berlin/Heidelberg, Germany: 2024. Probiotics to Prevent Celiac Disease and Inflammatory Bowel Diseases; pp. 95–111.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39060733</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bäumler A.J., Sperandio V. Interactions between the microbiota and pathogenic bacteria in the gut. Nature. 2016;535:85–93. doi: 10.1038/nature18849.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nature18849</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5114849</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27383983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tomasulo A., Simionati B., Facchin S. Microbiome One Health Model for a Healthy Ecosystem. Sci. One Health. 2024;3:100065. doi: 10.1016/j.soh.2024.100065.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.soh.2024.100065</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11262273</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39077385</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ross F.C., Patangia D., Grimaud G., Lavelle A., Dempsey E.M., Ross R.P., Stanton C. The interplay between diet and the gut microbiome: Implications for health and disease. Nat. Rev. Microbiol. 2024 doi: 10.1038/s41579-024-01068-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41579-024-01068-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39009882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y. Progress of Research on Probiotics as Dietary Supplements to Support Gut Health in Humans. Highlights Sci. Eng. Technol. 2024;91:333–337. doi: 10.54097/q5p93k16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.54097/q5p93k16</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Savaiano D.A., Hutkins R.W. Yogurt, cultured fermented milk, and health: A systematic review. Nutr. Rev. 2021;79:599–614. doi: 10.1093/nutrit/nuaa013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/nutrit/nuaa013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8579104</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32447398</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Granato D., Branco G.F., Nazzaro F., Cruz A.G., Faria J.A. Functional foods and nondairy probiotic food development: Trends, concepts, and products. Compr. Rev. Food Sci. Food Saf. 2010;9:292–302. doi: 10.1111/j.1541-4337.2010.00110.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1541-4337.2010.00110.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33467814</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yilmaz-Ersan L., Ozcan T., Akpinar-Bayizit A. Assessment of socio-demographic factors, health status and the knowledge on probiotic dairy products. Food Sci. Hum. Wellness. 2020;9:272–279. doi: 10.1016/j.fshw.2020.05.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fshw.2020.05.004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mollakhalili M.N., Mortazavian A.M., Sohrabvandi S., Cruz A.G.D., Mohammadi R. Probiotic supplements and food products: Comparison for different targets. Appl. Food Biotechnol. 2017;4:123–132.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hossain M.N., Ranadheera C.S., Fang Z., Ajlouni S. Healthy chocolate enriched with probiotics: A review. Food Sci. Technol. 2020;41:531–543. doi: 10.1590/fst.11420.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/fst.11420</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muchiri M.N., McCartney A., Methven L. Sensory profile and consumer preference of novel probiotic yoghurt enriched with orange sweet potato (Ipomoea batatas) Afr. J. Food Agric. Nutr. Dev. 2020;20:16471–16489. doi: 10.18697/ajfand.93.19565.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18697/ajfand.93.19565</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Machado-Oliveira M.C., Rodrigues H., Bisconsin-Junior A., Camillo G.H., Sierra H., Alegbeleye O., Gomez-Corona C., Micetic-Turk D., Paucar-Menacho L.M., Chincha A.A., et al. The role of culture in the representation of probiotic foods. Food Res. Int. 2024;194:114859. doi: 10.1016/j.foodres.2024.114859.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2024.114859</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39232504</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kothari D., Patel S., Kim S.-K. Probiotic supplements might not be universally-effective and safe: A review. Biomed. Pharmacother. 2019;111:537–547. doi: 10.1016/j.biopha.2018.12.104.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2018.12.104</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30597307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alqaydi T.K., Bedir A.S., Abu-Elsaoud A.M., El-Tarabily K.A., Al Raish S.M. An Assessment of the Knowledge, Attitude, and Practice of Probiotics and Prebiotics among the Population of the United Arab Emirates. Foods. 2024;13:2219. doi: 10.3390/foods13142219.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods13142219</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11276527</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39063303</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu M., Watson S. Flavor-Associated Applications in Health and Wellness Food Products. Springer; Berlin/Heidelberg, Germany: 2024. Market Overview of Health and Wellness Food Products; pp. 3–19.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chao M.M., Hong Y.-Y. Being a Bicultural Chinese: A Multilevel Perspective to Biculturalism. J. Psychol. Chin. Soc. 2007;8:141–157.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bogue J., Yu H. The influence of sociodemographic and lifestyle factors on consumers’ healthy cereal food choices. J. Food Prod. Mark. 2016;22:398–419.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bodke H., Jogdand S. Role of probiotics in human health. Cureus. 2022;14:e31313.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9733784</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36514580</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abouelela M.E., Helmy Y.A. Next-generation probiotics as novel therapeutics for improving human health: Current trends and future perspectives. Microorganisms. 2024;12:430. doi: 10.3390/microorganisms12030430.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/microorganisms12030430</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10972033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38543481</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou P., Chen C., Patil S., Dong S. Unveiling the therapeutic symphony of probiotics, prebiotics, and postbiotics in gut-immune harmony. Front. Nutr. 2024;11:1355542.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10881654</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38389798</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jankovic I., Sybesma W., Phothirath P., Ananta E., Mercenier A. Application of probiotics in food products—Challenges and new approaches. Curr. Opin. Biotechnol. 2010;21:175–181. doi: 10.1016/j.copbio.2010.03.009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.copbio.2010.03.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20417089</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zaib S., Hayat A., Khan I. Probiotics and their beneficial health effects. Mini Rev. Med. Chem. 2024;24:110–125.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37291788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kechagia M., Basoulis D., Konstantopoulou S., Dimitriadi D., Gyftopoulou K., Skarmoutsou N., Fakiri E.M. Health benefits of probiotics: A review. Int. Sch. Res. Not. 2013;2013:481651. doi: 10.5402/2013/481651.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5402/2013/481651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4045285</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24959545</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma T., Shen X., Shi X., Sakandar H.A., Quan K., Li Y., Jin H., Kwok L.-Y., Zhang H., Sun Z. Targeting gut microbiota and metabolism as the major probiotic mechanism-An evidence-based review. Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2023;138:178–198. doi: 10.1016/j.tifs.2023.06.013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2023.06.013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al Hossan A.A., Syed W., Babelghaith S.D., Al Arifi M.N. Knowledge, Attitude, and Practice of Probiotics Among Saudi Health Care Students—A Cross-Sectional Study From Saudi University in Riyadh Saudi Arabia. INQUIRY J. Health Care Organ. Provis. Financ. 2024;61:00469580231224821.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10826384</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38284356</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sundberg L., Agahi N., Fritzell J., Fors S. Why is the gender gap in life expectancy decreasing? The impact of age-and cause-specific mortality in Sweden 1997–2014. Int. J. Public Health. 2018;63:673–681. doi: 10.1007/s00038-018-1097-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00038-018-1097-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6015620</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29654335</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>French S.A., Tangney C.C., Crane M.M., Wang Y., Appelhans B.M. Nutrition quality of food purchases varies by household income: The SHoPPER study. BMC Public Health. 2019;19:231.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6390355</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30808311</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>AnaMaria C., Vodnar D.C. Exploring the gut-brain Axis: Potential therapeutic impact of Psychobiotics on mental health. Prog. Neuro-Psychopharmacol. Biol. Psychiatry. 2024;134:111073</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38914414</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jia L., Xiao L., Fu Y., Shao Z., Jing Z., Yuan J., Xie Y., Guo J., Wang Y., Geng W. Neuroprotective effects of probiotics on anxiety-and depression-like disorders in stressed mice by modulating tryptophan metabolism and the gut microbiota. Food Funct. 2024;15:2895–2905. doi: 10.1039/D3FO03897A.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D3FO03897A</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38404190</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>