<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39333954</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>28</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>01</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1471-230X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>24</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>27</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC gastroenterology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Gastroenterol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Accumulation of rare earth elements in human gallstones: a perspective from dietary and human health.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>324</StartPage><MedlinePgn>324</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">324</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12876-024-03426-1</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Gallstone disease poses a global threat to human health and is strongly linked to environmental factors. However, there is currently no data on the presence of rare earth elements (REEs) in human gallstones. This paper investigates the concentration and distribution of REEs in gallstones for the first time, aiming to explore the environmental implications on human health.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A total of 25 gallstone samples were collected in Shanghai and the content of REEs was measured by Inductively coupled plasma-Mass Spectrometry (ICP-MS) to explore the distribution of REEs in gallstones.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The concentration of REEs in gallstones ranged from 4.89 to 190.8 ng/g (mean 39.21). In most of the gallstone analyses, REEs have been detected and generally attributed to environmental exposure or food contamination. The Y/Ho ratio of gallstones was lower than that of continental rocks, similar to that in the blood, indicating limited fractionation during fluid transport processes in the gallbladder.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The upper continental crust (UCC)-normalized REEs pattern in gallstones showed depletion of light REEs, while most showed enrichment of heavy REEs. Positive Gd anomalies were found in most samples, while few samples suggested anthropogenic influence. Whether exogenous inputs or in vivo biofractionation lead to changes in REEs fractionated patterns require further analyses.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shen</LastName><ForeName>Shuang</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Digestive Endoscopic Center, Shanghai Sixth People's Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine, Shanghai, 200233, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Central Lab, School of Medicine, Shanghai Sixth People's Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University, Shanghai, 200233, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Han</LastName><ForeName>Guilin</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Biogeology and Environmental Geology, China University of Geosciences (Beijing), Beijing, 100083, China. hanguilin@cugb.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Frontiers Science Center for Deep-time Digital Earth, Institute of Earth Scineces, University of Geosciences (Beijing), 100083, Beijing, China. hanguilin@cugb.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dong</LastName><ForeName>Zhixia</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Digestive Endoscopic Center, Shanghai Sixth People's Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine, Shanghai, 200233, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wu</LastName><ForeName>Shan</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Digestive Endoscopic Center, Shanghai Sixth People's Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine, Shanghai, 200233, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ma</LastName><ForeName>Shunrong</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Biogeology and Environmental Geology, China University of Geosciences (Beijing), Beijing, 100083, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Frontiers Science Center for Deep-time Digital Earth, Institute of Earth Scineces, University of Geosciences (Beijing), 100083, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ding</LastName><ForeName>Ziyang</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Biogeology and Environmental Geology, China University of Geosciences (Beijing), Beijing, 100083, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Frontiers Science Center for Deep-time Digital Earth, Institute of Earth Scineces, University of Geosciences (Beijing), 100083, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhao</LastName><ForeName>Ye</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nu Instruments, Wrexham Industrial Estate, 74 Clywedog Road South, 13 9XS, Wresham, LL, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wan</LastName><ForeName>Xinjian</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Digestive Endoscopic Center, Shanghai Sixth People's Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine, Shanghai, 200233, China. slwanxinjian2020@126.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>41661144029</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>82200710</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Gastroenterol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100968547</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1471-230X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D008674">Metals, Rare Earth</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D042882" MajorTopicYN="Y">Gallstones</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008674" MajorTopicYN="Y">Metals, Rare Earth</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002681" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">China</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004781" MajorTopicYN="N">Environmental Exposure</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000009" MajorTopicYN="N">adverse effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004032" MajorTopicYN="N">Diet</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005506" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Contamination</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013058" MajorTopicYN="N">Mass Spectrometry</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000368" MajorTopicYN="N">Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bioavailable REE</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">China</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Gallstones</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Human health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Rare earth elements</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>10</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39333954</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11437671</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12876-024-03426-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12876-024-03426-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Piper DZ. Rare earth elements in the sedimentary cycle: a summary. Chem Geol. 1974;14(4):285–304.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Compton JS, White RA, Smith M. Rare earth element behavior in soils and salt pan sediments of a semi-arid granitic terrain in the Western Cape, South Africa. Chem Geol. 2003;201(3):239–55.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han G, Xu Z, Tang Y, Zhang G. Rare earth element patterns in the Karst terrains of Guizhou Province, China: implication for Water/Particle Interaction. Aquat Geochem. 2009;15(4):457–84.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang Y, Han G, Wu Q, Xu Z. Use of rare earth element patterns to trace the provenance of the atmospheric dust near Beijing, China. Environ Earth Sci. 2013;68(3):871–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao X, Han G, Zhang S, Wang D, Ma S. Anthropogenic Gadolinium Accumulation and Rare Earth element anomalies of the typical Urban River, North China: evidence from the three-dimensional tracing system. ACS Earth Space Chem. 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han G, Liu M, Li X, Zhang Q. Sources and geochemical behaviors of rare earth elements in suspended particulate matter in a wet-dry tropical river. Environ Res. 2023;218:115044.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36513127</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pang X, Li D, Peng A. Application of rare-earth elements in the agriculture of China and its environmental behavior in soil. Environ Sci Pollut Res. 2002;9(2):143–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12008295</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li X, Chen Z, Chen Z, Zhang Y. A human health risk assessment of rare earth elements in soil and vegetables from a mining area in Fujian Province, Southeast China. Chemosphere. 2013;93(6):1240–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23891580</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li X, Chen Z, Chen Z. Distribution and fractionation of rare earth elements in soil–water system and human blood and hair from a mining area in southwest Fujian Province, China. Environ Earth Sci. 2014;72(9):3599–608.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zaichick S, Zaichick V, Karandashev V, Nosenko S. Accumulation of rare earth elements in human bone within the lifespan. Metallomics. 2011;3(2):186–94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21173982</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei B, Li Y, Li H, Yu J, Ye B, Liang T. Rare earth elements in human hair from a mining area of China. Ecotoxicol Environ Saf. 2013;96:118–23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23830573</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brouziotis AA, Giarra A, Libralato G, Pagano G, Guida M, Trifuoggi M. Toxicity of rare earth elements: an overview on human health impact. Front Environ Sci. 2022;10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Portincasa P, Moschetta A, Palasciano G. Cholesterol gallstone disease. Lancet. 2006;368(9531):230–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16844493</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsing AW, Gao YT, Han TQ, Rashid A, Sakoda LC, Wang BS, et al. Gallstones and the risk of biliary tract cancer: a population-based study in China. Br J Cancer. 2007;97(11):1577–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2360257</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18000509</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duncan CB, Riall TS. Evidence-based current surgical practice: calculous gallbladder disease. J Gastrointest Surg. 2012;16(11):2011–25.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3496004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22986769</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y, Kong J, Wu S. Cholesterol gallstone disease: focusing on the role of gallbladder. Lab Invest. 2015;95(2):124–31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25502177</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun H, Warren J, Yip J, Ji Y, Hao S, Han W et al. Factors Influencing Gallstone Formation: Rev Literature Biomolecules. 2022;12(4).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9026518</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35454138</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Channa NA. Gallstone disease: a review. Pakistan Armed Forces Med J. 2008;58(2):197–208.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu H, Shao W, Liu Q, Liu N, Wang Q, Xu J, et al. Gut microbiota promotes cholesterol gallstone formation by modulating bile acid composition and biliary cholesterol secretion. Nat Commun. 2022;13(1):252.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8752841</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35017486</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsing AW, Gao Y-T, Devesa SS, Jin F, Fraumeni JF Jr. Rising incidence of biliary tract cancers in Shanghai, China. Int J Cancer. 1998;75(3):368–70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9455795</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsing AW, Bai Y, Andreotti G, Rashid A, Deng J, Chen J, et al. Family history of gallstones and the risk of biliary tract cancer and gallstones: a population-based study in Shanghai, China. Int J Cancer. 2007;121(4):832–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2885776</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17450525</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nelson SM, Gao Y-T, Nogueira LM, Shen M-C, Wang B, Rashid A, et al. Diet and biliary tract cancer risk in Shanghai, China. PLoS ONE. 2017;12(3):e0173935.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5348031</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28288186</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kratzer W, Mason RA, Kächele V. Prevalence of gallstones in sonographic surveys worldwide. 1999;27(1):1–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9888092</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waheed A, Li X, Tan M, Bao L, Liu J, Zhang Y, et al. Size distribution and sources of Trace metals in Ultrafine/Fine/Coarse Airborne particles in the atmosphere of Shanghai. Aerosol Sci Technol. 2011;45(2):163–71.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hatje V, Bruland KW, Flegal AR. Increases in Anthropogenic Gadolinium anomalies and Rare Earth element concentrations in San Francisco Bay over a 20 year record. Environ Sci Technol. 2016;50(8):4159–68.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26742888</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wysocka IA, Rogowska AM, Kostrz-Sikora P. Investigation of anthropogenic gadolinium in tap water of Polish cities: Gdansk, Krakow, Warszawa, and Wroclaw. Environ Pollut. 2023;323:121289.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36791951</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang Q, Yin H, Li J, Zhang L, Hou R, Wang S. Investigation of rare earth elements in urine and drinking water of children in mining area. Medicine. 2018;97(40).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6200459</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30290677</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brouziotis AA, Giarra A, Libralato G, Pagano G, Guida M, Trifuoggi M. Toxicity of rare earth elements: an overview on human health impact. Frontier Environ Sci. 2022;10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parviainen A, Roman-Alpiste MJ, Marchesi C, Suárez-Grau JM, Pérez-López R. New insights into the metal partitioning in different microphases of human gallstones. J Trace Elem Med Biol. 2017;44:339–48.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28965597</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li X, Han G. One-step chromatographic purification of K, ca, and Sr from geological samples for high precision stable and radiogenic isotope analysis by MC-ICP-MS. J Anal Spectrom. 2021;36(3):676–84.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang J, Liang D, Xu L, Liu Y, Jiang S, Han X et al. Associations between novel anthropometric indices and the prevalence of gallstones among 6,848 adults: a cross-sectional study. Front Nutr. 2024;11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11298442</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39104753</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haskin LA, Haskin MA, Frey FA, Wildeman TR. Relative and Absolute Terrestrial Abundances of the Rare Earths. In: Origin and Distribution of the Elements. edn. Edited by Ahrens LH: Pergamon; 1968: 889–912.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor SR, McLennan SM, Armstrong RL, Tarney J. The composition and evolution of the Continental Crust: Rare Earth element evidence from Sedimentary Rocks [and discussion]. Math Phys Sci. 1981;301(1461):381–99. Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London Series.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kulaksız S, Bau M. Contrasting behaviour of anthropogenic gadolinium and natural rare earth elements in estuaries and the gadolinium input into the North Sea. Earth Planet Sci Lett. 2007;260:361–71.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rogosnitzky M, Branch S. Gadolinium-based contrast agent toxicity: a review of known and proposed mechanisms. Biometals. 2016;29(3):365–76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4879157</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27053146</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lawrence MG, Ort C, Keller J. Detection of anthropogenic gadolinium in treated wastewater in South East Queensland, Australia. Water Res. 2009;43(14):3534–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19541341</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elderfield H, Greaves MJ. The rare earth elements in seawater. Nature. 1982;296(5854):214–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bau M, Dulski P. Anthropogenic origin of positive gadolinium anomalies in river waters. Earth Planet Sci Lett. 1996;143(1):245–55.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bau M, Knappe A, Dulski P. Anthropogenic gadolinium as a micropollutant in river waters in Pennsylvania and in Lake Erie, northeastern United States. Geochemistry. 2006;66(2):143–52.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiao T, Ma RH, Luo XB, Yang LQ, Luo ZL, Zheng PM. The systematic classification of gallbladder stones. PLoS ONE. 2013;8(10):e74887.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3790764</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24124459</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koeberl C, Bayer PM. Concentrations of rare earth elements in human brain tissue and kidney stones determined by neutron activation analysis. J Alloys Compd. 1992;180(1):63–70.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Q, Hong J, Lai G, Yang X, Chen G, Xu N, et al. What are exposure biomarkers of rare earth elements for the ionic rare earth occupational population? Environ Pollut. 2024;345:123499.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38350535</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mauro M, Crosera M, Monai M, Montini T, Fornasiero P, Bovenzi M, et al. Cerium Oxide nanoparticles absorption through Intact and Damaged Human skin. Molecules. 2019;24(20):3759.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6832931</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31635398</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang W, Yang Y, Wang D, Huang L. Toxic effects of Rare Earth elements on Human Health: a review. Toxics. 2024;12(5):317.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11125915</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38787096</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Islam MR, Akash S, Jony MH, alam MN, Nowrin FT, Rahman MM, et al. Exploring the potential function of trace elements in human health: a therapeutic perspective. Mol Cell Biochem. 2023;478(10):2141–71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36637616</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phelps T, Snyder E, Rodriguez E, Child H, Harvey P. The influence of biological sex and sex hormones on bile acid synthesis and cholesterol homeostasis. Biology Sex Differences. 2019;10(1):52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6880483</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31775872</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park SM. Sex/Gender Differences in Pancreatic and Biliary Diseases. In: Sex/Gender-Specific Medicine in Clinical Areas. edn. Edited by Kim N. Singapore: Springer Nature Singapore; 2024: 219–230.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang DG, Yang J, Zhang S, Yang DJ. A survey of 16 rare Earth elements in the major foods in China. Biomed Environ Sci. 2012;25(3):267–71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22840576</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang D, Sui H, Mao W, Wang Y, Yang D, Zhang L et al. Dietary exposure Assessment of Rare Earth elements in the Chinese Population. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19(23).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9738814</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36497658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi Z, Yong L, Liu Z, Wang Y, Sui H, Mao W, et al. Risk assessment of rare earth elements in fruits and vegetables from mining areas in China. Environ Sci Pollut Res Int. 2022;29(32):48694–703.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35195864</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arciszewska Ż, Gama S, Leśniewska B, Malejko J, Nalewajko-Sieliwoniuk E, Zambrzycka-Szelewa E, et al. The translocation pathways of rare earth elements from the environment to the food chain and their impact on human health. Process Saf Environ Prot. 2022;168:205–23.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdelnour SA, Abd El-Hack ME, Khafaga AF, Noreldin AE, Arif M, Chaudhry MT, et al. Impacts of rare earth elements on animal health and production: highlights of cerium and lanthanum. Sci Total Environ. 2019;672:1021–32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30999219</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Channa NA, Khand F, Memon AR, Memon AN. Association of tea and other addictive substances with gallstone disease in Southern Sindh, Pakistan. Forces Med J. 2008;58(4):363–71.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang X-N, Gu Y-G, Wang Z-H. Rare earth elements in different trophic level marine wild fish species. Environ Pollut. 2022;292:118346.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34656683</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pagano G, Thomas PJ, Di Nunzio A, Trifuoggi M. Human exposures to rare earth elements: present knowledge and research prospects. Environ Res. 2019;171:493–500.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30743241</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu J-K, Pan H, Huang S-M, Huang N-L, Yao C-C, Hsiao K-M, et al. Calcium content of different compositions of gallstones and pathogenesis of calcium carbonate gallstones. Asian J Surg. 2013;36(1):26–35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23270822</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noack CW, Dzombak DA, Karamalidis AK. Rare earth element distributions and trends in natural waters with a focus on groundwater. Environ Sci Technol. 2014;48(8):4317–26.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24628583</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mayfield DB, Fairbrother A. Examination of rare earth element concentration patterns in freshwater fish tissues. Chemosphere. 2015;120:68–74.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25000508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li J-X, Zheng L, Sun C-J, Jiang F-H, Yin X-F, Chen J-H, et al. Study on Ecological and Chemical Properties of Rare Earth elements in Tropical Marine organisms. Chin J Anal Chem. 2016;44(10):1539–46.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang H, Chen X, Ye J, Jia X, Zhang Q, He H. Analysis of the absorption and accumulation characteristics of rare earth elements in Chinese tea. J Sci Food Agric. 2020;100(8):3360–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32134117</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu L, Dai Y, Yuan Z, Li J. Effects of rare earth elements on telomerase activity and apoptosis of human peripheral blood mononuclear cells. Biol Trace Elem Res. 2007;116(1):53–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17634627</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hao Z, Li Y, Li H, Wei B, Liao X, Liang T, et al. Levels of rare earth elements, heavy metals and uranium in a population living in Baiyun Obo, Inner Mongolia, China: a pilot study. Chemosphere. 2015;128:161–70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25703899</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harkness JS, Darrah TH. From the crust to the cortical: the geochemistry of trace elements in human bone. Geochim Cosmochim Acta. 2019;249:76–94.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor SR, McLennan SM. The geochemical evolution of the continental crust. Rev Geophys. 1995;33(2):241–65.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borkowski M, Siekierski S. Factors affecting the position of Y and actinides(III) with respect to lanthanides in the NH4SCN - ADOGEN-464SCN extraction system. Radiochim Acta. 1992;56(1):31–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu X, Byrne RH. Comparative carbonate complexation of yttrium and gadolinium at 25°C and 0.7 mol dm – 3 ionic strength. Mar Chem. 1995;51(3):213–21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kawabe I, Kitahara Y, Naito K. Non-chondritic yttrium/holmium ratio and lanthanide tetrad effect observed in pre-cenozoic limestones. Geochem J. 1991;25(1):31–44.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Möller P, Morteani G, Dulski P. Anomalous gadolinium, cerium, and yttrium contents in the adige and isarco river waters and in the water of their tributaries (provinces Trento and Bolzano/Bozen, NE Italy). Acta Hydroch Hydrob. 2003;31(3):225–39.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han G, Liu C. Dissolved rare earth elements in river waters draining karst terrains in Guizhou Province, China. Aquat Geochem. 2007;13(1):95–107.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nozaki Y, Zhang J, Amakawa H. The fractionation between Y and Ho in the marine environment. Earth Planet Sci Lett. 1997;148(1):329–40.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao X, Chen Y, Wang X, Deng X. Effects of Redox potential and pH value on the release of rare earth elements from soil. Chemosphere. 2001;44(4):655–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11482653</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Towell DG, Spirn RV, Winchester JW. Europium anomalies and the Genesis of Basalt: a discussion. Chem Geol. 1968;4(3–4):461–4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao X, Han G, Liu J, Zhang S. Spatial distribution and sources of Rare Earth elements in Urban River Water: the indicators of anthropogenic inputs. Water. 2023;15(4):654.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han R, Wang Z, Shen Y, Wu Q, Liu X, Cao C, et al. Anthropogenic gd in urban river water: a case study in Guiyang, SW China. Elementa-Science Anthropocene. 2021;9(1):00147.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Darrah TH, Prutsman-Pfeiffer JJ, Poreda RJ, Ellen Campbell M, Hauschka PV, Hannigan RE. Incorporation of excess gadolinium into human bone from medical contrast agents. Metallomics. 2009;1(6):479–88.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21305156</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Idee JM, Port M, Raynal I, Schaefer M, Le Greneur S, Corot C. Clinical and biological consequences of transmetallation induced by contrast agents for magnetic resonance imaging: a review. Fundam Clin Pharmacol. 2006;20(6):563–76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17109649</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kümmerer K, Helmers E. Hospital effluents as a source of Gd in the aquatic environment. Environ Sci Technol. 2000;34:573–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang C-b, Zhang S, Jia Y-j, Duan H-f, Ma G-m, Zhang X-r, et al. Clinical application of dual-energy Spectral Computed Tomography in detecting cholesterol gallstones from surrounding bile. Acad Radiol. 2017;24(4):478–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27916593</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ratanaprasatporn L, Uyeda JW, Wortman JR, Richardson I, Sodickson AD. Multimodality Imaging, including dual-energy CT, in the evaluation of Gallbladder Disease. Radiographics. 2018;38(1):75–89.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29320323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>