<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39332563</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1879-0003</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>280</Volume><Issue>Pt 3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>25</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>International journal of biological macromolecules</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Int J Biol Macromol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A review on the encapsulation of "eco-friendly" compounds in natural polymer-based nanoparticles as next generation nano-agrochemicals for sustainable agriculture and crop management.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>136030</StartPage><MedlinePgn>136030</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2024.136030</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0141-8130(24)06839-9</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Crop management techniques and sustainable agriculture offer a comprehensive farming method that incorporates social, economic, and ecological factors. Sustainable agriculture places a high priority on soil health, water efficiency, and biodiversity conservation in order to develop resilient and regenerative food systems that can feed both the current and future generations. Our goal in this review is to give a thorough overview of current developments in the use of polysaccharides as raw materials for the encapsulation of natural chemicals in nanoparticles as novel crop protection products. The search for recent research articles and latest reviews has been carried out through pubmed, google scholar, BASE as search engines. Offer cutting-edge solutions for sustainable crop management that satisfy the demands of an expanding population, comply with changing legal frameworks, and address environmental issues by encasing natural compounds inside polysaccharide-based nanoparticles. A variety of natural substances, such as essential oils, plant extracts, antimicrobials compounds and miRNA, can be included in these nanoparticles. These materials have many advantages, such as biocompatibility, biodegradability and controlled release of active compounds. Thanks to their action mechanism, they are able to mediate hormone signaling and gene expression in different plant physiological aspects, as well as enhance their tolerance to abiotic stress conditions. Sustainable agriculture can be supported by this type of treatments, correctly developing food safety through the production of non-toxic nanoparticles, low-cost industrial scale-up and the use of biodegradable materials. Polysaccharide-based nanoparticles have a wide range of uses in agriculture: they improve crop yields, encourage "eco-friendly" farming methods and can decrease the concentrations of active ingredient used, providing an accurate and affective dosage without damaging further species, as well as avoiding treatment resistance risks. These nanoparticles can also reduce the negative effects of chemical fertilizers and pesticides, contributing to the environmentally friendly agricultural development. Furthermore, the application of polysaccharide-based nanoparticles is consistent with the expanding trend of green and sustainable agriculture.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mondéjar-López</LastName><ForeName>María</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Instituto Botánico, Departamento de Ciencia y Tecnología Agroforestal y Genética, Universidad de Castilla-La Mancha, Campus Universitario s/n, 02071 Albacete, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>García-Simarro</LastName><ForeName>Maria Paz</ForeName><Initials>MP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Instituto Botánico, Departamento de Ciencia y Tecnología Agroforestal y Genética, Universidad de Castilla-La Mancha, Campus Universitario s/n, 02071 Albacete, Spain; Naplatec S.L, Calle Mayor 36, 02001 Albacete, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Navarro-Simarro</LastName><ForeName>Pablo</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Instituto Botánico, Departamento de Ciencia y Tecnología Agroforestal y Genética, Universidad de Castilla-La Mancha, Campus Universitario s/n, 02071 Albacete, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gómez-Gómez</LastName><ForeName>Lourdes</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Instituto Botánico, Departamento de Ciencia y Tecnología Agroforestal y Genética, Universidad de Castilla-La Mancha, Campus Universitario s/n, 02071 Albacete, Spain; Facultad de Farmacia, Departamento de Ciencia y Tecnología Agroforestal y Genética, Universidad de Castilla-La Mancha, C/ José María Sánchez Ibáñez s/n, 02008 Albacete, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ahrazem</LastName><ForeName>Oussama</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Instituto Botánico, Departamento de Ciencia y Tecnología Agroforestal y Genética, Universidad de Castilla-La Mancha, Campus Universitario s/n, 02071 Albacete, Spain; Escuela Técnica Superior de Ingeniería Agronómica y de Montes y Biotecnología, Departamento de Ciencia y Tecnología Agroforestal y Genética, Universidad de Castilla-La Mancha, Campus Universitario s/n, 02071 Albacete, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Niza</LastName><ForeName>Enrique</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Instituto Botánico, Departamento de Ciencia y Tecnología Agroforestal y Genética, Universidad de Castilla-La Mancha, Campus Universitario s/n, 02071 Albacete, Spain; Facultad de Farmacia, Departamento de Ciencia y Tecnología Agroforestal y Genética, Universidad de Castilla-La Mancha, C/ José María Sánchez Ibáñez s/n, 02008 Albacete, Spain; Escuela Técnica Superior de Ingeniería Agronómica y de Montes y Biotecnología, Departamento de Ciencia y Tecnología Agroforestal y Genética, Universidad de Castilla-La Mancha, Campus Universitario s/n, 02071 Albacete, Spain. Electronic address: Enrique.niza@uclm.es.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Int J Biol Macromol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7909578</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0141-8130</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Agrochemicals</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Nanotechnology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Natural polymers</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39332563</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2024.136030</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0141-8130(24)06839-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>