<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39332551</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1879-0003</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>280</Volume><Issue>Pt 4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>25</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>International journal of biological macromolecules</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Int J Biol Macromol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The composition, extraction, functional property, quality, and health benefits of coconut protein: A review.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>135905</StartPage><MedlinePgn>135905</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2024.135905</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0141-8130(24)06714-X</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Coconut is widely appreciated for its distinctive flavor and is commonly utilized in the production of a variety of goods. Coconut protein, a by-product derived from coconut oil and coconut milk cake, is frequently underutilized or discarded. This study provides a comprehensive overview of the distribution and composition of coconut protein. Analyses reveal that coconut protein, specifically 11S globulin and 7S globulin, is predominantly found in coconut flesh. Furthermore, various extraction techniques for coconut protein, such as chemical, enzymatic, and physical methods, are discussed. The alkali dissolution and acid precipitation methods are widely utilized for extracting coconut protein, with the potential for enhancement through the incorporation of physical methods such as ultrasound. The evaluation of functional properties, quality, and health benefits of coconut protein is essential, given the limitations imposed by its solubility. Modification may be necessary to optimize its functional properties. Coconut presents a promising source of food protein, characterized by balanced amino acid composition, high digestibility, and low allergenic potential. In conclusion, this study provides a comprehensive overview of the extraction methods, functional properties, quality, and nutritional benefits of coconut protein, offering insights for potential future research directions in the field. Additionally, the information presented may serve as a valuable reference for incorporating coconut protein into plant-based food products.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Yang</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Food Nutrition and Functional Food of Hainan Province, School of Food Science and Engineering, Hainan University, Haikou 570228, China; Department of Nutritional Sciences, University of Connecticut, Storrs, CT 06269, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Tong</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Food Nutrition and Functional Food of Hainan Province, School of Food Science and Engineering, Hainan University, Haikou 570228, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jiang</LastName><ForeName>Lianzhou</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Food Nutrition and Functional Food of Hainan Province, School of Food Science and Engineering, Hainan University, Haikou 570228, China; College of Food Science, Northeast Agricultural University, Harbin, Heilongjiang 150030, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huang</LastName><ForeName>Zhaoxian</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Food Nutrition and Functional Food of Hainan Province, School of Food Science and Engineering, Hainan University, Haikou 570228, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Weimin</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Food Nutrition and Functional Food of Hainan Province, School of Food Science and Engineering, Hainan University, Haikou 570228, China; Key Laboratory of Tropical Fruits and Vegetables Quality and Safety for State Market Regulation, Hainan Institute for Food Control, Haikou 570228, China. Electronic address: zhwm1979@163.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Luo</LastName><ForeName>Yangchao</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nutritional Sciences, University of Connecticut, Storrs, CT 06269, United States of America. Electronic address: yangchao.luo@uconn.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Int J Biol Macromol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7909578</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0141-8130</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Coconut by-product</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Functional peptide</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Globulin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Plant protein</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39332551</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2024.135905</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0141-8130(24)06714-X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>