<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39332621</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2214-5753</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>25</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Current opinion in insect science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Curr Opin Insect Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Microbial interactions shaping host attractiveness: insights into dynamic behavioral relationships.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>101275</StartPage><MedlinePgn>101275</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.cois.2024.101275</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S2214-5745(24)00117-2</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Insects discern the presence of hosts (host plants) by integrating chemosensory, gustatory, and visual cues, with olfaction playing a pivotal role in this process. Among these factors, volatile signals produced by host-associated microbial communities significantly affect insect attraction. Microorganisms are widely and abundantly found on the surfaces of humans, plants, and insects. Notably, these microorganisms can metabolize compounds from the host surface and regulate the production of characteristic volatiles, which may guide the use of host microorganisms to modulate insect behavior. Essentially, the attraction of hosts to insects is intricately linked to the presence of their symbiotic microorganisms. This review underscores the critical role of microorganisms in shaping the dynamics of attractiveness between insects and their hosts.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Hong</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Resource Insects, Institute of Apicultural Research, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Beijing 100193, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhu</LastName><ForeName>Yibin</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>New Cornerstone Science Laboratory, Tsinghua-Peking Joint Center for Life Sciences, School of Basic Medical Sciences, Tsinghua University, Beijing 100084, China; Institute of Infectious Diseases, Shenzhen Bay Laboratory, Shenzhen, Guangdong 518000, China; Institute of Pathogenic Organisms, Shenzhen Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Shenzhen 518055, China; Southwest United Graduate School, Kunming 650092, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Yibaina</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>China National Center for Food Safety Risk Assessment, Beijing 100022, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jiang</LastName><ForeName>Liping</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Parasitology, School of Basic Medical Sciences, Central South University, Changsha, Hunan 410013, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shi</LastName><ForeName>Xiaolu</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Pathogenic Organisms, Shenzhen Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Shenzhen 518055, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cheng</LastName><ForeName>Gong</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>New Cornerstone Science Laboratory, Tsinghua-Peking Joint Center for Life Sciences, School of Basic Medical Sciences, Tsinghua University, Beijing 100084, China; Institute of Infectious Diseases, Shenzhen Bay Laboratory, Shenzhen, Guangdong 518000, China; Institute of Pathogenic Organisms, Shenzhen Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Shenzhen 518055, China; Southwest United Graduate School, Kunming 650092, China. Electronic address: gongcheng@mail.tsinghua.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Curr Opin Insect Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101635599</NlmUniqueID></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CoiStatement>Declaration of Competing Interest The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39332621</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cois.2024.101275</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2214-5745(24)00117-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>