<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39334412</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>30</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2055-0928</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>27</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC nutrition</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Nutr</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Association between empirically derived nutrient patterns and breast cancer: a case-control study in a Middle Eastern country.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>124</StartPage><MedlinePgn>124</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">124</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s40795-024-00934-x</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="PURPOSE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">The risk of breast cancer (BC) and related mortality have increased in Middle-East countries during recent decades. The relationship between several nutrient intakes and the risk of BC has been investigated in several studies. However, few studies have estimated the effects of patterns of different nutrient intake on the risk of BC in this region.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A total of 453 patients who were recently diagnosed with breast cancer and 516 healthy women participated in the current case-control study. To evaluate the dietary intakes, we used a validated 168-item food frequency questionnaire (FFQ) during the last year. Nutrient Patterns (NPs) were extracted through factor analysis (FA) of energy-adjusted twenty-six nutrients. The relationship between nutrient patterns and the risk of breast cancer in pre and post-menopausal women was estimated by multivariable regression.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Four major nutrient patterns were identified in the current study. The first nutrient pattern was rich in animal protein, retinol, riboflavin, pantothenic acid, cobalamin, and calcium. Higher saturated fatty acids (SFAs), mono-unsaturated fatty acids (MUFAs), polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFAs), and trans fatty acids (TFAs), and lower intakes of niacin were observed in nutrient pattern 2. The third nutrient pattern was rich in fiber, potassium, and vitamin C. Nutrient pattern 4, was associated with higher intakes of vegetable protein, alpha-tocopherol, and magnesium. A significant inverse relationship was observed between adherence to nutrient pattern 3 and the risk of BC in all participants [odds ratio (OR) = 0.70, 95% confidence interval (CI): 0.50, 0.97, P = 0.03) and pre-menopausal women (OR = 0.59 (0.39-0.89), P = 0.01).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Decreasing odds of breast cancer were observed by adherence to a nutrient pattern high in dietary fiber, vitamin C, and potassium. Future prospective investigations are recommended to confirm these findings.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dehghani</LastName><ForeName>Farimah</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Nutrition, School of Nutritional Sciences and Dietetics, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sasanfar</LastName><ForeName>Bahareh</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Center for Food Hygiene and Safety, School of Public Health, Shahid Sadoughi University of Medical Sciences, Yazd, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nutrition, School of Public Health, Shahid Sadoughi University of Medical Sciences, P O Box 8915173160, Yazd, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cancer Research Center, Cancer Institute of Iran, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, P.O.Box 13145158, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Student Research Committee, Shahid Sadoughi University of Medical Sciences, Yazd, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Toorang</LastName><ForeName>Fatemeh</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cancer Research Center, Cancer Institute of Iran, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, P.O.Box 13145158, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Nutrition, School of Nutritional Sciences and Dietetics, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Departments of Medical and Surgical Sciences, University of Bologna, Bologna, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zendehdel</LastName><ForeName>Kazem</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cancer Research Center, Cancer Institute of Iran, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, P.O.Box 13145158, Tehran, Iran. kzendeh@tums.ac.ir.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cancer Biology Research Center, Cancer Institute of Iran, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran. kzendeh@tums.ac.ir.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Breast Diseases Research Center, Cancer Institute of Iran, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran. kzendeh@tums.ac.ir.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Salehi-Abargouei</LastName><ForeName>Amin</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Center for Food Hygiene and Safety, School of Public Health, Shahid Sadoughi University of Medical Sciences, Yazd, Iran. abargouei@ssu.ac.ir.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Yazd Cardiovascular Research Center, Non-Communicable Diseases Research Institute, Shahid Sadoughi University of Medical Sciences, Yazd, Iran. abargouei@ssu.ac.ir.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nutrition, School of Public Health, Shahid Sadoughi University of Medical Sciences, P O Box 8915173160, Yazd, Iran. abargouei@ssu.ac.ir.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Nutr</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101672434</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2055-0928</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Breast cancer</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Case–control</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Middle-Eastern countries</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Nutrient pattern</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>31</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39334412</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11438089</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40795-024-00934-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s40795-024-00934-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Arnold M, Morgan E, Rumgay H, Mafra A, Singh D, Laversanne M, et al. Current and future burden of breast cancer: Global statistics for 2020 and 2040. The Breast. 2022;66:15–23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9465273</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36084384</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sung H, Ferlay J, Siegel RL, Laversanne M, Soerjomataram I, Jemal A, et al. Global Cancer Statistics 2020: GLOBOCAN Estimates of Incidence and Mortality Worldwide for 36 Cancers in 185 Countries. CA Cancer J Clin. 2021;71(3):209–49.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33538338</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taghavi A, Fazeli Z, Vahedi M, Baghestani AR, Pourhoseingholi A, Barzegar F, et al. Increased trend of breast cancer mortality in Iran. Asian Pac J Cancer Prev. 2012;13(1):367–70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22502702</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>AlizadehOtaghvar H, Hosseini M, Tizmaghz A, Shabestanipour G, Noori H. A review on metastatic breast cancer in Iran. Asian Pac J Trop Biomed. 2015;5(6):429–33.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naderimagham S, Alipour S, Djalalinia S, Kasaeian A, Noori A, Rahimzadeh S, et al. National and sub-national burden of breast cancer in Iran; 1990–2013. Arch Iran Med. 2014;17(12):794–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25481316</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Majeed W, Aslam B, Javed I, Khaliq T, Muhammad F, Ali A, et al. Breast cancer: major risk factors and recent developments in treatment. Asian Pac J Cancer Prev. 2014;15(8):3353–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24870721</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maas P, Barrdahl M, Joshi AD, Auer PL, Gaudet MM, Milne RL, et al. Breast cancer risk from modifiable and nonmodifiable risk factors among white women in the United States. JAMA Oncol. 2016;2(10):1295–302.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5719876</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27228256</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mourouti N, Kontogianni MD, Papavagelis C, Panagiotakos DB. Diet and breast cancer: a systematic review. Int J Food Sci Nutr. 2015;66(1):1–42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25198160</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kwan ML, Weltzien E, Kushi LH, Castillo A, Slattery ML, Caan BJ. Dietary patterns and breast cancer recurrence and survival among women with early-stage breast cancer. J Clin Oncol. 2009;27(6):919–26.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2668637</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19114692</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turati F, Carioli G, Bravi F, Ferraroni M, Serraino D, Montella M, et al. Mediterranean diet and breast cancer risk. Nutrients. 2018;10(3):326–36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5872744</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29518016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malmir H, Shayanfar M, Mohammad-Shirazi M, Tabibi H, Sharifi G, Esmaillzadeh A. Patterns of nutrients intakes in relation to glioma: A case-control study. Clin Nutr. 2019;38(3):1406–13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29960808</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang D, Xu P, Li Y, Wei B, Yang S, Zheng Y, et al. Association of vitamin C intake with breast cancer risk and mortality: a meta-analysis of observational studies. Aging. 2020;12(18):18415–35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7585084</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32991322</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nagel G, Linseisen J, van Gils CH, Peeters PH, Boutron-Ruault MC, Clavel-Chapelon F, et al. Dietary beta-carotene, vitamin C and E intake and breast cancer risk in the European Prospective Investigation into Cancer and Nutrition (EPIC). Breast Cancer Res Treat. 2010;119(3):753–65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19565333</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnson RK, Vanderlinden LA, DeFelice BC, Uusitalo U, Seifert J, Fan S, et al. Metabolomics-related nutrient patterns at seroconversion and risk of progression to type 1 diabetes. Pediatr Diabetes. 2020;21(7):1202–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7855902</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32686271</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gnagnarella P, Maisonneuve P, Bellomi M, Rampinelli C, Bertolotti R, Spaggiari L, et al. Nutrient intake and nutrient patterns and risk of lung cancer among heavy smokers: results from the COSMOS screening study with annual low-dose CT. Eur J Epidemiol. 2013;28(6):503–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23576215</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>JafariNasab S, Ghanavati M, Bahrami A, Rafiee P, Sadeghi A, Clark CCT, et al. Dietary nutrient patterns and the risk of colorectal cancer and colorectal adenomas: a case-control study. Eur J Cancer Prev. 2021;30(1):46–52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32039932</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tayyem RF, Mahmoud RI, Shareef MH, Marei LS. Nutrient intake patterns and breast cancer risk among Jordanian women: a case-control study. Epidemiol Health. 2019;41:e2019010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6533554</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30999736</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fereidani SS, Eini-Zinab H, Heidari Z, Jalali S, Sedaghat F, Rashidkhani B. Nutrient Patterns and Risk of Breast Cancer among Iranian Women: a Case- Control Study. Asian Pac J Cancer Prev. 2018;19(9):2619–24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6249482</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30256069</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Assi N, Moskal A, Slimani N, Viallon V, Chajes V, Freisling H, et al. A treelet transform analysis to relate nutrient patterns to the risk of hormonal receptor-defined breast cancer in the European Prospective Investigation into Cancer and Nutrition (EPIC). Public Health Nutr. 2016;19(2):242–54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10270861</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25702596</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edefonti V, Decarli A, La Vecchia C, Bosetti C, Randi G, Franceschi S, et al. Nutrient dietary patterns and the risk of breast and ovarian cancers. Int J Cancer. 2008;122(3):609–13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17764109</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ronco AL, de Stefani E, Aune D, Boffetta P, Deneo-Pellegrini H, Acosta G, et al. Nutrient patterns and risk of breast cancer in Uruguay. Asian Pac J Cancer Prev. 2010;11(2):519–24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20843144</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vahid F, Hatami M, Sadeghi M, Ameri F, Faghfoori Z, Davoodi SH. The association between the Index of Nutritional Quality (INQ) and breast cancer and the evaluation of nutrient intake of breast cancer patients: A case-control study. Nutrition (Burbank, Los Angeles County, Calif). 2018;45:11–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29129231</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mirmiran P, Esfahani FH, Mehrabi Y, Hedayati M, Azizi F. Reliability and relative validity of an FFQ for nutrients in the Tehran lipid and glucose study. Public Health Nutr. 2010;13(5):654–62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19807937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Esfahani FH, Asghari G, Mirmiran P, Azizi F. Reproducibility and relative validity of food group intake in a food frequency questionnaire developed for the Tehran Lipid and Glucose Study. J Epidemiol. 2010;20(2):150–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3900814</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20154450</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghaffarpour M, Houshiar-Rad A, Kianfar H. The manual for household measures, cooking yields factors and edible portion of foods. Tehran: Nashre Olume Keshavarzy. 1999;7(213):42–58.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haytowitz D, Lemar L, Pehrsson P, Exler J, Patterson K, Thomas R, et al. USDA national nutrient database for standard reference, release 24. US Department of Agriculture: Washington, DC, USA. 2011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. Global physical activity questionnaire (GPAQ) analysis guide. Geneva; 2012. p. 1–22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim J, Mueller CW. Factor analysis - statistical methods and practical issues. Office of justice programs. United States of America; 1978. p. 88.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tabrizi R, Moosazadeh M, Akbari M, Dabbaghmanesh MH, Mohamadkhani M, Asemi Z, et al. High prevalence of vitamin D deficiency among Iranian population: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Iran J Med Sci. 2018;43(2):125–39.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5936844</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29749981</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mozafarinia M, Sasanfar B, Toorang F, Salehi-Abargouei A, Zendehdel K. Association between dietary fat and fat subtypes with the risk of breast cancer in an Iranian population: a case-control study. Lipids Health Dis. 2021;20:1–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8520643</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34657612</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harris HR, Bergkvist L, Wolk A. Vitamin C intake and breast cancer mortality in a cohort of Swedish women. Br J Cancer. 2013;109(1):257–64.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3708583</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23736027</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nechuta S, Lu W, Chen Z, Zheng Y, Gu K, Cai H, et al. Vitamin supplement use during breast cancer treatment and survival: a prospective cohort study. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev. 2011;20(2):262–71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3057050</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21177425</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frajese GV, Benvenuto M, Fantini M, Ambrosin E, Sacchetti P, Masuelli L, et al. Potassium increases the antitumor effects of ascorbic acid in breast cancer cell lines in vitro. Oncol Lett. 2016;11(6):4224–34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4888082</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27313770</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farvid MS, Spence ND, Holmes MD, Barnett JB. Fiber consumption and breast cancer incidence: A systematic review and meta-analysis of prospective studies. Cancer. 2020;126(13):3061–75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32249416</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marzbani B, Nazari J, Najafi F, Marzbani B, Shahabadi S, Amini M, et al. Dietary patterns, nutrition, and risk of breast cancer: a case-control study in the west of Iran. Epidemiol Health. 2019;41:e2019003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6446065</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30754960</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aune D, Chan DS, Vieira AR, Rosenblatt DA, Vieira R, Greenwood DC, et al. Fruits, vegetables and breast cancer risk: a systematic review and meta-analysis of prospective studies. Breast Cancer Res Treat. 2012;134(2):479–93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22706630</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loo G. Redox-sensitive mechanisms of phytochemical-mediated inhibition of cancer cell proliferation (review). J Nutr Biochem. 2003;14(2):64–73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12667597</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Willcox JK, Ash SL, Catignani GL. Antioxidants and prevention of chronic disease. Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr. 2004;44(4):275–95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15462130</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frei B. Reactive oxygen species and antioxidant vitamins: mechanisms of action. Am J Med. 1994;97(3a):5S-13S; discussion 22S-8S.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8085584</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aubertin-Leheudre M, Gorbach S, Woods M, Dwyer JT, Goldin B, Adlercreutz H. Fat/fiber intakes and sex hormones in healthy premenopausal women in USA. J Steroid Biochem Mol Biol. 2008;112(1–3):32–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2656650</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18761407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Topping DL, Clifton PM. Short-chain fatty acids and human colonic function: roles of resistant starch and nonstarch polysaccharides. Physiol Rev. 2001;81(3):1031–64.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11427691</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manning PJ, Sutherland WH, McGrath MM, de Jong SA, Walker RJ, Williams MJ. Postprandial cytokine concentrations and meal composition in obese and lean women. Obesity (Silver Spring, Md). 2008;16(9):2046–52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19186329</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen LA, Zhao Z, Zang EA, Wynn TT, Simi B, Rivenson A. Wheat bran and psyllium diets: effects on N-methylnitrosourea-induced mammary tumorigenesis in F344 rats. J Natl Cancer Inst. 1996;88(13):899–907.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8656442</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>