<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39348094</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>30</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1613-4133</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>30</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Molecular nutrition &amp; food research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Mol Nutr Food Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Opinion Piece: New Plant-Based Food Products Between Technology and Physiology.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e2400376</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e2400376</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/mnfr.202400376</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The rapid growth of product sectors for plant-based meat and dairy alternatives has raised significant scientific interest in their nutritional and ecological benefits. Here, it outlines the fractionation of plant-based raw materials and describes the technologies applied in the production of meat and dairy substitutes. Moreover, the study describes the effects of these new products on human nutrient supply and metabolic responses. Examples of meat-like products produced by extrusion technology and dairy alternatives are provided, addressing production challenges and the effects of processing on nutrient digestibility and bioavailability. In contrast to animal-based products, plant-based protein ingredients can contain many compounds produced by plants for defense or symbiotic interactions, such as lectins, phytates, and a wide range of secondary metabolites. The intake of these compounds as part of a plant-based diet can influence the digestion, bioaccessibility, and bioavailability of essential nutrients such as minerals and trace elements but also of amino acids. This is a critical factor, especially in regions with limited plant species for human consumption and inadequate technologies to eliminate these compounds. To fully understand these impacts and ensure that plant-based diets meet human nutritional needs, well-controlled human studies are needed.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Molecular Nutrition &amp; Food Research published by Wiley‐VCH GmbH.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Schweiggert-Weisz</LastName><ForeName>Ute</ForeName><Initials>U</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Life Sciences, Technical University of Munich, 85354, Freising, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Fraunhofer Institute for Process Engineering and Packaging, 85354, Freising, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Etzbach</LastName><ForeName>Lara</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Life Sciences, Technical University of Munich, 85354, Freising, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gola</LastName><ForeName>Susanne</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Fraunhofer Institute for Process Engineering and Packaging, 85354, Freising, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kulling</LastName><ForeName>Sabine E</ForeName><Initials>SE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Max Rubner-Institut (MRI), Department of Safety and Quality of Fruit and Vegetables, 76131, Karlsruhe, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Diekmann</LastName><ForeName>Christina</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Nutritional and Food Science, University of Bonn, 53115, Bonn, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Egert</LastName><ForeName>Sarah</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4092-8981</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Nutritional and Food Science, University of Bonn, 53115, Bonn, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Daniel</LastName><ForeName>Hannelore</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Life Sciences, Technical University of Munich, 85354, Freising, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>German Federal Ministry of Education and Research (BMBF)</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>30</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Mol Nutr Food Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101231818</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1613-4125</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">dairy and meat replacers</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food technology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">human physiology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">isolates</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nutrient status</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">plant proteins</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">protein concentrates</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39348094</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/mnfr.202400376</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Z. Bashi, R. McCullough, L. Ong, M. Ramirez, Alternative Proteins: The Race for Market Share Is On, Vol. 11, McKinsey &amp; Company, Denver, United States 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joint FAO/WHO Codex Alimentarius Commission, World Health Organization, Joint FAO/WHO Food Standards Programme, in Codex general standard for soy protein products, Cereals, Pulses, Legumes and Vegetable Proteins, Rome, Italy, 2007.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) S. Saffarionpour, Food Bioprocess Technol. 2023, 17, 1141;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) B. Rajpurohit, Y. Li, J. Future Foods 2023, 3, 340.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) C. Wang, L. A. Johnson, J. Am. Oil Chem. Soc. 2001, 78, 189;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) Z. Jiang, M. Pulkkinen, Y. Wang, A.‐M. Lampi, F. L. Stoddard, H. Salovaara, V. Piironen, T. Sontag‐Strohm, LWT – Food Sci. Technol. 2016, 68, 295.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) A. Martin, V. Schmidt, R. Osen, J. Bez, E. Ortner, S. Mittermaier, J. Sci. Food Agric. 2022, 102, 5011;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) J. K. Chavan, S. S. Kadam, N. R. Reddy, Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 1993, 33, 189.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Sethi, S. K. Tyagi, R. K. Anurag, J. Food Sci. Technol. 2016, 53, 3408.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. S. U. Roland, L. Pouvreau, J. Curran, F. van de Velde, P. M. T. de Kok, Cereal Chem. 2017, 94, 58.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Fernando, LWT – Food Sci. Technol. 2021, 141, 110961.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Guo, Soy Food Products and Their Health Benefits in Functional Foods, Elsevier, Amsterdam 2009, pp. 237–277.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Rivera, K. Siliveru, Y. Li, Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2022, 64, 4179.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Etzbach, S. Gola, F. Küllmer, I.‐H. Acir, D. Wohlt, L. M. Ignatzy, S. Bader‐Mittermaier, U. Schweiggert‐Weisz, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA in press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Wang, F. Tuccillo, A.‐M. Lampi, A. Knaapila, M. Pulkkinen, S. Kariluoto, R. Coda, M. Edelmann, K. Jouppila, M. Sandell, V. Piironen, K. Katina, Compr. Rev. Food Sci. Food Saf. 2022, 21, 2898.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Lie‐Piang, N. Braconi, R. M. Boom, A. van der Padt, J. Clean. Prod. 2021, 292, 126046.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) P. A. Wierenga, H. Gruppen, Curr. Opin. Colloid Interface Sci. 2010, 15, 365;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) B. P. Ismail, L. Senaratne‐Lenagala, A. Stube, A. Brackenridge, Anim. Front. 2020, 10, 53.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Vogelsang‐O'Dwyer, I. L. Petersen, M. S. Joehnke, J. C. Sørensen, J. Bez, A. Detzel, M. Busch, M. Krueger, J. A. O'Mahony, E. K. Arendt, E. Zannini, Foods 2020, 9, 322.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Kyriakopoulou, J. K. Keppler, A. J. van der Goot, R. M. Boom, Annu. Rev. Food Sci. Technol. 2021, 12, 29.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E.‐M. Schmid, A. Farahnaky, B. Adhikari, P. J. Torley, Compr. Rev. Food Sci. Food Saf. 2022, 21, 4573.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Osen, U. Schweiggert‐Weisz, High‐Moisture Extrusion: Meat Analogues in Reference Module in Food Science, Elsevier, Amsterdam 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C.‐T. Ho, W. E. Riha, III, in The Maillard Reaction in Foods and Medicine, Elsevier, Amsterdam 2005, pp. 187–192.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Orozco‐Angelino, J. Espinosa‐Ramírez, S. O. Serna‐Saldívar, Food Res. Int. 2023, 112889.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Nikmaram, S. Y. Leong, M. Koubaa, Z. Zhu, F. J. Barba, R. Greiner, I. Oey, S. Roohinejad, Food Control 2017, 79, 62.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. J. Meade, E. A. Reid, J. A. Gerrard, J. AOAC Int. 2005, 88, 904.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. C. Cheftel, Food Chem. 1986, 20, 263.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Brennan, M. Brennan, E. Derbyshire, B. K. Tiwari, Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2011, 22, 570.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Naumann, U. Schweiggert‐Weisz, A. Martin, M. Schuster, P. Eisner, Food Hydrocoll. 2021, 111, 106222.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. M. Pedrosa, E. Guillamón, C. Arribas, Foods 2021, 10, 379.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. N. Riaz, M. Asif, R. Ali, Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2009, 49, 361.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Zhong, Z. Fang, M. L. Wahlqvist, J. M. Hodgson, S. K. Johnson, LWT – Food Sci. Technol. 2021, 140, 110767.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Havlik, V. Plachy, J. Fernandez, V. Rada, J. Sci. Food Agric. 2010, 90, 2352.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Imran, Z. Liyan, Eur. Food Res. Technol. 2023, 249, 2189.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. N. Riaz, Proteins in Food Processing, Elsevier, Amsterdam 2004, p. 517.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Osen, S. Toelstede, F. Wild, P. Eisner, U. Schweiggert‐Weisz, J. Food Eng. 2014, 127, 67.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. L. Dekkers, C. V. Nikiforidis, A. J. van der Goot, Innov. Food Sci. Emerg. Technol. 2016, 36, 193.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Zhang, L. Liu, H. Liu, A. Yoon, S. S. H. Rizvi, Q. Wang, Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2019, 59, 3267.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. Schuh, K. Allard, K. Herrmann, M. Gibis, R. Kohlus, J. Weiss, Meat Sci. 2013, 93, 240.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. L. Coughlin, L. Liberman, S. P. Ertem, J. Edmund, F. S. Bates, T. P. Lodge, Prog. Polym. Sci. 2021, 112, 101324.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) A. S. Bancil, A. M. Sandall, M. Rossi, B. Chassaing, J. O. Lindsay, K. Whelan, J. Crohns Colitis 2021, 15, 1068;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) N. Narula, N. H. Chang, D. Mohammad, E. C. L. Wong, A. N. Ananthakrishnan, S. S. M. Chan, F. Carbonnel, A. Meyer, Clin. Gastroenterol. Hepatol. 2483, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. K. Ryu, Y. K. Kang, E. W. Jeong, Y. Baek, K. Y. Lee, H. G. Lee, LWT – Food Sci. Technol. 2023, 174, 114431.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Voss, I.‐L. Hsiao, M. Ebisch, J. Vidmar, N. Dreiack, L. Böhmert, V. Stock, A. Braeuning, K. Loeschner, P. Laux, Food Chem. 2020, 327, 127000.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Vogelsang‐O'Dwyer, E. Zannini, E. K. Arendt, Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2021, 110, 364.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Leszczyńska, A. Wirkijowska, A. Gasiński, D. Średnicka‐Tober, J. Trafiałek, R. Kazimierczak, Appl. Sci. 2023, 13, 11267.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) S. Chalupa‐Krebzdak, C. J. Long, B. M. Bohrer, Int. Dairy J. 2018, 87, 84;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) M. Stöckl, L. Pferdmenges, L. Brühl, R. Greiner, A. Hüsken, R. Krüger, G. Langenkämper, A. Lencioni, A. Müller, M. Schmidt, E. Sciurba, S. T. Soukup, L. Formherz, J. Food Compos. Anal. 2024, 106553.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Reyes‐Jurado, N. Soto‐Reyes, M. Dávila‐Rodríguez, A. C. Lorenzo‐Leal, M. T. Jiménez‐Munguía, E. Mani‐López, A. López‐Malo, Food Rev. Int. 2023, 39, 2320.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Grasso, L. Alonso‐Miravalles, J. A. O'Mahony, Foods 2020, 9, 252.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Part, J. Kazantseva, S. Rosenvald, A. Kallastu, H. Vaikma, T. Kriščiunaite, D. Pismennõi, E. Viiard, Future Foods 2023, 7, 100212.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. E. Johnson, J. Dairy Sci. 2017, 100, 9952.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Chen, J. Lu, F. Liu, J. Nsor‐Atindana, F. Xu, H. D. Goff, J. Ma, F. Zhong, Food Hydrocoll. 2019, 88, 247.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Grossmann, D. J. McClements, Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2021, 118, 207.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Wang, F. Ren, in Starch Structure, Functionality and Application in Foods (Ed.: S. Wang), Springer, Berlin 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Masotti, S. Cattaneo, M. Stuknytė, I. de Noni, Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2018, 74, 158.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Mefleh, A. Pasqualone, F. Caponio, M. Faccia, J. Sci. Food Agric. 2022, 102, 8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. J. Craig, A. R. Mangels, C. J. Brothers, Nutrients 2022, 14, 1247.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Pham, S. Knowles, E. Bermingham, J. Brown, R. Hannaford, D. Cameron‐Smith, A. Braakhuis, Curr. Dev. Nutr. 2022, 6, nzac082.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. De Marco Castro, G. Valli, C. Buffière, C. Guillet, B. Mullen, J. Pratt, K. Horner, S. Naumann‐Gola, S. Bader‐Mittermaier, M. Paganini, G. de Vito, H. M. Roche, D. Dardevet, Nutrients 2023, 15, 35.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. J. M. Pinckaers, I. W. K. Kouw, S. H. M. Gorissen, L. H. P. Houben, J. M. Senden, W. K. Wodzig, L. C. de Groot, L. B. Verdijk, T. Snijders, L. J. C. van Loon, J. Nutr. 2022, 152, 2734.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Sandström, H. Andersson, B. Kivistö, A.‐S. Sandberg, J. Nutr. 1986, 116, 2209.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. de Jesús Rodríguez‐Romero, A. C. Durán‐Castañeda, A. P. Cárdenas‐Castro, J. A. Sánchez‐Burgos, V. M. Zamora‐Gasga, S. G. Sáyago‐Ayerdi, Food Chem.: X 2022, 13, 100195.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Bartlett, M. Kleiner, iScience 2022, 25, 105313.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. W. Solomons, M. Janghorbani, B. T. G. Ting, F. H. Steinke, M. Christensen, R. Bijlani, N. Istfan, V. R. Young, J. Nutr. 1982, 112, 1809.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Beal, F. Ortenzi, J. Fanzo, Lancet Planet Health 2023, 7, e233.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. N. Perera, C. L. Palliyaguruge, D. D. Eapasinghe, D. M. Liyanage, R. H. Seneviratne, S. M. Demini, J. Jayasinghe, M. Faizan, U. Rajagopalan, B. P. Galhena, Nutr. Bull. 2023, 48, 442.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Blanco‐Rojo, M. P. Vaquero, Innov. Food Sci. Emerg. Technol. 2019, 51, 126.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Jarzębski, M. Wieruszewski, M. Kościński, T. Rogoziński, J. Kobus‐Cisowska, T. Szablewski, J. Perła‐Kaján, K. Waszkowiak, J. Jakubowicz, Rev. Adv. Mater. Sci. 2023, 62, 20230128.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. D. Quintaes, R. Barberá, A. Cilla, Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2017, 57, 2028.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. K. Proulx, M. B. Reddy, J. Agric. Food Chem. 2006, 54, 1518.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Haase, S. Ellinger, J. Linseisen, M. Neuhäuser‐Berthold, M. Richter, German Nutrition Society (DGE), J. Trace Elem. Med. Biol. 2020, 61, 126536.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. A. Schmidt, F. L. Crowe, P. N. Appleby, T. J. Key, R. C. Travis, PLoS ONE 2013, 8, e56339.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Zhang, L. Lin, H. Liu, Asia Pac. J. Clin. Nutr. 2018, 27, 1239.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. Zhang, Adv. Clin. Chem. 2023, 116, 209.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) D. R. Garrel, M. Verdy, C. PetitClerc, C. Martin, D. Brule, P. Hamet, Am. J. Clin. Nutr. 1991, 53, 665;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) N. Dalbeth, K. Palmano, Curr. Rheumatol. Rep. 2011, 13, 132.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Adamcová, K. H. Laursen, N. Z. Ballin, Foods 2021, 10, 2796.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Katoch, A. Tripathi, J. Biosci. 2021, 46, 104.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Geraldo, C. S. Santos, E. Pinto, M. W. Vasconcelos, Front. Plant Sci. 2022, 13, 772054.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) A. Rodriguez‐Mateos, M. L. Sayec, A. Cheok, Proc. Nutr. Soc. 2024, 1;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) J. Godos, A. Micek, P. Mena, D. Del Rio, F. Galvano, S. Castellano, G. Grosso, Mol. Nutr. Food Res. 2024, 68, 2300472;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) M. d. A. Fagundes, A. R. C. Silva, G. A. Fernandes, M. P. Curado, Cancers 2022, 14, 5878;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>d) F. Liu, Y. Peng, Y. Qiao, Y. Huang, F. Song, M. Zhang, F. Song, Nutr. J. 2022, 21, 27.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Cassidy, A.‐M. Minihane, Am. J. Clin. Nutr. 2017, 105, 10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. Cheynier, Am. J. Clin. Nutr. 2005, 81, 223S.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. L. Bourvellec, C. M. Renard, Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2012, 52, 213.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) N. F. Bras, R. Goncalves, N. Mateus, P. A. Fernandes, M. J. Ramos, V. de Freitas, J. Agric. Food Chem. 2010, 58, 10668;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) R. Gonçalves, S. Soares, N. Mateus, V. de Freitas, J. Agric. Food Chem. 2007, 55, 7596.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Colletti, A. Attrovio, L. Boffa, S. Mantegna, G. Cravotto, Molecules 2020, 25, 2129.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. E. Geerts, B. L. Dekkers, A. van der Padt, A. J. van der Goot, Innov. Food Sci. Emerg. Technol. 2018, 45, 313.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) J. Medic, C. Atkinson, C. R. Hurburgh, J. Am. Oil Chem. Soc. 2014, 91, 363;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) B. Písaříková, Z. Zralý, Acta Vet. Brno 2010, 79, 211.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Fernández‐Quintela, M. T. Macarulla, A. S. Del Barrio, J. A. Martínez, Plant Foods Hum. Nutr. 1997, 51, 331.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Bähr, A. Fechner, K. Hasenkopf, S. Mittermaier, G. Jahreis, LWT – Food Sci. Technol. 2014, 59, 587.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>I. S. Muranyi, C. Otto, C. Pickardt, P. Koehler, U. Schweiggert‐Weisz, Food Res. Int. 2013, 54, 1419.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) N. Musco, M. I. Cutrignelli, S. Calabrò, R. Tudisco, F. Infascelli, R. Grazioli, V. L. Presti, F. Gresta, B. Chiofalo, J. Anim. Physiol. Anim. Nutr. 2017, 101, 1227;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) S. Naumann, U. Schweiggert‐Weisz, D. Haller, P. Eisner, Nutrients 2019, 11, 2117;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) H. Tizazu, S. A. Emire, Afr. J. Food Agric. Nutr. Dev. 2010, 10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>d) O. O. Olukomaiya, O. Q. Adiamo, W. C. Fernando, R. Mereddy, X. Li, Y. Sultanbawa, Food Chem. 2020, 315, 126238;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>e) H. E.‐S. Embaby, Food Sci. Biotechnol. 2010, 19, 1055.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. P. Hojilla‐Evangelista, D. J. Sessa, A. Mohamed, J. Am. Oil Chem. Soc. 2004, 81, 1153.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Mikić, V. Perić, V. Đorđević, M. Srebrić, V. Mihailović, Biotechnol. Anim. Husb. 2009, 25, 1181.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Adamidou, I. Nengas, K. Grigorakis, D. Nikolopoulou, K. Jauncey, Cereal Chem. 2011, 88, 80.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. S. do Carmo, P. Silventoinen‐Veijalainen, H. Zobel, U. Holopainen‐Mantila, S. Sahlstrøm, S. H. Knutsen, LWT – Food Sci. Technol. 2022, 163, 113509.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Sosulski, C. G. Youngs, J. Am. Oil Chem. Soc. 1979, 56, 292.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) S. A. Wani, P. Kumar, J. Food Technol. Res. 2014, 2, 124;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) H. Wang, L. A. Johnson, T. Wang, J. Am. Oil Chem. Soc. 2004, 81, 713.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. García Arteaga, S. Kraus, M. Schott, I. Muranyi, U. Schweiggert‐Weisz, P. Eisner, Foods 2021, 10, 758.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. M. Pedrosa, A. Varela, F. Domínguez‐Timón, C. A. Tovar, H. M. Moreno, A. J. Borderías, M. T. Díaz, Plant Foods Hum. Nutr. 2020, 75, 642.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. C. Karaca, N. Low, M. Nickerson, Food Res. Int. 2011, 44, 2742.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. De Angelis, A. Pasqualone, I. Allegretta, C. Porfido, R. Terzano, G. Squeo, C. Summo, Heliyon 2021, 7, e06177.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B.‐J. Gu, M. D. P. Masli, G. M. Ganjyal, J. Food Sci. 2020, 85, 404.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. B. Dhull, M. K. Kidwai, R. Noor, P. Chawla, P. K. Rose, Legume Sci. 2022, 4, e129.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Coda, M. Kianjam, E. Pontonio, M. Verni, R. Di Cagno, K. Katina, C. G. Rizzello, M. Gobbetti, Int. J. Food Microbiol. 2017, 248, 10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Coda, L. Melama, C. G. Rizzello, J. A. Curiel, J. Sibakov, U. Holopainen, M. Pulkkinen, N. Sozer, Int. J. Food Microbiol. 2015, 193, 34.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Vioque, M. Alaiz, J. Girón‐Calle, Food Chem. 2012, 132, 67.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>I.‐C. Mayer Labba, H. Frøkiær, A.‐S. Sandberg, Food Res. Int. 2021, 140, 110038.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) M. Schutyser, A. J. van der Goot, Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2011, 22, 154;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) O. B. Ocheme, O. E. Adedeji, C. E. Chinma, C. M. Yakubu, U. H. Ajibo, Food Sci. Nutr. 2018, 6, 1173.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Amin, I. L. Petersen, C. Malmberg, V. Orlien, ACS Food Sci. Technol. 2022, 2, 604.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Day, in Handbook of Food Proteins (Eds: G. O. Phillips, P. A. Williams), Elsevier, Amsterdam 2011, pp. 267–288.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Finnie, W. Atwell, Wheat Flour, AAC International, Minnesota, United States 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Létang, M.‐F. Samson, T.‐M. Lasserre, M. Chaurand, J. Abécassis, Cereal Chem. 2002, 79, 535.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. H. Azizah, H. Zainon, Malays. J. Nutr. 1997, 3, 131.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Ramulu, P. U. Rao, Plant Foods Hum. Nutr. 1997, 50, 249.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Silventoinen, K. Rommi, U. Holopainen‐Mantila, K. Poutanen, E. Nordlund, Food Bioprocess Technol. 2019, 12, 1487.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Amagliani, J. O'Regan, A. L. Kelly, J. A. O'Mahony, J. Food Compos. Anal. 2017, 59, 18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Gupta, G. K. Chandi, D. S. Sogi, Int. J. Food Eng. 2008, 4, 1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Bandyopadhyay, C. Chakraborty, A. K. Barman, J. Oleo Sci. 2012, 61, 525.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. K. Sharif, M. S. Butt, F. M. Anjum, S. H. Khan, Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2014, 54, 807.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. F. Shih, E. T. Champagne, K. Daigle, Z. Zarins, Food/Nahrung 1999, 43, 14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O. Laguna, A. Barakat, H. Alhamada, E. Durand, B. Baréa, F. Fine, P. Villeneuve, M. Citeau, S. Dauguet, J. Lecomte, Ind. Crops Prod. 2018, 118, 160.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Tanwar, A. Goyal, Oilseeds: Health Attributes and Food Applications, Springer, Berlin 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) F. M. Anjum, M. Nadeem, M. Issa Khan, S. Hussain, Br. Food J. 2012, 114, 544;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) O. Fagbenro, E. Adeparusi, W. Jimoh, Int. J. Chem. 2010, 20, 165.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Lannuzel, A. Smith, A. L. Mary, E. A. Della Pia, M. A. Kabel, S. de Vries, Anim. Feed Sci. Technol. 2022, 285, 115213.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. von der Haar, K. Müller, S. Bader‐Mittermaier, P. Eisner, Crops Lipids 2014, 21, D104.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Ivanova, H. Kalaydzhiev, T. Rustad, C. Silva, V. Chalova, Emir. J. Food Agric. 2017, 29, 170.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Kdidi, G. Vaca‐Medina, J. Peydecastaing, A. Oukarroum, N. Fayoud, A. Barakat, Powder Technol. 2019, 344, 10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) Y. Yoshie‐Stark, Y. Wada, A. Wäsche, Food Chem. 2008, 107, 32;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) V. J. Barthet, J. K. Daun, in: Canola: Chemistry, Production, Processing, and Utilization, Elsevier, Amsterdam 2011, pp. 119–162.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) T. G. Burger, I. Singh, C. Mayfield, J. L. Baumert, Y. Zhang, LWT – Food Sci. Technol. 2022, 153, 112495;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) Y. Zhang, M. Øverland, M. Sørensen, M. Penn, L. T. Mydland, K. D. Shearer, T. Storebakken, Aquaculture 2012, 344, 100.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) F. Keivaninahr, P. Gadkari, K. Z. Benis, M. Tulbek, S. Ghosh, RSC Adv. 2021, 11, 12117;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) C. Rempel, X. Geng, Y. Zhang, Food Chem. 2019, 276, 119.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) S. Protonotariou, A. Drakos, V. Evageliou, C. Ritzoulis, I. Mandala, J. Food Eng. 2014, 134, 24;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) P. Silventoinen, A. Kortekangas, D. Ercili‐Cura, E. Nordlund, Food Res. Int. 2021, 139, 109971;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) L. Day, M. A. Augustin, I. L. Batey, C. W. Wrigley, Trends Food Sci. Technol. 2006, 17, 82.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) S.‐W. Han, K.‐M. Chee, S.‐J. Cho, Food Chem. 2015, 172, 766;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) M. Esmaeili, A. Rafe, S.‐A. Shahidi, A. Ghorbani Hasan‐Saraei, Cereal Chem. 2016, 93, 58;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) S. Tang, N. S. Hettiarachchy, T. H. Shellhammer, J. Agric. Food Chem. 2002, 50, 7444.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) S. Vidosavljević, N. Bojanić, V. Stojkov, R. Čolović, O. Đuragić, A. Fišteš, V. Banjac, Food Feed Res. 2019, 46, 209;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) O. Orliac, F. Silvestre, A. Rouilly, L. Rigal, Ind. Eng. Chem. Res. 2003, 42, 1674;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) F. S. Taha, S. S. Mohamed, S. M. Wagdy, G. F. Mohamed, World Appl. Sci. J. 2013, 21, 651;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>d) M. A. Malik, C. S. Saini, Food Hydrocoll. 2017, 63, 705;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>e) P. R. Salgado, M. E. López‐Caballero, M. C. Gómez‐Guillén, A. N. Mauri, M. P. Montero, Food Hydrocoll. 2012, 29, 374;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>f) P. R. Salgado, S. E. Molina Ortiz, S. Petruccelli, A. N. Mauri, J. Am. Oil Chem. Soc. 2011, 88, 351;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>g) A. Barakat, F. Jérôme, X. Rouau, ChemSusChem 2015, 8, 1161.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) W. Jia, E. Rodriguez‐Alonso, M. Bianeis, J. K. Keppler, A. J. van der Goot, Innov. Food Sci. Emerg. Technol. 2021, 68, 102636;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) D. M. Klockeman, R. Toledo, K. A. Sims, J. Agric. Food Chem. 1997, 45, 3867;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) A. Gerzhova, M. Mondor, M. Benali, M. Aider, Food Biosci. 2015, 11, 56;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>d) C. Rempel, X. Li, X. Geng, Q. Liu, Y. Zhang, J. Sci. Food Agric. 2020, 100, 764.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Fleddermann, A. Fechner, A. Rößler, M. Bähr, A. Pastor, F. Liebert, G. Jahreis, Clin. Nutr. 2013, 32, 519.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. S. Hoefle, A. M. Bangert, A. Stamfort, K. Gedrich, M. J. Rist, Y.‐M. Lee, T. Skurk, H. Daniel, J. Nutr. 2015, 145, 467.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>I. W. K. Kouw, P. J. M. Pinckaers, C. L. Bourgot, J. M. X. van Kranenburg, A. H. Zorenc, L. C. de Groot, L. Verdijk, T. Snijders, L. J. C. van Loon, Br. J. Nutr. 2022, 128, 1955.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Kozior, R. W. Davies, M. Amigo‐Benavent, C. Fealy, P. M. Jakeman, Nutrients 2023, 15, 4211.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. J. M. Pinckaers, J. Domić, H. L. Petrick, A. M. Holwerda, J. Trommelen, F. K. Hendriks, L. H. P. Houben, J. P. B. Goessens, J. M. X. van Kranenburg, J. M. Senden, J. Nutr. 2023, 154, 2120.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Van Dam, A. Kardinaal, J. Troupin, A. Boulier, M. Hiolle, R. Wehrens, M. Mensink, Int. J. Food Sci. Nutr. 2023, 12, 1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Volk, C. Brandsch, U. Schlegelmilch, M. Wensch‐Dorendorf, F. Hirche, A. Simm, O. Gargum, C. Wiacek, P. G. Braun, J. F. Kopp, Nutrients 2020, 12, 2270.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>