<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39344983</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>30</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1526-4998</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>30</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Pest management science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Pest Manag Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Recent innovations in crop protection research.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/ps.8441</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>As the world's population continues to grow and demand for food increases, the agricultural industry faces the challenge of producing higher yields while ensuring the safety and quality of harvests, operators, and consumers. The emergence of resistance, pest shifts, and stricter regulatory requirements also urgently calls for further advances in crop protection and the discovery of new innovative products for sustainable crop protection. This study reviews recent highlights in innovation as presented at the 15th IUPAC International Congress of Crop Protection Chemistry held in New Delhi, in 2023. The following new products are discussed: the insecticides Indazapyroxamet, Dimpropyridaz and Fenmezoditiaz, the fungicides Mefentrifluconazole and Pyridachlomethyl, the nematicide Cyclobutrifluram, the herbicides Rimisoxafen, Dimesulfazet, and Epyrifenacil as well as the abiotic stress management product Anisiflupurin. In addition, the latest innovative research areas and discovery highlights in all areas of crop protection will be presented, including insecticidal alkyl sulfones and 1,3,4-trisubstituted pyrazoles, fungicidal picolinamides, herbicidal ketoenols, and trifluoromethylpyrazoles, as well as the latest advances in crop enhancement and green pest control research. © 2024 The Author(s). Pest Management Science published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Society of Chemical Industry.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Pest Management Science published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Society of Chemical Industry.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Maienfisch</LastName><ForeName>Peter</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8835-8792</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>CreInSol Consulting &amp; Biocontrols, Rodersdorf, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Koerber</LastName><ForeName>Karsten</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Global Research Crop Protection, BASF SE, Ludwigshafen, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>30</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Pest Manag Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100898744</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1526-498X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">crop enhancement</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">crop protection research</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">fungicides</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">green crop protection research</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">herbicides</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">insecticide</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">new innovations</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">recent discoveries</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39344983</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ps.8441</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Maienfisch P and Stevenson TM, Modern agribusiness‐markets, companies, benefits and challenges, in Discovery and Synthesis of Crop Protection Products. ACS Symposium Series 1204. ACS Publications, USA, pp. 1–13 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Godfray HC, Beddington JR, Crute IR, Haddad L, Lawrence D, Muir JF et al., Food security: the challenge of feeding 9 billion people. Science 327:812–818 (2010).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FSIN, 2020 Global Report on Food Crises (2020). Weblink: https://www.fsinplatform.org/global-report-food-crises-2020. Accessed May 2025.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sparks TC and Lorsbach BA, Perspectives on the agrochemical industry and agrochemical discovery. Pest Manag Sci 73:672–677 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oerke EC, Crop losses to pests. J Agric Sci 144:31–43 (2006).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oerke EC and Dehne HW, Safeguarding production – losses in major crops and the role of crop protection. Crop Prot 23:275–285 (2004).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sparks TC and Bryant RJ, Crop protection compounds – trends and perspective. Pest Manag Sci 77:3608–3616 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crop Life International. https://croplife.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/Time-and-Cost-To-Market-CP-2024.pdf, 2024. Accessed May 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maienfisch P and Mangelinckx IS, Recent innovation in crop protection research, in Recent Highlights in the Discovery and Optimization of Crop Protection Products, ed. by Maienfisch P and Mangelinckx IS. Academic Press, London, pp. 1–23 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maienfisch P and Mangelinckx IS, Recent innovation in crop protection research, in Recent Highlights in the Discovery and Optimization of Crop Protection Products. Academic Press, London, pp. 1–619 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maienfisch P and Stevenson TM, Discovery and Synthesis of Crop Protection Products (ACS Symposium, 1204, Band 1204), pp, 1–454 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barber DM, Jackson VE and Ling KB, Innovations in crop protection towards sustainable agriculture. Pest Manag Sci 79:4754–4756 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Umetsu N and Shirai Y, Development of novel pesticides in the 21st century. J Pestic Sci 45:54–74 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shelton KA and Lahm GP, Building a successful crop protection pipeline: molecular starting points for discovery, in Discovery and Synthesis of Crop Protection Products, Vol. 1204, ed. by Maienfisch P and Stevenson TM. ACS Symposium Series, Washington, pp. 15–23 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corsi C and Lamberth C, New paradigms in crop protection research: registrability and cost of goods, in Discovery and Synthesis of Crop Protection Products, Vol. 1204, ed. by Maienfisch P and Stevenson TM. ACS Symposium Series, Washington, pp. 25–37 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sakamoto N, Pesticide invention model in a Japanese company, in Discovery and Synthesis of Crop Protection Products, Vol. 1204, ed. by Maienfisch P and Stevenson TM. ACS Symposium Series, Washington, pp. 39–53 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loso MR, Garizi N, Hegde VB, Hunter JE and Sparks TC, Lead generation in crop protection research: a portfolio approach to agrochemical discovery. Pest Manag Sci 73:678–685 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duke SO, Pan Z, Bajsa‐Hirschel J, Tamang P, Hammerschmidt R, Lorsbach BA et al., Molecular targets of herbicides and fungicides ‐ are there useful overlaps for fungicide discovery? J Agric Food Chem 71:20532–20548 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sparks TC and Lorsbac BA, Insecticide discovery‐"chance favors the prepared mind". Pestic Biochem Physiol 192:105412 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sparks TC, Sparks JM and Duke SO, Natural product‐based crop protection compounds‐origins and future prospects. J Agric Food Chem 71:2259–2269 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sparks TC and Bryant RJ, Innovation in insecticide discovery: approaches to the discovery of new classes of insecticides. Pest Manag Sci 78:3226–3247 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sparks TC and Bryant RJ, Impact of natural products on discovery of, and innovation in, crop protection compounds. Pest Manag Sci 78:399–408 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Djoumbou‐Feunang Y, Wilmot J, Kinney J, Chanda P, Yu P, Sader A et al., Cheminformatics and artificial intelligence for accelerating agrochemical discovery. Front Chem 11:1292027 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mei LC, Chen HM, Dong AY, Huang GY, Liu YW, Zhang X et al., Pesticide informatics platform (PIP): an international platform for pesticide discovery, residue, and risk evaluation. J Agric Food Chem 70:6617–6623 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeschke P, Status and outlook for acaricide and insecticide discovery. Pest Manag Sci 77:64–76 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dayan FE, Current status and future prospects in herbicide discovery. Plants 8:341 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marrone PG, Status and potential of bioprotection products for crop protection, in Recent Highlights in the Discovery and Optimization of Crop Protection Products, ed. by Maienfisch P and Mangelinckx IS. Academic Press, London, pp. 25–38 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loiseleur O, Natural products in the discovery of agrochemicals. Chimia 71:810–822 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Preininger C, Sauer U, Bejarano A and Berninger T, Concepts and applications of foliar spray for microbial inoculants. Appl Microbiol Biotechnol 102:7265–7282 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Warrior P, Living systems as natural crop‐protection agents. Pest Manag Sci 56:681–687 (2000).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du Jardin P, Plant biostimulants: definition, concept, main categories and regulation. Sci Hortic 196:3–14 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lacey LA, Grzywacz D, Shapiro‐Ilan DI, Frutos R, Brownbridge M and Goettel MS, Insect pathogens as biological control agents: Back to the future. J Invertebr Pathol 132:1–41 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lahlali R, Ezrari S, Radouane N, Kenfaoui J, Esmaeel Q, El Hamss H et al., Biological control of plant pathogens: a global perspective. Microorganisms 10:596 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bramlett M, Plaetinck G and Maienfisch P, RNA‐based biocontrols—a new paradigm in crop protection. Engineering 6:522–527 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hough J, Howard J, Brown S, Portwood DE, Kilby PM and Dickman MJ, Strategies for the production of dsRNA biocontrols as alternatives to chemical pesticides. Front Bioeng Biotechnol 10:980592 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang YM, De‐Xing YDX, Liu Y, Zhang XY, Zhou YL, Zhang L et al., Peptides, new tools for plant protection in eco‐agriculture. Adv Agrochem 2:58–78 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corsi C, Accelerated innovation provides new game‐changing tools for farmers Weblink: https://www.syngenta.com/en/innovation-agriculture/our-stories/accelerated-innovation-provides-new-game-changing-tools-farmers. Accessed: May 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cassayre J, Crop protection chemistry: innovation with purpose. Chimia 75:561–563 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown N, Bioisosteres and scaffold hopping in medicinal chemistry. Mol Inform 33:458–462 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koyanagi T and Haga T, Bioisosterism in agrochemicals, in Synthesis and Chemistry of Agrochemicals IV, Vol. 584, Chapter 2, ed. by Baker DR, Fenyes JG and Basarab GS. American Chemical Society (ACS), Washington, D.C, pp. 15–24 (1995; ACS Symposium Series). https://doi.org/10.1021/bk-1995-0584.ch002.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lamberth C, Agrochemical lead optimization by scaffold hopping. Pest Manag Sci 74:282–292 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Langdon SR, Ertl P and Brown N, Bioisosteric replacement and scaffold hopping in lead generation and optimization. Mol Inf 29:366–385 (2010).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lima LM and Barreiro EJ, Bioisosterism: a useful strategy for molecular modification and drug design. Curr Med Chem 12:23–49 (2005).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meanwell NA, Synopsis of some recent tactical application of bioisosteres in drug design. J Med Chem 54:2529–2591 (2011).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meanwell NA, The influence of bioisosteres in drug design: tactical applications to address developability problems, in Tactics in Contemporary Drug Design, Vol. 9, ed. by Meanwell NA. Springer, Berlin, Germany, pp. 283–381 (2013). https://doi.org/10.1007/7355_2013_29.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maienfisch P and Lamberth C, Introduction to bioisosteric replacement and scaffold hopping in crop protection research. J Agric Food Chem 70:10941 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maienfisch P and Lamberth C, Introduction to recent highlights in bioisosteric replacements and scaffold hopping in crop protection research. J Agric Food Chem 71:18169–18170 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou C, Cheng J, Beadle R, Earley FG, Li Z and Maienfisch P, Design, synthesis and acaricidal activities of Cyflumetofen analogues based on carbon‐silicon isosteric replacement. Bioorg Med Chem 28:115509 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen M, Li Z, Shao X and Maienfisch P, Scaffold‐hopping approach to identify new chemotypes of Dimpropyridaz. J Agric Food Chem 70:11109–11122 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao X, Yang H, Liu C, Zhang R, Maienfisch P and Xu X, Bioisosterism and scaffold hopping in modern nematicide research. J Agric Food Chem 70:11042–11055 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen M, Li Z, Shao X and Maienfisch P, Bioisosteric‐replacement‐driven lead optimization of tyclopyrazoflor. J Agric Food Chem 70:11123–11137 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou C, Sun X, Fu W, Li Z, Cheng J and Maienfisch P, Rational exploration of novel SDHI fungicide through an amide‐β‐ketonitrile bioisosteric replacement strategy. J Agric Food Chem 71:5483–5495 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quan X, Xu L, Li Z and Maienfisch P, Design, synthesis, and properties of silicon‐containing meta‐diamide insecticides. J Agric Food Chem 71:18188–18196 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu L, Quan X, Li Z and Maienfisch P, Synthesis and biological activity of silicon‐containing Ethylsulfonylpyridine insecticides. J Agric Food Chem 71:18250–18259 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou C, Li Z, Qian X, Cheng J and Maienfisch P, Novel acaricidal silico‐containing pyrazolyl acrylonitrile derivatives identified through rational carbon‐silicon bioisosteric replacement strategy. J Agric Food Chem 71:18239–18249 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>15th IUPAC, International Congress of Crop Protection Chemistry Webpage: https://www.iupac2023.in/. Accessed: May 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spalthoff C, Salgado VL, Balu N, David MD, Hehlert P, Huang H et al., The novel pyridazine pyrazolecarboxamide insecticide dimpropyridaz inhibits chordotonal organ function upstream of TRPV channels. Pest Manag Sci 79:1635–1649 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goodchild J, Chen YJ, Blythe J, Firth LC, Hirst E, Bess K et al., A novel class of insecticidal alkylsulfones are potent inhibitors of vesicular acetylcholine transport. Pestic Biochem Physiol 201:105854 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sluder A, Shah S, Cassayre J, Clover R, Maienfisch P, Molleyres LP et al., Spiroindolines identify the vesicular acetylcholine transporter as a novel target for insecticide action. PLoS One 7:e34712 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clark DA, Fraga BG and Zhang W, PCT International Application WO2015038503 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Insecticide Resistance Action Committee, Mode of Action Classification https://irac-online.org/mode-of-action/classification-online/ accessed January 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nesterov A, Spalthoff C, Kandasamy R, Katana R, Ranki NB, Andrés M et al., TRP channels in insect stretch receptors as insecticide targets. Neuron 86:665–671 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spalthoff C, Salgado VL, Theis M, Geurten BRH and Gopfert MC, Flonicamid metabolite 4‐trifluoromethylnicotinamide is a chordotonal organ modulator insecticide. Pest Manag Sci 78:4802–4808 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kandasamy R, Costea PI, Stam L and Nesterov A, TRPV channel nanchung and TRPA channel water witch form insecticide‐activated complexes. Insect Biochem Mol Biol 149:103835 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng YX, Liu ZY, Lin PX, Su SC, Gao CF and Wu SF, Reverse genetic study reveals the molecular targets of chordotonal organ TRPV channel modulators. Pestic Biochem Physiol 196:105584 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang LX, Niu CD, Salgado VL, Lelito K, Stam L, Jia YL et al., Pymetrozine activates TRPV channels of brown planthopper Nilaparvata lugens. Pestic Biochem Physiol 153:77–86 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu X, Zheng C, Liu T and Liang P, Identification of amino acid residues that are crucial for afidopyropen binding to the TRPV channel of Myzus persicae (Sulzer). Int J Biol Macromol 260:129644 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stoller A, Jeanguenat A, Edmunds AE, Jung PJ, Muehlebach M and Renold P, PCT International Application WO2016005263, Syngenta Crop Protection AG (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takyo H, Takahashi M, Tanabe T, Nokura Y and Ito M, PCT International Application WO2012086848. Sumitomo Chemical Co., Ltd, (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ito M, Nokura, Takahashi M, Yamada H and Iwata I, Discovery of oxazosulfyl: a novel broad‐spectrum insecticide, in Recent Highlights in the Discovery and Optimization of Crop Protection Products, ed. by Maienfisch P and Mangelinckx IS. Academic Press, London, pp. 261–268 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamezaki M, Otsuki J and Natsuhara K, Insecticidal activity against rice pest of oxazosulfyl, a novel sulfyl insecticide. J. Pesticide Science (Tokyo, Japan) 49:31–37 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mulder R, Wellinga K, Van Daalen JJ et al., A new class of insecticides. Naturwissenschaften 62:531–532 (1975).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCann SF, Annis GD, Shapiro R, Piotrowski DW, Lahm GP, Long JK et al., The discovery of indoxacarb: oxadiazines as a new class of pyrazoline‐type insecticides. Pest Manag Sci 57:153–164 (2001).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wellinga K, Grosscurt AC and Van Hes RJ, Phenylcarbamoyl‐2‐Pyrazolines: A New Class of Insecticidal. Synthesis and Insecticital Properties of 3‐Phenyl‐1‐Phenidesylcarbamoyl‐2‐Pyrazolines. Agric Food Chem 25:987–992 (1977).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amad OK and Pahutski TF, PCT International Application WO2015077436, 2015, DuPont (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pahutski TF, Lahm GP, Kar M and Ahmad OK, CT International Application WO2013063282, 2013, DuPont (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agbio Crop, The Crop Protection Industry Report – Products, December 2023, AgbioInvestor https://agbioinvestor.com/agbiocrop-agrochemical-market-intelligence/ (accessed May 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dickhaut J, Adisechan A, Datta GK, Kuzmina O and Langewald J, PCT International Application WO2018177970 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang W, Mesoionic pyrido[1,2‐a]pyrimidinone insecticides: from discovery to Triflumezopyrim and Dicloromezotiaz. Acc Chem Res 50:2381–2388 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CWJr H, Cordova D, Zhang W, Barry JD, Leighty RM, Dietrich RF et al., Mesoionic insecticides: a novel class of insecticides that modulate nicotinic acetylcholine receptors. Pest Manag Sci 73:796–806 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang W, Holyoke CW Jr, Barry J, Cordova D, Leighty RM, Tong MHT et al., Mesoionic pyrido[1,2‐a]pyrimidinones: discovery of dicloromezotiaz as a lepidoptera insecticide acting on nicotinic acetylcholine receptors. Bioorg Med Chem Lett 27:911–917 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang W, Lahm GP, Pahutski TF and Hughes KA, Applying bioisosteric replacement strategy in the discovery and optimization of Mesoionic pyrido[1,2‐a]pyrimidinone insecticides: a review. J Agric Food Chem 70:11056–11062 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maienfisch P and Edmunds AJF, Thiazole and isothiazole ring‐containing compounds in crop protection. Adv Heterocycl Chem 121:35–88 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Montgomery M, Rendine S, Zimmer CT, Elias J, Schaetzer J, Pitterna T et al., Structural biology‐guided design, synthesis, and biological evaluation of novel insect nicotinic acetylcholine receptor Orthosteric modulators. J Med Chem 65:2297–2312 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Z, Li QX and Song B, Recent research progress in and perspectives of mesoionic insecticides: nicotinic acetylcholine receptor inhibitors. J Agric Food Chem 68:11039–11053 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fungicide Resistance Action Committee. Webpage: https://www.frac.info/, accessed May 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoffmeister M, Zito R, Boehm J and Stammler G, Mutations in Cyp51 of Venturia inaequalis and their effects on DMI sensitivity. J Plant Dis Prot 128:1467–1478 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song H, Wang S, Cai Q and Chen J, Research progress of triazole derivatives in the discovery of agricultural chemicals. J Heterocyclic Chem 61:365–386 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matsuzaki Y, Watanabe S, Harada T and Iwahashi F, Pyridachlometyl has a novel anti‐tubulin mode of action which could be useful in anti‐resistance management. Pest Manag Sci 76:1393–1401 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steinmetz MO and Prota AE, Structure‐based discovery and rational design of microtubule‐targeting agents. Curr Opin Struct Biol 87:102845 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Owen WJ, Yao C, Myung K, Kemmitt G, Leader A, Meyer K et al., Biological characterization of fenpicoxamid, a new fungicide with utility in cereals and other crops. Pest Manag Sci 73:2005–2016 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Owen WJ, Meyer KG, Meyer ST, Li F, Slanec TJ, Wang NX et al., Synthesis and biological activity of analogs of the antifungal antibiotic UK‐2A. II. Impact of modifications to the macrocycle benzyl position. Pest Manag Sci 75:1831–1846 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Owen WJ, Meyer K, Slanec TJ, Meyer ST, Wang NX, Fitzpatrick GM et al., Synthesis and biological activity of analogs of the antifungal antibiotic UK‐2A. III. Impact of modifications to the macrocycle isobutyryl ester position. Pest Manag Sci 76:277–286 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng H, Yang L, Liu HF, Zhang R, Chen C, Wu Y et al., N‐(4‐(2‐chloro‐4‐(trifluoromethyl)phenoxy)phenyl)picolinamide as a new inhibitor of mitochondrial complex III: synthesis, biological evaluation and computational simulations. Bioorg Med Chem Lett 30:127302 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yao C, Meyer KG, Gallup C, Bowling AJ, Hufnagl A, Myung K et al., Florylpicoxamid, a new picolinamide fungicide with broad spectrum activity. Pest Manag Sci 77:4483–4496 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackson V, Jordan L, Burgin RN, McGaw OJS, Muir CW and Ceban V, Application of molecular‐modeling, scaffold‐hopping, and bioisosteric approaches to the discovery of new heterocyclic picolinamides. J Agric Food Chem 70:11031–11041 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackson VE and Maienfisch P, Picolinamide complex III inhibitors: A review of quinone inside inhibitors and the importance of bioisosteric principles in the discoveries of these new fungicides, in Abstracts of Papers, No. 3739571. ACS Fall 2022, Chicago, IL, United States (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nicol JM, Turner SJ, Coyne DL, Nijs L, Hockland S and Maafi ZT, Current nematode threats to world agriculture, in Genomics and Molecular Genetics of Plant‐Nematode Interactions, ed. by Jones J, Gheysen G and Fenoll C. Springer, S Dordrecht (NL), pp. 21–43 (2011).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>IRAC nematodes resistance. https://irac-online.org/irac-nematicide-moa-classification-now-available/) (accessed May 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sparks TC, Crossthwaite AJ, Nauen R, Banba S, Cordova D, Earley F et al., Insecticides, biologics and nematicides: updates to IRAC's mode of action classification ‐ a tool for resistance management. Pestic Biochem Physiol 167:104587 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CropLife Australia. https://Croplife.org.au/wp-content/uploads/2023/07/2023-UPDATES_InsecticideRMS_Wide-nematodes.pdf. 2023. (accessed March 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loiseleur O, Slaats B and Maienfisch P, Nematicides, in Modern Crop Protection Compounds, Vol. 3, 3rd edn, ed. by Jeschke P, Witschel M, Krämer W and Schirmer U. Wiley, New Jersey, pp. 1585–1653 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O'Sullivan AC, Loiseleur O, Staiger R, Luksch T and Pitterna T, Preparation of N‐cyclylamides as nematicides. PCT International Application WO2013143811 A1 2013‐10‐03 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Tang Y, Xue Z, Wang Y, Shi Y, Gao X et al., Resistance risk and resistance‐related point mutation in SdhB and SdhC1of Cyclobutrifluram inFusarium pseudograminearum. J Agric Food Chem 71:1886–1895 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Long JK, Kar M, Riga E, Cordova D and Varanyak L, Novel triazolones as nematicides, in Abstracts of Papers, ACS Fall 2023. AGRO division of the American Chemical Society, San Francisco, CA, United States (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kar M and Long JK, PCT International Application WO2022026511. FMC, (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaines TA, Busi R and Kuepper A, Can new herbicide discovery allow weed management to outpace resistance evolution? Pest Manag Sci 77:3036–3041 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duke SO and Dayan FE, The search for new herbicide mechanisms of action: is there a'holy grail'? Pest Manag Sci 78:1303–1313 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qu RY, Bo H, Yang JF, Lin HY, Yang WC, Wu QY et al., Where are the new herbicides? Pest Manag Sci 77:2620–2625 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deprez NR, Reddy RP, Sharpe PL and Stevenson TM, PCT International Application WO2015108779. FMC, (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stevenson TM, Reddy R, Sharpe P, Deprez NR and Chittaboina S, Investigating the C‐H functionalization of aryl azoles: discovery of a new class of herbicides, in Abstracts of Papers, ACS Fall 2023. AGRO division of the American Chemical Society, San Francisco, CA, United States (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lichtenthaler HK, Mode of action of herbicides affecting acetyl‐CoA carboxylase and fatty acid biosynthesis. Zeitschrift fuer Naturforschung C 45:521–528 (1990).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muehlebach M, Brunner HG, Cederbaum F, Maetzke T, Mutti R, Schnyder A et al., Pesticide Chemistry in Crop Protection, Public Health, Environmental Safety, ed. by Hideo Ohkawa, Hisashi Miyagawa, Philip W. Lee, pp. 101–110 (2007).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fischer R, Bretschneider T, Lehr S, Franken EM, Malsam O, Voerste A et al., PCT International Application WO2010102758. Bayer, (2010).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kudou T, Tanima D, Masuzawa Y and Yano T, European Patent Application EP2336104, Nissan (2011).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food Safety Commission, Cabinet office. Gov Jpn Food Saf 11:36–39 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wanga Q, Songa HQ and Wanga Q, Fluorine‐containing agrochemicals in the last decade and approaches for fluorine incorporation. Chin Chem Lett 33:626–642 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sakurai K, Abe J, Hirasawa K, Takeuchi H and Kitamoto S, Absorption, distribution, metabolism, and excretion of a new herbicide, Epyrifenacil, in rats. J Agric Food Chem 69:13190–13199 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mattison LR, Beffa R, Bojack G, Bollenbach‐Wahl B, Doernbrack C, Dorn N et al., Frackenpohl. J Pest Manag Sci 79:2264–2280 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen L, Zhao J, Song J and Jameson PE, Cytokinin dehydrogenase: a genetic target for yield improvement in wheat. Plant Biotechnol J 18:614–630 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kon KF, Camblin P, Leipner J, Schmitt N and Thayumanavan AB, PCT International Application WO2017216003 A1 2017‐12‐21. Syngenta, (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kon KF, Leipner J, Schmitt N and Thayumanavan AB, PCT International Application WO2017216005 A1 2017‐12‐21. Syngenta, (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zatloukal M, Gemrotova M, Dolezal K, Havlicek L, Spichal L and Strnad M, Novel potent inhibitors of A. thaliana cytokinin oxidase/dehydrogenase. Bioorg Med Chem 16:9268–9275 (2008).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kudo T, Makita N, Kojima M, Tokunaga H and Sakakibara H, Cytokinin activity of cis‐zeatin and phenotypic alterations induced by overexpression of Putative cis‐Zeatin‐O‐glucosyltransferase in rice. Plant Physiol 160:319–331 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koprna R, De Diego N, Dundálková L and Spíchal L, Use of cytokinins as agrochemicals. Bioorg Med Chem 24:484–492 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burges HD ed, Formulation of Microbial Biopesticides: Beneficial Microorganisms, Nematodes and Seed Treatments. Springer Science &amp; Business Media, Heidelberg, Germany (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang J, Khan SA, Heckel DG and Bock R, Next‐generation insect‐resistant plants: RNAi‐mediated crop protection. Trends Biotechnol 35:871–882 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dubelman S, Fischer J, Zapata F, Huizinga K, Jiang C, Uffman J et al., Environmental fate of double‐stranded RNA in agricultural soils. PLoS One 9:e93155 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang C, Kovacs JM and Flores‐Verdugo F, The application of drone technology in the mapping and monitoring of wetland ecosystems: a review. Wetlands 38:829–842 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao C, The future of CRISPR technologies in agriculture. Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol 19:275–276 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barrangou R, CRISPR crops and sustainable agriculture. CRISPR J 6:1 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vega FE, Goettel MS, Blackwell M, Chandler D, Jackson MA, Keller S et al., Fungal entomopathogens: new insights on their ecology. Fungal Ecol 2:149–159 (2009).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Witzgall P, Kirsch P and Cork A, Sex pheromones and their impact on pest management. J Chem Ecol 36:80–100 (2010).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhagat D, Samanta SK and Bhattacharya S, Efficient management of fruit pests by pheromone nanogels. Sci Rep 3:1294 (2013).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>