<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39342780</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1618-095X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>135</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>19</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Phytomedicine : international journal of phytotherapy and phytopharmacology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Phytomedicine</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Dioscin improves fatty liver hemorrhagic syndrome by promoting ERα-AMPK mediated mitophagy in laying hens.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>156056</StartPage><MedlinePgn>156056</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.phymed.2024.156056</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0944-7113(24)00713-X</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Mitochondria play a crucial role in upholding metabolic homeostasis. Mitochondrial damage closely associated with the pathogenesis of fatty liver hemorrhagic syndrome (FLHS), while mitophagy being among the most effective methods for eliminating the damaged mitochondria. Dioscin, a natural extract, can activate autophagy; however, its effects on FLHS regarding mitophagy regulation remain unelucidated.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="PURPOSE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">We explored the impact of dioscin on FLHS induced by a high-energy and low-protein (HELP) diet in laying hens, mainly focused the protective effects of dioscin on mitochondrial injury.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHOD" NlmCategory="METHODS">To investigate the impact of dioscin on fatty liver syndrome in laying hens, we first induced the condition by feeding them a high-energy and low-protein diet. Then, we assessed lipid metabolism-related markers using oil red staining and a commercial detection kit. In addition, the role of dioscin on fatty liver syndrome in laying hens was confirmed by assessing the activation of hepatocyte fat deposition and hepatocyte apoptosis; and the mechanism of dioscin in FLHS was investigated through LMH cell experiment in vitro. Furthermore, CETSA and molecular docking were conducted for additional confirmation.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULT" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The results showed that dioscin alleviated mitochondrial damage, relieved the excessive deposition of hepatic lipid droplets and oxidative stress induced by HELP diet in laying hens. Furthermore, dioscin regulated the mitophagy by activating the estrogen receptor α (ERα)/adenosine 5'-monophosphate-activated protein kinase (AMPK) signaling pathway, thus mitigating mitochondria injury and apoptosis in hepatocytes. In addition, we found that dioscin promoted the translocation of nuclear transcription factor into nucleus by activating ERα-AMPK signaling, facilitating autophagic flux in the liver of laying hens and LMH cells. Furthermore, cells pretreated with the lysosomal acidification inhibitor bafilomycin A1 blocked the inhibitory effect of dioscin on the apoptosis induced by palmitic acid (PA)-stimulation in LMH cells, suggesting that dioscin reduces PA-induced apoptosis by activating mitophagy. Moreover, dioscin-induced lysosomal acidification and mitochondrial biogenesis were reversed in PA-induced LMH cells pretreated with ERα-specific inhibitor methylpiperidino pyrazole.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">This study firstly demonstrated that dioscin alleviates fatty liver syndrome induced by HELP diet in laying hens. The findings from this study illustrated that dioscin plays a significant role in reducing mitochondrial damage and apoptosis, and these beneficial effects mainly achieve through promotion of ERα-AMPK signaling, which mediates autophagy within the liver of laying hens fed a HELP-diets. These findings provide a theoretical basis for considering dioscin as a possible treatment option for mitigating FLHS in egg-laying hens.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024. Published by Elsevier GmbH.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xing</LastName><ForeName>Yuxiao</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Animal Physiology and Biochemistry, College of Veterinary Medicine, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing 210095, China; MOE Joint International Research Laboratory of Animal Health and Food Safety, College of Veterinary Medicine, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing 210095, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huang</LastName><ForeName>Benzeng</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Animal Physiology and Biochemistry, College of Veterinary Medicine, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing 210095, China; MOE Joint International Research Laboratory of Animal Health and Food Safety, College of Veterinary Medicine, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing 210095, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cui</LastName><ForeName>Ziyi</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Animal Physiology and Biochemistry, College of Veterinary Medicine, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing 210095, China; MOE Joint International Research Laboratory of Animal Health and Food Safety, College of Veterinary Medicine, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing 210095, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Quanwei</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Animal Physiology and Biochemistry, College of Veterinary Medicine, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing 210095, China; MOE Joint International Research Laboratory of Animal Health and Food Safety, College of Veterinary Medicine, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing 210095, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ma</LastName><ForeName>Haitian</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Animal Physiology and Biochemistry, College of Veterinary Medicine, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing 210095, China; MOE Joint International Research Laboratory of Animal Health and Food Safety, College of Veterinary Medicine, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing 210095, China. Electronic address: mahaitian@njau.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>19</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Phytomedicine</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9438794</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0944-7113</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Dioscin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Fatty liver hemorrhagic syndrome</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mitochondria injury</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mitochondrial apoptotic pathway</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mitophagy</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare the following financial interests/personal relationships which may be considered as potential competing interests: Haitian Ma reports financial support was provided by Nanjing Agricultural University College of Veterinary Medicine. Yuxiao Xing, Ziyi Cui, Benzeng Huang, Quanwei Zhang, Haitian Ma reports a relationship with Nanjing Agricultural University College of Veterinary Medicine that includes: employment. If there are other authors, they declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39342780</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.phymed.2024.156056</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0944-7113(24)00713-X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>