<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39348765</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>30</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1873-7072</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>463</Volume><Issue>Pt 4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>25</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Food chemistry</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Food Chem</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Authentication of edible herbal materials and food products using mass spectrometry based metabolites and inorganic constituents.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>141424</StartPage><MedlinePgn>141424</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.foodchem.2024.141424</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0308-8146(24)03074-7</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Medicinal food homologous (MFH) substances not only provide nutrition but also serve as a traditional means to overcome many health issues. Authentication of these products verifies their efficacity and assures consumers of a genuine product. In this review paper, we focus the determination of MFH authenticity including geographical identification and adulteration detection using mass spectrometry (liquid and gas chromatography) based metabolites and inorganic constituents (muti-elements and stable isotopes). The application of these techniques to determine product identification characteristics combined with chemometrics are discussed, along with the limitations of these techniques. Multi-elements, stable isotopes, and metabolite analysis are shown to provide an effective combination of techniques to resolve the origin of various MFH products. Most organic compounds from MFH products are identified using chromatographic separation techniques (HPLC, GC) combined with different detection methods. Chemometric analysis of organic and inorganic fingerprints offers a robust method to detect and classify mislabeled and suspected fraudulent samples of different MFH products.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024. Published by Elsevier Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wadood</LastName><ForeName>Syed Abdul</ForeName><Initials>SA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory for Managing Biotic and Chemical Threats to the Quality and Safety of Agro-products; Institute of Agro-Products Safety and Nutrition, Zhejiang Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Hangzhou 310021, China; Key Laboratory of Information Traceability for Agricultural Products, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs of China, Hangzhou 310021, China; Department of Food Science, University of Home Economics Lahore, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nie</LastName><ForeName>Jing</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory for Managing Biotic and Chemical Threats to the Quality and Safety of Agro-products; Institute of Agro-Products Safety and Nutrition, Zhejiang Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Hangzhou 310021, China; Key Laboratory of Information Traceability for Agricultural Products, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs of China, Hangzhou 310021, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Song</LastName><ForeName>Yan</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Center for Plants and Human Health, Institute of Urban Agriculture, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Chengdu 610213, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Chunlin</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory for Managing Biotic and Chemical Threats to the Quality and Safety of Agro-products; Institute of Agro-Products Safety and Nutrition, Zhejiang Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Hangzhou 310021, China; Key Laboratory of Information Traceability for Agricultural Products, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs of China, Hangzhou 310021, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rogers</LastName><ForeName>Karyne M</ForeName><Initials>KM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Information Traceability for Agricultural Products, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs of China, Hangzhou 310021, China; National Isotope Centre, GNS Science, 30 Gracefield Road, Lower Hutt 5040, New Zealand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khan</LastName><ForeName>Wahab Ali</ForeName><Initials>WA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science, University of Home Economics Lahore, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khan</LastName><ForeName>Abbas</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science, University of Home Economics Lahore, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xiao</LastName><ForeName>Jianbo</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Departement of Analytical Chemistry and Food Science, Faculty of Food Science and Technology, University of Vigo, 36310 Vigo, Spain.. Electronic address: jianboxiao@yahoo.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Hongyan</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Center for Plants and Human Health, Institute of Urban Agriculture, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Chengdu 610213, China. Electronic address: liuhongyan01@caas.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yuan</LastName><ForeName>Yuwei</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory for Managing Biotic and Chemical Threats to the Quality and Safety of Agro-products; Institute of Agro-Products Safety and Nutrition, Zhejiang Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Hangzhou 310021, China; Key Laboratory of Information Traceability for Agricultural Products, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs of China, Hangzhou 310021, China. Electronic address: ywytea@163.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Food Chem</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7702639</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0308-8146</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Adulteration</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Food fraud</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Geographical authentication</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Medicinal food homologous products</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Metabolites</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Stable isotopes</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39348765</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2024.141424</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0308-8146(24)03074-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>