<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39342672</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1873-3573</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>282</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>27</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Talanta</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Talanta</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Preparation and application of achiral UiO-66-NH<sub>2</sub> MOFs for enantioselective fluorescent detection of lysine enantiomers.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>126972</StartPage><MedlinePgn>126972</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.talanta.2024.126972</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0039-9140(24)01351-1</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Lysine (Lys) is an essential nutrient that plays a crucial role in the growth and development of living organisms. Chiral analysis of Lys holds significant importance for ensuring the safety of food, pharmaceuticals, and health products. In this work, an achiral Zr-based metal organic frameworks (MOFs), UiO-66-NH<sub>2</sub>, was proposed as a fluorescent probe to achieve rapid response to l-lysine (L-Lys) in solution. Additionally, Zr<sup>4+</sup> in the skeleton of UiO-66-NH<sub>2</sub> framework exhibited different binding capacities towards Lys enantiomers, leading to distinct fluorescence responses for L-Lys and d-lysine (D-Lys). Leveraging these properties, the UiO-66-NH<sub>2</sub> probe enabled accurate determination of L-Lys concentrations in solution, as well as the enantiomeric excess (ee) values of Lys solutions. Notably, in the detection of Lys enantiomers, the achiral UiO-66-NH<sub>2</sub> acted as both a chiral selector and a fluorescent indicator, greatly improving the efficiency and stability of the detection system. The probable mechanism was further elucidated by pH titration experiments and density functional theory calculations. Additionally, the general applicability of this mechanism was validated by similar amino MOFs. The application of the UiO-66-NH<sub>2</sub> fluorescent probe in analysis of infant formula milk powders and liquid milk samples confirmed the reliability of the method. Moreover, the construction of fluorescence test paper by immobilizing UiO-66-NH<sub>2</sub> onto filler papers enabled the rapid identification of Lys enantiomers. Compared to previous fluorescent analyses of chiral amino acids assisted by additional metal ions, this study presented a novel approach and methodology that offers high efficiency, stability, reproducibility and reusability for the identification and detection of Lys enantiomers, highlighting the potential of the UiO-66-NH<sub>2</sub> fluorescent probe in advancing analytical techniques.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Guo</LastName><ForeName>Dandan</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Drug Discovery Technology, Ningbo University, Ningbo, 315211, China. Electronic address: guodandan@nbu.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zheng</LastName><ForeName>Diya</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Drug Discovery Technology, Ningbo University, Ningbo, 315211, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Ding</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Ningbo College of Health Sciences, Ningbo, 315000, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tong</LastName><ForeName>Changlun</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Environmental Remediation and Ecological Health, Ministry of Education, College of Environmental and Resource Sciences, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, 310058, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huang</LastName><ForeName>Shaohua</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Drug Discovery Technology, Ningbo University, Ningbo, 315211, China; Qian Xuesen Collaborative Research Center of Astrochemistry and Space Life Sciences, Ningbo University, Ningbo, 315211, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Talanta</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>2984816R</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0039-9140</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Enantioselectivity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Fluorescent detection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Lysine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mechanism</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">UiO-66-NH(2)</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>59</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>59</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>17</Hour><Minute>59</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39342672</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.talanta.2024.126972</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0039-9140(24)01351-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>