<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39349972</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>30</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1750-3841</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>30</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of food science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Food Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A self-powered photoelectrochemical aptasensor using 3D-carbon nitride and carbon-based metal-organic frameworks for high-sensitivity detection of tetracycline in milk and water.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1750-3841.17398</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Antibiotic residues have become a significant challenge in food safety, threatening both ecosystem integrity and human health. To combat this problem, we developed an innovative photo-powered, self-powered aptasensor that employs a novel carbon-doped three-dimensional graphitic carbon nitride (3D-CN) combined with a metal-organic framework composed of N-doped copper(I) oxide-carbon (Cu<sub>2</sub>O@C) skeletons. The 3D-CN serves as the photoanode, offering stable photocurrent production due to its three-dimensional open framework structure. The N-doped Cu<sub>2</sub>O@C acts as the photocathode, providing oxidation protection for the metal core and enhancing light absorption due to its metal-organic framework structure. A key feature of our work is exploiting the Fermi level difference between the n-type photoanode and p-type photocathode, which facilitates faster migration of photogenerated electrons toward the photocathode, thereby enhancing the sensor's self-powered effect. Experimental results reveal that upon aptamer loading, the sensor can linearly detect tetracycline (TC) within a range of 0.5 pmol/L to 300 nmol/L, with a detection limit as low as 0.13 pmol/L. It also demonstrates excellent selectivity, stability, and reproducibility, making it applicable to real samples such as milk and river water. Consequently, our research provides a highly efficient and sensitive method for monitoring TC in food, with significant practical implications and profound impacts on food safety.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Institute of Food Technologists.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dai</LastName><ForeName>Ying</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Emergency Management, School of the Environment and Safety Engineering, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Peng</LastName><ForeName>Wangui</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Emergency Management, School of the Environment and Safety Engineering, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ji</LastName><ForeName>Yi</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Emergency Management, School of the Environment and Safety Engineering, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wei</LastName><ForeName>Jia</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Emergency Management, School of the Environment and Safety Engineering, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Che</LastName><ForeName>Junhao</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Emergency Management, School of the Environment and Safety Engineering, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huang</LastName><ForeName>Yongqiang</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Emergency Management, School of the Environment and Safety Engineering, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huang</LastName><ForeName>Weihong</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Emergency Management, School of the Environment and Safety Engineering, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Wenming</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Materials Science and Engineering, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Changzhou Engineering and Technology Institute of Jiangsu University, Changzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Wanzhen</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8782-9449</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Emergency Management, School of the Environment and Safety Engineering, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>(32072297)</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>(BK20231193)</GrantID><Agency>Jiangsu Natural Science Fund of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>(CE20232022)</GrantID><Agency>Changzhou City Key R&amp;D Plan for Agricultural Science and Technology Support Project</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>(YZ2021053)</GrantID><Agency>Science and Technology Planning Social Development Project of Yangzhou City</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>30</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Food Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0014052</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-1147</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">aptasensor</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">metal‐organic frameworks</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">photoelectrochemical</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">self‐powered</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">tetracycline</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39349972</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1750-3841.17398</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Aloui, M., Mentar, L., Beniaiche, A., &amp; Azizi, A. (2022). NH4Cl and KCl effect on the structural, morphological, optical and electrochemical properties of Cu2O nanoparticles and Cu2O nanostructures, galvanostatically electrodeposited. Journal of Solid State Chemistry, 315, 123435. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jssc.2022.123435</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ben Halima, H., Baraket, A., Vinas, C., Zine, N., Bausells, J., Jaffrezic‐Renault, N., Teixidor, F., &amp; Errachid, A. (2022). Selective antibody‐free sensing membranes for picogram tetracycline detection. Biosensors, 13(1), 71. https://doi.org/10.3390/bios13010071</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, X., Shi, R., Chen, Q., Zhang, Z., Jiang, W., Zhu, Y., &amp; Zhang, T. (2019). Three‐dimensional porous g‐C3N4 for highly efficient photocatalytic overall water splitting. Nano Energy, 59, 644–650. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.nanoen.2019.03.010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, Y., Wang, Y., Yan, P., Ouyang, Q., Dong, J., Qian, J., Chen, J., Xu, L., &amp; Li, H. (2020). Co3O4 nanoparticles/graphitic carbon nitride heterojunction for photoelectrochemical aptasensor of oxytetracycline. Analytica Chimica Acta, 1125, 299–307. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aca.2020.05.038</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng, W., Zheng, Z., Yang, J., Chen, M., Yao, Q., Chen, Y., &amp; Gao, W. (2019). The visible light‐driven and self‐powered photoelectrochemical biosensor for organophosphate pesticides detection based on nitrogen doped carbon quantum dots for the signal amplification. Electrochimica Acta, 296, 627–636. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.electacta.2018.11.086</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui, A., Dong, L., Hou, Y., Mu, X., Sun, Y., Wang, H., Zhong, X., &amp; Shan, G. (2024). NIR‐driven multifunctional PEC biosensor based on aptamer‐modified PDA/MnO2 photoelectrode for bacterial detection and inactivation. Biosensors and Bioelectronics, 257, 116320. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bios.2024.116320</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>del Campo, F. J. (2023). Self‐powered electrochemical sensors. Current Opinion in Electrochemistry, 41, 101356. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.coelec.2023.101356</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deng, Y., Tang, L., Zeng, G., Wang, J., Zhou, Y., Wang, J., Tang, J., Liu, Y., Peng, B., &amp; Chen, F. (2016). Facile fabrication of a direct Z‐scheme Ag2CrO4/g‐C3N4 photocatalyst with enhanced visible light photocatalytic activity. Journal of Molecular Catalysis A: Chemical, 421, 209–221. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.molcata.2016.05.024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deng, Y., Tang, L., Zeng, G., Wang, J., Zhou, Y., Wang, J., Tang, J., Wang, L., &amp; Feng, C. (2018). Facile fabrication of mediator‐free Z‐scheme photocatalyst of phosphorous‐doped ultrathin graphitic carbon nitride nanosheets and bismuth vanadate composites with enhanced tetracycline degradation under visible light. Journal of Colloid and Interface Science, 509, 219–234. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcis.2017.09.016</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Finklea, H. O. (1982). The preparation of TiO2 electrodes with minimum Mott‐Schottky frequency dispersion. Journal of the Electrochemical Society, 129, 2003. https://doi.org/10.1149/1.2124340</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao, Y., Tang, J., Zhou, Q., Yu, Z., Wu, D., &amp; Tang, D. (2024). Excited‐state intramolecular proton transfer‐driven photon‐gating for photoelectrochemical sensing of CO‐releasing molecule‐3. Analytical Chemistry, 96(12), 5014–5021. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.analchem.4c00324</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao, Y., Yu, Z., Huang, L., Zeng, Y., Liu, X., &amp; Tang, D. (2023). Photoinduced electron transfer modulated photoelectric signal: Toward an organic small molecule‐based photoelectrochemical platform for formaldehyde detection. Analytical Chemistry, 95(23), 9130–9137. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.analchem.3c01690</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gil, R. L., Amorim, C. M. P. G., Montenegro, M. d. C. B. S. M., &amp; Araújo, A. N. (2022). Cucurbit[8]uril‐based potentiometric sensor coupled to HPLC for determination of tetracycline residues in milk samples. Chemosensors, 10(3), 98. https://doi.org/10.3390/chemosensors10030098</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grande‐Martínez, Á., Moreno‐González, D., Arrebola‐Liébanas, F. J., Garrido‐Frenich, A., &amp; García‐Campaña, A. M. (2018). Optimization of a modified QuEChERS method for the determination of tetracyclines in fish muscle by UHPLC–MS/MS. Journal of Pharmaceutical and Biomedical Analysis, 155, 27–32. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpba.2018.03.029</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han, X., He, X., Sun, L., Han, X., Zhan, W., Xu, J., Wang, X., &amp; Chen, J. (2018). Increasing effectiveness of photogenerated carriers by in situ anchoring of Cu2O nanoparticles on a nitrogen‐doped porous carbon yolk–shell cuboctahedral framework. ACS Catalysis, 8(4), 3348–3356. https://doi.org/10.1021/acscatal.7b04219</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hill Pastor, L., Díaz Becerril, T., Galván Arellano, M., &amp; Peña Sierra, R. (2020). Sodium doping of Cu2O layers by reactive annealing of Cu2O covered with a NaCl nano‐film in a low‐oxygen atmosphere. Thin Solid Films, 693, 137711. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tsf.2019.137711</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Islas, G., Rodriguez, J. A., Perez‐Silva, I., Miranda, J. M., &amp; Ibarra, I. S. (2018). Solid‐phase extraction and large‐volume sample stacking‐capillary electrophoresis for determination of tetracycline residues in milk. Journal of Analytical Methods in Chemistry, 2018, 1–7. https://doi.org/10.1155/2018/5394527</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ismael, M. (2020). A review on graphitic carbon nitride (g‐C3N4) based nanocomposites: Synthesis, categories, and their application in photocatalysis. Journal of Alloys and Compounds, 846, 156446. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jallcom.2020.156446</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jalalian, S. H., Karimabadi, N., Ramezani, M., Abnous, K., &amp; Taghdisi, S. M. (2018). Electrochemical and optical aptamer‐based sensors for detection of tetracyclines. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 73, 45–57. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2018.01.009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, C., Zhu, L., Yang, W., He, X., Zhao, S., Zhang, X., Tang, W., Wang, J., Yue, T., &amp; Li, Z. (2019). Amino‐functionalized Al–MOF for fluorescent detection of tetracyclines in milk. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 67(4), 1277–1283. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jafc.8b06253</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, H., Xu, W., Qian, J., &amp; Li, T. (2021). Construction of a polymeric cobalt phthalocyanine@mesoporous graphitic carbon nitride composite for efficient photocatalytic CO2 reduction. Chemical Communications, 57(57), 6987–6990. https://doi.org/10.1039/d1cc02468j</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, X., Zheng, S., Hu, Y., Li, Z., Luo, F., &amp; He, Z. (2016). Electrochemical immunosensor based on the chitosan‐magnetic nanoparticles for detection of tetracycline. Food Analytical Methods, 9(10), 2972–2978. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12161‐016‐0480‐z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Low, S. S., Chen, Z., Li, Y., Lu, Y., &amp; Liu, Q. (2021). Design principle in biosensing: Critical analysis based on graphitic carbon nitride (G‐C3N4) photoelectrochemical biosensor. Trends in Analytical Chemistry, 145, 116454. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.trac.2021.116454</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo, Y., Zeng, R., Hao, Y., Chen, S., Zhang, P., &amp; Xu, M. (2024). Chemiluminescence‐driven photoelectrochemical sensor: A mini review. Electroanalysis, 36(1), e202300257. https://doi.org/10.1002/elan.202300257</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohammad‐Razdari, A., Ghasemi‐Varnamkhasti, M., Rostami, S., Izadi, Z., Ensafi, A. A., &amp; Siadat, M. (2020). Development of an electrochemical biosensor for impedimetric detection of tetracycline in milk. Journal of Food Science and Technology, 57(12), 4697–4706. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13197‐020‐04506‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mondal, R., Hasan, M. A. M., Zhang, R., Olin, H., &amp; Yang, Y. (2022). Nanogenerators‐based self‐powered sensors. Advanced Materials Technologies, 7(12), 2200282. https://doi.org/10.1002/admt.202200282</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niu, P., Zhang, L., Liu, G., &amp; Cheng, H. M. (2012). Graphene‐like carbon nitride nanosheets for improved photocatalytic activities. Advanced Functional Materials, 22(22), 4763–4770. https://doi.org/10.1002/adfm.201200922</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ouyang, Q., Liu, Y., Chen, Q., Guo, Z., Zhao, J., Li, H., &amp; Hu, W. (2017). Rapid and specific sensing of tetracycline in food using a novel upconversion aptasensor. Food Control, 81, 156–163. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2017.06.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng, B., Zhang, Z., Tang, L., Ouyang, X., Zhu, X., Chen, L., Fan, X., Zhou, Z., &amp; Wang, J. (2021). Self‐powered photoelectrochemical aptasensor for oxytetracycline cathodic detection based on a dual Z‐scheme WO3/g‐C3N4/MnO2 photoanode. Analytical Chemistry, 93(26), 9129–9138. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.analchem.1c00929</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shitanda, I., &amp; Tsujimura, S. (2021). Toward self‐powered real‐time health monitoring of body fluid components based on improved enzymatic biofuel cells. Journal of Physics: Energy, 3(3), 032002. https://doi.org/10.1088/2515‐7655/abebcb</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taghdisi, S. M., Danesh, N. M., Ramezani, M., &amp; Abnous, K. (2016). A novel M‐shape electrochemical aptasensor for ultrasensitive detection of tetracyclines. Biosensors and Bioelectronics, 85, 509–514. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bios.2016.05.048</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tu, C., Guo, Y., Dai, Y., Wei, W., Wang, W., Wu, L., &amp; Wang, A. (2019). Honey and milk by HPLC coupled with aptamer‐functionalized Fe3O4/graphene oxide magnetic solid‐phase extraction. Journal of Food Science, 84(12), 3624–3633. https://doi.org/10.1111/1750‐3841.14955</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, F., He, X., Sun, L., Chen, J., Wang, X., Xu, J., &amp; Han, X. (2018). Engineering an N‐doped TiO2@N‐doped C butterfly‐like nanostructure with long‐lived photo‐generated carriers for efficient photocatalytic selective amine oxidation. Journal of Materials Chemistry A, 6(5), 2091–2099. https://doi.org/10.1039/c7ta09166d</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, J., Lin, H., Sun, W., Xia, Y., Ma, J., Fu, J., Zhang, Z., Wu, H., &amp; Qian, M. (2016). Variations in the fate and biological effects of sulfamethoxazole, norfloxacin and doxycycline in different vegetable–soil systems following manure application. Journal of Hazardous Materials, 304, 49–57. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhazmat.2015.10.038</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xia, P., Zhu, B., Yu, J., Cao, S., &amp; Jaroniec, M. (2017). Ultra‐thin nanosheet assemblies of graphitic carbon nitride for enhanced photocatalytic CO2 reduction. Journal of Materials Chemistry A, 5(7), 3230–3238. https://doi.org/10.1039/c6ta08310b</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiong, M., Rong, Q., Meng, H., &amp; Zhang, X. (2017). Two‐dimensional graphitic carbon nitride nanosheets for biosensing applications. Biosensors and Bioelectronics, 89, 212–223. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bios.2016.03.043</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xue, J., Sun, Q., Han, C., Yang, Y., Xu, S., Li, Q., &amp; Qian, J. (2024). FeNi Prussian blue analogues on highly graphitized carbon nanosheets as efficient glucose sensors. Rare Metals, 43(6), 2730–2738. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12598‐024‐02620‐0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan, H., Zhang, K., Shentu, J., Shen, D., Li, N., &amp; Wang, M. (2017). Changes to tetracyclines and tetracycline resistance genes in arable soils after single and multiple applications of manure containing tetracyclines. Environmental Science and Pollution Research, 25(6), 5572–5581. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11356‐017‐0853‐x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan, K., Ji, W., Zhu, Y., Chen, F., &amp; Zhang, J. (2019). Photofuel cell coupling with redox cycling as a highly sensitive and selective self‐powered sensing platform for the detection of tyrosinase activity. Chemical Communications, 55(80), 12040–12043. https://doi.org/10.1039/c9cc05649a</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan, K., Yang, Y., Okoth, O. K., Cheng, L., &amp; Zhang, J. (2016). Visible‐light induced self‐powered sensing platform based on a photofuel cell. Analytical Chemistry, 88(12), 6140–6144. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.analchem.6b01600</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yao, K., Yin, X., Wang, T., &amp; Zeng, H. (2010). Synthesis, self‐assembly disassembly and reassembly of two types of Cu2O nanocrystals unifaceted with {001} or {110} planes. Journal of the American Chemical Society, 132(17), 6131–6144. https://doi.org/10.1021/ja100151f</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yi, Y., Zhao, W., Zeng, Z., Wei, C., Lu, C., Shao, Y., Guo, W., Dou, S., &amp; Sun, J. (2020). ZIF‐8@ZIF‐67‐derived nitrogen‐doped porous carbon confined CoP polyhedron targeting superior potassium‐ion storage. Small, 16(7), 1906566. https://doi.org/10.1002/smll.201906566</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu, L., Chen, H., Yue, J., Chen, X., Sun, M., Tan, H., Asiri, A. M., Alamry, K. A., Wang, X., &amp; Wang, S. (2019). Metal–organic framework enhances aggregation‐induced fluorescence of chlortetracycline and the application for detection. Analytical Chemistry, 91(9), 5913–5921. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.analchem.9b00319</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng, R., Luo, Z., Su, L., Zhang, L., Tang, D., Niessner, R., &amp; Knopp, D. (2019). Palindromic molecular beacon based Z‐scheme BiOCl‐Au‐CdS photoelectrochemical biodetection. Analytical Chemistry, 91(3), 2447–2454. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.analchem.8b05265</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng, R., Zhang, L., Su, L., Luo, Z., Zhou, Q., &amp; Tang, D. (2019). Photoelectrochemical bioanalysis of antibiotics on rGO‐Bi2WO6‐Au based on branched hybridization chain reaction. Biosensors and Bioelectronics, 133, 100–106. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bios.2019.02.067</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, H., Liang, F., Zhang, B., Li, S., &amp; Shang, H. (2022). Precisely controlled CdS/NiO nanomaterials by atomic layer deposition for excellent photoelectrochemical biosensor. Journal of Alloys and Compounds, 928, 167052. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jallcom.2022.167052</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, S., Sun, Q., Liu, X., Li, H., Wang, J., &amp; Chen, M. (2022). Ratiometric fluorescence detection of tetracycline for tetracycline adjuvant screening in bacteria. Sensors and Actuators B: Chemical, 372, 132687. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.snb.2022.132687</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Z., Tian, Y., Huang, P., &amp; Wu, F. Y. (2020). Using target‐specific aptamers to enhance the peroxidase‐like activity of gold nanoclusters for colorimetric detection of tetracycline antibiotics. Talanta, 208, 120342. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.talanta.2019.120342</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu, B., Zhang, L., Cheng, B., Yu, Y., &amp; Yu, J. (2021). H2O molecule adsorption on s‐triazine‐based g‐C3N4. Chinese Journal of Catalysis, 42(1), 115–122. https://doi.org/10.1016/s1872‐2067(20)63598‐7</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>