<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39343870</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>29</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1471-2229</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>24</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>30</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC plant biology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Plant Biol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Effects of copper sulphate stress on the morphological and biochemical characteristics of Spinacia oleracea and Avena sativa.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>889</StartPage><MedlinePgn>889</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">889</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12870-024-05566-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Plants are subjected to various biotic and abiotic stresses that significantly impact their growth and productivity. To achieve balanced crop growth and yield, including for leafy vegetables, the continuous application of micronutrient is crucial. This study investigates the effects of different concentrations of copper sulphate (0, 75, 125, and 175 ppm) on the morphological and biochemical features of Spinacia oleracea and Avena sativa. Morphological parameters such as plant height, leaf area, root length, and fresh and dry weights were optimized at a concentration of 75 ppm copper sulfate. At this concentration, chlorophyll a &amp; b levels increased significantly in Spinacia oleracea (462.9 and 249.8 𝜇𝑔/𝑔), and Avena sativa (404.7 and 437.63𝜇𝑔/𝑔). However, carotenoid content and sugar levels in Spinacia oleracea were negatively affected, while sugar content in Avena sativa increased at 125 ppm (941.6 µg/ml). Protein content increased in Spinacia oleracea (75 ppm, 180.3 µg/ml) but decreased in Avena sativa. Phenol content peaked in both plants at 75 ppm (362.2 and 244.5 µg/ml). Higher concentrations (175 ppm) of copper sulfate reduced plant productivity and health. Plants exposed to control and optimal concentrations (75 and 125 ppm) of copper sulpate exhibited the best health and growth compared to those subjected to higher concentrations. Maximum plant height, leaf area, root length, fresh and dry weights were observed at lower concentrations (75 and 125 ppm) of copper sulfate, while higher concentrations caused toxicity. Optimal copper sulfate levels enhanced chlorophyll a, chlorophyll b, total chlorophyll, protein, and phenol contents but inhibited sugar and carotenoid contents in both Spinacia oleracea and Avena sativa. Overall, increased copper sulfate treatment adversely affected the growth parameters and biochemical profiles of these plants.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zeb</LastName><ForeName>Umar</ForeName><Initials>U</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Food and Biological Engineering, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang, 212013, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biology, Faculty of Biological and Biomedical Science, The University of Haripur, Haripur, Khyber Pakhtunkhwa, 22620, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rahim</LastName><ForeName>Fazli</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Botany, Bacha Khan University Charsadda, Charsadda, Khyber Pakhtunkhwa, 24420, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Azizullah</LastName><ForeName>Azizullah</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biology, Faculty of Biological and Biomedical Science, The University of Haripur, Haripur, Khyber Pakhtunkhwa, 22620, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Saleh</LastName><ForeName>Ibrahim A</ForeName><Initials>IA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Science, Zarqa University, Zarqa, 13110, Jordan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wali</LastName><ForeName>Sher</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Botany, Islamia College University Peshawar, Peshawar, Khyber Pakhtunkhwa, 25120, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khan</LastName><ForeName>Asif Ali</ForeName><Initials>AA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Food and Biological Engineering, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang, 212013, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khan</LastName><ForeName>Hanif</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Pharmacy, Anhui University of Chinese Medicine, Hefei, 230012, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fiaz</LastName><ForeName>Sajid</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Molecular Biology and Biotechnology, The University of Lahore, Lahore, 54590, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>AbdElgawad</LastName><ForeName>Hamada</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Botany and Microbiology, Faculty of Science, Beni-Suef University, Beni-Suef, 65541, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Iqbal</LastName><ForeName>Babar</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Environment and Safety Engineering, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang, 212000, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Okla</LastName><ForeName>Mohammad K</ForeName><Initials>MK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Botany and Microbiology Department, College of Science, King Saud University, P.O. Box 2455, Riyadh, 11451, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fahad</LastName><ForeName>Shah</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Agronomy, Abdul Wali Khan University Mardan, Mardan, 23200, Khyber Pakhtunkhwa, Pakistan. shah_fahad80@yahoo.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cui</LastName><ForeName>Feng-Jie</ForeName><Initials>FJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Food and Biological Engineering, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang, 212013, China. fengjiecui@ujs.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>30</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Plant Biol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100967807</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1471-2229</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>1406-65-1</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D002734">Chlorophyll</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>LRX7AJ16DT</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D019327">Copper Sulfate</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>36-88-4</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D002338">Carotenoids</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>YF5Q9EJC8Y</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000077194">Chlorophyll A</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>5712ZB110R</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="C037184">chlorophyll b</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D010940">Plant Proteins</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018724" MajorTopicYN="Y">Spinacia oleracea</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000187" MajorTopicYN="N">drug effects</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000254" MajorTopicYN="N">growth &amp; development</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002734" MajorTopicYN="Y">Chlorophyll</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019327" MajorTopicYN="Y">Copper Sulfate</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018554" MajorTopicYN="Y">Avena</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000187" MajorTopicYN="N">drug effects</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000254" MajorTopicYN="N">growth &amp; development</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018515" MajorTopicYN="N">Plant Leaves</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000187" MajorTopicYN="N">drug effects</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000254" MajorTopicYN="N">growth &amp; development</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002338" MajorTopicYN="N">Carotenoids</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013312" MajorTopicYN="N">Stress, Physiological</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000187" MajorTopicYN="N">drug effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000077194" MajorTopicYN="N">Chlorophyll A</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010940" MajorTopicYN="N">Plant Proteins</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Avena sativa protein</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Chlorophyll a</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Copper</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Micronutrients</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Plant stress</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39343870</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11441127</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12870-024-05566-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12870-024-05566-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Gaspar T, Franck T, Bisbis B, Kevers C, Jouve L, Hausman JF, et al. concepts in plant stress physiology. Application to plant tissue cultures. Plant Growth Regul. 2002;37:263–285.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saleem A, Zulfiqar A, Ali B, Naseeb MA, Almasaudi AS, Harakeh SJ. Iron sulfate (FeSO4) improved physiological attributes and antioxidant capacity by reducing oxidative stress of Oryza sativa L. cultivars in alkaline soil. Sustainability. 2022;14(24):16845.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rizwan N, Khan QU, Khan AAJPJB. Potassium dynamic in the rhizosphere of maize (ZEA MAYS L.) grown under induced saline sodic condition. Pak J Bot. 2022;54(1):25–31.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashraf M, Foolad MRJE. Botany e: roles of glycine betaine and proline in improving plant abiotic stress resistance. Environ Exp Bot. 2007;59(2):206–16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Isik GJPJB. Ecophysiological responses of solanum lycopersicum L. to different levels of salt stress. Pak J Bot. 2022;54(1):1–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Z, Huang B, Xu QJJASHS. Effects of abscisic acid on drought responses of Kentucky bluegrass. J Am Soc Hortic Sci. 2003;128(1):36–41.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yasmeen S, Wahab A, Saleem MH, Ali B, Qureshi KA, Jaremko MJS. Melatonin as a foliar application and adaptation in lentil (Lens culinaris Medik.) Crops under drought stress. 2022, 14(24):16345.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bahadur A, Ahmad R, Afzal A, Feng H, Suthar V, Batool A, Khan A, Mahmood-ul-Hassan MJC. The influences of Cr-tolerant rhizobacteria in phytoremediation and attenuation of cr (VI) stress in agronomic sunflower (Helianthus annuus L.). 2017, 179:112–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28364646</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hasegawa PM, Bressan RA, Zhu J-K. Bohnert HJJAropb: Plant cellular and molecular responses to high salinity. 2000, 51(1):463–99.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15012199</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muranaka S, Shimizu K, Kato MJP. A salt-tolerant cultivar of wheat maintains photosynthetic activity by suppressing sodium uptake. Photosynthetica. 2002;40:505–15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saravu K, Jose J, Bhat MN, Jimmy B, Shastry BJ. Acute ingestion of copper sulphate: a review on its clinical manifestations and management. 2007;11(2):74.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iqbal S, Khan AM, Dilshad I, Moatter K, Ahmed T, Gilani SAJP, Biology A. 84. Influence of seed priming with CuSO4 and ZnSO4 on germination and seedling growth of oat under NaCl stress. Pure and Appl Biol. 2020;9(1):897–912.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elzaawely AA, Xuan TD, Tawata SJE, Botany E. Changes in essential oil, kava pyrones and total phenolics of Alpinia zerumbet (pers.) BL Burtt. &amp; RM Sm. Leaves exposed to copper sulphate. Environ Exp Bot. 2007;59(3):347–53.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ponmurugan P, Manjukarunambika K, Elango V, Gnanamangai BMJJEN. Antifungal activity of biosynthesised copper nanoparticles evaluated against red root-rot disease in tea plants. 2016;11(13):1019–31.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kranner I, Minibayeva FV, Beckett RP, Seal CEJNP. What is stress? Concepts, definitions and applications in seed science. 2010, 188(3):655–673.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20854396</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salah M, Mansour M, Zogona D, Xu XJFRI. Nanoencapsulation of anthocyanins-loaded β-lactoglobulin nanoparticles: characterization, stability, and bioavailability in vitro. 2020, 137:109635.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33233214</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shahbaz M, Ravet K, Peers G, Pilon MJFPS. Prioritization of copper for the use in photosynthetic electron transport in developing leaves of hybrid poplar. 2015, 6:407.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4452806</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26089828</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bergquist S. Bioactive compounds in baby spinach (Spinacia oleracea L.), vol. 2006; 2006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmad P, Ahanger MA, Alyemeni MN, Wijaya L, Egamberdieva D, Bhardwaj R, Ashraf MJJPI. Zinc application mitigates the adverse effects of NaCl stress on mustard [Brassica juncea (L.) Czern &amp; Coss] through modulating compatible organic solutes, antioxidant enzymes, and flavonoid content. 2017, 12(1):429–37.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Citak S, Sonmez SJS. Effects of conventional and organic fertilization on spinach (Spinacea Oleracea L.) growth, yield, vitamin C and nitrate concentration during two successive seasons. 2010, 126(4):415–20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arain SM, Sial MA, Jamali KDJPJB. Identification of wheat mutants with improved drought tolerance and grain yield potential using biplot analysis. 2022, 54(1):45–55.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rao K, Tabassum B, Babu SR, Raja A. Banji DJWjop, sciences p: preliminary phytochemical screening of Spinacia oleracea L. 2015, 4(6):532–51.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeb U, Batool A, Khan H, Ullah H, Gul B. Ethnobotanical assessment of Hazar Nao Hills, District Malakand, Khyber Pakhtunkhwa, Pakistan. Int J App Exp Biol. 2022;1(2):59–66.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Upadhyaya C, Upadhyaya T, Patel. Attributes of non-ionizing radiation of 1800 MHz frequency on plant health and antioxidant content of Tomato (Solanum Lycopersicum) plants. J Radiat Res App Sci. 2022;15(1):54–68.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ribera A, Bai Y, Wolters A-MA, van Treuren R, Kik CJE. A review on the genetic resources, domestication and breeding history of spinach (Spinacia oleracea L.). 2020;216:1–21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeb U, Wang X, AzizUllah A, Fiaz S, Khan H, Ullah S, et al. Comparative genome sequence and phylogenetic analysis of chloroplast for evolutionary relationship among Pinus species. Saudi J Biol Sci. 2022;29(3):1618–27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8913380</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35280541</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rasane P, Jha A, Sabikhi L, Kumar A. Unnikrishnan VJJofs, technology: nutritional advantages of oats and opportunities for its processing as value added foods-a review. 2015, 52:662–75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4325078</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25694675</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Syed S, Gadhe K. Katke SJJoP, Phytochemistry: studies on physical, chemical and mineral evaluation of oats (Avena sativa). 2020, 9(5):79–82.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan M, Zhang Z, Wang F, Li Z, Hu YJJPN, Science S. Effect of nitrogen forms and levels on β-glucan accumulation in grains of oat (Avena sativa L.) plants. 2009, 172(6):861–6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yongguang M, Jixiang L, Chunsheng M, Zhanwu GJNBHAC-N. Effects of NaCl stress on the growth and physiological changes in oat (Avena sativa) seedlings. 2015, 43(2):468–72.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Djuric M, Mladenovic J, Pavlovic R, Murtic N, Murtic S, Milic V, Šekularac GJAJB. Aluminium content in leaf and root of oat (Avena sativa L.) grown on pseudogley soil. 2011, 10(77):17837–40.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boczkowska M, Tarczyk EJGR, Evolution C. Genetic diversity among Polish landraces of common oat (Avena sativa L.). 2013, 60:2157–69.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Achleitner A, Tinker NA, Zechner E, Buerstmayr HJT, Genetics A. Genetic diversity among oat varieties of worldwide origin and associations of AFLP markers with quantitative traits. 2008, 117:1041–53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18633590</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deming J, Carpenter S. Determination of extracellular polymeric substances (EPS) using a modified phenol-sulfuric acid (PSA) assay for sugars. 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pérez-Patricio M, Camas-Anzueto JL, Sanchez-Alegría A, Aguilar-González A, Gutiérrez-Miceli F, Escobar-Gómez E, Voisin Y, Rios-Rojas C. Grajales-Coutiño RJS: optical method for estimating the chlorophyll contents in plant leaves. 2018, 18(2):650.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5855050</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29470432</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar A, Aery NCJJPN. Biochemical changes, biomass production, and productivity of Triticum aestivum as a function of increasing molybdenum application. 2023, 46(10):2351–62.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan H, et al. Phytoremediation of selected heavy metals using Bryophyllum daigremontianum (Raym-Hamet &amp; H. Perrier) A. Berger. Bangladesh J Bot. 2020;49(1):21–27.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alhammad BA, Seleiman MF, Harrison MTJA. Hydrogen peroxide mitigates cu stress in wheat. 2023, 13(4):862.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stuckey JW, Neaman A, Verdejo J, Navarro-Villarroel C, Peñaloza P, Dovletyarova EAJJSS, Nutrition P. Zinc alleviates copper toxicity to lettuce and oat in copper-contaminated soils. 2021, 21:1229–35.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parwez R, Aqeel U, Aftab T, Khan MMA, Naeem MJPP, Biochemistry. Melatonin supplementation combats nickel-induced phytotoxicity in Trigonella foenum-graecum L. plants through metal accumulation reduction, upregulation of NO generation, antioxidant defence machinery and secondary metabolites. 2023:107981.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37639982</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheikh L, Younis U, Shahzad AS, Hareem M, Elahi NN, Danish SJPJB. Evaluating the effects of cadmium under saline conditions on leafy vegetables by using acidified biochar. 2023, 55:1537.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pathak A, Haq S, Meena N, Dwivedi P, Kothari SL, Kachhwaha SJP. Multifaceted Role of Nanomaterials in Modulating In Vitro Seed Germination, Plant Morphogenesis, Metabolism and Genetic Engineering. 2023, 12(17):3126.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10490111</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37687372</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Russo C, Nugnes R, Orlo E, di Matteo A, De Felice B, Montanino C, Lavorgna M, Isidori MJEP. Diclofenac eco-geno-toxicity in freshwater algae, rotifers and crustaceans. 2023, 335:122251.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37506803</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reshi ZA, Ahmad W, Lukatkin AS, Javed SBJM. From nature to lab: a review of secondary Metabolite Biosynthetic pathways, Environmental influences, and in Vitro approaches. 2023, 13(8):895.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10456650</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37623839</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salah M, Xu XJJMS. Anthocyanin-β-lactoglobulin nanoparticles in acidic media: synthesis, characterization and interaction study. 2021, 1232:129995.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan A, Khan AA, Hasan SA, Irfan M, Ahmad MJJPN. Changes in morphology and yield attributes of Nigella sativa L. by copper (cu) induced toxicity. 2023:1–13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dotaniya M, Sharma A, Nagar M, Dotaniya C, Doutaniya R. Saha JJBoEC, Toxicology: can application of Pressmud Mediated Plant Nutrient Dynamics under Lead Contaminated Soils of Indian Vertisol? 2023, 110(2):44.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36680693</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paschal A. WASTEWATER REUSE FOR IRRIGATION: investigation of heavy metals and pharmaceuticals impact on crop irrigation. In.; 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeb U, Aziz T, Azizullah A, Zan XY, Khan AA, Bacha SAS, et al. Complete mitochondrial genomes of edible mushrooms: features, evolution, and phylogeny. Physiol Plant. 2024;176(3):e14363.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38837786</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arnon DIJPp. Copper enzymes in isolated chloroplasts. Polyphenoloxidase Beta vulgaris. 1949;24(1):1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC437905</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16654194</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moustakas M, Ouzounidou G, Symeonidis L, Karataglis SJSS, Nutrition P. Field study of the effects of excess copper on wheat photosynthesis and productivity. 1997, 43(3):531–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gong Q, Li Z-h, Wang L, Zhou J-y, Kang Q, Niu D-dJES, Research P. Gibberellic acid application on biomass, oxidative stress response, and photosynthesis in spinach (Spinacia oleracea L.) seedlings under copper stress. 2021, 28(38):53594–604.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34036494</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmad F, Jabeen K, Iqbal S, Umar A, Ameen F, Gancarz M, Eldin Darwish DB. Influence of silicon nano-particles on Avena sativa L. to alleviate the biotic stress of Rhizoctonia solani. 2023, 13(1):15191.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10502127</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37709782</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feigl G, Kumar D, Lehotai N, Pető A, Molnár Á, Rácz É, Ördög A, Erdei L, Kolbert Z, Laskay GJABH. Comparing the effects of excess copper in the leaves of Brassica juncea (L. Czern) and Brassica napus (L.) seedlings: growth inhibition, oxidative stress and photosynthetic damage. 2015, 66(2):205–21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26081276</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dagari M, Umar GJCJ. Impacts of EDTA on uptake and accumulation of Cu2 + by spinach (Spinacia oleracea L.) seedlings replanted in hydroponic solutions. 2017, 8(1):74–80.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ambrosini VG, Rosa DJ, de Melo GWB, Zalamena J, Cella C, Simão DG, da Silva LS, Dos Santos HP, Toselli M, Tiecher TLJPP et al. High copper content in vineyard soils promotes modifications in photosynthetic parameters and morphological changes in the root system of ‘Red Niagara’plantlets. 2018, 128:89–98.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29772492</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahanger MA, Agarwal R, Tomar NS, Shrivastava MJJ. Potassium induces positive changes in nitrogen metabolism and antioxidant system of oat (Avena sativa L cultivar Kent). J Plant Interact. 2015;10(1):211–23.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo TR, Zhang GP, Zhang YH. Physiological changes in barley plants under combined toxicity of aluminum, copper and cadmium. Colloids Surf B Biointerfaces. 2007;57(2):182–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17344036</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang WL, Wu FL, Huang HY, Huang WT, Deng CL, Yang LT, et al. Excess copper-induced alterations of protein profiles and related physiological parameters in citrus leaves. Plants. 2020;9(3):291.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7154894</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32121140</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Younis U, Malik SA, Rizwan M, Qayyum MF, Ok YS, Shah MHR, et al. Biochar enhances the cadmium tolerance in spinach (Spinacia oleracea) through modification of cd uptake and physiological and biochemical attributes. Environ Sci Pollut Res. 2016;23:21385–94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27502564</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zengin FK, Kirbag SJ. Effects of copper on chlorophyll, proline, protein and abscisic acid level of sunflower (Helianthus annuus L.) seedlings. J Environ Biol. 2007;28(3):561.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18380075</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferreira IC, Barros L, Soares ME, Bastos ML, Pereira JA. Antioxidant activity and phenolic contents of Olea europaea L. leaves sprayed with different copper formulations. Food Chem. 2007;103(1):188–195.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Şahin S, Bilgin, MJJotSoF. Agriculture: Olive tree (Olea europaea L.) leaf as a waste by-product of table olive and olive oil industry: a review. 2018;98(4):1271–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28799642</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Batool A, Azizullah A, Ullah K, Shad S, Khan FU, Seleiman MF, et al. Green synthesis of Zn-doped TIO2 nanoparticles from Zanthoxylum armatum. BMC Plant Biol. 2024;24(1):820.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11365237</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39215226</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>