<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39354563</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2055-5660</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Porcine health management</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Porcine Health Manag</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Dynamic of swine influenza virus infection in weaned piglets in five enzootically infected herds in Germany, a cohort study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>36</StartPage><MedlinePgn>36</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">36</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s40813-024-00390-w</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Within the last decades industrial swine herds in Europe grown significantly, creating an optimized reservoir for swine influenza A viruses (swIAV) to become enzootic, particularly in piglet producing herds among newborn, partly immunologically naïve piglets. To date, the only specific control measure to protect piglets from swIAV is the vaccination of sows, which provides passive immunity through maternally derived antibodies in colostrum of vaccinated sows. Interruption of infection chains through management practices have had limited success. This study focused on weaned piglets in five enzootically swIAV infected swine herds in North-West and North-East Germany and aimed to better understand swIAV infection patterns to improve piglet protection and reduce zoonotic risks. Participating farms fulfilled the following inclusion criteria: sow herd with ≥ 400 sows (actual size 600-1850 sows), piglets not vaccinated against influenza A virus and a history of recurrent respiratory problems associated with continuing influenza A virus infection. Influenza vaccination was performed in all sow herds, except for one, which discontinued vaccination during the study.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">First swIAV detections in weaned piglets occurred at 4 weeks of age in the nursery and continued to be detected in piglets up to 10 weeks of age showing enzootic swIAV infections in all herds over the entire nursery period. This included simultaneous circulation of two subtypes in a herd and co-infection with two subtypes in individual animals. Evidence for prolonged (at least 13 days) shedding was obtained in one piglet based on two consecutive swIAV positive samplings. Possible re-infection was suspected in twelve piglets based on three samplings, the second of which was swIAV negative in contrast to the first and third sampling which were swIAV positive. However, swIAV was not detected in nasal swabs from either suckling piglets or sows in the first week after farrowing.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Predominantly, weaned piglets were infected. There was no evidence of transmission from sow to piglet based on swIAV negative nasal swabs from sows and suckling piglets. Prolonged virus shedding by individual piglets as well as the co-circulation of different swIAV subtypes in a group or even individuals emphasize the potential of swIAV to increase genetic (and potentially phenotypic) variation and the need to continue close monitoring. Understanding the dynamics of swIAV infections in enzootically infected herds has the overall goal of improving protection to reduce economic losses due to swIAV-related disease and consequently to advance animal health and well-being.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Schmies</LastName><ForeName>Kathrin</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Field Station for Epidemiology, University of Veterinary Medicine Hannover, Foundation, Bakum, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hennig</LastName><ForeName>Christin</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Diagnostic Virology, Friedrich-Loeffler-Institut, Greifswald-Insel Riems, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rose</LastName><ForeName>Nicolas</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Epidemiology, Health and Welfare Research Unit, French Agency for Food, Environmental and Occupational Health and Safety (ANSES), Ploufragan, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fablet</LastName><ForeName>Christelle</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Epidemiology, Health and Welfare Research Unit, French Agency for Food, Environmental and Occupational Health and Safety (ANSES), Ploufragan, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Harder</LastName><ForeName>Timm</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Diagnostic Virology, Friedrich-Loeffler-Institut, Greifswald-Insel Riems, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Grosse Beilage</LastName><ForeName>Elisabeth</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Field Station for Epidemiology, University of Veterinary Medicine Hannover, Foundation, Bakum, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Graaf-Rau</LastName><ForeName>Annika</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Diagnostic Virology, Friedrich-Loeffler-Institut, Greifswald-Insel Riems, Germany. annika.graafrau@helmholtz-hioh.de.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathogen Evolution, Helmholtz Institute for One Health, Greifswald, Germany. annika.graafrau@helmholtz-hioh.de.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>2821ERA24</GrantID><Agency>ICRAD</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2821ERA24</GrantID><Agency>ICRAD</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>434507207</GrantID><Agency>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Porcine Health Manag</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101684126</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2055-5660</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Genotypes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Influenza A virus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Shedding</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Variation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Weaned piglets</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39354563</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11446054</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40813-024-00390-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s40813-024-00390-w</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Chun J. Influenza including its infection among pigs. Natl Med J China. 1919;5:34–44.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koen JS. A practical method for field diagnosis of swine diseases. Vet Med. 1919;14:468–70.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shope RE. Swine influenza: III. Filtration experiments and etiology. J Exp Med. 1931;54(3):373–85.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2132000</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19869924</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anderson TK, Macken CA, Lewis NS, Scheuermann RH, Van Reeth K, Brown IH, et al. A phylogeny-based global nomenclature system and automated annotation tool for H1 hemagglutinin genes from swine influenza A viruses. mSphere. 2016;1(6):e00275-e316.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5156671</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27981236</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Jong JC, Smith DJ, Lapedes AS, Donatelli I, Campitelli L, Barigazzi G, et al. Antigenic and genetic evolution of swine influenza A (H3N2) viruses in Europe. J Virol. 2007;81(8):4315–22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1866135</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17287258</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brookes SM, Núñez A, Choudhury B, Matrosovich M, Essen SC, Clifford D, et al. Replication, pathogenesis and transmission of pandemic (H1N1) 2009 virus in non-immune pigs. PLoS ONE. 2010;5(2): e9068.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2816721</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20140096</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chauhan RP, Gordon ML. A systematic review analyzing the prevalence and circulation of influenza viruses in swine population worldwide. Pathogens. 2020;9(5):355–409.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7281378</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32397138</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kothalawala H, Toussaint MJM, Gruys E. An overview of swine influenza. Vet Q. 2006;28(2):45–53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16841566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loeffen WL, Kamp EM, Stockhofe-Zurwieden N, van Nieuwstadt AP, Bongers JH, Hunneman WA, et al. Survey of infectious agents involved in acute respiratory disease in finishing pigs. Vet Rec. 1999;145(5):123–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10466829</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deblanc C, Quéguiner S, Gorin S, Chastagner A, Hervé S, Paboeuf F, et al. Evaluation of the pathogenicity and the escape from vaccine protection of a new antigenic variant derived from the european human-like reassortant swine H1N2 influenza virus. Viruses. 2020;12(10):1155.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7599989</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33053905</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hemmink JD, Morgan SB, Aramouni M, Everett H, Salguero FJ, Canini L, et al. Distinct immune responses and virus shedding in pigs following aerosol, intra-nasal and contact infection with pandemic swine influenza A virus, A(H1N1)09. Vet Res. 2016;47(1):103.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5073419</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27765064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deblanc C, Hervé S, Gorin S, Cador C, Andraud M, Quéguiner S, et al. Maternally-derived antibodies do not inhibit swine influenza virus replication in piglets but decrease excreted virus infectivity and impair post-infectious immune responses. Vet Microbiol. 2018;216:142–52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29519509</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saade G, Deblanc C, Bougon J, Marois-Créhan C, Fablet C, Auray G, et al. Coinfections and their molecular consequences in the porcine respiratory tract. Vet Res. 2020;51(1):80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7296899</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32546263</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cornelison AS, Karriker LA, Williams NH, Haberl BJ, Stalder KJ, Schulz LL, et al. Impact of health challenges on pig growth performance, carcass characteristics, and net returns under commercial conditions. Transl Anim Sci. 2018;2(1):50–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7107292</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32289106</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boeters M, Garcia-Morante B, van Schaik G, Segalés J, Rushton J, Steeneveld W. The economic impact of endemic respiratory disease in pigs and related interventions: a systematic review. Porc Health Manag. 2023;9(1):45.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10583309</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37848972</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cador C, Rose N, Willem L, Andraud M. Maternally derived immunity extends swine influenza A virus persistence within farrow-to-finish pig farms: insights from a stochastic event-driven metapopulation model. PLoS ONE. 2016;11(9):e0163672.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5035019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27662592</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pitzer VE, Aguas R, Riley S, Loeffen WL, Wood JL, Grenfell BT. High turnover drives prolonged persistence of influenza in managed pig herds. J R Soc Interface. 2016;13(119):20160138.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4938081</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27358277</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loeffen WLA, Heinen PP, Bianchi ATJ, Hunneman WA, Verheijden JHM. Effect of maternally derived antibodies on the clinical signs and immune response in pigs after primary and secondary infection with an influenza H1N1 virus. Vet Immunol and Immunopath. 2003;92(1–2):23–35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12628761</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryt-Hansen P, Larsen I, Kristensen CS, Krog JS, Wacheck S, Larsen LE. Longitudinal field studies reveal early infection and persistence of influenza A virus in piglets despite the presence of maternally derived antibodies. Vet Res. 2019;50(1):36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6530179</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31113477</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chamba Pardo FO, Wayne S, Culhane MR, Perez A, Allerson M, Torremorell M. Effect of strain-specific maternally-derived antibodies on influenza A virus infection dynamics in nursery pigs. PLoS ONE. 2019;14(1): e0210700.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6331129</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30640929</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almeida HM, Storino GY, Pereira DA, Gatto IR, Mathias LA, Montassier HJ, et al. A cross-sectional study of swine influenza in intensive and extensive farms in the northeastern region of the state of Sao Paulo. Brazil Trop Anim Health Prod. 2017;49(1):25–30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27637594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neumann EJ. Diseases transmission and biosecurity. In: Zimmermann JJ, Karriker LA, Ramirez A, Schwartz KJ, Stevenson GW, editors. Diseases of swine. 10 ed2012. p. 145.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ito T, Couceiro JNSS, Kelm S, Baum LG, Krauss S, Castrucci MR, et al. Molecular basis for the generation in pigs of influenza A viruses with pandemic potential. J Virol. 1998;72(9):7367–73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC109961</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9696833</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryt-Hansen P, Pedersen AG, Larsen I, Kristensen CS, Krog JS, Wacheck S, et al. Substantial antigenic drift in the hemagglutinin protein of swine influenza A viruses. Viruses. 2020;12(2):248.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7077184</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32102230</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Henritzi D, Petric PP, Lewis NS, Graaf A, Pessia A, Starick E, et al. Surveillance of European domestic pig populations identifies an emerging reservoir of potentially zoonotic swine influenza A viruses. Cell Host Microbe. 2020;28(4):614–27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32721380</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lopez-Moreno G, Schmitt C, Spronk T, Culhane M, Torremorell M. Evaluation of internal farm biosecurity measures combined with sow vaccination to prevent influenza A virus infection in groups of due-to-wean pigs. BMC Vet Res. 2022;18(1):393.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9643894</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36348373</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang CC, Chen JR, Tseng YC, Hsu CH, Hung YF, Chen SW, et al. Glycans on influenza hemagglutinin affect receptor binding and immune response. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2009;106(43):18137–42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2775302</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19822741</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holtkamp D, Torremorell M, Corzo CA, Linhares DCL, Almeida MN, Yeske P, et al. Proposed modifications to porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome virus herd classification. J Swine Health Prod. 2021:261–70.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>State Office for Statistics LS, Agricultural census in Lower Saxony 2020 [Available from: https://www.giscloud.nrw.de/arcgis/apps/storymaps/stories/1391a24920d04deb9133a10000c45067 (27.03.2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Graaf-Rau A, Hennig C, Lillie-Jaschniski K, Koechling M, Stadler J, Boehmer J, et al. Emergence of swine influenza A virus, porcine respirovirus 1 and swine orthopneumovirus in porcine respiratory disease in Germany. Emerg Microbes Infect. 2023;12(2):2239938.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10402848</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37470510</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loeffen WL, Hunneman WA, Quak J, Verheijden JH, Stegeman JA. Population dynamics of swine influenza virus in farrow-to-finish and specialised finishing herds in the Netherlands. Vet Microbiol. 2009;137(1–2):45–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19181461</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lillie-Jaschniski K, Lisgara M, Pileri E, Jardin A, Velazquez E, Köchling M, et al. A new sampling approach for the detection of swine influenza A virus on european sow farms. Vet Sci. 2022;9(7):338.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9324471</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35878355</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garrido-Mantilla J, Sanhueza J, Alvarez J, Culhane MR, Davies P, Allerson MW, et al. Impact of nurse sows on influenza A virus transmission in pigs under field conditions. Prev Vet Med. 2021;188: 105257.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33472145</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cador C, Hervé S, Andraud M, Gorin S, Paboeuf F, Barbier N, et al. Maternally-derived antibodies do not prevent transmission of swine influenza A virus between pigs. Vet Res. 2016;47(1):86.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4988049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27530456</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ciuoderis-Aponte K, Diaz A, Muskus C, Peña M, Hernández-Ortiz J, Osorio J. Farm management practices, biosecurity and influenza a virus detection in swine farms: a comprehensive study in Colombia. Porc Health Manag. 2022;8(1):42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9532805</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36199147</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryt-Hansen P, Nielsen HG, Sørensen SS, Larsen I, Kristensen CS, Larsen LE. The role of gilts in transmission dynamics of swine influenza virus and impacts of vaccination strategies and quarantine management. Porc Health Manag. 2022;8(1):19.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9069814</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35513878</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kyriakis CS, Rose N, Foni E, Maldonado J, Loeffen WLA, Madec F, et al. Influenza A virus infection dynamics in swine farms in Belgium, France, Italy and Spain, 2006–2008. Vet Microbiol. 2013;162(2–4):543–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23201246</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takemae N, Shobugawa Y, Nguyen PT, Nguyen T, Nguyen TN, To TL, et al. Effect of herd size on subclinical infection of swine in Vietnam with influenza A viruses. BMC Vet Res. 2016;12(1):227.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5057248</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27724934</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reynolds JJ, Torremorell M, Craft ME. Mathematical modeling of influenza A virus dynamics within swine farms and the effects of vaccination. PLoS ONE. 2014;9(8): e106177.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4146608</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25162536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu Z, Tian X, Lai R, Ji C, Li X. Airborne transmission of common swine viruses. Porcine Health Manag. 2023;9(1):50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10619269</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37908005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alonso C, Raynor PC, Davies PR, Torremorell M. Concentration, size distribution, and infectivity of airborne particles carrying swine viruses. PLoS ONE. 2015;10(8): e0135675.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4545937</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26287616</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fablet C, Simon G, Dorenlor V, Eono F, Eveno E, Gorin S, et al. Different herd level factors associated with H1N1 or H1N2 influenza virus infections in fattening pigs. Prev Vet Med. 2013;112(3–4):257–65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23968780</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poljak Z, Dewey CE, Martin SW, Christensen J, Carman S, Friendship RM. Prevalence of and risk factors for influenza in southern Ontario swine herds in 2001 and 2003. Can J Vet Res. 2008;72:7–17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2117371</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18214156</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spackman E, Senne DA, Myers TJ, Bulaga LL, Garber LP, Perdue ML, et al. Development of a real-time reverse transcriptase PCR assay for type A influenza virus and the Avian H5 and H7 hemagglutinin subtypes. J Clin Microbiol. 2002;40(9):3256–60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC130722</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12202562</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garrido-Mantilla J, Alvarez J, Culhane M, Nirmala J, Cano JP, Torremorell M. Comparison of individual, group and environmental sampling strategies to conduct influenza surveillance in pigs. BMC Vet Res. 2019;15(1):61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6376652</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30764815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nathues H, Woeste H, Doehring S, Fahrion AS, Doherr MG, Grosse Beilage E. Detection of Mycoplasma hyopneumoniae in nasal swabs sampled from pig farmers. Vet Rec. 2012;170(24):623.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22645154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simon-Grife M, Martin-Valls GE, Vilar MJ, Busquets N, Mora-Salvatierra M, Bestebroer TM, et al. Swine influenza virus infection dynamics in two pig farms; results of a longitudinal assessment. Vet Res. 2012;43:24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3353254</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22452923</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferreira JB, Grgić H, Friendship R, Wideman G, Nagy É, Poljak Z. Longitudinal study of influenza A virus circulation in a nursery swine barn. Vet Res. 2017;48(1):63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5634873</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29017603</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diaz A, Perez A, Sreevatsan S, Davies P, Culhane M, Torremorell M. Association between influenza A virus infection and pigs subpopulations in endemically infected breeding herds. PLoS ONE. 2015;10(6): e0129213.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4468154</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26076494</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allerson M, Deen J, Detmer SE, Gramer MR, Joo HS, Romagosa A, et al. The impact of maternally derived immunity on influenza A virus transmission in neonatal pig populations. Vaccine. 2013;31(3):500–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3534892</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23174202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryt-Hansen P, Larsen I, Kristensen CS, Krog JS, Larsen LE. Limited impact of influenza A virus vaccination of piglets in an enzootic infected sow herd. Res Vet Sci. 2019;127:47–56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31677416</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simon-Grife M, Martin-Valls GE, Vilar MJ, Garcia-Bocanegra I, Mora M, Martin M, et al. Seroprevalence and risk factors of swine influenza in Spain. Vet Microbiol. 2011;149(1–2):56–63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21112702</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Reeth K, Labarque G, Pensaert M. Serological profiles after consecutive experimental infections of pigs with European H1N1, H3N2, and H1N2 swine influenza viruses. Viral Immunol. 2006;19(3):373–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16987057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Unterweger C, Debeerst S, Klingler E, Auer A, Redlberger-Fritz M, Stadler J, et al. Herausforderungen bei der Influenzadiagnostik in einem Schweinebetrieb – ein Fallbericht. Tierarztl Prax Ausg G Grosstiere Nutztiere. 2021;49(06):425–31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34861735</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Renshaw HW. Influence of antibody-mediated immune suppression on clinical, viral, and immune responses to swine influenza infection. Am J Vet Res. 1975;36(1):5–13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">123140</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kitikoon P, Nilubol D, Erickson BJ, Janke BH, Hoover TC, Sornsen SA, et al. The immune response and maternal antibody interference to a heterologous H1N1 swine influenza virus infection following vaccination. Vet Immunol Immunopathol. 2006;112(3–4):117–28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16621020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hause BM, Stine DL, Sheng Z, Wang Z, Chakravarty S, Simonson RR, et al. Migration of the swine influenza virus δ-cluster hemagglutinin N-linked glycosylation site from N142 to N144 results in loss of antibody cross-reactivity. Clin Vaccine Immunol. 2012;19(9):1457–64.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3428406</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22815146</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simon G, Larsen LE, Durrwald R, Foni E, Harder T, Van Reeth K, et al. European surveillance network for influenza in pigs: surveillance programs, diagnostic tools and Swine influenza virus subtypes identified in 14 European countries from 2010 to 2013. PLoS ONE. 2014;9(12): e115815.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4277368</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25542013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rose N, Hervé S, Eveno E, Barbier N, Eono F, Dorenlor V, et al. Dynamics of influenza A virus infections in permanently infected pig farms: evidence of recurrent infections, circulation of several swine influenza viruses and reassortment events. Vet Res. 2013;44(1):72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3846378</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24007505</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>grosse Beilage E, Wendt M. Influenza. Diagnostik und Gesundheitsmanagement im Schweinebestand. 1. Stuttgart: Eugen Ulmer KG 2013. p. 235–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grau-Roma L, Hjulsager CK, Sibila M, Kristensen CS, López-Soria S, Enøe C, et al. Infection, excretion and seroconversion dynamics of porcine circovirus type 2 (PCV2) in pigs from post-weaning multisystemic wasting syndrome (PMWS) affected farms in Spain and Denmark. Vet Microbiol. 2009;135(3–4):272–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19027247</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allende R, Laegreid WW, Kutish GF, Galeota JA, Wills RW, Osorio FA. Porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome virus: description of persistence in individual pigs upon experimental infection. J Virol. 2000;74(22):10834–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC110963</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11044133</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>King J, Harder T, Beer M, Pohlmann A. Rapid multiplex MinION nanopore sequencing workflow for Influenza A viruses. BMC Infect Dis. 2020;20(1):648.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7468549</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32883215</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun H, Xiao Y, Liu J, Wang D, Li F, Wang C, et al. Prevalent Eurasian avian-like H1N1 swine influenza virus with 2009 pandemic viral genes facilitating human infection. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2020;117(29):17204–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7382246</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32601207</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>