<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39353529</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>05</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-0953</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>263</Volume><Issue>Pt 2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>29</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Environmental research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Environ Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Exploring the association between urinary bisphenol A, S, and F levels and semen quality parameters: Findings from Led-Fertyl cross-sectional study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>120086</StartPage><MedlinePgn>120086</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.envres.2024.120086</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0013-9351(24)01993-5</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Infertility is recognized as a multifaceted condition affecting approximately 15% of couples globally, influenced by various factors including genetic predisposition and environmental exposures. Among these environmental factors, bisphenol A (BPA) emerges as a prominent Endocrine-disrupting chemical (EDCs) widely distributed, leading to chronic human exposure in daily life. As regulations on BPA became more stringent, alternative substances such as bisphenol S (BPS) and bisphenol F (BPF) have emerged. Animal studies have demonstrated a dose-dependent decline in fertility and embryotoxicity following chronic exposure to BPA. However, literature data on human studies are limited and heterogeneous. Additionally, even less is known about the relationship between exposure to the BPA analogues (BPS and BPF) and sperm quality. Therefore, the present study aimed to examine the association between urinary concentrations of BPA, BPF, and BPS and semen quality parameters among 195 adult Spanish men from the Led-Fertyl study cohort using multiple linear regression models adjusted by potential confounding variables. Our results revealed an inverse association between log-transformed creatinine-adjusted concentration (ng/mg) of BPA and BPF levels and the percentage of sperm vitality (β: 3.56 %; 95%CI: 6.48 to -0.63 and β: 4.14 %; 95%CI: 6.97 to -1.31; respectively). Furthermore, participants in the highest quartile of BPA and BPF urinary concentration exhibited lower sperm vitality compared to those in the lowest quartile (β: 6.90 %; 95%CI: 11.60 to -2.15 and β: 9.68 %; 95%CI: 14.43 to -4.94; respectively). These results supply epidemiological evidence establishing a relationship between bisphenols urine exposure and sperm quality, suggesting that a re-evaluation of the overall safety of BPA alternatives is warranted.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Martínez</LastName><ForeName>María Ángeles</ForeName><Initials>MÁ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institut d'Investigació Sanitària Pere Virgili (IISPV), Reus, Spain; Universitat Rovira i Virgili, Departament de Bioquímica i Biotecnologia, Alimentació, Nutrició, Desenvolupament i Salut Mental ANUT-DSM, Reus, Spain; Centro de Investigación Biomédica en Red Fisiopatología de la Obesidad y la Nutrición (CIBEROBN), Institute of Health Carlos III, Madrid, Spain; Department of Pharmacology, therapeutics and Toxicology, Faculty of veterinary. Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona, Cerdanyola del Vallès, 08193, Catalonia, Spain. Electronic address: mariaangeles.martinez@iispv.cat.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Salas-Huetos</LastName><ForeName>Albert</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institut d'Investigació Sanitària Pere Virgili (IISPV), Reus, Spain; Universitat Rovira i Virgili, Departament de Bioquímica i Biotecnologia, Alimentació, Nutrició, Desenvolupament i Salut Mental ANUT-DSM, Reus, Spain; Centro de Investigación Biomédica en Red Fisiopatología de la Obesidad y la Nutrición (CIBEROBN), Institute of Health Carlos III, Madrid, Spain; Universitat Rovira i Virgili, Departament de Ciències Mediques Bàsiques, Unitat de Medicina Preventiva, Alimentació, Nutrició, Desenvolupament i Salut Mental ANUT-DSM, Reus, Spain; Department of Nutrition, Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health, Harvard University, Boston, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fernández de la Puente</LastName><ForeName>María</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institut d'Investigació Sanitària Pere Virgili (IISPV), Reus, Spain; Universitat Rovira i Virgili, Departament de Bioquímica i Biotecnologia, Alimentació, Nutrició, Desenvolupament i Salut Mental ANUT-DSM, Reus, Spain; Centro de Investigación Biomédica en Red Fisiopatología de la Obesidad y la Nutrición (CIBEROBN), Institute of Health Carlos III, Madrid, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Valle-Hita</LastName><ForeName>Cristina</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institut d'Investigació Sanitària Pere Virgili (IISPV), Reus, Spain; Universitat Rovira i Virgili, Departament de Bioquímica i Biotecnologia, Alimentació, Nutrició, Desenvolupament i Salut Mental ANUT-DSM, Reus, Spain; Centro de Investigación Biomédica en Red Fisiopatología de la Obesidad y la Nutrición (CIBEROBN), Institute of Health Carlos III, Madrid, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Marquès</LastName><ForeName>Montse</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Universitat Rovira i Virgili, Departament de Bioquímica i Biotecnologia, Alimentació, Nutrició, Desenvolupament i Salut Mental ANUT-DSM, Reus, Spain; Universitat Rovira i Virgili, Departament de Ciències Mèdiques Bàsiques, Laboratori de Toxicologia i Salut Ambiental. Center of Environmental, Food and Toxicological Technology-TecnATox. Reus, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Del Egido-González</LastName><ForeName>Claudia</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institut d'Investigació Sanitària Pere Virgili (IISPV), Reus, Spain; Universitat Rovira i Virgili, Departament de Bioquímica i Biotecnologia, Alimentació, Nutrició, Desenvolupament i Salut Mental ANUT-DSM, Reus, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Davila-Cordova</LastName><ForeName>Estefanía</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institut d'Investigació Sanitària Pere Virgili (IISPV), Reus, Spain; Universitat Rovira i Virgili, Departament de Bioquímica i Biotecnologia, Alimentació, Nutrició, Desenvolupament i Salut Mental ANUT-DSM, Reus, Spain; Centro de Investigación Biomédica en Red Fisiopatología de la Obesidad y la Nutrición (CIBEROBN), Institute of Health Carlos III, Madrid, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mestres</LastName><ForeName>Cristina</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institut d'Investigació Sanitària Pere Virgili (IISPV), Reus, Spain; Universitat Rovira i Virgili, Departament de Bioquímica i Biotecnologia, Alimentació, Nutrició, Desenvolupament i Salut Mental ANUT-DSM, Reus, Spain; Hospital Universitari Sant Joan de Reus, Universitat Rovira i Virgili, IISPV, Alimentaciò, Nutrició, Desenvolupament i Salut Mental ANUT-DSM, Reus, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Petersen</LastName><ForeName>Maria Skaalum</ForeName><Initials>MS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of the Faroe Islands, Tórshavn, Faroe Islands; Department of Research, the National Hospital of the Faroe Islands, Tórshavn, Faroe Islands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Babio</LastName><ForeName>Nancy</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institut d'Investigació Sanitària Pere Virgili (IISPV), Reus, Spain; Universitat Rovira i Virgili, Departament de Bioquímica i Biotecnologia, Alimentació, Nutrició, Desenvolupament i Salut Mental ANUT-DSM, Reus, Spain; Centro de Investigación Biomédica en Red Fisiopatología de la Obesidad y la Nutrición (CIBEROBN), Institute of Health Carlos III, Madrid, Spain. Electronic address: nancy.babio@urv.cat.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Salas-Salvadó</LastName><ForeName>Jordi</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institut d'Investigació Sanitària Pere Virgili (IISPV), Reus, Spain; Universitat Rovira i Virgili, Departament de Bioquímica i Biotecnologia, Alimentació, Nutrició, Desenvolupament i Salut Mental ANUT-DSM, Reus, Spain; Centro de Investigación Biomédica en Red Fisiopatología de la Obesidad y la Nutrición (CIBEROBN), Institute of Health Carlos III, Madrid, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Environ Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0147621</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0013-9351</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bisphenols</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Chemical analogues</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Endocrine disruptors</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Infertility</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Semen quality</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>38</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>38</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>11</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39353529</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2024.120086</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0013-9351(24)01993-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>