<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39357359</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>02</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1873-3336</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>480</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>27</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of hazardous materials</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Hazard Mater</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Innovative hierarchical porous hydrophilic molecularly imprinted resin for high-throughput detection of perfluorocarboxylic acids in milk using 96-well plate SPE-LC-MS/MS.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>135989</StartPage><MedlinePgn>135989</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2024.135989</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0304-3894(24)02568-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The accumulation of perfluorocarboxylic acids (PFCAs) in environment and foods represents a significant threat to public health due to the long-term ingestion of contaminated food. This study introduces a novel adsorbent, the hierarchical porous hydrophilic molecularly imprinted resin (HPHMIR), which was synthesized by integrating molecular imprinting techniques with hydrophilic resins. The HPHMIR, characterized by its extensive mesoporous structure (average pore width ∼9.71 nm) and favorable imprinting factors (2.6-5.0), facilitates the effective adsorption of PFCAs from complex matrices through multiple interaction mechanisms, including hydrogen bonding and electrostatic interactions. This innovative material was employed in a 96-well plate format for solid-phase extraction (SPE), and combined with LC-MS/MS, a high-throughput method for the determination of PFCAs in milk was developed. The proposed method demonstrated exceptional performance, including excellent linearity (0.48-240 ng mL<sup>-1</sup>; r ≥ 0.9986), low detection limits (0.04-0.11 ng mL<sup>-1</sup>), high precision (relative standard deviation ≤ 9.9 %), and satisfactory recovery (75.7-118.1 %). These results highlight the efficacy of the method in extracting trace levels of PFCAs from complicated sample matrices, presenting a promising alternative for monitoring PFCA contamination and advancing public health standards.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Lansen</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of New Pharmaceutical Preparations and Excipients, Key Laboratory of Medicinal Chemistry and Molecular Diagnosis of Ministry of Education, College of Chemistry and Materials Science, Hebei University, Baoding 071002, China; Hebei Key Laboratory of Public Health Safety, College of Pharmaceutical Sciences, College of Public Health, School of Life Science, Hebei University, Baoding 071002, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Pengfei</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hebei Key Laboratory of Public Health Safety, College of Pharmaceutical Sciences, College of Public Health, School of Life Science, Hebei University, Baoding 071002, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bai</LastName><ForeName>Ligai</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of New Pharmaceutical Preparations and Excipients, Key Laboratory of Medicinal Chemistry and Molecular Diagnosis of Ministry of Education, College of Chemistry and Materials Science, Hebei University, Baoding 071002, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cao</LastName><ForeName>Jiankun</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hebei Key Laboratory of Public Health Safety, College of Pharmaceutical Sciences, College of Public Health, School of Life Science, Hebei University, Baoding 071002, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yan</LastName><ForeName>Hongyuan</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of New Pharmaceutical Preparations and Excipients, Key Laboratory of Medicinal Chemistry and Molecular Diagnosis of Ministry of Education, College of Chemistry and Materials Science, Hebei University, Baoding 071002, China; Hebei Key Laboratory of Public Health Safety, College of Pharmaceutical Sciences, College of Public Health, School of Life Science, Hebei University, Baoding 071002, China. Electronic address: yanhy@hbu.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>J Hazard Mater</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9422688</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0304-3894</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">96-Well plate</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Milk</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Molecularly imprinted resin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Perfluorocarboxylic acid</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Solid-phase extraction</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of Competing Interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper. Declaration of Competing Interest The authors declare no competing financial interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>9</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39357359</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2024.135989</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0304-3894(24)02568-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>