<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39352655</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>01</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1678-4405</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Brazilian journal of microbiology : [publication of the Brazilian Society for Microbiology]</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Braz J Microbiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Carvacrol-loaded chia mucilage nanocapsules as sanitizer to control Salmonella, Escherichia coli and Listeria monocytogenes in green cabbage.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s42770-024-01528-2</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Cabbage is susceptible to various microbiological risks, frequently serving as a vehicle for pathogenic bacteria, mainly Salmonella and Escherichia coli. Therefore, ensuring the safety of this vegetable is essential to reduce the risk of foodborne illnesses. Traditional sanitization using chlorinated water, although effective, raises concerns due to the production of potentially carcinogenic compounds, and this method is banned in some countries. In recent years, alternative sanitizing methods have been developed using essential oils (EOs). However, EOs present high volatility, limited solubility in water, and strong odor and taste. This study introduces an innovative approach to overcome these disadvantages by employing carvacrol encapsulated into chia mucilage nanocapsules (CMNC), prepared through high-energy homogenization. Encapsulating carvacrol in chia mucilage nanocapsules helps to mask its strong sensory characteristics, making it more suitable and acceptable for use in food applications. The antimicrobial efficacy of CMNC (1.67 mg/mL), carvacrol emulsion (CE: 10.6 mg/mL), and chlorine solution (CS: 200 ppm) was evaluated against Salmonella, E. coli, and Listeria monocytogenes. CMNC decreased Salmonella to levels below the detection limit of the technique (&lt; 2 log CFU/g), reduced 3.5 log CFU/g of E. coli, and 2.5 log CFU/g of L. monocytogenes. These results are similar to or better than those obtained with CS. In addition, sanitizing cabbage with CMNC preserved the firmness and color of the samples, important aspects for consumer acceptance. This innovative approach is promising for increasing the food safety of cabbage, while mitigating the potential drawbacks associated with traditional sanitization methods.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s) under exclusive licence to Sociedade Brasileira de Microbiologia.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cacciatore</LastName><ForeName>Fabíola Ayres</ForeName><Initials>FA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratório de Microbiologia e Higiene de Alimentos, Departamento de Ciência de Alimentos, Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul, Porto Alegre, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cardoso</LastName><ForeName>Louise Thomé</ForeName><Initials>LT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratório de Microbiologia e Higiene de Alimentos, Departamento de Ciência de Alimentos, Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul, Porto Alegre, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Scherer</LastName><ForeName>Alina</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratório de Microbiologia e Higiene de Alimentos, Departamento de Ciência de Alimentos, Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul, Porto Alegre, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jaskulski</LastName><ForeName>Vinícius de Oliveira</ForeName><Initials>VO</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratório de Microbiologia e Higiene de Alimentos, Departamento de Ciência de Alimentos, Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul, Porto Alegre, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Malheiros</LastName><ForeName>Patrícia da Silva</ForeName><Initials>PDS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratório de Microbiologia e Higiene de Alimentos, Departamento de Ciência de Alimentos, Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul, Porto Alegre, Brazil. patricia.malheiros@ufrgs.br.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Brandelli</LastName><ForeName>Adriano</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9307-6471</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratório de Nanobiotecnologia e Microbiologia Aplicada, Departamento de Ciência de Alimentos, Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul, Porto Alegre, Brazil. abrand@ufrgs.br.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centro de Nanociência e Nanotecnologia, Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul, Porto Alegre, Brazil. abrand@ufrgs.br.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>308880/2021-8</GrantID><Agency>Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior</GrantID><Agency>Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Brazil</Country><MedlineTA>Braz J Microbiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101095924</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1517-8382</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Food pathogens</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Foodborne infections</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Green cabbage</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Natural antimicrobials</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sanitization</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39352655</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s42770-024-01528-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s42770-024-01528-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>López-Gálvez F, Gómez PA, Artés F, Artés-Hernández F, Aguayo E (2021) Interactions between microbial food safety and environmental sustainability in the fresh produce supply chain. Foods 10:1655. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods10071655</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods10071655</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34359525</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8307063</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Macieira A, Barbosa J, Teixeira P (2021) Food safety in local farming of fruits and vegetables. Int J Environ Res Pub Health 18:9733. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph18189733</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph18189733</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>CDC (2023) List of Selected Multistate Foodborne Outbreak Investigations. Center for Disease Control and Prevention. https://www.cdc.gov/foodsafety/outbreaks/lists/outbreaks-list.html?CDC_AA_refVal=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.cdc.gov%2Ffoodsafety%2Foutbreaks%2Fmultistate-outbreaks%2Foutbreaks-list.html . Accessed 12 December 2023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yegin Y, Perez-Lewis KL, Liu S, Kerth CR, Cisneros-Zevallos L, Castillo A, Akbulut M, Taylor TM (2021) Antimicrobial-loaded polymeric micelles inhibit enteric bacterial pathogens on spinach leaf surfaces during multiple simulated pathogen contamination events. Front Sustain Food Syst 5:646980. https://doi.org/10.3389/fsufs.2021.646980</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fsufs.2021.646980</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Corato U (2020) Improving the shelf-life and quality of fresh and minimally-processed fruits and vegetables for a modern food industry: a comprehensive critical review from the traditional technologies into the most promising advancements. Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr 60:940–975. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2018.1553025</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2018.1553025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30614263</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pereira DM, Ferreres F, Valentão P, Andrade PB (2011) Brassica seeds: Metabolomics and biological potential. In: Preedy VR, Watson RR, Patel VB (eds) Nuts and seeds in Health and Disease Prevention. Elsevier, London, pp 83–91. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-12-375688-6.10009-X</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-375688-6.10009-X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sow LC, Tirtawinata F, Yang H, Shao Q, Wang S (2017) Carvacrol nanoemulsion combined with acid electrolysed water to inactivate bacteria, yeast in vitro and native microflora on shredded cabbages. Food Control 76:88–95. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2017.01.007</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2017.01.007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Tayyar NA, Youssef AM, Al-Hindi RR (2020) Edible coatings and antimicrobial nanoemulsions for enhancing shelf life and reducing foodborne pathogens of fruits and vegetables: a review. Sustain Mater Technol 26:e00215. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.susmat.2020.e00215</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.susmat.2020.e00215</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mendoza IC, Luna EO, Pozo MD, Vasquez MV, Montoya DC, Moran GC, Romero LG, Yépez X, Salazar R, Romero-Peña M, Leon JC (2022) Conventional and non-conventional disinfection methods to preovent microbial contamination in minimally processed fruits and vegetables. LWT Food Sci Technol 165:113714. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2022.113714</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2022.113714</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mritunjay SK, Kumar V (2017) A study on prevalence of microbial contamination on the surface of raw salad vegetables. 3 Biotech 7:13. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13205-016-0585-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13205-016-0585-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28391475</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5385173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erickson MC, Liao J-Y, Payton AS, Cook PW, Bakker HCD, Bautista J, Díaz-Pérez JC (2019) Survival of Salmonella enterica and Escherichia coli O157:H7 sprayed onto the foliage of field-grown cabbage plants. J Food Protect 82:479–485. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362-028X.JFP-18-326</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4315/0362-028X.JFP-18-326</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soni DK, Singh M, Singh DV, Dubey SK (2014) Virulence and genotypic characterization of Listeria monocytogenes isolated from vegetable and soil samples. BMC Microbiol 14:241. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12866-014-0241-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12866-014-0241-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25195727</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4172985</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith CR, Bond H, Kearney A, Chau K, Chui L, Gerrie M, Honish L, Oukouomi Lowé Y, Mah V, Manore AJW (2023) Fermenting a place in history: the first outbreak of Escherichia coli O157 associated with kimchi in Canada. Epidemiol Infect 151:e106. https://doi.org/10.1017/s0950268823000882</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/s0950268823000882</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37288513</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10369422</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Whitworth J (2022) English salad testing finds Listeria strain behind the past outbreak. Food Safety News. https://www.foodsafetynews.com/2022/12/english-salad-testing-finds-listeria-strain-behind-past-outbreak . Acessed 3 June 2024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kowalska B (2023) Fresh vegetables and fruit as a source of Salmonella bacteria. Ann Agric Environ Med 30:9–14. https://doi.org/10.26444/aaem/156765</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.26444/aaem/156765</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36999850</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bansal V, Siddiqui MW, Rahman MS (2015) Minimally processed foods: overview. In: Siddiqui MW, Rahman MS (eds) Minimally processed foods: technologies for Safety, Quality and Convenience. Springer, Cham, pp 1–15. https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-10677-9_1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-10677-9_1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pizzo JS, Visentainer JV, da Silva ALBR, Rodrigues C (2023) Application of essential oils as sanitizer alternatives on the postharvest washing of fresh produce. Food Chem 407:135101. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2022.135101</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2022.135101</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36481474</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poimenidou SV, Bikouli VC, Gardeli C, Mitsi C, Tarantilis PA, Nychas GJ, Skandamis PN (2016) Effect of single or combined chemical and natural antimicrobial interventions on Escherichia coli O157:H7, total microbiota and color of packaged spinach and lettuce. Int J Food Microbiol 220:6–18. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2015.12.013</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2015.12.013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26773252</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gadelha J, Allende A, López-Gálvez F, Fernández P, Gil M, Egea J (2019) Chemical risks associated with ready‐to‐eat vegetables: quantitative analysis to estimate formation and/or accumulation of disinfection byproducts during washing. EFSA J 17:e170913. https://doi.org/10.2903/j.efsa.2019.e170913</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2903/j.efsa.2019.e170913</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32626471</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7015476</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen CH, Yin HB, Teng Z, Byun S, Guan Y, Luo Y, Upadhyay A, Patel J (2021) Nanoemulsified carvacrol as a novel washing treatment reduces Escherichia coli O157:H7 on spinach and lettuce. J Food Protect 84:2163–2173. https://doi.org/10.4315/JFP-21-151</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4315/JFP-21-151</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raffo A, Paoletti F (2022) Fresh-cut vegetables processing: environmental sustainability and food safety issues in a comprehensive perspective. Front Sustain Food Syst 5:681459. https://doi.org/10.3389/fsufs.681459</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fsufs.681459</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COT (2006) COT statement on a commercial survey investigating the occurrence of disinfectants and disinfection by-products in prepared salads. Committee on Toxicity of Chemicals in Food, Consumer Products and the Enviroment, London</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cimowsky S, Kumar GD, da Silva ALBR, White E, Kerr WL, Rodrigues C, Juneja VK, Dunn LL (2022) Postharvest control of Escherichia coli O157:H7 on romaine lettuce using a novel pelargonic acid sanitizer. LWT Food Sci Technol 154:112168. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2021.112168</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2021.112168</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duan L, Jiang T, Zhou Y, Bai X, Wang Y, Lü X, Xia X, Lin L, Shi C (2023) The inactivation of Shigella flexneri by synergistic effect of ultrasound combined with basil essential oil nanoemulsion and application in cabbage cleaning. Food Control 156:110142. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2023.110142</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2023.110142</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cardoso LT, Alexandre B, Cacciatore FA, Magedans YVS, Fett-Neto AG, Contri RV, Malheiros PS (2023) Carvacrol-loaded nanoemulsions produced with a natural emulsifier for lettuce sanitization. Food Res Int 168:112748. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2023.112748</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2023.112748</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37120202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roobab U, Khan AW, Lorenzo JM, Arshad RN, Chen BR, Zeng XA, Bekhit AE, Suleman R, Aadil RM (2021) A systematic review of clean-label alternatives to synthetic additives in raw and processed meat with a special emphasis on high-pressure processing (2018–2021). Food Res Int 150:110792. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2021.110792</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2021.110792</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34865807</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang H, Wang S, Goon K, Gilbert A, Nguyen Huu C, Walsh M, Nitin N, Wrenn S, Tikekar RV (2020) Inactivation of foodborne pathogens based on synergistic effects of ultrasound and natural compounds during fresh produce washing. Ultrason Sonochem 64:104983. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ultsonch.2020.104983</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ultsonch.2020.104983</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32006935</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Z, Tan Y, McClements DJ (2021) Investigate the adverse effects of foliarly applied antimicrobial nanoemulsion (carvacrol) on spinach. LWT Food Sci Technol 141:110936. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2021.110936</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2021.110936</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Komaiko JS, McClements DJ (2016) Formation of food-grade nanoemulsions using low-energy preparation methods: a review of available methods. Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf 15:331–352. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541-4337.12189</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.12189</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33371595</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kang JH, Song KB (2018) Inhibitory effect of plant essential oil nanoemulsions against Listeria monocytogenes, Escherichia coli O157:H7, and Salmonella Typhimurium on red mustard leaves. Innov Food Sci Emerg Technol 45:447–454. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ifset.2017.09.019</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ifset.2017.09.019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park JB, Kang JH, Song KB (2018) Geranium essential oil emulsion containing benzalkonium chloride as a wash solution on fresh-cut vegetables. Food Bioprocess Technol 11:2164–2171. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11947-018-2177-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11947-018-2177-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao D, Ye R, Davidson PM, Hayes DG, Golden DA, Zhong Q (2011) Sucrose monolaurate improves the efficacy of sodium hypochlorite against Escherichia coli O157:H7 on spinach. Int J Food Microbiol 145:64–68. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2010.11.029</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2010.11.029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21168229</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kang JH, Park SJ, Park JB, Song KB (2019) Surfactant type affects the washing effect of cinnamon leaf essential oil emulsion on kale leaves. Food Chem 271:122–128. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2018.07.203</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2018.07.203</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30236656</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhargava K, Conti DS, da Rocha SRP, Zhang Y (2015) Application of an oregano oil nanoemulsion to the control of foodborne bacteria on fresh lettuce. Food Microbiol 47:69–73. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fm.2014.11.007</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fm.2014.11.007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25583339</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Assadpour E, Jafari SM (2019) A systematic review on nanoencapsulation of food bioactive ingredients and nutraceuticals by various nanocarriers. Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr 59:3129–3151. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2018.1484687</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2018.1484687</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29883187</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferreira CD, Nunes IL (2019) Oil nanoencapsulation: development, application, and incorporation into the food market. Nanoscale Res Lett 14:9. https://doi.org/10.1186/s11671-018-2829-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s11671-018-2829-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30617711</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6323048</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ter Horst B, Moiemen NS, Grover LM (2019) Natural polymers: Biomaterials for skin scaffolds. In: García-Gareta E (ed) Biomaterials for skin repair and regeneration. Woodhead Publishing, Oxford, pp 151–192. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-08-102546-8.00006-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/B978-0-08-102546-8.00006-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taheri A, Jafari SM (2019) Gum-based nanocarriers for the protection and delivery of food bioactive compounds. Adv Colloid Interface Sci 269:277–295. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cis.2019.04.009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cis.2019.04.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31132673</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cacciatore FA, Maders C, Alexandre B, Pinilla CMB, Brandelli A, Malheiros PS (2022) Carvacrol encapsulation into nanoparticles produced from Chia and flaxseed mucilage: characterization, stability and antimicrobial activity against Salmonella and Listeria monocytogenes. Food Microbiol 108:104116. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fm.2022.104116</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fm.2022.104116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36088121</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>CLSI (1999) Methods for determining bactericidal activity of Antimicrobial agents; approved Guideline. Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute, Berwyn</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brasil (2004) Resolução N<sup>o</sup> 216, de 15 de setermbro de 2004. Dispõe Sobre Regulamento Técnico De Boas Práticas para Serviços De Alimentação. Agência Nacional de Vigilância Sanitária</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McGlynn W (2004) Food technology fact sheet: guidelines for the use of chlorine bleach as a sanitizer in food processing operations. Oklahoma State University, Stillwater</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kabir N, Aras S, Allison A, Adhikari J (2019) Interactions of carvacrol, caprylic acid, habituation, and mild heat for pressure-based inactivation of O157 and non-O157 serogroups of Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli in acidic environment. Microorganisms 7:145. https://doi.org/10.3390/microorganisms7050145</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/microorganisms7050145</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31126074</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6560415</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee JY, Garcia CV, Shin GH, Kim JT (2019) Antibacterial and antioxidant properties of hydroxypropyl methylcellulose-based active composite films incorporating oregano essential oil nanoemulsions. LWT Food Sci Technol 106:164–171. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2019.02.061</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2019.02.061</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lei C, Engeseth NJ (2021) Comparison of growth characteristics, functional qualities, and texture of hydroponically grown and soil-grown lettuce. LWT Food Sci Technol 150:111931. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2021.111931</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2021.111931</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brasil (2022) Instrução Normativa - IN N<sup>o</sup> 161, de 1<sup>o</sup> de julho de 2022. Estabelece os Padrões Microbiológicos dos Alimentos. Agência Nacional de Vigilância Sanitária</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>NACMCF (2015) Response to questions posed by the department of defense regarding microbiological criteria as indicators of process control or insanitary conditions. National Advisory Committee on Microbiological Criteria for Foods (USA), Washington</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhunia AK (2018) Listeria monocytogenes. In: Bhunia AK (ed) Foodborne Microbial pathogens. Food Science Text Series. Springer, New York, pp 229–248. https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4939-7349-1_13</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-1-4939-7349-1_13</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kang JH, Song KB (2018b) Combined effect of a positively charged cinnamon leaf oil emulsion and organic acid on the inactivation of Listeria monocytogenes inoculated on fresh-cut Treviso leaves. Food Microbiol 76:146–153. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fm.2018.05.004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fm.2018.05.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30166135</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>FDA (2019) Mann Packing Co., Inc. voluntarily recalls vegetable products sold in the United States and Canada due to potential health risks. https://www.fda.gov/safety/recalls-market-withdrawals-safety-alerts/mann-packingco-inc-voluntarily-recalls-vegetable-products-sold-united-states-andcanada-due . Accessed 5 November 2023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FDA (2021) 5000 Years Foods, Inc. recall cabbage kimchi because of possible health risk. https://www.fda.gov/safety/recalls-market-withdrawals-safety-alerts/5000-years-foods-inc-recall-cabbage-kimchi-because-possiblehealth-risk . Accessed 5 November 2023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CDC (2023) Listeria outbreak linked to packaged salads produced by Dole. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. https://www.cdc.gov/listeria/outbreaks/packaged-salad-mix-12-21/index.html . Accessed 20 December 2023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schifferstein HNJ, Wehrle T, Carbon CC (2019) Consumer expectations for vegetables with typical and atypical colors: the case of carrots. Food Qual Prefer 72:98–108. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodqual.2018.10.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodqual.2018.10.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen XD, Majumdar A (2008) Drying technologies in food processing. Wiley, London</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuan W, Teo CHM, Yuk HG (2019) Combined antibacterial activities of essential oil compounds against Escherichia coli O157:H7 and their application potential on fresh-cut lettuce. Food Control 96:112–118. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2018.09.005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2018.09.005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>