<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39358707</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1471-2458</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>24</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>02</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC public health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Public Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A cross-sectional study of the relative availability and prominence of shelf space allocated to healthy and unhealthy foods in supermarkets in urban Ireland, by area-level deprivation.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>2689</StartPage><MedlinePgn>2689</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">2689</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12889-024-19671-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Diet-related noncommunicable diseases (NCDs) are a leading cause of ill-health and death across Europe. In Ireland, dietary intakes of saturated fat, free sugar and salt exceed World Health Organization recommendations, and excess consumption follows a social gradient increasing population risk of diet-related NCDs. The retail food environment can influence consumer food choice and subsequent dietary intakes. In high income countries, supermarkets are an increasingly influential actor in consumer food availability, choice, purchase, and subsequent food intake. This study aims to assess the relative availability and prominence of healthy and unhealthy foods in Irish supermarkets, by area-level deprivation.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">This study used a cross-sectional study design, and applied a validated measure, as described in the INFORMAS Protocol: Food Retail - Food availability in supermarkets. Between October 2021 and February 2022, shelf space (m<sup>2</sup>) (height or depth (cm) × length (cm)) and prominence (visibility), of foods, classified as healthy and unhealthy and represented by a proxy indicator, were collected in supermarkets (n = 36) in County Dublin, Ireland. Overall the proportion of mean relative shelf space (m<sup>2</sup>), allocated to healthy and unhealthy foods, and its prominence, by area-level deprivation, and retailer, were determined. We used t-tests and one-way ANOVA to analyse possible differences between the proportion of relative shelf space available to healthy and unhealthy foods, and its prominence, by area-level deprivation and retailer.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The study found the proportion of shelf space measured allocated to unhealthy food was 68.0% (SD 10.6). Unhealthy foods were more likely to be in areas of high prominence. Overall, there was no statistically significant difference between the proportion of relative shelf space available to unhealthy foods in areas of high and low deprivation. A statistically significant difference in the proportion of relative shelf space allocated to healthy and unhealthy food by area level deprivation was found in one retailer.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Unhealthy foods had a higher proportion of shelf space and were more prominent than healthy foods in supermarkets in County Dublin, Ireland. The current availability and prominence of foods in supermarkets does not align with Food Based Dietary Guideline recommendations and does not support consumers to make healthier food choices. There is a need for supermarkets in Ireland to improve the availability and prominence of healthy foods to support consumers to make healthier food choices.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>O'Mahony</LastName><ForeName>S</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Safety Authority of Ireland, The Exchange, Georges Dock, Dublin 1, Ireland. somahony@fsai.ie.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Food and Health, School of Agriculture and Food Science, University College Dublin (UCD), Belfield, Dublin 4, Ireland. somahony@fsai.ie.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Collins</LastName><ForeName>N</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Safety Authority of Ireland, The Exchange, Georges Dock, Dublin 1, Ireland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Doyle</LastName><ForeName>G</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Business, UCD, Belfield, Dublin 4, Ireland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>UCD Geary Institute of Public Policy, UCD, Belfield, Dublin 4, Ireland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>McCann</LastName><ForeName>A</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Safety Authority of Ireland, The Exchange, Georges Dock, Dublin 1, Ireland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Burke</LastName><ForeName>K</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Mathematics and Statistics, University of Limerick, Co. Limerick, Ireland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Moore</LastName><ForeName>A</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Geography and Environmental Sciences, Ulster University, Coleraine, Northern Ireland, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gibney</LastName><ForeName>E R</ForeName><Initials>ER</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Food and Health, School of Agriculture and Food Science, University College Dublin (UCD), Belfield, Dublin 4, Ireland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Agriculture and Food Science, UCD, Belfield, Dublin 4, Ireland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>02</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Public Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100968562</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1471-2458</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007494" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Ireland</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003430" MajorTopicYN="N">Cross-Sectional Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000085943" MajorTopicYN="Y">Supermarkets</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005523" MajorTopicYN="Y">Food Supply</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014505" MajorTopicYN="N">Urban Population</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000072001" MajorTopicYN="N">Diet, Healthy</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Area-level deprivation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Retail food environment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Supermarket</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Unhealthy food availability</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Unhealthy food visibility</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39358707</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11445997</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12889-024-19671-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12889-024-19671-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Nettleton JA, Brouwer IA, Geleijnse JM, Hornstra G. Saturated Fat Consumption and Risk of Coronary Heart Disease and ischemic stroke: a Science Update. Ann Nutr Metab. 2017;70(1):26–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5475232</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28125802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fiolet T, Srour B, Sellem L, Kesse-Guyot E, Allès B, Méjean C, et al. Consumption of ultra-processed foods and cancer risk: results from NutriNet-Santé prospective cohort. BMJ. 2018;360:k322.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5811844</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29444771</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Q, Afshin A, Yakoob MY, Singh GM, Rehm CD, Khatibzadeh S, et al. Impact of Nonoptimal intakes of Saturated, Polyunsaturated, and Trans Fat on Global burdens of Coronary Heart Disease. J Am Heart Association. 2016;5(1):e002891.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4859401</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26790695</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Irish Universities Nutrition Alliance. National adult nutrition survey II. 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moore Heslin A, O’Donnell A, Kehoe L, Walton J, Flynn A, Kearney J, et al. Adolescent overweight and obesity in Ireland—trends and sociodemographic associations between 1990 and 2020. Pediatr Obes. 2023;18(2):e12988.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10077905</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36287113</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitchell LB-SS, Stanley I, Hegarty T, McCann L, Mehegan J, Murrin C, Heinen M, Kelleher, Cacciottolo J. The Childhood Obesity Surveillance Initiative (COSI) in the Republic of Ireland - findings from 2018 and 2019. Ireland: HSE; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Irish Universities Nutrition Alliance. National adult nutrition survey. 2011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brug J. Determinants of healthy eating: motivation, abilities and environmental opportunities. Fam Pract. 2008;25(Suppl 1):i50–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18826991</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shepherd R. Social determinants of food choice. Proc Nutr Soc. 1999;58(4):807–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10817147</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rose D. Economic determinants and Dietary Consequences of Food Insecurity in the United States. J Nutr. 1999;129(2):S517–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10064321</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gilmore AB, Fabbri A, Baum F, Bertscher A, Bondy K, Chang H-J, et al. Defining and conceptualising the commercial determinants of health. Lancet. 2023;401(10383):1194–213.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36966782</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vogel C, Abbott G, Ntani G, Barker M, Cooper C, Moon G, et al. Examination of how food environment and psychological factors interact in their relationship with dietary behaviours: test of a cross-sectional model. Int J Behav Nutr Phys Activity. 2019;16(1):12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6354411</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30700323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen PJ, Antonelli M. Conceptual Models of Food Choice: influential factors related to Foods, Individual Differences, and Society. Foods. 2020;9(12).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7766596</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33353240</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glanz K, Sallis JF, Saelens BE, Frank LD. Healthy nutrition environments: concepts and measures. Am J Health Promot. 2005;19(5):330–3. ii.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15895534</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vandevijvere S, Vanderlee L. Effect of Formulation, Labelling, and Taxation policies on the Nutritional Quality of the Food Supply. Curr Nutr Rep. 2019;8(3):240–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31321705</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liberato SC, Bailie R, Brimblecombe J. Nutrition interventions at point-of-sale to encourage healthier food purchasing: a systematic review. BMC Public Health. 2014;14(1):919.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4180547</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25192584</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brimblecombe J, McMahon E, De Silva K, Ferguson M, Miles E, Wycherley T et al. Transforming food retail for better health: the healthy stores 2020 trial. Eur J Pub Health. 2020;30(Supplement_5).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vargas C, Whelan J, Brimblecombe J, Brock J, Christian M, Allender S. Co-creation of healthier food retail environments: a systematic review to explore the type of stakeholders and their motivations and stage of engagement. Obes Rev. 2022;23(9):e13482.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9540769</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35670030</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Winkler MR, Zenk SN, Baquero B, Steeves EA, Fleischhacker SE, Gittelsohn J et al. A model depicting the Retail Food Environment and Customer Interactions: components, outcomes, and future directions. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020;17(20).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7589434</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33086537</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glanz K, Bader MD, Iyer S. Retail grocery store marketing strategies and obesity: an integrative review. Am J Prev Med. 2012;42(5):503–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22516491</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pulker CE, Trapp GSA, Scott JA, Pollard CM. What are the position and power of supermarkets in the Australian food system, and the implications for public health? A systematic scoping review. Obes Rev. 2018;19(2):198–218.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29193744</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hawkes C. Sales promotions and food consumption. Nutr Rev. 2009;67(6):333–42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19519674</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kantar World Panel. Grocery market share Ireland 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martyn DM, McNulty BA, Walton J, Flynn A, Nugent AP, Gibney MJ. Eating location trends in a representative sample of Irish adults. Proceedings of the Nutrition Society. 2011;70(OCE3):E54.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaughan CA, Cohen DA, Ghosh-Dastidar M, Hunter GP, Dubowitz T. Where do food desert residents buy most of their junk food? Supermarkets. Public Health Nutr. 2017;20(14):2608–16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5380604</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27702412</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaw SC, Ntani G, Baird J, Vogel CA. A systematic review of the influences of food store product placement on dietary-related outcomes. Nutr Rev. 2020;78(12):1030–45.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7666915</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32483615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Healthy Ireland. Non-broadcast media advertising and marketing of food and non-alcoholic beverages, including sponsorship and retail product placement: voluntary code of practice. 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Food (Promotion and Placement) (England) Regulations 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muir S, Dhuria P, Roe E, Lawrence W, Baird J, Vogel C. UK government’s new placement legislation is a ‘good first step’: a rapid qualitative analysis of consumer, business, enforcement and health stakeholder perspectives. BMC Med. 2023;21(1):33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9878939</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36703194</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>INFORMAS. Food Retail Module: Food Availability in Supermarkets. 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vandevijvere S, Waterlander W, Molloy J, Nattrass H, Swinburn B. Towards healthier supermarkets: a national study of in-store food availability, prominence and promotions in New Zealand. Eur J Clin Nutr. 2018;72(7):971–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29343854</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schultz S, Cameron AJ, Grigsby-Duffy L, Robinson E, Marshall J, Orellana L, et al. Availability and placement of healthy and discretionary food in Australian supermarkets by chain and level of socio-economic disadvantage. Public Health Nutr. 2021;24(2):203–14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10195512</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32792022</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vandevijvere S, Van Dam I, Inaç Y, Smets V. Unhealthy food availability, prominence and promotion in a representative sample of supermarkets in Flanders (Belgium): a detailed assessment. Archives Public Health. 2023;81(1):154.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10463948</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37608383</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Central Statistics Office. Census of population 2022. 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Central Statistics Office. Ordnance survey Ireland electoral divisions boundaries 2015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haase T, Pratschke J. The 2016 pobal HP deprivation index 2017 [Available from: www.trutzhaase.eu].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vandevijvere S, Mackenzie T, Mhurchu CN. Indicators of the relative availability of healthy versus unhealthy foods in supermarkets: a validation study. Int J Behav Nutr Phys Activity. 2017;14(1):53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5405544</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28441947</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kerr J, Sallis JF, Bromby E, Glanz K. Assessing reliability and validity of the GroPromo audit tool for evaluation of grocery store marketing and promotional environments. J Nutr Educ Behav. 2012;44(6):597–603.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23140564</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Donnell A, Buffini M, Kehoe L, Nugent A, Kearney J, Walton J, et al. The prevalence of overweight and obesity in Irish children between 1990 and 2019. Public Health Nutr. 2020;23(14):2512–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10200483</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32613932</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elorriaga N, Moyano DL, López MV, Cavallo AS, Gutierrez L, Panaggio CB et al. Urban Retail Food environments: relative availability and prominence of exhibition of healthy vs. Unhealthy foods at supermarkets in Buenos Aires, Argentina. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18(3).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7908167</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33499044</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maguire ER, Burgoine T, Penney TL, Forouhi NG, Monsivais P. Does exposure to the food environment differ by socioeconomic position? Comparing area-based and person-centred metrics in the Fenland Study, UK. Int J Health Geogr. 2017;16(1):33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5586029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28877706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Obesity Healthy Alliance. Out of place: the extent of unhealthy foods in prime locations in supermarkets. 2018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adam A, Jensen JD. What is the effectiveness of obesity related interventions at retail grocery stores and supermarkets? —a systematic review. BMC Public Health. 2016;16(1):1247.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5192566</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28031046</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vogel C, Crozier S, Penn-Newman D, Ball K, Moon G, Lord J, et al. Altering product placement to create a healthier layout in supermarkets: outcomes on store sales, customer purchasing, and diet in a prospective matched controlled cluster study. PLoS Med. 2021;18(9):e1003729.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8423266</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34491999</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Department of Health. A healthy weight for Ireland: obesity policy and action plan 2016–2025. Dublin: The Stationery Office; 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blake MR, Backholer K, Lancsar E, Boelsen-Robinson T, Mah C, Brimblecombe J, et al. Investigating business outcomes of healthy food retail strategies: a systematic scoping review. Obes Rev. 2019;20(10):1384–99.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31397087</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaw HJ. Food deserts: towards the development of a classification. Geogr Annaler: Ser B Hum Geogr. 2006;88(2):231–47.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Layte R, Harrington J, Sexton E, Perry IJ, Cullinan J, Lyons S. Irish exceptionalism? Local food environments and dietary quality. J Epidemiol Community Health. 2011;65(10):881–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21372065</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cooksey-Stowers K, Schwartz MB, Brownell KD. Food Swamps Predict Obesity Rates Better Than Food Deserts in the United States. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2017;14(11).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5708005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29135909</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Consumer Data Research Centre. Priority Places for Food Index. https://www.cdrc.ac.uk/priority-places-for-food-index/2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mikic A. Healthy by design: utilizing Choice Architecture to Improve Food environments. Curr Dev Nutr. 2020;4(Supplement2):718.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Sullivan S. Dunnes retains highest market share among Irish grocery retailers. Checkout. 2024.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>