<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39359713</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2045-452X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Toxicology research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Toxicol Res (Camb)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Assessment of the toxic influence of locally formulated pesticides on hepatic and renal biomarkers in male Wistar rats.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>tfae157</StartPage><MedlinePgn>tfae157</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">tfae157</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1093/toxres/tfae157</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">There is growing concern of the potential damage to vital organs after long term exposure to locally formulated pesticides in rural area of Nigeria. This study was designed to assessed the effects of the individual chemical compound and their combination on the kidney and liver of rats' model.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODOLOGY" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Fifty-four rats divided into six groups and three sub-groups were exposed to 25, 50 and 75% dose of each of the pesticide's LD<sub>50</sub> for 4 h at 3 days interval in an inhalation chamber for 28 days. Alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alkaline phosphatase (ALP), total bilirubin (TOT_BIL), creatinine and urea assay showed significant increase at the aforementioned doses in comparison to the control group. The red blood cell counts, hematocrit and hemoglobin concentrations were significantly altered in the rats administered varying doses of the pesticides when compared with the control. Similar result was obtained for the differential white blood cell counts. Histopathological examinations of the liver tissue of rats showed infiltrated sinusoids, traces of karypyknosis, vacuolar degeneration and microvesicular steatosis while that of the renal tissue showed glomeruli atrophy leading to widened Bowman's spaces as well as few shrunken glomeruli and varied level of degenerative tubular changes to tubular necrosis.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This study established that individual pesticides and their mixture is toxic to the liver and kidney, as evidenced by the elevated markers of renal and liver functions and distortion of the structure of both organs as revealed by their photomicrographs. Therefore, it is a matter of public health significance to regularly monitor pesticide residues in foods and humans in order to assess the food safety risk and population exposure to pesticides.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s) 2024. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Adeyele</LastName><ForeName>Esther Itunuoluwa</ForeName><Initials>EI</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0006-2370-8994</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Ecology and Environmental Studies, Obafemi Awolowo University, Road 7, P.M.B 13, Ile Ife, Osun State, 220282, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ayanyemi</LastName><ForeName>Esther Olutomilayo</ForeName><Initials>EO</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0005-5196-1332</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Ecology and Environmental Studies, Obafemi Awolowo University, Road 7, P.M.B 13, Ile Ife, Osun State, 220282, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Akomolafe</LastName><ForeName>Rufus Ojo</ForeName><Initials>RO</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7812-8563</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physiological Sciences, Faculty of Basic Medical Sciences, Obafemi Awolowo University, Road 7, P.M.B 13, Ile Ife, Osun State, 220282, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sesan</LastName><ForeName>Olaoluwa Olukiran</ForeName><Initials>OO</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5948-7982</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physiological Sciences, Faculty of Basic Medical Sciences, Obafemi Awolowo University, Road 7, P.M.B 13, Ile Ife, Osun State, 220282, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Aladesanmi</LastName><ForeName>Omolara Titilayo</ForeName><Initials>OT</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7213-3505</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Ecology and Environmental Studies, Obafemi Awolowo University, Road 7, P.M.B 13, Ile Ife, Osun State, 220282, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Adetutu</LastName><ForeName>Aderonke Okoya</ForeName><Initials>AO</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2487-4426</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Ecology and Environmental Studies, Obafemi Awolowo University, Road 7, P.M.B 13, Ile Ife, Osun State, 220282, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>30</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Toxicol Res (Camb)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101587950</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2045-452X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">kidney</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">liver</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">naphthalene</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">organophosphates</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pesticides</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">rats</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>59</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>58</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39359713</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11442146</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/toxres/tfae157</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">tfae157</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Remya VR, George JS, Thomas S. Manufacturing of slow- and controlled-release pesticides. In: Rakhimol KR, Thomas S, Volova T, Jayachandran K, editors. Controlled release of pesticides for sustainable agriculture. Cham: Springer; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Research Council . Pesticides in the diets of infants and children. In: Committee of Pesticides in the diets of infants and children. Board of Agriculture and Board on environmental studies and toxicology. Washington DC: National Academics Press; 1993. 10.17226/2126.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.17226/2126</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang W, Jiang F, Ou J. Global pesticide consumption and pollution: with China as a focus. Proc Int Acad Ecol Environ Sci. 2011:1(2):125–44.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith WD. Pesticide toxicity. In: Extension safety program. The Texas A and M University system; Texas, 2011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kingsley AI, Sunday PI, Blessing AA. Histological assessment of the effects of pyrethroid insecticide Mortein on the lungs of adult Wistar rats. IOSR J Dent Med Sci. 2015:14(1):77–80.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaur K, Kaur R. Occupational pesticides exposure, impaired DNA repair and diseases. Indian J Occup Environ Med. 2018:22(2):74–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6176703</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30319227</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dizdaroglu M, Jaruga P, Birincioglu M, Rodriguez H. Free radical-induced damage to DNA: mechanisms and measurement. Free Radic Biol Med. 2002:32(11):1102–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12031895</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evans MD, Dizdaroglu M, Cooke MS. Oxidative DNA damage and disease: induction, repair and significance. Mutat Res. 2004:567(1):1–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15341901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lindahl T, Barnes DE. Repair of endogenous DNA damage. Cold Spring Harb Symp Quant Biol. 2000:65:127–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12760027</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baldi I, Lebailly P, Mohammed-Brahim B, Letenneur L, Dartigues J-F, Brochard P. Neurodegenerative diseases and exposure to pesticides in the elderly. Am J Epidemiol. 2003:157(5):409–14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12615605</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fokina KV, Bezuglyĭ VP. Role of chlora and organophosphate pesticide compleses in the etiology of cerebral atherosclerosis. Vrach Delo. 1978:4:19–23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">664589</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zamzila AN, Aminu I, Niza S, Razman MR, Hadi MA. Chronic organophosphate pesticide exposure and coronary artery disease: finding a bridge. IIUM Research, Invention and Innovation Exhibition; 2011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Umar M, Stephen SH, Abdullahi M, Garba M. Dichlorvos concentrations in locally formulated pesticide (Ota-piapia) utilized in northeastern Nigeria. Sci Res Essay. 2010:5(1):049–54.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency . Integrated risk information system (IRIS) on Dichlorvos. Washington, DC: National Centre for Environmental Assessment Office of Research and Development; 1999.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okoroiwu UH, Iwara AI. Dichlorvos toxicity: a public health perspective. Interdiscip Toxicol. 2018:11(2):129–37.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6829687</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31719784</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lydy M, Belden J, Wheelock C, Hammock B, Denton D. Challenges in regulating pesticide mixtures. Ecol Soc. 2004:9(6):1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muñoz-Quezada MT, Lucero BA, Iglesias VP, Muñoz MP, Cornejo CA, Achu E, Baumert B, Hanchey A, Concha C, Brito AM, et al. . Chronic exposure to organophosphate (OP) pesticides and neuropsychological functioning in farm workers: a review. Int J Occup Environ Health. 2016:22(1):68–79.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4894272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27128815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamanyire R, Karalliedde I. Organophospate toxicity and occupational exposure. Occup Med. 2004:54(2):69–75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15020723</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cherian MA, Roshini C, Peter VJ, Cherian AM. Oximes in organophosphorus poisoning. Indian J Crit Care Med. 2005:9(3): 155–63.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Colovic BM, Krstic DZ, Lazarevic-Pasti TD, Bondzic AM, Vasic MV. Acetylcholinesterase inhibitors: pharmacology and toxicology. Curr Neuropharmacol. 2013:11(3):315–35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3648782</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24179466</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fullerton GD, Bruce N, Gordon BS. Indoor air pollution from biomass fuel smoke is a major health concern in the developing world. Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg. 2008:102(9):843–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2568866</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18639310</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lam LN, Smith RK, Gauthier A, Bates NM. Kerosene: a review of household uses and their hazards in low and middle-income countries. J Toxicol Environ Health. 2012:15(6):396–432.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3664014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22934567</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnson M, Damazio OA. Hepatotoxicity of household kerosene on liver enzyme markers and its effect on haematological and oxidative stress parameter on Wistar rats. Sci J Med Clin Trials. 2014:3(3):79–86.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uboh FE, Akpanabiatu MI, Eyong UE, Ebong PE, Oka OO. Evaluation of toxicological implication exposure to kerosene and petrol fumes in rats. Acta Biologica Scegediensis. 2005:49:19–22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jyoti J, Neeraj D, Anu Y, Ajay S. Camphor induced seizures in an adult: a revisit. J Clin Toxicol. 2018:8(5):396.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chedi BAZ, Aliyu M. Effect and management of acute dichlorvos poisoning in Wistar rats. Bayero J Pure and Appl Sci. 2010:3(2):1–3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ikpesu TO, Ariyo AB. Health implications of excessive use and abuse of pesticides by the rural dwellers in developing countries: the need for awareness. Greener J Environ Manage Public Saf. 2013:2(5):180–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tayeb W, Nakbi A, Trabelsi M, Attia N, Miled A, Hammami M. Hepatotoxicity induced by sub-acute exposure of rats to 2, 4-dichlorophenoxyacetic acid-based herbicide “désormone lourd”. J Hazard Mater. 2010:180(1–3):225–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20447766</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang HY, Tan JYL, Lim CC. Abnormal liver function tests in the symptomatic pregnant patients: the local experience in Singapore. Ann Acad Med. 2004:33(2):204–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15098635</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garba SU, Aminu NA, Musa HA, Ahmad MA, Musa AB, et al. . Biochemical and histopathological changes in liver of albino rats exposed to 1% Dichlorvos pesticide at sub-acute period. J Pharm Biomed Sci. 2013:3(2):1–6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lala V, Minter DA. Liver function tests. In: StatPearls (internet). Treasure Island (FL): StatPearls Publishing; 2018.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29494096</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mossa TAH, Refaie AA, Ramadan A. Effect of exposure to mixture of four organophosphate insecticides at No observed adverse effect level dose on rat liver: the protective role of vitamin C. Res J Environ Toxicol. 2011:5(6):323–35.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agina AO, Omoja UV, Ekere OS, Odo S, Agina CB. A study on dichlorvos induced hematology, clinical biochemistry and reproductive abnormalities in male albino rats. J Mol Pathophysiol. 2016:6(1):5–11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma AD, Mallick AR, Ghosh AK. Free radicals and their role in different clinical conditions: an overview. Int J Pharm Sci Res. 2010:1(3):185–92.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karami-Mohajeri S, Abdollahi M. Mitochondrial dysfunction and organophosphorus compounds. Toxicol Appl Pharmacol. 2013:270(1):39–44.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23578477</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Achuba IF, Nwokogba CC. Effects of honey supplementation on hydrocarbon-induced kidney and liver damage in Wistar albino rats. Biokemistri. 2015:27(1):50–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yaman I, Balikci E. Protective effects of nigella sativa against gentamicin-induced nephrotoxicity in rats. Exp Toxicol Pathol. 2010:62(2):183–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19398313</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naggayi M, Mukiibi N, Iliya E. The protective effects of aqueous extract of Carica papaya seeds in paracetamol induced nephrotoxicity in male Wistar rats. J Afr Health Sci. 2015:15(2):598–605.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4480493</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26124809</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ojo AO, Oyinloye BE, Ajiboye BO, Ojo AB, Akintayo CO, Okezie B. Dichlorvos induced nephrotoxicity in rat kidney: protective effects of Alstonia Boonei stem bark extract. Int J Pathol. 2014:1:429–37.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kingsley CK, Solomon NI, Odudu A. Haematological, biochemical and antioxidant changes in Wistar rats exposed to Dichlorvos based insecticide formulation used in Southeast Nigeria. Toxics J. 2016:4:28–35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5606651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29051431</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Begum G. Carbofuran insecticide induced biochemical alterations in liver and muscle tissues of the fish Clarias batrachus (Linn) and recovery response. Aquat Toxicol. 2004:66(1):83–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14687981</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaikh IA, Gautam RK. Effect of organophosphate pesticide, Nuvan on serum biochemical parameters of fresh water catfish Heteropneustes fossilis (Bloch.), international research journal of environment. Science. 2014:3(10):1–6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zaware SG. Environmental impact assessment on soil pollution issue about human health. Int Res J Environ Sci. 2014:3(11):78–81.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chinedu I, Friday OU. Renal protective effect of Ethanolic leaf extract of Gongronema latifolium Benth in acetaminophen induced renal toxicity in male albino rats. Am Chem Sci J. 2015:8(3):1–10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uhegbu FO, Imo C, Ifeanacho NG. Effect of exposure of male albino rats to kerosene, diesel and petrol on kidney function. Int Res J Environ Sci. 2015:4(11):12–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Afshar S, Heidari R, Farshid AA, Ilkhanipour M. Effect of oral Administration of Fenitrothion on biochemical and Hematological parameters in rats. Pak J Biol Sci. 2008:11(13):1742–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18819630</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akinrotimi OA, Abu OMG, Ansa EJ, Edun OM, George OS. Haematological responses of Tilapia guineensis to acute stress. Int J Nat Appl Sci. 2009:5:338–48.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mansour SA, Mossa AH. Comparative effects of some insecticides as technical and formulated on male albino rats. J Egypt Soc Toxicol. 2005:32:41–54.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalender Y, Uzunhisarcikli M, Ogutcu A, Acikgoz F, Kalender S. Effects of diazinon on pseudocholinesterase activity and haematological indices in rats: the protective role of vitamin E. Environ Toxicol Pharmacol. 2006:22(1):46–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21783685</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Attar MA, Al-Taisan AW. Preventive effects of black seed (nigella Sativa) extract on Sprague Dawley rats exposed to Diazinon. Aust J Basic Appl Sci. 2010:4(5):957–68.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Awad OM, El Fiki SA, Aboushanab RAI, Hassanin NMA, Rahman R. Influence of exposure to pesticides on liver enzymes and cholinesterase levels in male agriculture workers. Global NEST J. 2014:16(5):1006–15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nassar MK, Salim MY, Malhat MF. Assessment of pesticide residues in human blood and effects of occupational exposure on haematological and hormonal qualities. Pak J Biol Sci. 2016:19(3):95–105.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29023046</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Everds EN, Synder WP, Bailey LK, Bolon B, Creasy MD, Foley MG, Rosol JT, Sellers T. Interpreting stress responses during routine toxicity studies: a review of the biology, impact, and assessment. Toxicol Pathol. 2013:41(4):560–614.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23475558</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adeoti OT, Belonwu DC, Matthew OW, Justice OS. Implications of acute, sub chronic and chronic exposure to different pesticides via inhalation on male Wistar rats. Bioeng Biosci. 2017:5(4):74–85.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okonkwo CO, Ohaeri CO, Atangwho JI. Haematological changes in rats exposed to insecticidal oils from the leaves of Cassia occidentalis and Euphorbia milii. Heliyon. 2016:5(5):e01746.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6536728</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31193578</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Sahhaf YZ. Toxicity of Sumithion in albino rats: haematological and biochemical studies. J Appl Sci. 2006:6(14):2959–62.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ita SO, Udofia UA. Comparative study of some haematological parameters in rats following ingestion of crude oil (Nigerian bonny light), petrol, kerosene and diesel. Asian J Biol Sci. 2011:4(6):498–505.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edem VF, Akinyoola SB, Olaniyi JA, Rahamon SK, Owoeye O, Arinola G. Haematological parameter of Wistar rats exposed to 2,2Dichlorovinyl dimethyl phosphate chemical. Asian J Experim Biol Sci. 2012:3(4):838–41.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ajiboso SOO, Gbate M, Ajari OI, Adeyemo SO. Subchronic inhalation toxicity studies of 2, 2 – Dichlorovinyl dimethyl phosphate (DDVP) in albino rats. Adv Biol Res. 2012:6(4):133–40.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hossen S, Tanvir ME, Prince BM, Paul S, Saha M, Ali Y, Gan HS, Khali I, Karim N. Protective mechanism of turmeric on Carbofuran- induced Hematological and hepatic toxicities in a rat model. Pharm Biol. 2017:55(1):1937–45.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7012003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28675957</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>