<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39357492</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>02</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1873-4235</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>267</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>26</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Biosensors &amp; bioelectronics</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Biosens Bioelectron</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A portable micro-nanochannel bio-3D printed liver microtissue biosensor for DON detection.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>116810</StartPage><MedlinePgn>116810</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.bios.2024.116810</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0956-5663(24)00816-9</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>We investigated a portable micro-nanochannel biosensor 3D-printed liver microtissues for rapid and sensitive deoxynivalenol (DON) detection. The screen-printed carbon electrode (SPCE) was modified with nanoporous anodic aluminum oxide (AAO), gold nanoparticles (AuNPs), and cytochrome C oxidase (COx) to enhance sensor performance. Gelatin methacrylate hydrogel, combined with hepatocellular carcinoma cells, formed the bioink for 3D printing. Liver microtissues were prepared through standardized and high-throughput techniques via bio-3D printing technology. These microtissues were immobilized onto modified electrodes to fabricate liver microtissue sensors. The peak current of this biosensor was positively correlated with DON concentration, as determined by cyclic voltammetry (CV), within a linear detection range of 2∼40 μg/mL. The standard curve equation is denoted by I<sub>CV(μA)</sub> = = 18.76956 + 0.03107C<sub>DON(μg/mL)</sub>, with a correlation coefficient R<sup>2</sup> was 0.99471(n＝3). A minimum detection limit of 1.229 μg/mL was calculated from the formula, indicating the successful construction of a portable micro-nanochannel bio-3D printed liver microtissue biosensor. It provides innovative ideas for developing rapid and convenient instrumentation to detect mycotoxin hazards after grain production. It also holds significant potential for application in the prediction and assessment of post-production quality changes in grain.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Nanwei</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science and Engineering, Collaborative Innovation Center for Modern Grain Circulation and Safety, Key Laboratory of Grains and Oils Quality Control and Processing, Nanjing University of Finance and Economics, Nanjing, Jiangsu, 210023, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hu</LastName><ForeName>Wei</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science and Engineering, Collaborative Innovation Center for Modern Grain Circulation and Safety, Key Laboratory of Grains and Oils Quality Control and Processing, Nanjing University of Finance and Economics, Nanjing, Jiangsu, 210023, China; Harbin University of Commerce, Harbin, 150028, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jiang</LastName><ForeName>Hui</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nanjing Institute for Food and Drug Control, Nanjing, Jiangsu, 211198, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jiang</LastName><ForeName>Donglei</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science and Engineering, Collaborative Innovation Center for Modern Grain Circulation and Safety, Key Laboratory of Grains and Oils Quality Control and Processing, Nanjing University of Finance and Economics, Nanjing, Jiangsu, 210023, China. Electronic address: dljiang@nufe.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Lifeng</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science and Engineering, Collaborative Innovation Center for Modern Grain Circulation and Safety, Key Laboratory of Grains and Oils Quality Control and Processing, Nanjing University of Finance and Economics, Nanjing, Jiangsu, 210023, China. Electronic address: wanglifeng_8@163.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Biosens Bioelectron</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9001289</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0956-5663</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bionic sensing strategy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">DON detection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Liver microtissue</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Micro-nano channel</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Portable electrochemical biosensor</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Three-dimensional bio-printing</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>12</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39357492</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bios.2024.116810</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0956-5663(24)00816-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>