<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Curated"><PMID Version="1">39358742</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>05</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1475-2875</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>23</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>02</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Malaria journal</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Malar J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Avian malaria in a feral-pet pigeon: a case report.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>294</StartPage><MedlinePgn>294</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">294</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12936-024-05116-5</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Avian malaria is caused by diverse parasite species of the genus Plasmodium, and it affects various bird species. The occurrence of this disease in some wild bird species is sparsely documented due to the scarce availability of samples. Hence the pathogenicity in some hosts is not completely known. In addition, feral birds may act as reservoirs bridging the transmission cycle from wild migratory birds to domestic and zoo-kept bird species.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CASE PRESENTATION" NlmCategory="METHODS">An owner of pigeons adopted a feral pigeon (Columba livia forma domestica) and housed it together with his other pet-pigeons. The bird died unexpectedly a few weeks after a surgical procedure and necropsy revealed a severely anaemic carcass, with pale organs and hydropericardium. Histopathologic analysis revealed inflammatory infiltrates in the lung and liver, and monocytes and Kupffer cells contained haemozoin pigment indicative of phagocytosis of Plasmodium-infected erythrocytes. A high erythrocytic infection rate of 18% was evident in tissues and blood vessels in various organs. Furthermore, the thyroid had masses classified as thyroid carcinomas. Immunohistochemistry with anti- Plasmodium falciparum HSP70 antibody revealed positive signals in erythrocytes and intravascular leucocytes. Further microscopy analysis using a Hemacolor-stained impression smear revealed a high parasitaemia with an asynchronous infection showing all erythrocytic stages. Molecular diagnosis by PCR identified Plasmodium relictum, lineage GRW11 as the aetiological agent. The bird presented died most likely due to an acute infection as evidenced by the high blood parasitaemia, leading to major erythrocyte destruction. Further analyses of feral pigeons (n = 22) did not reveal any additional cases of Plasmodium infections.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">This study reports the first mortality associated with P. relictum lineage GRW11. The study supports previous studies, suggesting that Plasmodium infections are not frequent in pigeons. Host conditions like immunosuppression due to the tumour may have influenced the infection outcome in this fatal case. Use of anti-P. falciparum HSP70 antibody for detection of P. relictum antigens for immune assays in blood and tissue samples will be a useful tool for future studies.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Muchaamba</LastName><ForeName>Gillian</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Parasitology, Vetsuisse and Medical Faculty, University of Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wellcome Centre for Integrative Parasitology, University of Glasgow, Glasgow, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Graduate School of Cellular and Biomedical Sciences, University of Bern, Bern, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Venugopal</LastName><ForeName>Kannan</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Parasitology, Vetsuisse and Medical Faculty, University of Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wellcome Centre for Integrative Parasitology, University of Glasgow, Glasgow, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gächter</LastName><ForeName>Bettina</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Section for Poultry and Rabbit Diseases (NRGK), Institute for Food Safety and Hygiene, Vetsuisse Faculty, University of Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vogler</LastName><ForeName>Barbara</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Section for Poultry and Rabbit Diseases (NRGK), Institute for Food Safety and Hygiene, Vetsuisse Faculty, University of Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hetzel</LastName><ForeName>Udo</ForeName><Initials>U</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Veterinary Pathology,  Vetsuisse Faculty, University of Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Albini</LastName><ForeName>Sarah</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Section for Poultry and Rabbit Diseases (NRGK), Institute for Food Safety and Hygiene, Vetsuisse Faculty, University of Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Marti</LastName><ForeName>Matthias</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Parasitology, Vetsuisse and Medical Faculty, University of Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland. Matthias.Marti@uzh.ch.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wellcome Centre for Integrative Parasitology, University of Glasgow, Glasgow, UK. Matthias.Marti@uzh.ch.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>F-52204-07-01</GrantID><Agency>Stiftung für wissenschaftliche Forschung an der Universität Zürich</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>F-52204-07-01</GrantID><Agency>Stiftung für wissenschaftliche Forschung an der Universität Zürich</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D002363">Case Reports</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>02</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Malar J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101139802</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1475-2875</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010856" MajorTopicYN="Y">Columbidae</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000469" MajorTopicYN="N">parasitology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008289" MajorTopicYN="Y">Malaria, Avian</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000469" MajorTopicYN="N">parasitology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010961" MajorTopicYN="Y">Plasmodium</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="N">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000145" MajorTopicYN="N">classification</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017809" MajorTopicYN="N">Fatal Outcome</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D057805" MajorTopicYN="N">Pets</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000469" MajorTopicYN="N">parasitology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001715" MajorTopicYN="N">Bird Diseases</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000469" MajorTopicYN="N">parasitology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000473" MajorTopicYN="N">pathology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Columba livia forma domestica</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Plasmodium relictum</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Avian malaria</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Heat shock protein 70</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Histopathology</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39358742</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11446001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12936-024-05116-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12936-024-05116-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Rigal S, Dakos V, Alonso H, Auniņš A, Benkő Z, Brotons L, et al. Farmland practices are driving bird population decline across Europe. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2023;120: e2216573120.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10214186</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37186854</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>European birds of conservation concern. Populations, trends and national responsibilities. [https://www.birdlife.ch/sites/default/files/documents/European_Birds_of_Conservation_Concern.pdf]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Birds of Switzerland- Feral Pigeon Columba livia domestica [https://www.vogelwarte.ch/en/birds-of-switzerland/feral-pigeon/]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cano-Terriza D, Guerra R, Lecollinet S, Cerdà-Cuéllar M, Cabezón O, Almería S, et al. Epidemiological survey of zoonotic pathogens in feral pigeons (Columba livia var. domestica) and sympatric zoo species in Southern Spain. Comp Immunol Microbiol Infect Dis. 2015;43:22–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26616657</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haag-Wackernagel D, Bircher AJ. Ectoparasites from feral pigeons affecting humans. Dermatology. 2010;220:82–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20016127</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haag-Wackernagel D, Moch H. Health hazards posed by feral pigeons. J Infect. 2004;48:307–13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15066331</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niederehe H. Toxoplasma-Infektion bei verwilderten Tauben. Tierärztliche. Umschau. 1964;19:256–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nourani L, Baghkheirati AA, Zargar M, Karimi V, Djadid ND. Haemoproteosis and avian malaria in Columbidae and Corvidae from Iran. Vet Med Sci. 2021;7:2043–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8464302</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34240581</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prompiram P, Mongkolphan C, Poltep K, Chunchob S, Sontigun N, Chareonviriyaphap T. Baseline study of the morphological and genetic characteristics of Haemoproteus parasites in wild pigeons (Columba livia) from paddy fields in Thailand. Int J Parasitol Parasit Wildlife. 2023;21:153–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10205435</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37228837</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scaglione FE, Pregel P, Cannizzo FT, Pérez-Rodríguez AD, Ferroglio E, Bollo E. Prevalence of new and known species of haemoparasites in feral pigeons in northwest Italy. Malar J. 2015;14:99.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4350268</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25888761</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chagas C, Guimarães L, Monteiro E, Valkiūnas G, Katayama M, Santos S, et al. Hemosporidian parasites of free-living birds in the São Paulo Zoo. Brazil Parasitol Res. 2016;115:1443–52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26677094</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maharana BR, Kumar B. Pseudomalaria in a domestic pigeon: a case report. J Parasit Dis. 2017;41:295–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5339187</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28316429</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nebel C, Harl J, Pajot A, Weissenböck H, Amar A, Sumasgutner P. High prevalence and genetic diversity of Haemoproteus columbae (Haemosporida: Haemoproteidae) in feral pigeons Columba livia in Cape Town. South Africa Parasitol Res. 2020;119:447–63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6985069</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31883048</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosyadi I, Salasia SIO, Argamjav B, Sato H. Impact of subclinical Haemoproteus columbae infection on farmed domestic pigeons from Central Java (Yogyakarta), Indonesia, with special reference to changes in the hemogram. Pathogens. 2021;10:440.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8067996</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33917259</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haider M, Al-Rubaie A, Abd E, Qazaz A, Mahmood A. Prevalence of Plasmodium relictum in pigeons detected by PCR. Online J Vet Res. 2019;23:170–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>da Silva AP, Stoute S, Hauck R, Shivaprasad HL, Jerry C. A case report of avian malaria (Plasmodium spp.) in pen-reared pigeons (Columba livia). Avian Dis. 2021;65:213–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34412450</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nagarajan K, Arunkumar S, Kumar V, Venkata SRG. An occurrence of avian malaria in domestic pigeons in Tamil Nadu. India J Entomol Zool Studies. 2021;9:2285–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martínez-de la Puente J, Santiago-Alarcon D, Palinauskas V, Bensch S. Plasmodium relictum. Trends Parasitol. 2021;37:355–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32660871</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palinauskas V, Valkiūnas G, Bolshakov CV, Bensch S. Plasmodium relictum (lineage P-SGS1): effects on experimentally infected passerine birds. Exp Parasitol. 2008;120:372–80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18809402</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valkiūnas G, Ilgūnas M, Bukauskaitė D, Fragner K, Weissenböck H, Atkinson CT, et al. Characterization of Plasmodium relictum, a cosmopolitan agent of avian malaria. Malar J. 2018;17:184.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5930738</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29720195</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lalubin F, Delédevant A, Glaizot O, Christe P. Temporal changes in mosquito abundance (Culex pipiens), avian malaria prevalence and lineage composition. Parasit Vectors. 2013;6:307.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4029311</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24499594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huijben S, Schaftenaar W, Wijsman A, Paaijmans K, Takken W, Takken W, et al. Emerging pests and vector-borne diseases in Europe. In: Takken W, Knols BGJ, editors., et al., Wageningen Academic Publishers. Wageningen; 2007.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>González-Olvera M, Hernandez-Colina A, Himmel T, Eckley L, Lopez J, Chantrey J, et al. Molecular and epidemiological surveillance of Plasmodium spp. during a mortality event affecting Humboldt penguins (Spheniscus humboldti) at a zoo in the UK. Int J Parasitol Parasites Wildl. 2022;19:26–37.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9403903</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36035627</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meister SL, Wyss F, Wenker C, Hoby S, Basso WU. Avian haemosporidian parasites in captive and free-ranging, wild birds from zoological institutions in Switzerland: molecular characterization and clinical importance. Int J Parasitol Parasites Wildl. 2023;20:46–55.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9849939</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36688077</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glaizot O, Fumagalli L, Iritano K, Lalubin F, Van Rooyen J, Christe P. High prevalence and lineage diversity of avian malaria in wild populations of great tits (Parus major) and mosquitoes (Culex pipiens). PLoS ONE. 2012;7: e34964.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3323596</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22506060</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meister S, Richard O, Hoby S, Gurtner C, Basso W. Fatal avian malaria in captive Atlantic puffins (Fratercula arctica) in Switzerland. Int J Parasitol Parasites Wildl. 2021;14:97–106.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7848291</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33552896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ross R. Memoirs: with a full account of the great malaria problem and its solution. London: John Murray; 1923.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garnham PCC. Malaria parasites and other Haemosporidia. Oxford: Blackwell; 1966.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joice R, Nilsson SK, Montgomery J, Dankwa S, Egan E, Morahan B, et al. Plasmodium falciparum transmission stages accumulate in the human bone marrow. Sci Transl Med. 2014. 10.1126/scitranslmed.3008882.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4175394</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25009232</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanz S, Bandini G, Ospina D, Bernabeu M, Mariño K, Fernández-Becerra C, et al. Biosynthesis of GDP-fucose and other sugar nucleotides in the blood stages of Plasmodium falciparum. J Biol Chem. 2013;288:16506–17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3675586</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23615908</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ciloglu A, Ellis VA, Bernotienė R, Valkiūnas G, Bensch S. A new one-step multiplex PCR assay for simultaneous detection and identification of avian haemosporidian parasites. Parasitol Res. 2019;118:191–201.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30536121</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hellgren O, Waldenström J, Bensch S. A new PCR assay for simultaneous studies of Leucocytozoon, Plasmodium, and Haemoproteus from avian blood. J Parasitol. 2004;90:797–802.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15357072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pantchev A, Sting R, Bauerfeind R, Tyczka J, Sachse K. New real-time PCR tests for species-specific detection of Chlamydophila psittaci and Chlamydophila abortus from tissue samples. Vet J. 2009;181:145–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18413292</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Annaheim D, Vogler BR, Sigrist B, Vögtlin A, Hüssy D, Breitler C, et al. Screening of healthy feral pigeons (Columba livia domestica) in the City of Zurich reveals continuous circulation of pigeon Paramyxovirus-1 and a serious threat of transmission to domestic poultry. Microorganisms. 2022;10:1656.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9412584</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36014074</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ISO I: 6579–1: 2017/Amd 1: 2020—Microbiology of the Food Chain—Horizontal Method for the Detection, Enumeration and Serotyping of Salmonella—Part 1: Detection of Salmonella spp.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29803313</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kazlauskienė R, Bernotienė R, Palinauskas V, Iezhova TA, Valkiūnas G. Plasmodium relictum (lineages pSGS1 and pGRW11): complete synchronous sporogony in mosquitoes Culex pipiens pipiens. Exp Parasitol. 2013;133:454–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23337824</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palinauskas V, Žiegytė R, Šengaut J, Bernotienė R. Experimental study on primary bird co-infection with two Plasmodium relictum lineages-pSGS1 and pGRW11. Animals (Basel). 2022;12:1879.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9331599</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35892529</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valkiūnas G. Avian Malaria Parasites and other Haemosporidia. Bova Raton: CRC Press; 2004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hill CM. Anemia as a cause of death in bird malaria. Am J Epidemiol. 1942;36:143–6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pendl H, Hernández-Lara C, Kubacki J, Borel N, Albini S, Valkiūnas G. Exo-erythrocytic development of Plasmodium matutinum (lineage pLINN1) in a naturally infected roadkill fieldfare Turdus pilaris. Malar J. 2022;21:148.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9107739</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35570274</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ilgūnas M, Bukauskaitė D, Palinauskas V, Iezhova TA, Dinhopl N, Nedorost N, et al. Mortality and pathology in birds due to Plasmodium (Giovannolaia) homocircumflexum infection, with emphasis on the exoerythrocytic development of avian malaria parasites. Malar J. 2016;15:256.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4857288</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27146519</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coban C, Lee MSJ, Ishii KJ. Tissue-specific immunopathology during malaria infection. Nat Rev Immunol. 2018;18:266–78.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7097228</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29332936</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pham T-T, Lamb TJ, Deroost K, Opdenakker G, Van den Steen PE. Hemozoin in malarial complications: more questions than answers. Trends Parasitol. 2021;37:226–39.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33223096</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raffaelle G, Marchiafava E. Considerations on the relationship between exerythrocytic forms and relapse in malaria. Geneva, World Health Organization; 1965. https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/65268</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Himmel T, Harl J, Matt J, Nedorost N, Iezhova T, Ilgūnas M, et al. RNAscope in situ hybridization reveals microvascular sequestration of Plasmodium relictum pSGS1 blood stages but absence of exo-erythrocytic dormant stages during latent infection of Serinus canaria. Malar J. 2024;23:70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10924391</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38459560</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farmer JN, Moore AK. Periodicity and synchronicity of Plasmodium relictum in the pigeon. Proc Iowa Acad Sci. 1962;69:636–44.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams RB. Avian malaria: clinical and chemical pathology of Plasmodium gallinaceum in the domesticated fowl Gallus gallus. Avian Pathol. 2005;34:29–47.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15763737</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valkiūnas G, Iezhova TA. Insights into the biology of Leucocytozoon species (Haemosporida, Leucocytozoidae): why Is there slow research progress on agents of Leucocytozoonosis? Microorganisms. 2023;11:1251.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10221462</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37317225</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pigeault R, Cozzarolo CS, Choquet R, Strehler M, Jenkins T, Delhaye J, et al. Haemosporidian infection and co-infection affect host survival and reproduction in wild populations of great tits. Int J Parasitol. 2018;48:1079–87.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30391229</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dinhopl N, Mostegl MM, Richter B, Nedorost N, Maderner A, Fragner K, et al. Application of in-situ hybridization for the detection and identification of avian malaria parasites in paraffin wax-embedded tissues from captive penguins. Avian Pathol. 2011;40:315.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3145101</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21711191</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hliscs M, Nahar C, Frischknecht F, Matuschewski K. Expression profiling of Plasmodium berghei HSP70 genes for generation of bright red fluorescent parasites. PLoS ONE. 2013;8: e72771.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3754930</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24013507</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Niz M, Meibalan E, Mejia P, Ma S, Brancucci NMB, Agop-Nersesian C, et al. Plasmodium gametocytes display homing and vascular transmigration in the host bone marrow. Sci Adv. 2018. 10.1126/sciadv.aat3775.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5966192</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29806032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>