<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39362103</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1873-7072</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>463</Volume><Issue>Pt 4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Food chemistry</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Food Chem</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>On-demand removable hydrogel film derived from gallic acid-phycocyanin and polyvinyl alcohol for fruit preservation.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>141404</StartPage><MedlinePgn>141404</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.foodchem.2024.141404</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0308-8146(24)03054-1</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Postharvest spoilage of fruits accounts for significant losses ranging between 20 %-30 %, leading to considerable resource wastage and economic downturns. The development of an effective fresh-keeping packaging material is of paramount importance. This study introduces an innovative on-demand removable active fruit fresh-keeping film (GPP), created by embedding a GP (gallic acid-phycocyanin) fiber mesh hydrogel with functional properties into a polyvinyl alcohol (PVA) matrix. The resultant GPP hydrogel-based film demonstrates outstanding UV and water vapor barrier capabilities, mechanical stability, resistance to external mechanical stress, universal surface adhesion, antibacterial efficacy, and on-demand removal attributes, while being devoid of potential toxicity hazards. Utilizing grapes and blueberries as representative fruits, it is shown that the GPP hydrogel film significantly preserves the fruits' hardness, pH, total soluble solids content (TSS), and minimizes the rate of weight loss, thereby prolonging the shelf life to 13 days for grapes and 20 days for blueberries at ambient temperature. These results underscore the potential of this hydrogel-based film as an invaluable material for fruit preservation within the food industry.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gong</LastName><ForeName>Wei</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shenzhen Key Laboratory of Food Nutrition and Health, College of Chemistry and Environmental Engineering and Institute for Innovative Development of Food Industry, Shenzhen University, Shenzhen 518060, China; State Key Laboratory of Marine Food Processing and Safety Control, Dalian Polytechnic University, Dalian 116034, China; National Engineering Research Center of Seafood, Collaborative Innovation Center of Seafood Deep Processing, School of Food Science and Technology, Dalian Polytechnic University, Dalian 116034, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Ting-Qi</ForeName><Initials>TQ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shenzhen Key Laboratory of Food Nutrition and Health, College of Chemistry and Environmental Engineering and Institute for Innovative Development of Food Industry, Shenzhen University, Shenzhen 518060, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>He</LastName><ForeName>Wan-Ying</ForeName><Initials>WY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Marine Food Processing and Safety Control, Dalian Polytechnic University, Dalian 116034, China; National Engineering Research Center of Seafood, Collaborative Innovation Center of Seafood Deep Processing, School of Food Science and Technology, Dalian Polytechnic University, Dalian 116034, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Yu-Xin</ForeName><Initials>YX</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Marine Food Processing and Safety Control, Dalian Polytechnic University, Dalian 116034, China; National Engineering Research Center of Seafood, Collaborative Innovation Center of Seafood Deep Processing, School of Food Science and Technology, Dalian Polytechnic University, Dalian 116034, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hu</LastName><ForeName>Jiang-Ning</ForeName><Initials>JN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Marine Food Processing and Safety Control, Dalian Polytechnic University, Dalian 116034, China; National Engineering Research Center of Seafood, Collaborative Innovation Center of Seafood Deep Processing, School of Food Science and Technology, Dalian Polytechnic University, Dalian 116034, China. Electronic address: hujiangning2005@hotmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Food Chem</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7702639</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0308-8146</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Fruit</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Gallic acid</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Packaging film</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Phycocyanin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Polyvinyl alcohol</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper. The following are the supplementary data related to this article. Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2024.141404.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39362103</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2024.141404</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0308-8146(24)03054-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>