<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39361053</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>06</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1573-7438</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>56</Volume><Issue>8</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>03</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Tropical animal health and production</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Trop Anim Health Prod</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The effect of Vachellia eriolaba leaf meal inclusion on growth performance, blood parameters and methane gas emission in lambs fed diets containing ammoniated maize stover.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>323</StartPage><MedlinePgn>323</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">323</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s11250-024-04149-x</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The study evaluated the effect of Vachellia erioloba leaf meal in diets containing ammoniated maize stove on growth performance, methane emission and heath of growing lambs. Thirty-two female lambs were allocated to the following four dietary treatments: total mixed ration (TMR, control), 20% inclusion of untreated maize stover (UMS), 20% inclusion of ammoniated maize stover (AMS), and combined inclusion of 10% ammoniated maize stover and 10% Vachellia erioloba leaves (AMSVL). Each treatment was replicated 8 times and a lamb in an individual pen was regarded as an experimental unit in a completely randomized design. Feed intake was higher (P &lt; 0.05) in lambs fed the AMS and AMSVL diets compared to those fed UMS. Final body weights were higher in lambs fed the AMS and AMSVL diets. Both average daily gain (ADG) and feed convention ratio (FCR) were not affected by diet. In comparison with the AMS and AMSVL diets, the lambs fed the UMS diet had the highest (P &lt; 0.05) methane emission. Overall, lambs fed the control diets had the lowest (P &lt; 0.05) methane gas emission. Blood hematological values were affected by diet with the AMSVL fed lambs having the highest (P &lt; 0.05) mean platelet volume (MPV) and procalcitonin (PCT) values. Furthermore, total albumin, amylase and total bilirubin were the highest (P &lt; 0.05) in lambs fed on the AMSVL diet. Lambs fed on AMS diet had the highest (P &lt; 0.05) serum urea levels. It can be concluded that combined inclusion of ammoniated maize stover and Vachellia leaves improved feed value and lamb performance when compared to the individual inclusion of both UMS and AMS.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chelopo</LastName><ForeName>G M</ForeName><Initials>GM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Agricultural Science, Faculty of Natural Sciences and Agriculture, North-West University, P. Bag X 2046, Mmabatho, 2735, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Security and Safety Niche area, Faculty of Agriculture, Science and Technology, North-West University, P Bag X 2046, Mmabatho, 2735, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Marume</LastName><ForeName>U</ForeName><Initials>U</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1285-5797</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Agricultural Science, Faculty of Natural Sciences and Agriculture, North-West University, P. Bag X 2046, Mmabatho, 2735, South Africa. upenyu.marume@nwu.ac.za.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Security and Safety Niche area, Faculty of Agriculture, Science and Technology, North-West University, P Bag X 2046, Mmabatho, 2735, South Africa. upenyu.marume@nwu.ac.za.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Trop Anim Health Prod</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>1277355</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0049-4747</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>OP0UW79H66</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D008697">Methane</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>7664-41-7</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000641">Ammonia</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000821" MajorTopicYN="Y">Animal Feed</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003313" MajorTopicYN="Y">Zea mays</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008697" MajorTopicYN="Y">Methane</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004032" MajorTopicYN="Y">Diet</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000662" MajorTopicYN="N">veterinary</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018515" MajorTopicYN="Y">Plant Leaves</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000824" MajorTopicYN="N">Animal Nutritional Physiological Phenomena</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D034561" MajorTopicYN="N">Sheep, Domestic</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000254" MajorTopicYN="N">growth &amp; development</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000502" MajorTopicYN="N">physiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011897" MajorTopicYN="N">Random Allocation</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000641" MajorTopicYN="N">Ammonia</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000097" MajorTopicYN="N">blood</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012756" MajorTopicYN="N">Sheep</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000254" MajorTopicYN="N">growth &amp; development</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000097" MajorTopicYN="N">blood</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000502" MajorTopicYN="N">physiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Growth performance</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Haematology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Lambs</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Methane gas emission</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Serum biochemistry</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors have no relevant financial or non-financial interests to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39361053</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11449980</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11250-024-04149-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s11250-024-04149-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Abera K, Crespo O, Seid J, Mequanent F (2018) Simulating the impact of climate change on maize production in Ethiopia, East Africa. Environ Syst Res 7(1):4. 10.1186/s40068-018-0107-z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdul SB, Ahmed H, Jokthan MR, Adamu HY, Yashimi SM (2012) Effects of level of ficus (Ficus sycomorus) supplementation on voluntary feed intake, nutrient digestibility and nitrogen balance in Yankasa bucks fed urea treated maize stover basal diet Iranian. J Appl Anim Sci 2:151–155</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aluwong T, Wuyep PA, Allam L (2011) Livestock-environment interactions: methane emissions from ruminants. Afr J Biotechnol 10(8):1265–1269. 10.5897/AJB10.1117</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arora DS, Sharma RK, Chandra P (2011) Biodelignification of wheat straw and its effect on in vitro digestibility and antioxidant properties. Int Biodeterior Biodegrad 2352–358. 10.1016/j.ibiod.2010.12.009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barde RE, Aya VE, Ari MM, Musa M, Yakubu. A (2010) Performance of west African dwarf (WAD) goats fed urea-treated maize offal as supplement to natural herbage. Niger Vet J 31(3):219–223. 10.4314/nvj.v31i3.68971</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beauchemin KA, Kreuzer M, O’Mara F, McAllister TA (2008) Nutritional management for enteric methane abatement: a review. Aust J Exp Agric 48:21–27</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beigh YA, Ganai AM, Ahmad HA, Mir DM, Bhat MA, Muzamil S (2018) Blood Metabolic Profile of Lambs Fed Complete Diet Supplemented with exogenous fibrolytic enzymes cocktail. J Anim Health Prod 6(4):96. 10.17582/journal.jahp/2018/6.4.96.102</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Belanche A, Martín-García I, Jiménez E, Jonsson NN, Yañez-Ruiz DR (2021) A novel ammoniation treatment of barley as a strategy to optimize rumen pH, feed degradability and microbial protein synthesis in sheep. J Sci Food Agric 101:5541–5549. http://refhub.elsevier.com/S0377-8401(22)00148-1/sbref2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8451892</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33709464</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benchaar C, Pomar C, Chiquette J (2001) Evaluation of dietary strategies to reduce methane production in ruminants: a model-Ling approach. Can J Anim Sci 81:563–574. 10.4141/A00-119</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benchaar C, McAllister TA, Chouinard PY (2008b) Digestion, ruminal fermentation, ciliate protozoal populations, and milk production from dairy cows fed cinnamaldehyde, quebracho condensed tannin, or yucca schidigera saponin extracts. J Dairy Sci 91:4765–4777. 10.3168/jds.2008-1338</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19038952</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borjesson DL, Christopher MM, Walter MB (2000) Biochemical and hematologic reference intervals for free-ranging Desert Bighorn Sheep. J Wildl Dis 36(2):294–300. 10.7589/0090-3558-36.2.294</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10813611</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Broderick GA, Clayton MK (1997) A statistical evaluation of animal and nutritional factors influencing concentrations of milk urea nitrogen. J Dairy Sci 80:2964–2971. 10.3168/jds.s0022-0302(97)76262-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9406089</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown D, Ng’ambi J, Norris D (2018) Effect of tanniniferous Vachellia karroo leaf meal inclusion level on feed intake, digestibility and live weight gain of goats fed a Setaria verticillata grass hay-based diet. J Appl Anim Res 46(1):248–253. 10.1080/09712119.2017.1289939</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buthane TF, Motsei LE, Mnisi CM, Ravhuhali LE (2021) Effect of anhydrous ammonia gas treatment of low-quality cereal straws on chemical composition and in vitro ruminal fermentation. Range Manage Agrofor 42(1):150–156</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chelopo GM, Marume U (2022) The effect of ammoniated maize stover inclusion in diets on growth performance, physiological characteristics and meat quality in lambs. Anim Prod Sci 63(2):168–177. 10.1071/AN22045</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dayani O, Dadvar P, Afsharmanesh P (2011) Effect of dietary whole cottonseed and crude protein level on blood parameters and performance of fattening lambs. Small Ruminant Res 97:48–54. 10.1016/j.smallrumres.2011.02.007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eckard RJ, Grainger C, De Klein CAM (2010) Options for the abatement of methaneand nitrous oxide from ruminant production: a review. Livest Sci 130:47–56. 10.1016/j.livsci.2010.02.010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta RK, Kesari AN, Watal G et al (2005) Nutritional and hypoglycemic effect of fruit pulp of Annona squamosa in normal healthy and alloxan-induced diabetic rabbits. Annals Nutr Metabolism 49(6):407–413</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16230844</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang Y, Jones R, Compiani R, Grossi S, Johnson PCD, Eckersall PD, Rossi S, Jonsson CA, N.N (2022) Effects of ammonia-treated maize on growth performance of beef cattle. Anim Feed Sci Technol 290:115350. 10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2022.115350</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kabir F, Sultana MS, Shahjalal M, Khan MJ, Alam MZ (2004) Effect of protein supplementation on growth performance in female goats and sheep under grazing condition. Pakistan J Nutr 3:237–239. 10.3923/pjn.2004.237.239</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kraidees MS (2005) Influence of Urea treatment and soybean meal (urease) addition on the utilization of wheat straw by Sheep. Asian-Australasian. J Anim Sci 18(7):957–965. 10.5713/ajas.2005.957</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kraiem K, Abdouli H (1991) Goodrich Comparison of the effects of urea and ammonia treatments of wheat straw on intake, digestibility and performance of sheep. Livest Prod Sci 29:311–321</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu JX, Yao J, Yan B, Yu JQ, Shi ZQ (2001) Effects of mulberry leaves to replace rapeseed meal on performance of sheep feeding on ammoniated rice straw diet. Small Ruminant Res 39:131–136. 10.1016/s0921-4488</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11182305</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lynch JPL, O’Kiely P, Murphy R, Doyle EM (2014) Changes in chemical composition and digestibility of three maize stover components digested by white-rot fungi. J Anim Physiol Anim Nutr 98(4):731–738. 10.1111/jpn.12131</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24112093</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahesh MS, Mohini M (2013) Biological treatment of crop residues for ruminant feeding: a review. Afr J Biotechnol 12(27):4221–4231. 10.5897/AJB2012.2940</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Makkar HPS (2003) Quantification of tannins in tree and shrub foliage: a laboratory manual. Joint FAO/IAEA, Division of Nuclear Techniques in Food and Agriculture, Dordrecht: Kluwer Academic</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marume U, Chimonyo M, Dzama K (2012) Influence of dietary supplementation with Vachellia karroo on experimental haemonchosis in indigenous Xhosa lop-eared goats of. South Afr Livest Sci 144:132–139. 10.1016/j.livsci.2011.11.007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Merck, Manual (2012) Haematologic reference ranges. Merck veterinary manual. Retrieved from http://www.merckmanuals.com</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Metawi H, Eissa M, Anwar M, Ghobashy H, Saber A, El-Wakeel S, Sadek MW, Abd Elgawad M (2017) Potential of tannin ferrous plants to improve efficiency of sheep production in dry areas. Egypt J Sheep Goat Sci 12(2):35–45. 10.21608/ejsgs.2017.26318</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mlambo V, Mould FL, Sikosana JLN, Smith T, Owen E, Mueller-Har-vey I (2008) Chemical composition and in vitro fermentation of tannin-rich tree fruits. Anim Feed Sci Technol 140:402–417. 10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2007.03.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mnisi CM, Mlambo V (2017) Influence of harvesting site on chemical composition and potential protein value of Vachellia erioloba, A. Nilotica and Ziziphus mucronata leaves for ruminants. J Anim Physiol Anim Nutr 101:994–1003. 10.1111/jpn.12535</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27439886</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Montoya-Flores MD, Molina-Botero IC, Arango J, Romano-Muñoz JL, Solorio-Sánchez FJ, Aguilar-Pérez CF, Ku-Vera JS (2020) Effect of dried leaves of Leucaena leucocephala on rumen fermentation, rumen microbial population, and enteric methane production in crossbred heifers. Animals 10(300): 1–17. 10.3390/ani10020300</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7070482</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32069951</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ngongoni NT, Mapiye C, Mwale M, Mupeta B, Chimonyo M (2009) Sunflower based rations for small-medium milk producing dairy cows. Pakistan J Nutr 8(4):377–383. 10.3923/pjn.2009.377.383</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ningrat RWS, Zain M, Suryani E, Suryani H (2018) Effects of supplementation of different sources of tannins on nutrient digestibility, methane production and daily weight gain of beef cattle fed on ammoniated oil palm frond based diet. Int J Zoological Res 14(1):8–13. 10.3923/ijzr.2018.8.13</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olafadehan OA (2011) Change in hematological and biochemical diagnostic parameters of Red Sokoto goats fed tannin-rich Pterocarpus erinaceus forage diets. Veterinarski Arhiv 81:471–483</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paswan JK, Kumar K, Kumar S, Chandramoni A, Kumar A, Kumar D, Kumar A (2016) Effect of feeding Vachellia nilotica pod meal on hematobiochemical profile and fecal egg count in goats. Vet World 9(12):1400–1406. 10.14202/vetworld.2016.1400-1406</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5234054</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28096612</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raghuvansi SKS, Prasad R, Tripathi MK, Mishra AS, Chaturvedi OH, Misra AK, Sarasat BL, Jakhmola RC (2007) Effect of complete feed blocks or grazing and supplementation of lambs on performance, nutrient utilization, and rumen fermentation and rumen microbial enzymes. Animal 1:221–226. 10.1017/S1751731107284058</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22444287</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rani S, Rasyid R, Desmawati D (2018) High intake of green tea decreased hemoglobin and hematocrit levels in Rattus novergicus strain wistar albino. Nternational J Res Med Sci Technol 6(11):3688–3692. 10.18203/2320-6012.ijrms20184431</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ravhuhali1 KE, Mlambo V, Beyene TS, Palamuleni LG (2020) Effects of soil type on density of trees and nutritive value of tree leaves in selected communal areas of South Africa. S Afr J Anim Sci 50. 10.4314/sajas.v50i1.10</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sallam SMA, EL- Gendy MN, Anwar MM, Fahmy WG, El-Zarkouny SZ, Hashem NM, El-Din ANM, Attia MFA, Wakeel EA, Zeitoun MM (2017) Productive and Reproductive Traits of Sheep Fed Vachellia Saligna leaves-based diets. Int J Agric Environ Biotechnol 2(6) 2456 – 1878. 10.22161/ijeab/2.6.9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Solaiman S, Thomas J, Dupre Y, Min BR, Gurung N, Terrill TH, Haenlein GFW (2010) Effect of feeding sericea lespedeza (Lespedeza cuneata) on growth performance, blood metabolites, and carcass characteristics of Kiko crossbred male kids. Small Ruminant Res 93:149–156. 10.1016/j.smallrumres.2010.05.015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sorg D (2022) Measuring livestock CH4 emissions with the laser methane detector. Rev Methane 1:38–57. 10.3390/methane1010004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soul W, Mupangwa J, Muchenje V, Mphendolo TC (2019) Biochemical indices and heamtological parameters of goats’ fed lablab purpureus and Vigna unguiculata as supplements to a Chloris gayana basal diet. Veterinary Anim Sci 8:100073. 10.1016/j.vas.2019.100073</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7386721</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32734090</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Souzza MA, Detmann E, Paulino MF, Sampaio CB, Lazzarini I, Filho SV (2010) Intake, digestibility and rumen dynamics of neutral detergent fibre in cattle fed low quality tropical forage and supplement with nitrogen and/or starch. Trop Anim Health Prod 42:1299–1310. 10.1007/s11250-010-9566-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20386983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spanghero M, Mason F, Zanfi C, Nikulina A (2017) Effect of diets differing in protein concentration (low vs medium) and nitrogen source (urea vs soybean meal) on in vitro rumen fermentation and on performance of finishing Italian simmental bulls. Livest Sci 196:14–21. 10.1016/j.livsci.2016.12.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Statistical Analysis Systems (SAS) (2012) Proprietary Software Release 9.3. Statistical Analysis Systems Institute, Inc., Cary</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sundstoel F, Coxworth E, Mowat DN (1978) Improving the nutritive value of straw and other low quality roughage by treatment with ammonia. World Anim Rev 26:13–21</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tavendale MH, Meagher LP, Pacheco D, Walker N, Attwood GT, Sivakumaran S (2005) Methane production from in vitro rumen incubations with Lotus pedunculatus and Medicago sativa, and effects of extractable condensed tannin fractions on methanogenesis. Anim Feed Sci Technolnology 123–124(1):403–419. 10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2005.04.037</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Undi M, Kawonga KC, Musendo RM (2001) Nutritive value of maize stover/pasture legume mixtures as dry season supplementation for sheep. Small Ruminant Res 40:261–267. 10.1016/S0921-4488(01)00175-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11323211</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waghorn GC, Shelton ID, McNabb WC (1994) Effects of condensed tannins in Lotus pedunculatus on its nutritive value for sheep. 1. Non-nitrogenous aspects. J Agric Sci 123:99–107. 10.1017/S0021859600067824</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wan Zahari M, Abu Hassan O, Wong HK, Liang JB (2003) Utilization of oil palm frond-based diets for beef and dairy production in Malaysia. Asian-Australasian J Anim Sci 16(4):625–634. 10.5713/ajas.2003.625</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yadete GK (2014) Effect of wheat straw urea treatment and Leucaena leucocephala foliage hay supplementation on intake, digestibility, nitrogen balance and growth of lambs. Int J Livest Prod 6(4):88–96. 10.5897/IJLP12.04</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang X, Medrano RF, Wang M, Beauchemin KA, Ma Z, Wang R, Wen J, Bernard LA, Tan Z (2019) Effects of urea plus nitrate pretreated rice straw and corn oil supplementation on fiber digestibility, nitrogen balance, rumen fermentation, microbiota and methane emissions in goats. J Anim Sci Biotechnol 10(6):1–10. 10.1186/s40104-019-0312-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6343244</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30680191</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao MD, Di LF, Tang ZY, Jiang W, Li CY (2019) Effect of tannins and cellulose on growth performance, nutrients digestibility, blood profiles, intestinal morphology and carcass characteristics in Hu sheep. Asian-Australasian J Anim Sci 32:1540–1547. 10.5713/ajas.18.0901</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6718903</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31010984</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao Y, Nan X, Yang L, Zheng S, Jiang L, Xiong B (2020) A review of enteric methane emission measurement techniques in ruminants. Animals 10:1004. 10.3390/ani10061004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7341254</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32521767</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>