<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39366617</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>05</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1879-0003</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>281</Volume><Issue>Pt 1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>02</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>International journal of biological macromolecules</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Int J Biol Macromol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Physicochemical and biological characterization of the lipid particles with bovine serum albumin corona.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>136223</StartPage><MedlinePgn>136223</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2024.136223</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0141-8130(24)07032-6</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Diacylglycerol-based nanoparticles are promising bioactive delivery systems. However, limited understanding of their interaction with biological entities restricts their clinical use. This study investigated the protein corona formed on medium and long chain diacylglycerol (MLCD)-based solid lipid nanoparticles (NPs) modified by Polyoxethylene stearate (PEG) and compared to glyceryl tristearate (TG) and cetyl palmitate (CP) nanoparticles. Bovine serum albumin (BSA) formed corona with MLCD NPs through hydrophobic interactions and hydrogen bonding, contributing to a decrease in α-helix, an increase in β-sheet and a change in the microenvironment of Tyr residues. Owing to higher lipid hydrophilicity, MLCD NPs showed a much lower affinity for BSA than TG and CP NPs, and the binding constant with BSA was increased for larger NPs. PEG modification and the protein corona reduced the uptake of NPs by macrophages but exerted little influence on B16 cell. Among the NPs with different lipid core, the MLCD NPs showed a lower macrophages cell uptake but higher B16 cell uptake, suggesting a longer circulation time in blood but higher cancer cell internalization. This work shed light on the interactions between MLCD NPs and proteins, which is significant for application as nanocarriers with improved biological efficacy.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024. Published by Elsevier B.V.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Canfeng</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>JNU-UPM International Joint Laboratory on Plant Oil Processing and Safety, Department of Food Science and Engineering, Jinan University, Guangzhou 510632, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alfredo</LastName><ForeName>Ying Ye</ForeName><Initials>YY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>JNU-UPM International Joint Laboratory on Plant Oil Processing and Safety, Department of Food Science and Engineering, Jinan University, Guangzhou 510632, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lee</LastName><ForeName>Yee Ying</ForeName><Initials>YY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Science, Monash University Malaysia, Bandar Sunway 47500, Selangor, Malaysia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tan</LastName><ForeName>Chin Ping</ForeName><Initials>CP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Technology, Faculty of Food Science and Technology, Universiti Putra Malaysia, 43300, Selangor, Malaysia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Yong</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>JNU-UPM International Joint Laboratory on Plant Oil Processing and Safety, Department of Food Science and Engineering, Jinan University, Guangzhou 510632, China. Electronic address: twyong@jnu.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Qiu</LastName><ForeName>Chaoying</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>JNU-UPM International Joint Laboratory on Plant Oil Processing and Safety, Department of Food Science and Engineering, Jinan University, Guangzhou 510632, China. Electronic address: tcyqiu@jnu.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>02</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Int J Biol Macromol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7909578</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0141-8130</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Cellular uptake</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Lipid composition</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">MLCD nanoparticles</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Particle size</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Protein corona</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare the following financial interests/personal relationships which may be considered as potential competing interests: Yong Wang reports financial support was provided by Guangdong Basic and Applied Basic Research Foundation. Chaoying Qiu reports financial support was provided by Department of Science and Technology of Guangdong Province under grant. Chaoying Qiu reports was provided by Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities. If there are other authors, they declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>14</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39366617</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2024.136223</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0141-8130(24)07032-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>