<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39363479</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>04</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1615-9314</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>47</Volume><Issue>19</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of separation science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Sep Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Development of an Untargeted Method for the Analysis of the Volatile Profile of Onions via Solid-Phase Microextraction Arrow-Headspace-Gas Chromatography-Mass Spectrometry Using Design of Experiments.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e202400305</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e202400305</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jssc.202400305</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The distinctive aroma of onions, consisting primarily of sulfur-containing compounds, is one of the reasons for the popularity of the vegetable. The rapid enzymatic and chemical reactions that occur after the destruction of onion bulb tissue render the analysis of the volatile profile challenging. Therefore, sample preparation is a crucial step in the analysis of the onion volatilome, but it often does not receive the necessary attention in the literature. In this work, we focused on two aspects: Firstly, we compared different sample preparation approaches to maximize the volatile yield and to enable the description of the onion volatile profile as it would emerge after a solid-phase microextraction (SPME) Arrow sampling procedure. For headspace (HS)-gas chromatography-mass spectrometry analysis, onion juice with the addition of an ammonium sulfate solution proved to be the best option. Secondly, we optimized the HS sampling and desorption parameters (enrichment time, enrichment temperature, agitator speed, desorption time) for onion volatiles using the efficient design of experiments (DoE) approach. The optimal conditions for the analysis with HS-SPME Arrow were an enrichment time of 75 min at 60°C with an agitator speed of 713 rpm and a desorption time of 120 s.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Journal of Separation Science published by Wiley‐VCH GmbH.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Böckstiegel</LastName><ForeName>Lea</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0001-1750-3232</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Safety and Quality of Fruit and Vegetables, Max Rubner-Institut, Federal Research Institute of Nutrition and Food, Karlsruhe, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Schaumann</LastName><ForeName>Theresa</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Safety and Quality of Fruit and Vegetables, Max Rubner-Institut, Federal Research Institute of Nutrition and Food, Karlsruhe, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Egert</LastName><ForeName>Björn</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0006-0625-1531</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Safety and Quality of Fruit and Vegetables, Max Rubner-Institut, Federal Research Institute of Nutrition and Food, Karlsruhe, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kulling</LastName><ForeName>Sabine E</ForeName><Initials>SE</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9956-2702</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Safety and Quality of Fruit and Vegetables, Max Rubner-Institut, Federal Research Institute of Nutrition and Food, Karlsruhe, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Weinert</LastName><ForeName>Christoph H</ForeName><Initials>CH</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1015-8667</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Safety and Quality of Fruit and Vegetables, Max Rubner-Institut, Federal Research Institute of Nutrition and Food, Karlsruhe, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>2819OE019</GrantID><Agency>BMEL</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>J Sep Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101088554</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1615-9306</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D055549">Volatile Organic Compounds</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D052617" MajorTopicYN="Y">Solid Phase Microextraction</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008401" MajorTopicYN="Y">Gas Chromatography-Mass Spectrometry</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019697" MajorTopicYN="Y">Onions</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055549" MajorTopicYN="Y">Volatile Organic Compounds</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="N">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">GC‐MS</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SPME arrow</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">design of experiments</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">onions</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">volatilomics</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39363479</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jssc.202400305</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>E. Block and E. M. Calvey, Sulfur Compounds in Foods (Washington, D.C.: American Chemical Society, 1994) 63–79.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. M. Løkke, M. Edelenbos, E. Larsen, and A. Feilberg, “Investigation of Volatiles Emitted From Freshly Cut Onions (Allium cepa L.) by Real Time Proton‐Transfer Reaction‐Mass Spectrometry (PTR‐MS),” Sensors 12 (2012): 16060–16076.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Ferary and J. Auger, “What is the True Odour of Cut Allium? Complementarity of Various Hyphenated Methods: Gas Chromatography Mass Spectrometry and High‐Performance Liquid Chromatography Mass Spectrometry With Particle Beam and Atmospheric Pressure Ionization Interfaces in Sulphenic Acids Rearrangement Components Discrimination,” Journal of Chromatography A 750 (1996): 63–74.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Granvogl and P. Schieberle, Developments in Food Science, eds. W. L. P. Bredie and M. A. Petersen (Amsterdam, NL: Elsevier, 2006), 359–362.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Block, D. Putman, and S. H. Zhao, “Allium Chemistry: GC‐MS Analysis of Thiosulfinates and Related Compounds From Onion, Leek, Scallion, Shallot, Chive, and Chinese Chive,” Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry 40 (1992): 2431–2438.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. S. Cantrell, J. T. Seale, S. A. Arispe, and O. M. McDougal, “Determination of Organosulfides From Onion Oil,” Foods 9 (2020): 884.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Granvogl, M. Christlbauer, and P. Schieberle, “Quantitation of the Intense Aroma Compound 3‐mercapto‐2‐methylpentan‐1‐ol in Raw and Processed Onions (Allium cepa) of Different Origins and in Other Allium Varieties Using a Stable Isotope Dilution Assay,” Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry 52 (2004): 2797–2802.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Ferreira, R. Perestrelo, M. Caldeira, and J. S. Camara, “Characterization of Volatile Substances in Apples From Rosaceae Family by Headspace Solid‐Phase Microextraction Followed by GC‐qMS,” Journal of Separation Science 32 (2009): 1875–1888.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Ceccarelli, B. Farneti, I. Khomenko, et al., “Nectarine Volatilome Response to Fresh‐Cutting and Storage,” Postharvest Biology and Technology 159 (2020): 111020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Q. Zhou, S. Liu, Y. Liu, and H. Song, “Comparative Analysis of Volatiles of 15 Brands of Extra‐Virgin Olive Oils Using Solid‐Phase Micro‐Extraction and Solvent‐Assisted Flavor Evaporation,” Molecules 24 (2019): 1512.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Fernandes, A. Gois, F. Mendes, R. Perestrelo, S. Medina, and J. S. Câmara, “Typicality Assessment of Onions (Allium cepa) From Different Geographical Regions Based on the Volatile Signature and Chemometric Tools,” Foods 9 (2020): 375.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Järvenpää, Z. Zhang, R. Huopalahti, and J. W. King, “Determination of Fresh Onion (Allium cepa L.) Volatiles by Solid Phase Microextraction Combined With Gas Chromatography‐Mass Spectrometry,” Journal of Food Investigation and Research 207 (1998): 39–43.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. D'Auria and R. Racioppi, “HS‐SPME‐GC‐MS Analysis of Onion (Allium cepa L.) and Shallot (Allium ascalonicum L.),” Food Research 1 (2017): 161–165.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Machová, T. Bajer, D. Šilha, K. Ventura, and P. Bajerová, “Release of Volatile Compounds From Sliced Onion Analysed by Gas Chromatography Coupled to Mass Spectrometry and Its Antimicrobial Activity,” Journal of Food and Nutrition Research 58 (2019): 393–400.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Taglienti, F. Araniti, A. Piscopo, and A. Tiberini, “Characterization of Volatile Organic Compounds in ‘rossa Di Tropea’ onion by Means of Headspace Solid‐Phase Microextraction Gas Chromatography–Mass Spectrometry (Hs/spme gc–ms) and Sensory Analysis,” Agronomy 11 (2021): 874.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. S. Herrington, G. A. Gómez‐Ríos, C. Myers, G. Stidsen, and D. S. Bell, “Hunting Molecules in Complex Matrices With SPME Arrows: A Review,” Separations 7 (2020): 12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Asikin, K. Shimoda, M. Takeuchi, et al., “Free and Glycosidically Bound Volatile Compounds in Okinawan Pineapple (Ananas comosus),” Applied Sciences 12 (2022): 9522.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>I. Šikuten, P. Štambuk, J. Karoglan Kontić, E. Maletić, I. Tomaz, and D. Preiner, “Optimization of SPME‐Arrow‐GC/MS Method for Determination of Free and Bound Volatile Organic Compounds From Grape Skins,” Molecules 26 (2021): 7409.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Pellacani, M. Cocchi, C. Durante, and L. Strani, “Exploring the Effect of Different Storage Conditions on the Aroma Profile of Bread by Using Arrow‐SPME GC‐MS and Chemometrics,” Molecules 28 (2023): 3587.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Zeng, Y. Wang, H. Han, Y. Cao, and B. Wang, “Changes in Key Aroma Compounds and Esterase Activity of Monascus‐Fermented Cheese Across a 30‐Day Ripening Period,” Foods 11 (2022): 4026.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Y. Lee, W. S. Kim, Y. Y. Lee, Y. S. Choi, H. Choi, and H. W. Jang, “Solid‐Phase Microextraction Arrow for the Volatile Organic Compounds in Soy Sauce,” Journal of Separation Science 42 (2019): 2942–2948.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. S. Aurum, T. Imaizumi, M. Thammawong, et al., “Predicting Indonesian Coffee Origins Using Untargeted SPME − GCMS ‐ based Volatile Compounds Fingerprinting and Machine Learning Approaches,” European Food Research and Technology 249 (2023): 2137–2149.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A.‐M. Jagatić Korenika, D. Preiner, I. Tomaz, M. Skendrović Babojelić, and A. Jeromel, “Aroma Profile of Monovarietal Pét‐Nat Ciders: The Role of Croatian Traditional Apple Varieties,” Horticulturae 8 (2022): 689.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Mondy, D. Duplat, J. P. Christides, I. Arnault, and J. Auger, “Aroma Analysis of Fresh and Preserved Onions and Leek by Dual Solid‐Phase Microextraction–Liquid Extraction and Gas Chromatography–Mass Spectrometry,” Journal of Chromatography A 963 (2002): 89–93.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Kremr, P. Bajerová, T. Bajer, A. Eisner, M. Adam, and K. Ventura, “Using Headspace Solid‐Phase Microextraction for Comparison of Volatile Sulphur Compounds of Fresh Plants Belonging to Families Alliaceae and Brassicaceae,” Journal of Food Science and Technology 52 (2015): 5727–5735.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>I. Arnault, N. Mondy, F. Cadoux, and J. Auger, “Possible Interest of Various Sample Transfer Techniques for Fast Gas Chromatography–mass Spectrometric Analysis of True Onion Volatiles,” Journal of Chromatography A 896 (2000): 117–124.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Xie, Q. Wu, S. Wei, et al., “Optimization of Headspace Solid‐Phase Micro‐Extraction Conditions (HS‐SPME) and Identification of Major Volatile Aroma‐Active Compounds in Chinese Chive (Allium Tuberosum Rottler),” Molecules 27 (2022): 2425.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Hüffer, X. L. Osorio, M. A. Jochmann, B. Schilling, and T. C. Schmidt, “Multi‐Walled Carbon Nanotubes as Sorptive Material for Solventless in‐Tube Microextraction (ITEX2)—A Factorial Design Study,” Analytical and Bioanalytical Chemistry 405 (2013): 8387–8395.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Lioupi, I. Sampsonidis, C. Virgiliou, et al., “Optimisation of the HS‐SPME/GC‐MS Approach by Design of Experiments Combined With Chemometrics for the Classification of Cretan Virgin Olive Oils,” Metabolites 12 (2022): 114.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Liu, Y. Su, and Y. Guo, “Determination of Highly Volatile Compounds in Fresh Onion (Allium cepa L.) by Room‐Temperature Enrichment Headspace‐Trap Coupled to Cryotrapping GC–MS,” Separation Science Plus 1 (2018): 530–538.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. T. Weldegergis, A. G. J. Tredoux, and A. M. Crouch, “Application of a Headspace Sorptive Extraction Method for the Analysis of Volatile Components in South African Wines,” Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry 55 (2007): 8696–8702.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. J. Rodrı́guez‐Bencomo, J. E. Conde, F. Garcı́a‐Montelongo, and J. P. Pérez‐Trujillo, “Determination of Major Compounds in Sweet Wines by Headspace Solid‐Phase Microextraction and Gas Chromatography,” Journal of Chromatography A 991 (2003): 13–22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U. Dziekońska‐Kubczak, K. Pielech‐Przybylska, P. Patelski, and M. Balcerek, “Development of the Method for Determination of Volatile Sulfur Compounds (VSCs) in Fruit Brandy With the Use of HS‐SPME/GC‐MS,” Molecules 25 (2020): 1232.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Metrani, G. K. Jayaprakasha, and B. S. Patil, “Optimization of Experimental Parameters and Chemometrics Approach to Identify Potential Volatile Markers in Seven Cucumis Melo Varieties Using HS–SPME–GC–MS,” Food Analytical Methods 15 (2022): 607–624.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Zhang, P. Zhan, H. Tian, Z. Wei, and P. Wang, “Optimization of HS‐SPME Using Artificial Neural Network and Response Surface Methodology in Combination With Experimental Design for Determination of Volatile Components by Gas Chromatography‐Mass Spectrometry in Korla Pear Juice,” Food Analytical Methods 11 (2018): 2218–2228.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Xiao, Q. Wu, Y. Niu, et al., “Optimization of Headspace Solid‐Phase Micro‐Extraction and Its Application in Analysis of Volatile Compounds in Cherry Tomato by Gas Chromatography,” Food Analytical Methods 10 (2017): 596–609.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Cecchi, F. Ieri, P. Vignolini, N. Mulinacci, and A. Romani, “Characterization of Volatile and Flavonoid Composition of Different Cuts of Dried Onion (Allium cepa L.) by HS‐SPME‐GC‐MS, HS‐SPME‐GC×GC‐TOF and HPLC‐DAD,” Molecules 25 (2020): 408.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Nandakumar, G. Eyres, D. Burritt, B. Kebede, M. Leus, and I. Oey, “Impact of Pulsed Electric Fields on the Volatile Compounds Produced in Whole Onions (Allium cepa and Allium fistulosum),” Foods 7 (2018): 183.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. T. Kebede, T. Grauwet, L. Mutsokoti, et al., “Comparing the Impact of High Pressure High Temperature and Thermal Sterilization on the Volatile Fingerprint of Onion, Potato, Pumpkin and Red Beet,” Food Research International 56 (2014): 218–225.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. S. Günther, A. J. Matich, K. B. Marsh, and L. Nicolau, “Development of a Quantitative Method for Headspace Analysis of Methylsulfanyl‐Volatiles From Kiwifruit Tissue,” Food Research International 44 (2011): 1331–1338.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Canac‐Arteaga, F. Begnaud, C. Viallon, and J. L. Berdagué, “Effect of Adding Hygroscopic Salts on the Analysis of the Volatile Fraction of Cheese,” Analysis 28 (2000): 973–979.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. M. Haynes, D. R. Lide, and T. J. Bruno, CRC Handbook of Chemistry and Physics (Boca Raton, FL: CRC Press LLC, 2014), p.‐4–48.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Block, A. J. Dane, and R. B. Cody, “Crushing Garlic and Slicing Onions: Detection of Sulfenic Acids and Other Reactive Organosulfur Intermediates From Garlic and Other Alliums Using Direct Analysis in Real‐Time Mass Spectrometry (DART‐MS),” Phosphorus, Sulfur, and Silicon and the Related Elements 186 (2011): 1085–1093.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Li, Y. Dadmohammadi, and A. Abbaspourrad, “Flavor Components, Precursors, Formation Mechanisms, Production and Characterization Methods: Garlic, Onion, and Chili Pepper Flavors,” Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition 62 (2021): 8265–8287.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>