<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39362117</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1873-376X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>1247</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>20</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of chromatography. B, Analytical technologies in the biomedical and life sciences</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Chromatogr B Analyt Technol Biomed Life Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Thin film microextraction of apixaban from plasma based on the covalent organic framework coated on a mesh prior to liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>124302</StartPage><MedlinePgn>124302</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.jchromb.2024.124302</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S1570-0232(24)00311-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>In this research, a new covalent organic framework was synthesized and utilized as a coating in thin film microextraction for the extraction of apixaban from plasma samples. This coating was applied to the mesh modified through immersion in a HF solution. The extracted drug was then analyzed using liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry. By combining the high specific surface area and selectivity of the covalent organic framework, along with integrating the innovative thin film microextraction method and a sensitive analysis system, an efficient analytical approach was achieved. The target analyte was preconcentrated and extracted by immersing of the covalent organic framework-coated mesh as an absorbent into the biological sample. Subsequently, a sonication process was conducted for a specific duration. Following this, the extracted analyte was desorbed using acetonitrile as the elution solvent. The effective parameters of the proposed technique were optimized by using "one-parameter-at-a-time" strategy and the optimal conditions were selected. By integrating the developed method notable achievements were made in the terms of low limits of detection and quantification (0.17 and 0.56 µg/L, respectively), a wide linear range (0.05-250 µg/L), intra- and inter day precisions (with relative standard deviations of ≤14 %), as well as satisfactory extraction recoveries (53 % and 54 % in plasma and deionized water, respectively). Hence, it can be concluded that the introduced technique exhibits high efficiency and reliability when applied to biological samples.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Changizi Kecheklou</LastName><ForeName>Aysan</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Analytical Chemistry, Faculty of Chemistry, University of Tabriz, Tabriz, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Afshar Mogaddam</LastName><ForeName>Mohammad Reza</ForeName><Initials>MR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food and Drug Safety Research Center, Tabriz University of Medical Sciences, Tabriz, Iran; Chemistry and Chemical Engineering Department, Khazar University, 41 Mehseti Street, Baku AZ1096, Azerbaijan; Pharmaceutical Analysis Research Center, Tabriz University of Medical Sciences, Tabriz, Iran. Electronic address: Afsharmogaddam@tbzmed.ac.ir.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sorouraddin</LastName><ForeName>Saeed Mohammad</ForeName><Initials>SM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Analytical Chemistry, Faculty of Chemistry, University of Tabriz, Tabriz, Iran. Electronic address: ssorureddin@tabrizu.ac.ir.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Farajzadeh</LastName><ForeName>Mir Ali</ForeName><Initials>MA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Analytical Chemistry, Faculty of Chemistry, University of Tabriz, Tabriz, Iran; Engineering Faculty, Near East University, 99138 Nicosia, North Cyprus, Mersin 10, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fathi</LastName><ForeName>Ali Akbar</ForeName><Initials>AA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Analytical Chemistry, Faculty of Chemistry, University of Tabriz, Tabriz, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>20</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>J Chromatogr B Analyt Technol Biomed Life Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101139554</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1570-0232</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Apixaban</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Covalent organic framework</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Plasma</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Thin film microextraction</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39362117</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jchromb.2024.124302</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S1570-0232(24)00311-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>