<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39368760</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>05</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1872-7573</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>03</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of ethnopharmacology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Ethnopharmacol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Traditional uses, phytochemical constituents, pharmacological properties, and quality control of Pseudostellaria heterophylla (Miq.) Pax.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>118871</StartPage><MedlinePgn>118871</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.jep.2024.118871</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0378-8741(24)01170-X</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="ETHNOPHARMACOLOGIC RELEVANCE" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Pseudostellaria heterophylla (Miq.) Pax belongs to the Caryophyllaceae family, which is widely used in traditional Chinese medicine in Asia. P. heterophylla was first documented in the classical text Bencao Congxin, also known as "Haier Shen". As a renowned folk medicine with a long history of medicinal application in China, this plant is frequently employed to address spleen deficiency and fatigue, loss of appetite, and weakness after illness. In recent years, P. heterophylla has gained significant global attention as an important medicinal plant, attributable to its pharmacological activities on the immune and endocrine systems, as well as its diverse applications.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="AIM OF THE WORK" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">This review aims to deliver a comprehensive and analytical overview of the ethnopharmacology, phytochemistry, pharmacology, pharmacokinetics, toxicology, and quality control of P. heterophylla, while also offering novel insights and opportunities for future research.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIALS AND METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Relevant information regarding P. heterophylla was gathered from various databases, including Web of Science, PubMed, ACS Publications, Google Scholar, Baidu Scholar, and CNKI, in addition to The Catalogue of Life, the Flora of China database, and The World Flora Online. All published articles in multiple languages have been included and properly cited. The chemical structure of the compound was illustrated utilizing ChemDraw 19.0 software.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">P. heterophylla has been traditionally employed to address a range of ailments, including cancer, cardiovascular diseases, diabetes, and respiratory disorders. More than 289 active constituents have been identified in P. heterophylla, comprising cyclic peptides, polysaccharides, saponins, alkaloids, flavonoids, nucleosides, and amino acids. Pharmacological investigations have demonstrated that P. heterophylla and its active constituents exhibit a broad spectrum of biological activities, including anti-cancer, immunomodulatory, antioxidant, hypoglycemic, anti-inflammatory effects, modulation of intestinal flora, enhancement of cognitive function, and inhibition of tyrosine kinase activity. Furthermore, it is extensively utilized in the functional food and cosmetics industries.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">As a dual-purpose resource for both food and medicine, P. heterophylla possesses significant health care functions and considerable edible and medicinal value, with promising prospects for future development and utilization. However, numerous investigations into the biological activities of P. heterophylla are primarily focused on its extracts and bioactive constituents, and the mechanisms underlying the actions of these extracts and components remain unclear, with a dearth of studies on clinical efficacy and safety. Consequently, further detailed in vitro and in vivo studies investigating the mechanisms of action of pure active compounds of P. heterophylla are warranted, along with additional clinical investigations to ascertain the safety and efficacy of the plant for human use.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024. Published by Elsevier B.V.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lei</LastName><ForeName>Ziwen</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shaanxi Key Laboratory of Chinese Medicine Fundamentals and New Drugs Research, School of Pharmacy, Shaanxi University of Chinese Medicine, Xi'an 712046, Shaanxi, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Luan</LastName><ForeName>Fei</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shaanxi Key Laboratory of Chinese Medicine Fundamentals and New Drugs Research, School of Pharmacy, Shaanxi University of Chinese Medicine, Xi'an 712046, Shaanxi, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zou</LastName><ForeName>Junbo</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shaanxi Key Laboratory of Chinese Medicine Fundamentals and New Drugs Research, School of Pharmacy, Shaanxi University of Chinese Medicine, Xi'an 712046, Shaanxi, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Xiaofei</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shaanxi Key Laboratory of Chinese Medicine Fundamentals and New Drugs Research, School of Pharmacy, Shaanxi University of Chinese Medicine, Xi'an 712046, Shaanxi, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhai</LastName><ForeName>Bingtao</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shaanxi Key Laboratory of Chinese Medicine Fundamentals and New Drugs Research, School of Pharmacy, Shaanxi University of Chinese Medicine, Xi'an 712046, Shaanxi, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xin</LastName><ForeName>Bao</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Public Health, Shaanxi University of Chinese Medicine, Xi'an 712046, Shaanxi, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sun</LastName><ForeName>Jing</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shaanxi Key Laboratory of Chinese Medicine Fundamentals and New Drugs Research, School of Pharmacy, Shaanxi University of Chinese Medicine, Xi'an 712046, Shaanxi, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Guo</LastName><ForeName>Dongyan</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shaanxi Key Laboratory of Chinese Medicine Fundamentals and New Drugs Research, School of Pharmacy, Shaanxi University of Chinese Medicine, Xi'an 712046, Shaanxi, P. R. China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Jingyuan</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shaanxi Key Laboratory of Chinese Medicine Fundamentals and New Drugs Research, School of Pharmacy, Shaanxi University of Chinese Medicine, Xi'an 712046, Shaanxi, P. R. China. Electronic address: wangjingyuan@sntcm.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shi</LastName><ForeName>Yajun</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shaanxi Key Laboratory of Chinese Medicine Fundamentals and New Drugs Research, School of Pharmacy, Shaanxi University of Chinese Medicine, Xi'an 712046, Shaanxi, P. R. China. Electronic address: 2051004@sntcm.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Ireland</Country><MedlineTA>J Ethnopharmacol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7903310</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0378-8741</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Ethnopharmacology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pharmacokinetics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pharmacology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Phytochemistry</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pseudostellaria heterophylla (Miq.) Pax</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Quality control</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of Competing Interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper. The authors declare the following financial interests/personal relationships which may be considered as potential competing interests:</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39368760</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2024.118871</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0378-8741(24)01170-X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>