<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39367085</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2045-2322</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>14</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>04</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Scientific reports</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Sci Rep</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Effects of physical refining process on quality and stability of argan oil (Argania Spinosa (L.) Skeels).</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>23045</StartPage><MedlinePgn>23045</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">23045</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1038/s41598-024-74466-6</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Subquality argan kernels are 30% cheaper than the regular kernels mandatory used to prepare edible argan oil. The use of these argan kernels for the preparation of argan oil intended to be a cosmetic ingredient, after bleaching and deodorization, is therefore particularly economically appealing. The oxidative stability of Argan oil prepared from subquality kernels is unknown. It was evaluated over a period of storage of 12 weeks at 60 °C, then compared with that of argan oil stored under the same conditions and originating from the same initial batch, but which had subsequently been simply bleached and deodorized (physical refining). Physical refining led to an increase in initial oil quality due the loss of free fatty acids (up to 30% for refined argan oil), primary and secondary oxidation products but also to a dramatic decrease of the oxidative stability of argan oil caused by the loss of tocopherols, witnessed by the up to 94% loss after 12 weeks under accelerated storage conditions. As a conclusion, the oxidative stability of argan oil prepared from subquality argan kernels remains difficult to be adequately and efficiently evaluated since the initial quality of the argan kernels is the subject of great variations.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Asbbane</LastName><ForeName>Abderrahim</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biotechnology, Analytical Sciences and Quality Control Team, Polydisciplinary Faculty of Taroudant, Ibn Zohr University, Agadir, Morocco.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bousaid</LastName><ForeName>Zahra</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biotechnology, Analytical Sciences and Quality Control Team, Polydisciplinary Faculty of Taroudant, Ibn Zohr University, Agadir, Morocco.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Guillaume</LastName><ForeName>Dominique</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine-Pharmacy, UMR 7312-CNRS, 51 rue Cognacq-Jay, Reims, 51100, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>El Harkaoui</LastName><ForeName>Said</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Federal Research Institute for Nutrition and Food, Department of Safety and Quality of Cereals, Working Group for Lipid Research, Max Rubner-Institut, Schützenberg 12, D-32756, Detmold, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Matthäus</LastName><ForeName>Bertrand</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Federal Research Institute for Nutrition and Food, Department of Safety and Quality of Cereals, Working Group for Lipid Research, Max Rubner-Institut, Schützenberg 12, D-32756, Detmold, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Charrouf</LastName><ForeName>Zoubida</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Sciences, Mohammed V University, Rabat, Morocco.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Goh</LastName><ForeName>Khang Wen</ForeName><Initials>KW</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Data Science and Information Technology, INTI International University, Nilai, Malaysia. khangwen.goh@newinti.edu.my.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Srasom</LastName><ForeName>Nanthida</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Health Sciences, Shinawatra University, Sam Khok, Pathum Thani, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bouayahya</LastName><ForeName>Abdelahakim</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Human Pathologies Biology, Department of Biology, Faculty of Sciences, Mohammed V University, Rabat, 10090, Morocco.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gharby</LastName><ForeName>Saïd</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biotechnology, Analytical Sciences and Quality Control Team, Polydisciplinary Faculty of Taroudant, Ibn Zohr University, Agadir, Morocco. s.gharby@uiz.ac.ma.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Sci Rep</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101563288</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2045-2322</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Hydroperoxide</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Oil preservation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Primary oxidation product</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Schaal oven test</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Secondary oxidation product</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39367085</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11452372</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-74466-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1038/s41598-024-74466-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Charrouf, Z. &amp; Guillaume, D. Argan oil, the 35-years-of-research product. Eur. J. Lipid Sci. Technol.116, 1316–1321 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Monfalouti, H. E., Guillaume, D., Denhez, C. &amp; Charrouf, Z. Therapeutic potential of argan oil: a review. J. Pharm. Pharmacol.62, 1669–1675 (2010).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21054392</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khong, N. M. H. &amp; Chan, K. W. Chapter 24 - Biological activities of argan (Argania Spinosa L.) oil: evidences from in vivo studies. in Multiple Biological Activities of Unconventional Seed Oils (ed Mariod, A. A.) 295–316 (Academic, doi:10.1016/B978-0-12-824135-6.00008-8. (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gharby, S. et al. Shelf-life of Moroccan prickly pear (Opuntia ficus-indica) and argan (Argania Spinosa) oils: a comparative study. Grasas Aceites. 72, e397–e397 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oubannin, S. et al. A comparative evaluation of proximate composition, elemental profiling and oil physicochemical properties of black cumin (Nigella sativa L.) seeds and argan (Argania Spinosa L. Skeels) kernels. Chem. Data Collect.41, 100920 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harhar, H., Gharby, S., Guillaume, D. &amp; Charrouf, Z. Effect of argan kernel storage conditions on argan oil quality. Eur. J. Lipid Sci. Technol.112, 915–920 (2010).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Charrouf, Z., Guillaume, D. &amp; Driouich, A. The argan tree, an asset for Morocco. Biofutur Fr.https://api.semanticscholar.org/CorpusID:134037379 (2002).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Charrouf, Z. &amp; Guillaume, D. Should the Amazigh Diet (regular and moderate argan-oil consumption) have a beneficial impact on Human Health? Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr.50, 473–477 (2010).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20373191</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gharby, S. et al. Oxidative stability of edible argan oil: a two-year study. LWT - Food Sci. Technol.44, 1–8 (2011).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Demnati, D., Pacheco, R., Martínez, L. &amp; Sánchez, S. Effect of roasting temperature and Time on the Chemical Composition and Oxidative Stability of Argan (Argania Spinosa L.) oils. Eur. J. Lipid Sci. Technol.120, 1700136 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gracka, A. et al. Storage-Induced changes in Volatile compounds in Argan oils obtained from raw and roasted kernels. J. Am. Oil Chem. Soc.95, 1475–1485 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gharby, Guillaume, D., Elibrahimi, M. &amp; Charrouf, Z. Physico-Chemical Properties and Sensory Analysis of Deodorized Argan Oil. ACS Food Sci. Technol.1, 275–281 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guillaume, D. &amp; Charrouf, Z. Argan oil and other argan products: use in dermocosmetology. Eur. J. Lipid Sci. Technol.113, 403–408 (2011).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goik, U., Goik, T. &amp; Załęska, I. The properties and Application of Argan Oil in Cosmetology. Eur. J. Lipid Sci. Technol.121, 1800313 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin, C. A., Milinsk, M. C., Visentainer, J. V. &amp; Matsushita, M. De-souza, N. E. Trans fatty acid-forming processes in foods: a review. Acad. Bras. Ciênc. 79, 343–350 (2007).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17625687</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramli, M. R. et al. Effects of Degumming and Bleaching on 3-MCPD esters formation during physical refining. J. Am. Oil Chem. Soc.88, 1839–1844 (2011).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaisali, C., Charanyaa, S., Belur, P. D. &amp; Regupathi, I. Refining of edible oils: a critical appraisal of current and potential technologies. Int. J. Food Sci. Technol.50, 13–23 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karim, N. A. A., Othman, N. H. &amp; Yusoff, M. M. Vegetable Oil RefiningRefining. in Recent Advances in Edible Fats and Oils Technology: Processing, Health Implications, Economic and Environmental Impact (eds Lee, Y. Y., Tang, T. K., Phuah, E. T. &amp; Lai, O. M.) 101–140 (Springer, Singapore, doi:10.1007/978-981-16-5113-7_4. (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verhé, R., Verleyen, T., Van Hoed, V. &amp; De Greyt, W. Influence of refining of vegetable oils on minor components. J. OIL PALM. Res.18, 168–179 (2006).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Y. et al. Comparison of the characteristics and oxidation kinetic parameters of flaxseed (Linum usitatissimum L.) oil products with different refining degree. J. Food Process. Preserv. 44, e14753 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gharby, S. Refining Vegetable Oils: Chemical and Physical Refining. Sci. World J. 6627013 (2022). (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8767382</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35069038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ISO 660. Corps gras d’origines animale et végétale — Détermination de l’indice d’acide et de l’acidité. (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ISO 3656. Animal and vegetable fats and oils — Determination of ultraviolet absorbance expressed as specific UV extinction. (2011). https://www.iso.org/standard/51008.html (2011).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ISO 3960. Animal and vegetable fats and oils — Determination of peroxide value — Iodometric (visual) endpoint determination. ISO (2017). https://www.iso.org/cms/render/live/en/sites/isoorg/contents/data/standard/07/12/71268.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ISO 6885. Animal and vegetable fats and oils — Determination of anisidine value. ISO (2016). https://www.iso.org/cms/render/live/en/sites/isoorg/contents/data/standard/06/95/69593.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ISO 12966-2. Animal and vegetable fats and oils — Gas chromatography of fatty acid methyl esters — Part 2: Preparation of methyl esters of fatty acids. ISO (2017). https://www.iso.org/cms/render/live/en/sites/isoorg/contents/data/standard/07/21/72142.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gharby, S., Harhar, H., Guillaume, D., Haddad, A. &amp; Charrouf, Z. The Origin of Virgin Argan Oil’s high oxidative Stability Unraveled. Nat. Prod. Commun.7, 1934578X1200700520 (2012).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22799092</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kharbach, M. et al. Selected-ion flow-tube mass-spectrometry (SIFT-MS) fingerprinting versus chemical profiling for geographic traceability of Moroccan argan oils. Food Chem.263, 8–17 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29784331</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ISO 9936. Animal and vegetable fats and oils — Determination of tocopherol and tocotrienol contents by high-performance liquid chromatography. (2016). https://www.iso.org/obp/ui/#iso:std:iso:9936:ed-3:v1:en</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Szydłowska-Czerniak, A. &amp; Szłyk, E. Spectrophotometric determination of total phosphorus in rape seeds and oils at various stages of technological process: calculation of phospholipids and non-hydratable phospholipids contents in rapeseed oil. Food Chem.81, 613–619 (2003).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Christidis, G. E. &amp; Kosiari, S. Decolorization of vegetable oils: a study of the mechanism of adsorption of β-carotene by an acid-activated bentonite from Cyprus. Clays Clay Min.51, 327–333 (2003).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Monte, M. L., Monte, M. L., Pohndorf, R. S., Crexi, V. T. &amp; Pinto, L. A. A. Bleaching with blends of bleaching earth and activated carbon reduces color and oxidation products of carp oil. Eur. J. Lipid Sci. Technol.117, 829–836 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gharby, S. et al. Oxidative stability of cosmetic argan oil: a one-year study. J. Cosmet. Sci.65, 81–87 (2014).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24797024</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kharbach, M. et al. Characterization and classification of PGI Moroccan argan oils based on their FTIR fingerprints and chemical composition. Chemom Intell. Lab. Syst.162, 182–190 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>SNIMA. Corps gras d’origine animale et végétale- Huilesd’argane. Spéci‚cations, Norme Marocaine NM08.5.090. Snima, Rabat (Morocco). (2003). https://moam.info/catalogue-des-normes-marocaines_5a2ff7ad1723dd18ec3869b9.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zufarov, O., Serkayev, K. &amp; Isroilova, S. Influence of Chemical and physical refining processes on phospholipid and total Tocopherol content in sunflower oil. Am. J. Polym. Sci.13, 1–5 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oey, S. B., van der Fels-Klerx, H. J., Fogliano, V. &amp; van Leeuwen, S. P. J. Effective physical refining for the mitigation of processing contaminants in palm oil at pilot scale. Food Res. Int.138, 109748 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33292933</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chew, S. C. &amp; Nyam, K. L. Chapter 6 - Refining of edible oils. in Lipids and Edible Oils (ed. Galanakis, C. M.) 213–241Academic Press, doi: (2020). 10.1016/B978-0-12-817105-9.00006-9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duman, E. &amp; Özcan, M. M. The influence of industrial refining stages on the physico-chemical properties, fatty acid composition and sterol contents in hazelnut oil. J. Food Sci. Technol.57, 2501–2506 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7270387</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32549600</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choe, E. &amp; Min, D. B. Mechanisms and Factors for Edible Oil Oxidation. Compr. Rev. Food Sci. Food Saf.5, 169–186 (2006).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grompone, M. A. Anisidine value as a measurement of the latent damage of fats. Grasas Aceites. 42, 8–13 (1991).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chew, S. C., Tan, C. P., Long, K. &amp; Nyam, K. L. Effect of chemical refining on the quality of kenaf (hibiscus cannabinus) seed oil. Ind. Crops Prod.89, 59–65 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan, F. et al. Effect of the chemical refining process on composition and oxidative stability of evening primrose oil. J. Food Process. Preserv. 44, e14800 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gharby, S. et al. Induced changes in olive oil subjected to various chemical refining steps: a comparative study of quality indices, fatty acids, bioactive minor components, and oxidation stability kinetic parameters. Chem. Data Collect.33, 100702 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ortega-García, J. et al. Refining of high oleic safflower oil: Effect on the sterols and tocopherols content. Eur. Food Res. Technol.223, 775–779 (2006).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kreps, F. et al. Influence of deodorization temperature on formation of tocopherol esters and fatty acids polymers in vegetable oil. Eur. J. Lipid Sci. Technol.119, 1600027 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Charrouf, Z. &amp; Guillaume, D. Ethnoeconomical, ethnomedical, and phytochemical study of Argania Spinosa (L.) Skeels. J. Ethnopharmacol.67, 7–14 (1999).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10616955</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bruscatto, M. H., Pestana-Bauer, V. R., Otero, D. M. &amp; Zambiazi, R. C. Effects of heating temperature on the tocopherol contents of chemically and physically refined rice bran oil. Grasas Aceites. 70, e294–e294 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lucci, P., Bertoz, V., Pacetti, D., Moret, S. &amp; Conte, L. Effect of the refining process on total hydroxytyrosol, Tyrosol, and Tocopherol Contents of Olive Oil. Foods. 9, 292 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7143469</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32150867</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Altuntas, A. H., Ketenoglu, O., Cetinbas, S., Erdogdu, F. &amp; Tekin, A. Deacidification of Crude Hazelnut Oil using molecular distillation – multiobjective optimization for free fatty acids and Tocopherol. Eur. J. Lipid Sci. Technol.120, 1700369 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siger, A., Nogala-Kalucka, M. &amp; Lampart-Szczapa, E. The content and antioxidant activity of Phenolic compounds in Cold-pressed plant oils. J. Food Lipids. 15, 137–149 (2008).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steel, C. J., Dobarganes, M. C. &amp; Barrera-Arellano, D. The influence of natural tocopherols during thermal oxidation of refined and partially hydrogenated soybean oils. Grasas Aceites. 56, 46–52 (2005).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bruscatto, M. H. et al. Degradation of Tocopherols in Rice Bran Oil Submitted to Heating at different temperatures. J. Chromatogr. Sci.47, 762–765 (2009).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19835684</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marmesat, S., Velasco, L., Ruiz-Méndez, M. V., Fernández-Martínez, J. M. &amp; Dobarganes, C. Thermostability of genetically modified sunflower oils differing in fatty acid and tocopherol compositions. Eur. J. Lipid Sci. Technol.110, 776–782 (2008).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Magariño, M., Mateo, C. M. &amp; Nolasco, S. M. Kinetics of tocopherol degradation during the storage of wheat germ oil. Can. J. Chem. Eng.93, 1999–2004 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kmiecik, D., Fedko, M., Siger, A. &amp; Kulczyński, B. Degradation of Tocopherol Molecules and its impact on the polymerization of Triacylglycerols during Heat Treatment of Oil. Molecules. 24, 4555 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6943668</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31842452</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barouh, N., Bourlieu-Lacanal, C., Figueroa-Espinoza, M. C., Durand, E. &amp; Villeneuve, P. Tocopherols as antioxidants in lipid-based systems: the combination of chemical and physicochemical interactions determines their efficiency. Compr. Rev. Food Sci. Food Saf.21, 642–688 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34889039</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin-Rubio, A. S., Sopelana, P. &amp; Guillén, M. D. Assessment of Soybean Oil Oxidative Stability from Rapid Analysis of its minor Component Profile. Molecules. 25, 4860 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7594062</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33096833</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>