<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39369650</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>06</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1873-2690</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>216</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>30</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Plant physiology and biochemistry : PPB</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Plant Physiol Biochem</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Ionic and nano calcium to reduce cadmium and arsenic toxicity in plants: Review of mechanisms and potentials.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>109169</StartPage><MedlinePgn>109169</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.plaphy.2024.109169</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0981-9428(24)00837-4</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Contamination of agricultural soils with heavy metal(loid)s like arsenic (As) and cadmium (Cd) is an ever increasing concern for crop production, quality, and global food security. Numerous in-situ and ex-situ remediation approaches have been developed to reduce As and Cd contamination in soils. However, field-scale applications of conventional remediation techniques are limited due to the associated environmental risks, low efficacy, and large capital investments. Recently, calcium (Ca) and Ca-based nano-formulations have emerged as promising solutions with the large potential to mitigate As and Cd toxicity in soil for plants. This review provides comprehensive insights into the phytotoxic effects of As and Cd stress/toxicity and discusses the applications of Ca-based ionic and nano-agrochemicals to alleviate As and Cd toxicity in important crops such as rice, wheat, maize, and barley. Further, various molecular and physiological mechanisms induced by ionic and nano Ca to mitigate As and Cd stress/toxicity in plants are discussed. This review also critically analyzes the efficiency of these emerging Ca-based approaches, both ionic and nano-formulations, in mitigating As and Cd toxicity in comparison to conventional remediation techniques. Additionally, future perspectives and ecological concerns of the remediation approaches encompassing ionic and nano Ca have been discussed. Overall, the review provides an updated and in-depth knowledge for developing sustainable and effective strategies to address the challenges posed by As and Cd contamination in agricultural crops.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier Masson SAS. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nazir</LastName><ForeName>Muhammad Mudassir</ForeName><Initials>MM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Environment and Safety Engineering, School of Emergency Management, Jiangsu Province Engineering Research Center of Green Technology and Contingency Management for Emerging Pollutants, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang 212013, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Guanlin</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Environment and Safety Engineering, School of Emergency Management, Jiangsu Province Engineering Research Center of Green Technology and Contingency Management for Emerging Pollutants, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang 212013, China; Jiangsu Collaborative Innovation Center of Technology and Material of Water Treatment, Suzhou University of Science and Technology, Suzhou 215009, China. Electronic address: liguanlin@ujs.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nawaz</LastName><ForeName>Mohsin</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Environment and Safety Engineering, School of Emergency Management, Jiangsu Province Engineering Research Center of Green Technology and Contingency Management for Emerging Pollutants, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang 212013, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Noman</LastName><ForeName>Muhammad</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Plant Protection and Microbiology, Zhejiang Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Hangzhou 310021, China; College of Arts and Sciences, Gulf University for Science and Technology, Kuwait.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zulfiqar</LastName><ForeName>Faisal</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Horticultural Sciences, Faculty of Agriculture and Environment, The Islamia University of Bahawalpur, Bahawalpur 63100, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ahmed</LastName><ForeName>Temoor</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Biotechnology, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou 310058, China; Department of Life Sciences, Western Caspian University, Baku, Azerbaijan; MEU Research Unit, Middle East University, Amman, Jordan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jalil</LastName><ForeName>Sanaullah</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Biotechnology, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou 310058, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ijaz</LastName><ForeName>Munazza</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Biotechnology, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou 310058, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kuzyakov</LastName><ForeName>Yakov</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Soil Science of Temperate Ecosystems, University of Göttingen, Göttingen, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Du</LastName><ForeName>Daolin</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Jingjiang College, Institute of Environment and Ecology, School of Emergency Management, School of Environment and Safety Engineering, School of Agricultural Engineering, Jiangsu University, Zhenjiang 212013, China. Electronic address: ddl@ujs.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>30</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>France</Country><MedlineTA>Plant Physiol Biochem</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9882449</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0981-9428</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Agriculture</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Arsenic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Cadmium</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Calcium</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Heavy metal remediation</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>35</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>35</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>7</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39369650</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.plaphy.2024.109169</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0981-9428(24)00837-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>