<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39364150</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>05</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2296-861X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>11</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Frontiers in nutrition</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Front Nutr</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Effect of konjac glucomannan on gut microbiota from hyperuricemia subjects <i>in vitro</i>: fermentation characteristics and inhibitory xanthine oxidase activity.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1465940</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1465940</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1465940</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3389/fnut.2024.1465940</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The disorder of uric acid metabolism is closely associated with gut microbiota and short-chain fatty acids (SCFAs) dysregulation, but the biological mechanism is unclear, limiting the development of uric acid-lowering active polysaccharides. Konjac glucomannan (KGM) could attenuate metabolic disturbance of uric acid and modulate the gut microbiota. However, the relationship between uric acid metabolism and gut microbiota is still unknown.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">In this study, The fecal samples were provided by healthy volunteers and hyperuricemia (HUA) patients. Fecal samples from healthy volunteers was regarded as the NOR group. Similarly, 10% HUA fecal suspension was named as the HUA group. Then, fecal supernatant was inoculated into a growth basal medium containing glucose or KGM, and healthy fecal samples were designated as the NOR-GLU and NOR-KGM groups, while HUA fecal samples were designated as the HUA-GLU and HUA-KGM groups. All samples were cultured in an anaerobic bag system. After fermentation for 24 h, the samples were collected for further analysis of composition of intestinal microbiota, SCFAs concentration and XOD enzyme activity.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The results showed that KGM could be utilized and degraded by the gut microbiota from HUA subjects, and it could modulate the composition and structure of their HUA gut microbiota to more closely resemble that of a healthy group. In addition, KGM showed a superior modulated effect on HUA gut microbiota by increasing <i>Megasphaera</i>, <i>Faecalibacterium</i>, <i>Lachnoclostridium</i>, <i>Lachnospiraceae</i>, <i>Anaerostipes</i>, and <i>Ruminococcus</i> levels and decreasing <i>Butyricicoccus</i>, <i>Eisenbergiella</i>, and <i>Enterococcus</i> levels. Furthermore, the fermentation solution of KGM showed an inhibitory effect on xanthine oxidase (XOD) enzyme activity, which might be due to metabolites such as SCFAs.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">In conclusion, the effect of KGM on hyperuricemia subjects was investigated based on the gut microbiota <i>in vitro</i>. In the present study. It was found that KGM could be metabolized into SCFAs by HUA gut microbiota. Furthermore, KGM could modulate the structure of HUA gut microbiota. At the genus level, KGM could decrease the relative abundances of <i>Butyricicoccus</i>, <i>Eisenbergiella</i>, and <i>Enterococcus</i>, while <i>Lachnoclostridium</i> and <i>Lachnospiraceae</i> in HUA gut microbiota were significantly increased by the addition of KGM. The metabolites of gut microbiota, such as SCFAs, might be responsible for the inhibition of XOD activity. Thus, KGM exhibited a superior probiotic function on the HUA gut microbiota, which is expected as a promising candidate for remodeling the HUA gut microbiota.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Deng, Zhou, Feng, Bao, Zhang, Luo and Li.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Deng</LastName><ForeName>Jie</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shunde Vocational and Technical College, Foshan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Kai</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Jiangxi Oil-Tea Camellia, College of Pharmacy and Life Science, Jiujiang University, Jiujiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Feng</LastName><ForeName>Caimin</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shunde Vocational and Technical College, Foshan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bao</LastName><ForeName>Yilu</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shunde Vocational and Technical College, Foshan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Zhiming</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shunde Vocational and Technical College, Foshan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Luo</LastName><ForeName>Wenfeng</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Central Laboratory of Panyu Central Hospital, The Affiliated Panyu Central Hospital of Guangzhou Medical University, Guangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Meiying</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Guangdong Provincial Key Lab of Food Safety and Quality, South China Agricultural University, Guangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>19</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Front Nutr</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101642264</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2296-861X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">hyperuricemia</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">konjac glucomannan</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">short-chain fatty acids</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">uric acid</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">xanthine oxidase activity</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>10</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>9</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39364150</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11446875</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fnut.2024.1465940</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Zhou MQ, Huang X, Li R, Zhang Z, Zhang L, Gao X, et al. . Association of dietary patterns with blood uric acid concentration and hyperuricemia in northern Chinese adults. Nutr J. (2022) 21:42. doi: 10.1186/s12937-022-00789-7, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12937-022-00789-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9219223</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35739563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Shen Z, Zhu B, Zhang H, Zhang X, Ding X. Demographic, regional and temporal trends of hyperuricemia epidemics in mainland China from 2000 to 2019: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Glob Health Action. (2021) 14:1874652. doi: 10.1080/16549716.2021.1874652, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/16549716.2021.1874652</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7833047</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33475474</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ekpenyong CE, Daniel N. Roles of diets and dietary factors in the pathogenesis, management and prevention of abnormal serum uric acid levels. PharmaNutrition. (2015) 3:29–45. doi: 10.1016/j.phanu.2014.12.001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.phanu.2014.12.001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang W, Pang J, Ha EH, Zhou M, Li Z, Tian S, et al. . Development of novel NLRP3-XOD dual inhibitors for the treatment of gout. Bioorg Med Chem Lett. (2020) 30:126944. doi: 10.1016/j.bmcl.2019.126944, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bmcl.2019.126944</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31924495</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li X, Chen Y, Gao X, Wu Y, El-Seedi HR, Cao Y, et al. . Antihyperuricemic effect of green alga Ulva lactuca ulvan through regulating urate transporters. J Agric Food Chem. (2021) 69:11225–35. doi: 10.1021/acs.jafc.1c03607</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.jafc.1c03607</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34549578</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li X, Gao X, Zhang H, Liu Y, Sarker MMR, Wu Y, et al. . The anti-hyperuricemic effects of green alga Enteromorpha prolifera polysaccharide via regulation of the uric acid transporters in vivo. Food Chem Toxicol. (2021) 158:112630. doi: 10.1016/j.fct.2021.112630</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2021.112630</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34687833</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crane JK, Naeher TM, Broome JE, Boedeker EC. Role of host xanthine oxidase in infection due to enteropathogenic and Shiga-toxigenic Escherichia coli. Infect Immun. (2013) 81:1129–39. doi: 10.1128/IAI.01124-12, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/IAI.01124-12</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3639607</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23340314</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chu Y, Sun S, Huang Y, Gao Q, Xie X, Wang P, et al. . Metagenomic analysis revealed the potential role of gut microbiome in gout. npj Biofilms Microbiomes. (2021) 7:66. doi: 10.1038/s41522-021-00235-2, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41522-021-00235-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8352958</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34373464</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ni C, Li X, Wang L, Li X, Zhao J, Zhang H, et al. . Lactic acid bacteria strains relieve hyperuricaemia by suppressing xanthine oxidase activity via a short-chain fatty acid-dependent mechanism. Food Funct. (2021) 12:7054–67. doi: 10.1039/D1FO00198A, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D1FO00198A</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34152353</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dangana E, Omolekulo TE, Areola ED, Olaniyi KS, Soladoye AO, Olatunji LA. Sodium acetate protects against nicotine-induced excess hepatic lipid in male rats by suppressing xanthine oxidase activity. Chem Biol Interact. (2020) 316:108929. doi: 10.1016/j.cbi.2019.108929, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cbi.2019.108929</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31857090</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen H, Nie Q, Hu J, Huang X, Zhang K, Nie S. Glucomannans alleviated the progression of diabetic kidney disease by improving kidney metabolic disturbance. Mol Nutr Food Res. (2019) 63:e1801008. doi: 10.1002/mnfr.201801008, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/mnfr.201801008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30901508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y, Deng L, Wu C, Zheng L, Zhong G. Konjac glucomannan improves hyperuricemia through regulating xanthine oxidase, adenosine deaminase and urate transporters in rats. J Funct Foods. (2018) 48:566–75. doi: 10.1016/j.jff.2018.07.062</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jff.2018.07.062</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mao Y-H, Xu Y, Song F, Wang ZM, Li YH, Zhao M, et al. . Protective effects of konjac glucomannan on gut microbiome with antibiotic perturbation in mice. Carbohydr Polym. (2022) 290:119476. doi: 10.1016/j.carbpol.2022.119476</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.carbpol.2022.119476</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35550768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deng J, Zou X, Liang Y, Zhong J, Zhou K, Zhang J, et al. . Hypoglycemic effects of different molecular weight konjac glucomannans via intestinal microbiota and SCFAs mediated mechanism. Int J Biol Macromol. (2023) 234:122941. doi: 10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2022.12.160, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2022.12.160</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36563827</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deng J, Zhong J, Long J, Zou X, Wang D, Song Y, et al. . Hypoglycemic effects and mechanism of different molecular weights of konjac glucomannans in type 2 diabetic rats. Int J Biol Macromol. (2020) 165:2231–43. doi: 10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2020.10.021</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2020.10.021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33058981</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li M, Li G, Shang Q, Chen X, Liu W, Pi X’e, et al. . In vitro fermentation of alginate and its derivatives by human gut microbiota. Anaerobe. (2016) 39:19–25. doi: 10.1016/j.anaerobe.2016.02.003, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.anaerobe.2016.02.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26891629</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang M, Zhu X, Wu J, Huang Z, Zhao Z, Zhang X, et al. . Prevalence of hyperuricemia among Chinese adults: findings from two nationally representative cross-sectional surveys in 2015–16 and 2018–19. Front Immunol. (2022) 12:791983. doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2021.791983, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2021.791983</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8858821</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35197964</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J, Chen Y, Zhong H, Chen F, Regenstein J, Hu X, et al. . The gut microbiota as a target to control hyperuricemia pathogenesis: potential mechanisms and therapeutic strategies. Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr. (2022) 62:3979–89. doi: 10.1080/10408398.2021.1874287, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10408398.2021.1874287</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33480266</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo YJ, Yu Y, Li H, Ding X, Li X, Jing X, et al. . Inulin supplementation ameliorates hyperuricemia and modulates gut microbiota in Uox-knockout mice. Eur J Nutr. (2021) 60:2217–30. doi: 10.1007/s00394-020-02414-x, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00394-020-02414-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8137640</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33104864</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu D, Chen R, Li Q, Lai X, Sun L, Zhang Z, et al. . Tea (Camellia sinensis) ameliorates hyperuricemia via uric acid metabolic pathways and gut microbiota. Nutrients. (2022) 14:2666. doi: 10.3390/nu14132666, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu14132666</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9268162</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35807846</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou X, Zhang B, Zhao X, Lin Y, Zhuang Y, Guo J, et al. . Chlorogenic acid prevents hyperuricemia nephropathy via regulating TMAO-related gut microbes and inhibiting the PI3K/AKT/mTOR pathway. J Agric Food Chem. (2022) 70:10182–93. doi: 10.1021/acs.jafc.2c03099, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.jafc.2c03099</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35950815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ren F, Jin Q, Jin Q, Qian Y, Ren X, Liu T, et al. . Genetic evidence supporting the causal role of gut microbiota in chronic kidney disease and chronic systemic inflammation in CKD: a bilateral two-sample Mendelian randomization study. Front Immunol. (2023) 14:1287698. doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2023.1287698, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2023.1287698</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10652796</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38022507</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao E, Zhang W, Geng B, You B, Wang W, Li X. Intestinal dysbacteriosis leads to kidney stone disease. Mol Med Rep. (2021) 23:180. doi: 10.3892/mmr.2020.11819</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3892/mmr.2020.11819</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7809898</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33655334</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma Q, Chen M, Liu Y, Tong Y, Liu T, Wu L, et al. . Lactobacillus acidophilus fermented dandelion improves hyperuricemia and regulates gut microbiota. Fermentation. (2023) 9:352. doi: 10.3390/fermentation9040352</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/fermentation9040352</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dou L, Liu C, Chen X, Yang Z, Hu G, Zhang M, et al. . Supplemental Clostridium butyricum modulates skeletal muscle development and meat quality by shaping the gut microbiota of lambs. Meat Sci. (2023) 204:109235. doi: 10.1016/j.meatsci.2023.109235, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2023.109235</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37301103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vacca M, Celano G, Calabrese FM, Portincasa P, Gobbetti M, de Angelis M. The controversial role of human gut lachnospiraceae. Microorganisms. (2020) 8:573. doi: 10.3390/microorganisms8040573</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/microorganisms8040573</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7232163</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32326636</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan L, Han P, Ma S, Peng R, Wang C, Kong W, et al. . Abnormal metabolism of gut microbiota reveals the possible molecular mechanism of nephropathy induced by hyperuricemia. Acta Pharm Sin B. (2020) 10:249–61. doi: 10.1016/j.apsb.2019.10.007, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.apsb.2019.10.007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7016297</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32082971</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Makki K, Deehan EC, Walter J, Bäckhed F. The impact of dietary fiber on gut microbiota in host health and disease. Cell Host Microbe. (2018) 23:705–15. doi: 10.1016/j.chom.2018.05.012</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2018.05.012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29902436</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Li L, Tian J, Zheng F, Liao H, Zhao Z, et al. . Insoluble fiber in barley leaf attenuates hyperuricemic nephropathy by modulating gut microbiota and short-chain fatty acids. Foods. (2022) 11:3482. doi: 10.3390/foods11213482, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/foods11213482</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9656210</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36360095</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo Z, Zhang J, Wang Z, Ang KY, Huang S, Hou Q, et al. . Intestinal microbiota distinguish gout patients from healthy humans. Sci Rep. (2016) 6:20602. doi: 10.1038/srep20602, PMID:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/srep20602</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4757479</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26852926</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>