<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39368541</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>05</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1873-6351</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>03</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Food and chemical toxicology : an international journal published for the British Industrial Biological Research Association</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Food Chem Toxicol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Caffeine Intake from Foods and Beverages and Trends among Chinese Children and Adolescents: 2004-2018.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>115025</StartPage><MedlinePgn>115025</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.fct.2024.115025</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0278-6915(24)00591-X</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The popularity of caffeinated foods and beverages poses risks of high caffeine exposure among Chinese children and adolescents. Nevertheless, there is a lack of national assessments on their caffeine consumption.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To estimate daily caffeine intake and analyze time trends among Chinese children and adolescents.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">The study subjects were participants of the China Health and Nutrition Survey in 2004, 2006, 2009 and 2011, and the National Food and Beverage Consumption Survey in 2014 and 2018. Caffeine content was determined using chromatographic instrument. The Monte Carlo simulation was utilized to estimate daily caffeine intake and the Kruskal-Wallis test was used to analyze differences between population characteristics. To examine yearly trends in caffeine intake from 2004 to 2018, the partial Mann-Kendall test was applied.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The median daily caffeine intake of Chinese children and adolescents was 0.17 (95%CI: 0.15-0.20) mg/kg BW/day. Main contributors were tea (55.52%), sodas (19.52%) and tea beverages (10.37%). Approximately 4.68% of individuals consumed caffeine exceeding 2.5 mg/kg BW/day. Higher caffeine intake was observed in adolescents aged 12-17 years, males, and consumers residing in northeastern China. While no significant overall yearly trends in caffeine intake were detected from 2004 to 2018, there was an increase in intake driven by beverage consumption between 2006 and 2014.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">This study provided a national assessment of caffeine consumption among Chinese children and adolescents. Caffeinated beverages like tea, soda, and tea beverages emerged as major contributors to caffeine intake. These findings could contribute to the regulation of caffeine consumption and the promotion of healthy habits among children and adolescents.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024. Published by Elsevier Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tong</LastName><ForeName>Ou</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Food Safety Risk Assessment, National Health Commission of the People's Republic of China (China National Center for Food Safety Risk Assessment), Guangqu Road, Beijing, 100022, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cao</LastName><ForeName>Yue</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Food Safety Risk Assessment, National Health Commission of the People's Republic of China (China National Center for Food Safety Risk Assessment), Guangqu Road, Beijing, 100022, Beijing, China; School of Public Health, Tongji Medical College, Huazhong University of Science and Technology, Hangkong Road, Wuhan, 430030, Hubei, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Song</LastName><ForeName>Yan</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Food Safety Risk Assessment, National Health Commission of the People's Republic of China (China National Center for Food Safety Risk Assessment), Guangqu Road, Beijing, 100022, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Song</LastName><ForeName>Jian</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food and Nutrition Institute, Shandong Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Jinan, 250014, Shandong, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xiao</LastName><ForeName>Xiao</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Food Safety Risk Assessment, National Health Commission of the People's Republic of China (China National Center for Food Safety Risk Assessment), Guangqu Road, Beijing, 100022, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yong</LastName><ForeName>Ling</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Food Safety Risk Assessment, National Health Commission of the People's Republic of China (China National Center for Food Safety Risk Assessment), Guangqu Road, Beijing, 100022, Beijing, China; China National Center of Technology Innovation for Dairy, West Guochuang Road, Hohhot, 010110, Inner Mongolia, China. Electronic address: yongling@cfsa.net.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wei</LastName><ForeName>Sheng</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Public Health and Emergency Management, Southern University of Science and Technology, 1088 Academy Avenue, Nanshan District, Shenzhen, 518055, Guangdong, China. Electronic address: ws2008cn@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Food Chem Toxicol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8207483</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0278-6915</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">adolescent</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">caffeine intake</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">children</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">dietary sources</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">trends</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of Competing Interest ☐ The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper. ☐ The author is an Editorial Board Member/Editor-in-Chief/Associate Editor/Guest Editor for [Journal name] and was not involved in the editorial review or the decision to publish this article. ☒ The authors declare the following financial interests/personal relationships which may be considered as potential competing interests: Ling Yong reports financial support was provided by National Health Commission of the People's Republic of China; China National Center of Technology Innovation for Dairy (2023-QTXM-3); Chinese Institute of Food Science and Technology.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39368541</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2024.115025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0278-6915(24)00591-X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>