<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39362392</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>06</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1567-7257</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>125</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Infection, genetics and evolution : journal of molecular epidemiology and evolutionary genetics in infectious diseases</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Infect Genet Evol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Discovery of the first sea turtle adenovirus and turtle associated circoviruses.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>105677</StartPage><MedlinePgn>105677</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.meegid.2024.105677</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S1567-1348(24)00128-X</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Turtles are an evolutionarily unique and morphologically distinctive order of reptiles, and many species are globally endangered. Although a high diversity of adenoviruses in scaled reptiles is well-documented, turtle adenoviruses remain largely understudied. To investigate their molecular diversity, we focused on the identification and characterisation of adenoviruses in turtle-derived organ, swab and egg samples. Since reptile circoviruses have been scarcely reported and no turtle circoviruses have been documented to date, we also screened our samples for circoviruses. Host-virus coevolution is a common feature of these viral families, so we aimed to investigate possible signs of this as well. Two screening projects were conducted: one on Brazilian samples collected from animals in their natural habitat, and the other on Hungarian pet shop samples. Nested PCR systems were used for the detection of adeno- and circoviruses and purified PCR products were Sanger sequenced. Phylogenetic trees for the viruses were reconstructed based on the adenoviral DNA polymerase and hexon genes, circoviral Rep genes, and for the turtle hosts based on mitochondrial cytochrome b amino acid sequences. During the screening, testadeno-, siadeno-, and circovirus strains were detected. The circovirus strains were classified into the genus Circovirus, exhibiting significant evolutionary divergence but forming a monophyletic clade within a group of fish circoviruses. The phylogenetic tree of turtles reflected their taxonomic relationships, showing a deep bifurcation between suborders and distinct monophyletic clades corresponding to families. A similar clustering pattern was observed among the testadenovirus strains in their phylogenetic tree. As a result, this screening of turtle samples revealed at least three new testadenoviruses, including the first sea turtle adenovirus, evidence of coevolution between testadenoviruses and their hosts, and the first turtle associated circoviruses. These findings underscore the need for further research on viruses in turtles, and more broadly in reptiles, to better understand their viral diversity and the evolutionary processes shaping host-virus interactions.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tóth</LastName><ForeName>Alexandra V</ForeName><Initials>AV</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>HUN-REN Veterinary Medical Research Institute, 1143 Budapest, Hungária krt. 21, Hungary. Electronic address: toth_alexandra98@hotmail.hu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Berta</LastName><ForeName>Péter</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>HUN-REN Veterinary Medical Research Institute, 1143 Budapest, Hungária krt. 21, Hungary.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Harrach</LastName><ForeName>Balázs</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>HUN-REN Veterinary Medical Research Institute, 1143 Budapest, Hungária krt. 21, Hungary. Electronic address: harrach.balazs@vmri.hun-ren.hu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ursu</LastName><ForeName>Krisztina</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Veterinary Diagnostic Directorate, National Food Chain Safety Office, 1143 Budapest, Tábornok u. 2, Hungary. Electronic address: ursuk@nebih.gov.hu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jejesky de Oliveira</LastName><ForeName>Ana Paula</ForeName><Initials>AP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Wildlife Health, Department of Ecosystem Ecology, University of Vila Velha, 29102-920 Vila Velha, Espírito Santo, Av. Comissário José Dantas de Melo 21, Boa Vista, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vicentini</LastName><ForeName>Fernando</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Health Sciences Center, Federal University of Recôncavo da Bahia, 44574-490 Santo Antônio de Jesus, Bahia, Avenida Carlos Amaral, 1015, Brazil. Electronic address: vicentini@ufrb.edu.br.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rossi</LastName><ForeName>João Luiz</ForeName><Initials>JL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Wildlife Health, Department of Ecosystem Ecology, University of Vila Velha, 29102-920 Vila Velha, Espírito Santo, Av. Comissário José Dantas de Melo 21, Boa Vista, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Papp</LastName><ForeName>Tibor</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>HUN-REN Veterinary Medical Research Institute, 1143 Budapest, Hungária krt. 21, Hungary.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kaján</LastName><ForeName>Győző L</ForeName><Initials>GL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>HUN-REN Veterinary Medical Research Institute, 1143 Budapest, Hungária krt. 21, Hungary. Electronic address: kajan.gyozo@vmri.hun-ren.hu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Infect Genet Evol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101084138</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1567-1348</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Adenovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Circovirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Coevolution</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Testudines</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39362392</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.meegid.2024.105677</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S1567-1348(24)00128-X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>