<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39366957</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2396-8370</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>8</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>04</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>NPJ science of food</Title><ISOAbbreviation>NPJ Sci Food</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Prediction of deoxynivalenol contamination in spring oats in Sweden using explainable artificial intelligence.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>75</StartPage><MedlinePgn>75</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">75</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1038/s41538-024-00310-w</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Weather conditions and agronomical factors are known to affect Fusarium spp. growth and ultimately deoxynivalenol (DON) contamination in oat. This study aimed to develop predictive models for the contamination of spring oat at harvest with DON on a regional basis in Sweden using machine-learning algorithms. Three models were developed as regional risk-assessment tools for farmers, crop collectors, and food safety inspectors, respectively. Data included: weather data from different oat growing periods, agronomical data, site-specific data, and DON contamination data from the previous year. Results showed that: (1) RF models were able to predict DON contamination at harvest with a total classification accuracy of minimal 0.72; (2) good predictions could already be made in June; (3) rainfall, relative humidity, and wind speed in different oat growing stages, followed by crop variety and elevation were the most important features for predicting DON contamination in spring oats at harvest.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>X</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8633-8971</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Business Economics Group, Wageningen University, Hollandseweg 1, Wageningen, the Netherlands. xinxin2.wang@wur.nl.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wageningen Food Safety Research, Akkermaalsbos 2, Wageningen, the Netherlands. xinxin2.wang@wur.nl.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Borjesson</LastName><ForeName>T</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agroväst Livsmedel AB, PO Box 234, Skara, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wetterlind</LastName><ForeName>J</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Soil and Environment, Swedish, University of Agricultural Sciences, Skara, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>van der Fels-Klerx</LastName><ForeName>H J</ForeName><Initials>HJ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7801-394X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Business Economics Group, Wageningen University, Hollandseweg 1, Wageningen, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wageningen Food Safety Research, Akkermaalsbos 2, Wageningen, the Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>NPJ Sci Food</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101739627</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2396-8370</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>15</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39366957</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11452490</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41538-024-00310-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1038/s41538-024-00310-w</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Hjelkrem, A.-G. R. et al. DON content in oat grains in Norway related to weather conditions at different growth stages. Eur. J. Plant Pathol.148, 577–594 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munkvold, G. Crop management practices to minimize the risk of mycotoxins contamination in temperate-zone maize. Mycotoxin Reduct. Grain Chains1, 59–77 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chain, E. P. O. C. I. T. F. et al. Risks to human and animal health related to the presence of deoxynivalenol and its acetylated and modified forms in food and feed. EFSA J.15, e04718 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7010102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32625635</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Commission, E. Commission Regulation (EC) No 1881/2006 of 19 December 2006 setting maximum levels for certain contaminants in foodstuffs. J. Eur. Union364, 5–24 (2006).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Persson, T. et al. Predicting deoxynivalenol in oats under conditions representing Scandinavian production regions. Food Addit. Contam.: A34, 1026–1038 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28332416</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moretti, A., Pascale, M. &amp; Logrieco, A. F. Mycotoxin risks under a climate change scenario in Europe. Trends Food Sci. Technol.84, 38–40 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perrone, G., Ferrara, M., Medina, A., Pascale, M. &amp; Magan, N. Toxigenic fungi and mycotoxins in a climate change scenario: Ecology, genomics, distribution, prediction and prevention of the risk. Microorganisms8, 1496 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7601308</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33003323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krebs, H., Dubois, D., Kulling, C. &amp; Forrer, H. Effects of preceding crop and tillage on the incidence of Fusarium spp. and mycotoxin deoxynivalenol content in winter wheat grain. Agrarforschung7, 264–268 (2000).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Champeil, A., Doré, T. &amp; Fourbet, J.-F. Fusarium head blight: epidemiological origin of the effects of cultural practices on head blight attacks and the production of mycotoxins by Fusarium in wheat grains. Plant Sci.166, 1389–1415 (2004).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Czaban, J. et al. Colonisation of winter wheat grain by Fusarium spp. and mycotoxin content as dependent on a wheat variety, crop rotation, a crop management system and weather conditions. Food Addit. Contam.: A32, 874–910 (2015).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25705931</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Janssen, E., Liu, C. &amp; Van der Fels-Klerx, H. Fusarium infection and trichothecenes in barley and its comparison with wheat. World Mycotoxin J.11, 33–46 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marzec-Schmidt, K. et al. Modelling the effects of weather conditions on cereal grain contamination with deoxynivalenol in the Baltic Sea Region. Toxins13, 737 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8618390</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34822522</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaukoranta, T., Hietaniemi, V., Rämö, S., Koivisto, T. &amp; Parikka, P. Contrasting responses of T-2, HT-2 and DON mycotoxins and Fusarium species in oat to climate, weather, tillage and cereal intensity. Eur. J. Plant Pathol.155, 93–110 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu, X. et al. Developing logistic models to relate the accumulation of DON associated with Fusarium head blight to climatic conditions in Europe. Eur. J. Plant Pathol.137, 689–706 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prandini, A., Sigolo, S., Filippi, L., Battilani, P. &amp; Piva, G. Review of predictive models for Fusarium head blight and related mycotoxin contamination in wheat. Food Chem. Toxicol.47, 927–931 (2009).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18634842</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lindblad, M., Börjesson, T., Hietaniemi, V. &amp; Elen, O. Statistical analysis of agronomical factors and weather conditions influencing deoxynivalenol levels in oats in Scandinavia. Food Addit. Contam.: Part A29, 1566–1571 (2012).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22296582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, X., Liu, C. &amp; van der Fels-Klerx, H. Regional prediction of multi-mycotoxin contamination of wheat in Europe using machine learning. Food Res. Int.159, 111588 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35940788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castano-Duque, L., Vaughan, M., Lindsay, J., Barnett, K. &amp; Rajasekaran, K. Gradient boosting and bayesian network machine learning models predict aflatoxin and fumonisin contamination of maize in Illinois–First USA case study. Front. Microbiol.13, 1039947 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9684211</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36439814</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, N. et al. Improved aflatoxin and fumonisin forecasting models for maize (PREMA and PREFUM), using combined mechanistic and Bayesian network modelling–Serbia as a case study. Front. Microbiol.12, 630 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8098437</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33967981</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Camardo Leggieri, M., Mazzoni, M. &amp; Battilani, P. Machine learning for predicting mycotoxin occurrence in maize. Front. Microbiol.12, 782 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8062859</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33897675</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petch, J., Di, S. &amp; Nelson, W. Opening the black box: the promise and limitations of explainable machine learning in cardiology. Can. J. Cardiol.38, 204–213 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34534619</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, S. et al. A predictive model on deoxynivalenol in harvested wheat in China: Revealing the impact of the environment and agronomic practicing. Food Chem.405, 134727 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36335729</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kolawole, O. et al. Agronomic factors influencing the scale of fusarium mycotoxin contamination of oats. J. Fungi7, 965 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8619034</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34829252</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matumba, L. et al. Five keys to prevention and control of mycotoxins in grains: A proposal. Glob. Food Secur.30, 100562 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, C., Manstretta, V., Rossi, V. &amp; der Fels-Klerx, V. Comparison of three modelling approaches for predicting deoxynivalenol contamination in winter wheat. Toxins10, 267 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6071054</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30004414</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Fels-Klerx, H. et al. Decision support system for integrated management of mycotoxins in feed and food supply chains. World Mycotoxin J.15, 119–133 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torelli, E., Firrao, G., Bianchi, G., Saccardo, F. &amp; Locci, R. The influence of local factors on the prediction of fumonisin contamination in maize. J. Sci. Food Agric.92, 1808–1814 (2012).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22228027</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yudarwati, R., Hongo, C., Sigit, G., Barus, B. &amp; Utoyo, B. Bacterial leaf blight detection in rice crops using ground-based spectroradiometer data and multi-temporal satellites images. J. Agric. Sci.12, 38 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan, X. et al. Effect of aviation spray adjuvant on improving control of fusarium head blight and reducing mycotoxin contamination in wheat. Agriculture11, 1284 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Selvaraj, J. N. et al. Limited survey of deoxynivalenol in wheat from different crop rotation fields in Yangtze-Huaihe river basin region of China. Food Control53, 151–155 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Landschoot, S., Audenaert, K., Waegeman, W., De Baets, B. &amp; Haesaert, G. Influence of maize–wheat rotation systems on Fusarium head blight infection and deoxynivalenol content in wheat under low versus high disease pressure. Crop Prot.52, 14–21 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blandino, M., Pilati, A., Reyneri, A. &amp; Scudellari, D. Effect of maize crop residue density on Fusarium head blight and on deoxynivalenol contamination of common wheat grains. Cereal Res. Commun.38, 550–559 (2010).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bottalico, A. &amp; Perrone, G. In Mycotoxins in plant disease 611–624 (Springer, 2002).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piikki, K. &amp; Söderström, M. Digital soil mapping of arable land in Sweden–Validation of performance at multiple scales. Geoderma352, 342–350 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biau, G. &amp; Scornet, E. A random forest guided tour. Test25, 197–227 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Géron, A. Hands-on machine learning with Scikit-Learn, Keras, and TensorFlow: Concepts, tools, and techniques to build intelligent systems. (“O’Reilly Media, Inc.”, 2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, L. &amp; Shami, A. On hyperparameter optimization of machine learning algorithms: Theory and practice. Neurocomputing415, 295–316 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lundberg, S. M. et al. From local explanations to global understanding with explainable AI for trees. Nat. Mach. Intell.2, 56–67 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7326367</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32607472</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>