<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39369000</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2396-8370</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>8</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>06</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>NPJ science of food</Title><ISOAbbreviation>NPJ Sci Food</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Comprehensive analysis of PFAS presence from environment to plate.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>80</StartPage><MedlinePgn>80</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">80</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1038/s41538-024-00319-1</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) pose an emerging environmental risk impacting food products and ecosystems. This study analyzes over 150,000 entries from food safety authorities and scientific publications from 2017 onwards. Our findings show that fish &amp; seafood, and biota have the highest PFAS concentrations due to environmental contamination and bioaccumulation. Surface water samples also frequently contain PFAS, raising concerns about long-term ecological and human health effects. Comprehensive strategies are essential to mitigate these risks.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dimitrakopoulou</LastName><ForeName>Maria-Eleni</ForeName><Initials>ME</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0511-3034</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agroknow, 110 Pentelis, Maroussi, Greece. medimitrakopoulou@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Karvounis</LastName><ForeName>Manos</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agroknow, 110 Pentelis, Maroussi, Greece.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Marinos</LastName><ForeName>George</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agroknow, 110 Pentelis, Maroussi, Greece.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Theodorakopoulou</LastName><ForeName>Zacharoula</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agroknow, 110 Pentelis, Maroussi, Greece.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Aloizou</LastName><ForeName>Eleni</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agroknow, 110 Pentelis, Maroussi, Greece.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Petsangourakis</LastName><ForeName>George</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agroknow, 110 Pentelis, Maroussi, Greece.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Papakonstantinou</LastName><ForeName>Mihalis</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agroknow, 110 Pentelis, Maroussi, Greece.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Stoitsis</LastName><ForeName>Giannis</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agroknow, 110 Pentelis, Maroussi, Greece.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>06</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>NPJ Sci Food</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101739627</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2396-8370</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>16</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39369000</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11455986</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41538-024-00319-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1038/s41538-024-00319-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Kwiatkowski, C. F. et al. Scientific basis for managing PFAS as a chemical class. Environ. Sci. Technol. Lett.7, 532–543 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8297807</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34307722</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin, L. R. et al. PFAS levels and determinants of variability in exposure in European teenagers—results from the HBM4EU aligned studies (2014–2021). Int. J. Hyg. Environ. Health247, 114057 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9758614</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36327670</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Silva, A. O. et al. PFAS exposure pathways for humans and wildlife: a synthesis of current knowledge and key gaps in understanding. Environ. Toxicol. Chem.40, 631–657 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7906948</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33201517</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manea, S. et al. Exposure to PFAS and small for gestational age new-borns: a birth records study in Veneto Region (Italy). Environ. Res.184, 109282 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32120121</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lohmann, R. &amp; Letcher, R. J. ScienceDirect The universe of fluorinated polymers and polymeric substances and potential environmental impacts and concerns. Curr. Opin. Green Sustain. Chem.41, 100795 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10062242</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37009204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bulson, E. E., Remucal, C. K. &amp; Hicks, A. L. End-of-life circulation of PFAS in metal recycling streams: a sustainability-focused review. Resour. Conserv. Recycl.194, 106978 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rehman, A. U., Crimi, M. &amp; Andreescu, S. Current and emerging analytical techniques for the determination of PFAS in environmental samples. Trends Environ. Anal. Chem.37, e00198 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stefano, P. H. P. et al. Occurrence and distribution of per-and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) in surface and groundwaters in an urbanized and agricultural area, Southern Brazil. Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res.30, 6159–6169 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35987853</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhong, M. et al. Automated online solid-phase extraction liquid chromatography tandem mass spectrometry investigation for simultaneous quantification of per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances, pharmaceuticals and personal care products, and organophosphorus flame retardants. J. Chromatogr. A1602, 350–358 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31257039</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lam, N. H., Cho, C. R., Kannan, K. &amp; Cho, H. S. A nationwide survey of perfluorinated alkyl substances in waters, sediment and biota collected from aquatic environment in Vietnam: distributions and bioconcentration profiles. J. Hazard. Mater.323, 116–127 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27106518</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tröger, R., Klöckner, P., Ahrens, L. &amp; Wiberg, K. Micropollutants in drinking water from source to tap—method development and application of a multiresidue screening method. Sci. Total Environ.627, 1404–1432 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30857104</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saleeby, B. et al. Isomers of emerging per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances in water and sediment from the Cape Fear River, North Carolina, USA. Chemosphere262, 128359 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33182107</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olomukoro, A. A., Emmons, R. V., Godage, N. H., Cudjoe, E. &amp; Gionfriddo, E. Ion exchange solid phase microextraction coupled to liquid chromatography/laminar flow tandem mass spectrometry for the determination of perfluoroalkyl substances in water samples. J. Chromatogr. A1651, 462335 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34174636</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simmonet-Laprade, C. et al. Investigation of the spatial variability of poly- and perfluoroalkyl substance trophic magnification in selected riverine ecosystems. Sci. Total Environ.686, 393–401 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31181525</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mottaleb, M. A., Ding, Q. X., Pennell, K. G., Haynes, E. N. &amp; Morris, A. J. Direct injection analysis of per and polyfluoroalkyl substances in surface and drinking water by sample filtration and liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry. J. Chromatogr. A1653, 462426 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8935770</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34352431</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zafeiraki, E. et al. Occurrence of perfluoroalkyl substances (PFASs) in a large number of wild and farmed aquatic animals collected in the Netherlands. Chemosphere232, 415–423 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31158636</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McDermett, K. S., Guelfo, J., Anderson, T. A., Reible, D. &amp; Jackson, A. W. The development of diffusive equilibrium, high-resolution passive samplers to measure perfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) in groundwater. Chemosphere303, 134686 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35489449</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>MacGillivray, A. R. Temporal trends of per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances in Delaware River Fish, USA. Integr. Environ. Assess. Manag.17, 411–421 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32940944</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ng, K. et al. Target and suspect screening of 4777 per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) in river water, wastewater, groundwater and biota samples in the Danube River Basin. J. Hazard. Mater.436, 129276 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35739789</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chow, S. J. et al. Comparative investigation of PFAS adsorption onto activated carbon and anion exchange resins during long-term operation of a pilot treatment plant. Water Res.226, 119198 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11330578</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36240713</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor, M. D. Survey design for quantifying perfluoroalkyl acid concentrations in fish, prawns and crabs to assess human health risks. Sci. Total Environ.652, 59–65 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30359802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mazzoni, M. et al. Perfluoroalkyl acids in fish of Italian deep lakes: environmental and human risk assessment. Sci. Total Environ.653, 351–358 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30412880</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harrad, S., Wemken, N., Drage, D. S., Abdallah, M. A. E. &amp; Coggins, A. M. Perfluoroalkyl substances in drinking water, indoor air and dust from Ireland: implications for human exposure. Environ. Sci. Technol.53, 13449–13457 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31702898</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, X., Chen, M., Gong, P. &amp; Wang, C. Perfluorinated alkyl substances in snow as an atmospheric tracer for tracking the interactions between westerly winds and the Indian Monsoon over western China. Environ. Int.124, 294–301 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30660842</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sackaria, M. &amp; Elango, L. Organic micropollutants in groundwater of India—a review. Water Environ. Res.92, 504–523 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31545539</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bradley, P. M. et al. Mixed organic and inorganic tapwater exposures and potential effects in greater Chicago area, USA. Sci. Total Environ.719, 137236 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9140060</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32126404</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mesfin Tefera, Y. et al. Food grown on fire stations as a potential pathway for firefighters’ exposure to per- and poly-fluoroalkyl substances (PFAS). Environ. Int.168, 107455 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35964536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>East, A., Anderson, R. H. &amp; Salice, C. J. Per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) in surface water near US Air Force Bases: prioritizing individual chemicals and mixtures for toxicity testing and risk assessment. Environ. Toxicol. Chem.40, 859–870 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33026654</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woudneh, M. B., Chandramouli, B., Hamilton, C. &amp; Grace, R. Effect of sample storage on the quantitative determination of 29 PFAS: observation of analyte interconversions during storage. Environ. Sci. Technol.53, 12576–12585 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31578061</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu, L. et al. Discovery of a Novel polyfluoroalkyl benzenesulfonic acid around oilfields in northern China. Environ. Sci. Technol.51, 14173–14181 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29218982</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aristizabal-Henao, J. J. et al. Ticks as novel sentinels to monitor environmental levels of per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS). Environ. Sci.: Process. Impacts23, 1301–1307, (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34369533</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chiesa, L. M. et al. Detection of perfluoroalkyl acids and sulphonates in Italian eel samples by HPLC-HRMS Orbitrap. Chemosphere193, 358–364 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29149712</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Skaggs, C. S. &amp; Logue, B. A. Ultratrace analysis of per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances in drinking water using ice concentration linked with extractive stirrer and high performance liquid chromatography–tandem mass spectrometry. J. Chromatogr. A1659, 462493 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34706316</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Qwen, Yang, G. P., Zhang, Zming &amp; Zhang, J. Optimization of sample preparation and chromatography for the determination of perfluoroalkyl acids in sediments from the Yangtze Estuary and East China Sea. Chemosphere205, 524–530 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29709802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Y. et al. Natural biofilm as a potential integrative sample for evaluating the contamination and impacts of PFAS on aquatic ecosystems. Water Res.215, 118233 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35248909</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Procopio, N. A. et al. Occurrence and source identification of perfluoroalkyl acids (PFAAs) in the Metedeconk River Watershed, New Jersey. Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res.24, 27125–27135 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28963602</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jurikova, M., Dvorakova, D. &amp; Pulkrabova, J. The occurrence of perfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) in drinking water in the Czech Republic: a pilot study. Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res.29, 60341–60353 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35420337</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Annunziato, K. M. et al. Chemical characterization of a legacy aqueous film-forming foam sample and developmental toxicity in zebrafish (Danio rerio). Environ. Health Perspect.128, 1–13 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7510953</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32966100</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uwah, E. I., Nwoke, I. B., Inam, E. J., Udosen, I. E. &amp; Udosen, E. D. Human health risk assessment of heavy metal contamination in New Calabar River. Bull. Environ. Contam. Toxicol.105, 317–324 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32601980</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, Y. et al. Perfluoroalkyl acids in drinking water of china in 2017: distribution characteristics, influencing factors and potential risks. Environ. Int.123, 87–95 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30502598</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaccher, V. et al. Levels of persistent organic pollutants (POPs) in foods from the first regional Sub-Saharan Africa Total Diet Study. Environ. Int.135, 105413 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31881431</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koch, A. et al. Contaminants in aquatic and terrestrial environments per- and polyfluoroalkyl contaminated freshwater impacts adjacent riparian food webs per- and polyfluoroalkyl contaminated freshwater impacts adjacent riparian food webs. Environ. Sci. Technol.54, 11951–11960 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32870664</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu, Q. et al. Comprehensive screening of polar emerging organic contaminants including PFASs and evaluation of the trophic transfer behavior in a freshwater food web. Water Res.218, 118514 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35545009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bradley, P. M. et al. Pilot-scale expanded assessment of inorganic and organic tapwater exposures and predicted effects in Puerto Rico, USA. Sci. Total Environ.788, 147721 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8504685</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34134358</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schrenk, D. et al. Risk to human health related to the presence of perfluoroalkyl substances in food. EFSA J.18, e06223 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7507523</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32994824</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knutsen, H., Mæhlum, T., Haarstad, K., Slinde, G. A. &amp; Arp, H. P. H. Leachate emissions of short- and long-chain per- and polyfluoralkyl substances (PFASs) from various Norwegian landfills. Environ. Sci.: Process. Impacts21, 1970–1979 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31411188</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Langberg, H. A., Hale, S. E., Breedveld, G. D., Jenssen, B. M. &amp; Jartun, M. A review of PFAS fingerprints in fish from Norwegian freshwater bodies subject to different source inputs. Environ. Sci.: Process. Impacts24, 330–342 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35079763</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali, A. M. et al. The fate of poly- and perfluoroalkyl substances in a marine food web influenced by land-based sources in the Norwegian Arctic. Environ. Sci.: Process. Impacts23, 588–604 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33704290</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Janousek, R. M., Mayer, J. &amp; Knepper, T. P. Is the phase-out of long-chain PFASs measurable as fingerprint in a defined area? Comparison of global PFAS concentrations and a monitoring study performed in Hesse, Germany from 2014 to 2018. Trends Anal. Chem.120, 115393 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Röhler, K., Haluska, A. A., Susset, B., Liu, B. &amp; Grathwohl, P. Long-term behavior of PFAS in contaminated agricultural soils in Germany. J. Contam. Hydrol.241, 1–10 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34245996</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koppenberg, M. &amp; Hirsch, S. Markup estimation: a comparison of contemporary methods at the example of European food retailers. Agribusiness38, 108–133 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jane L Espartero, L. et al. Health-related toxicity of emerging per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances: comparison to legacy PFOS and PFOA. Environ. Res.212, 113431 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35569538</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hayman, N. T., Rosen, G., Colvin, M. A., Conder, J. &amp; Arblaster, J. A. Aquatic toxicity evaluations of PFOS and PFOA for five standard marine endpoints. Chemosphere273, 129699 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33524752</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wan, H. T., Lai, K. P. &amp; Wong, C. K. C. Comparative analysis of PFOS and PFOA toxicity on Sertoli cells. Environ. Sci. Technol.54, 3465–3475 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32119782</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vedagiri, U. K., Anderson, R. H., Loso, H. M. &amp; Schwach, C. M. Ambient levels of PFOS and PFOA in multiple environmental media. Remediation28, 9–51 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sunderland, E. M. et al. A review of the pathways of human exposure to poly- and perfluoroalkyl substances (PFASs) and present understanding of health effects. J. Exposure Sci. Environ. Epidemiol.29, 131–147 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6380916</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30470793</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Death, C. et al. Per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) in livestock and game species: a review. Sci. Total Environ.774, 144795 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33609849</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banyoi, S. M., Porseryd, T., Larsson, J., Grahn, M. &amp; Dinnétz, P. The effects of exposure to environmentally relevant PFAS concentrations for aquatic organisms at different consumer trophic levels: systematic review and meta-analyses. Environ. Pollut.315, 120422 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36244496</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brunn, H. et al. PFAS: forever chemicals—persistent, bioaccumulative and mobile. Reviewing the status and the need for their phase out and remediation of contaminated sites. Environ. Sci. Eur.35, 1–50 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Domingo, J. L. &amp; Nadal, M. Human exposure to per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) through drinking water: a review of the recent scientific literature. Environ. Res.177, 108648 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31421451</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cordner, A. et al. PFAS contamination in Europe: generating knowledge and mapping known and likely contamination with “expert-reviewed” journalism. Environ. Sci. Technol.10.1021/acs.est.3c09746 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38569050</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aminot, Y. et al. Environmental risks associated with contaminants of legacy and emerging concern at European aquaculture areas. Environ. Pollut.252, 1301–1310 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31252127</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, C. et al. Assessing the contribution of atmospheric transport and tourism activities to the occurrence of perfluoroalkyl acids (PFAAs) in an Alpine Nature Reserve. Sci. Total Environ.697, 133851 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31479908</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Danielsson, S., Faxneld, S. &amp; Soerensen, A. L. The Swedish National Monitoring Programme for Contaminants in Marine Biota (until 2018 year’s data) Temporal Trends and Spatial variations Det svenska nationella miljöövervakningsprogrammet för miljögifter i biota (fram till 2018 års data)Temporal (Swedish Museum of Natural History, Stockholm, Sweden, 2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prevedouros, K., Cousins, I. T., Buck, R. C. &amp; Korzeniowski, S. H. Sources, fate and transport of perfluorocarboxylates. Environ. Sci. Technol.40, 32–44 (2006).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16433330</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Armitage, J. et al. Modeling global-scale fate and transport of perfluorooctanoate emitted from direct sources. Environ. Sci. Technol.40, 6969–6975 (2006).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17154003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dhore, R. &amp; Murthy, G. S. Per/polyfluoroalkyl substances production, applications and environmental impacts. Bioresour. Technol.341, 125808 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34455249</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gebbink, W. A. &amp; van Leeuwen, S. P. J. Environmental contamination and human exposure to PFASs near a fluorochemical production plant: review of historic and current PFOA and GenX contamination in the Netherlands. Environ. Int.137, 105583 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32106048</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brase, R. A., Mullin, E. J. &amp; Spink, D. C. Legacy and emerging per-and polyfluoroalkyl substances: analytical techniques, environmental fate, and health effects. Int. J. Mol. Sci.22, 1–30 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7863963</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33498193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Göckener, B. et al. Tracking down unknown PFAS pollution—the direct TOP assay in spatial monitoring of surface waters in Germany. Sci. Total Environ.898, 165425 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37429475</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herlory, O. et al. Perfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) occurrence, concentrations and spatial distribution along the French Mediterranean coast and lagoons, based on active biomonitoring. Mar. Pollut. Bull.202, 116419 (2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38677107</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herzke, D. et al. Targeted PFAS analyses and extractable organofluorine—enhancing our understanding of the presence of unknown PFAS in Norwegian wildlife. Environ. Int.171, 107640 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36525896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Office, H. &amp; C. F. Safety. Risk Management of PFAS in Norway. How to manage the Risk? (H. Office, H. &amp; C. F. Safety, n.d.).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Monitoring. Contaminants in Coastal Waters of Norway 2013 Miljøgifter i norske kystområder 2013 (E. Monitoring, 2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rüdel, H. et al. Tissue concentrations of per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) in German freshwater fish: derivation of fillet-to-whole fish conversion factors and assessment of potential risks. Chemosphere292, 133483 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34979204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui, D., Li, X. &amp; Quinete, N. Occurrence, fate, sources and toxicity of PFAS: What we know so far in Florida and major gaps. Trends Anal. Chem.130, 115976 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tokranov, A. K. et al. Surface-water/groundwater boundaries affect seasonal PFAS concentrations and PFAA precursor transformations. Environ. Sci.: Process. Impacts23, 1893–1905 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8673475</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34779453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lewis, A. J. et al. Exposure pathways and bioaccumulation of per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances in freshwater aquatic ecosystems: key considerations. Sci. Total Environ.822, 153561 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35101505</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munoz, G. et al. Bioaccumulation and trophic magnification of emerging and legacy per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) in a St. Lawrence River food web. Environ. Pollut.309, 119739 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35817301</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Namiesnik, J. et al. Concentration of bioactive compounds in mussels Mytilus galloprovincialis as an indicator of pollution. Chemosphere73, 938–944 (2008).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18701128</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Viarengo, A. &amp; Canesi, L. Mussels as biological indicators of pollution. Aquaculture94, 225–243 (1991).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mcgeoch, M. A. The selection, testing and application of terrestrial insects as bioindicators The selection, testing and application of terrestrial insects as bioindicators. Biol. Rev. Camb. Philos. Soc.73, 181–201 (1998).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cominetti, M. C., de Almeida, R. F. C., Csordas, B. G., &amp; Andreotti, R. Ticks as bioindicators the presence of Trypanosoma spp. in Campo Grande City, Ms, Brazil. In International Symposium on Tick Control and Tick-borne Diseases, Vol. 3 (eds Gado, E. &amp; de Corte) (Campo Grande, MS, 1992).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, L., Qu, Y., Huang, J. &amp; Weber, R. Per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFASs) in Chinese drinking water: risk assessment and geographical distribution. Environ. Sci. Eur.33, (2021). 10.1186/s12302-020-00425-3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Domingo, J. L. et al. Human exposure to perfluorinated compounds in Catalonia, Spain: contribution of drinking water and fish and shellfish. J. Agric. Food Chem.60, 4408–4415 (2012).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22494245</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Babayev, M. et al. PFAS in drinking water and serum of the people of a southeast Alaska community: a pilot study. Environ. Pollut.305, 119246 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9090981</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35367506</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giari, L. et al. PFAS levels in fish species in the Po River (Italy): new generation PFAS, fish ecological traits and parasitism in the foreground. Sci. Total Environ.876, 162828 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36924966</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barbo, N., Stoiber, T., Naidenko, O. V. &amp; Andrews, D. Q. Locally caught freshwater fish across the United States are likely a significant source of exposure to PFOS and other perfluorinated compounds. Environ. Res.220, 115165 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36584847</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar, E. et al. Distribution of perfluoroalkyl acids in fish species from the Baltic Sea and freshwaters in Finland. Chemosphere291, 132688 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34718016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Panieri, E., Baralic, K., Djukic-Cosic, D., Djordjevic, A. B. &amp; Saso, L. PFAS molecules: a major concern for the human health and the environment. Toxics10, 1–55 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8878656</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35202231</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo, M. et al. Distribution of perfluorinated alkyl substances in marine shellfish along the Chinese Bohai Sea coast. J. Environ. Sci. Health-Part B Pestic. Food Contam. Agric. Wastes54, 271–280 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30628846</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeong, Y. J. et al. Comparing levels of perfluorinated compounds in processed marine products. Food Chem. Toxicol.126, 199–210 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30797874</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bedi, M., Sapozhnikova, Y., Taylor, R. B. &amp; Ng, C. Per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) measured in seafood from a cross-section of retail stores in the United States. J. Hazard. Mater.459, 132062 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37480610</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glüge, J. et al. An overview of the uses of per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS). Environ. Sci.: Process. Impacts22, 2345–2373 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7784712</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33125022</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kurwadkar, S. et al. Per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances in water and wastewater: a critical review of their global occurrence and distribution. Sci. Total Environ.809, 151003 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10184764</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34695467</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadia, M. et al. Forever legacies? Profiling historical PFAS contamination and current influence on groundwater used for drinking water. Sci. Total Environ.890, 164420 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37236451</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hepburn, E. et al. Contamination of groundwater with per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) from legacy landfills in an urban re-development precinct. Environ. Pollut.248, 101–113 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30784829</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anderson, J. K. et al. Grouping of PFAS for human health risk assessment: findings from an independent panel of experts. Regul. Toxicol. Pharmacol.134, 105226 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35817206</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ojo, A. F., Peng, C. &amp; Ng, J. C. Assessing the human health risks of per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances: a need for greater focus on their interactions as mixtures. J. Hazard. Mater.407, 124863 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33373965</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>