<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39363262</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>04</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>06</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1477-3155</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>22</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>03</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of nanobiotechnology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Nanobiotechnology</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Truncated M13 phage for smart detection of E. coli under dark field.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>599</StartPage><MedlinePgn>599</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">599</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12951-024-02881-y</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The urgent need for affordable and rapid detection methodologies for foodborne pathogens, particularly Escherichia coli (E. coli), highlights the importance of developing efficient and widely accessible diagnostic systems. Dark field microscopy, although effective, requires specific isolation of the target bacteria which can be hindered by the high cost of producing specialized antibodies. Alternatively, M13 bacteriophage, which naturally targets E. coli, offers a cost-efficient option with well-established techniques for its display and modification. Nevertheless, its filamentous structure with a large length-diameter ratio contributes to nonspecific binding and low separation efficiency, posing significant challenges. Consequently, refining M13 phage methodologies and their integration with advanced microscopy techniques stands as a critical pathway to improve detection specificity and efficiency in food safety diagnostics.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">We employed a dual-plasmid strategy to generate a truncated M13 phage (tM13). This engineered tM13 incorporates two key genetic modifications: a partial mutation at the N-terminus of pIII and biotinylation at the hydrophobic end of pVIII. These alterations enable efficient attachment of tM13 to diverse E. coli strains, facilitating rapid magnetic separation. For detection, we additionally implemented a convolutional neural network (CNN)-based algorithm for precise identification and quantification of bacterial cells using dark field microscopy.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The results obtained from spike-in and clinical sample analyses demonstrated the accuracy, high sensitivity (with a detection limit of 10 CFU/μL), and time-saving nature (30 min) of our tM13-based immunomagnetic enrichment approach combined with AI-enabled analytics, thereby supporting its potential to facilitate the identification of diverse E. coli strains in complex samples.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The study established a rapid and accurate detection strategy for E. coli utilizing truncated M13 phages as capture probes, along with a dark field microscopy detection platform that integrates an image processing model and convolutional neural network.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yuan</LastName><ForeName>Jiasheng</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Veterinary Medicine, Institute of Comparative Medicine, Yangzhou University, Yangzhou, 225009, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Jiangsu Coinnovation Center for Prevention and Control of Important Animal Infectious Diseases and Zoonoses, Yangzhou University, Yangzhou, 225009, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Joint International Research Laboratory of Agriculture and Agri-Product Safety, The Ministry of Education of China, Yangzhou University, Yangzhou, 225009, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhu</LastName><ForeName>Huquan</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Veterinary Medicine, Institute of Comparative Medicine, Yangzhou University, Yangzhou, 225009, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Shixinyi</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Veterinary Medicine, Institute of Comparative Medicine, Yangzhou University, Yangzhou, 225009, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Thierry</LastName><ForeName>Benjamin</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Future Industries Institute, University of South Australia, Mawson Lakes Campus, Adelaide, SA, 5095, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Chih-Tsung</ForeName><Initials>CT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Future Industries Institute, University of South Australia, Mawson Lakes Campus, Adelaide, SA, 5095, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Chen</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Information Engineering, Yangzhou University, Yangzhou, 225127, China. chen.zhang@yzu.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Jiangsu Province Engineering Research Centre of Knowledge Management and Intelligent Service, Yangzhou University, Yangzhou, 225127, China. chen.zhang@yzu.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Xin</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Veterinary Medicine, Institute of Comparative Medicine, Yangzhou University, Yangzhou, 225009, China. zhou_xin@126.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Jiangsu Coinnovation Center for Prevention and Control of Important Animal Infectious Diseases and Zoonoses, Yangzhou University, Yangzhou, 225009, China. zhou_xin@126.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Joint International Research Laboratory of Agriculture and Agri-Product Safety, The Ministry of Education of China, Yangzhou University, Yangzhou, 225009, China. zhou_xin@126.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>32271435</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Nanobiotechnology</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101152208</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1477-3155</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017104" MajorTopicYN="Y">Bacteriophage M13</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004926" MajorTopicYN="Y">Escherichia coli</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008853" MajorTopicYN="N">Microscopy</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016571" MajorTopicYN="N">Neural Networks, Computer</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005516" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Microbiology</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010957" MajorTopicYN="N">Plasmids</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Convolutional neural network</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Dark field microscopy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Escherichia coli</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Rapid quantification</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Truncated M13 bacteriophage</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors have declared that no competing interest exists.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39363262</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11451008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12951-024-02881-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12951-024-02881-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Braun P, Beyer W, Hanczaruk M, Riehm JM, Antwerpen M, Otterbein C, Oesterheld J, Grass G. Reoccurring Bovine Anthrax in Germany on the same pasture after 12 years. J Clin Microbiol. 2022;60(3): e0229121.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8925895</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35195442</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Begley M, Hill C. Stress adaptation in foodborne pathogens. Annu Rev Food Sci Technol. 2015;6:191–210.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25665171</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaper JB, Nataro JP, Mobley HL. Pathogenic Escherichia coli. Nat Rev Microbiol. 2004;2(2):123–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15040260</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed A, Rushworth JV, Hirst NA, Millner PA. Biosensors for whole-cell bacterial detection. Clin Microbiol Rev. 2014;27(3):631–46.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4135896</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24982325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Slomovic S, Pardee K, Collins JJ. Synthetic biology devices for in vitro and in vivo diagnostics. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2015;112(47):14429–35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4664311</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26598662</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Felföldi T, Heéger Z, Vargha M, Márialigeti K. Detection of potentially pathogenic bacteria in the drinking water distribution system of a hospital in Hungary. Clin Microbiol Infect. 2010;16(1):89–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19519854</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palumbo JD, Borucki MK, Mandrell RE, Gorski L. Serotyping of Listeria monocytogenes by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay and identification of mixed-serotype cultures by colony immunoblotting. J Clin Microbiol. 2003;41(2):564–71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC149718</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12574247</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin H-Y, Li D-W, Zhang N, Gu Z, Long Y-T. Analyzing carbohydrate-protein interaction based on single plasmonic nanoparticle by conventional dark field microscopy. ACS Appl Mater Interfaces. 2015;7(22):12249–53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25985863</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scherr SM, Daaboul GG, Trueb J, Sevenler D, Fawcett H, Goldberg B, Connor JH, Ünlü MS. Real-time capture and visualization of individual viruses in complex media. ACS Nano. 2016;10(2):2827–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5019356</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26760677</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu H, Tang F, Dai J, Wang C, Zhou X. Ultrasensitive and rapid count of Escherichia coli using magnetic nanoparticle probe under dark-field microscope. BMC Microbiol. 2018;18(1):100.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6122661</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30176804</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen F, Di T, Yang CT, Zhang T, Thierry B, Zhou X. Naked-Eye enumeration of single chlamydia pneumoniae based on light scattering of gold nanoparticle probe. ACS sensors. 2020;5(4):1140–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32207302</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuan J, Shen J, Chen M, Lou Z, Zhang S, Song Z, Li W, Zhou X. Artificial intelligence-assisted enumeration of ultra-small viruses with dual dark-field plasmon resonance probes. Biosens Bioelectron. 2022;199: 113893.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34923308</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braun P, Wolfschläger I, Reetz L, Bachstein L, Jacinto AC, Tocantins C, Poppe J, Grass G. Rapid microscopic detection of bacillus anthracis by fluorescent receptor binding proteins of bacteriophages. Microorganisms. 2020;8(6):934.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7356292</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32575866</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Born F, Braun P, Scholz HC, Grass G. Specific detection of yersinia pestis based on receptor binding proteins of phages. Pathogens. 2020;9(8):611.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7460101</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32727041</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schofield DA, Molineux IJ, Westwater C. Diagnostic bioluminescent phage for detection of Yersinia pestis. J Clin Microbiol. 2009;47(12):3887–94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2786668</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19828743</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meile S, Kilcher S, Loessner MJ, Dunne M. Reporter phage-based detection of bacterial pathogens: design guidelines and recent developments. Viruses. 2020;12(9):944.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7552063</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32858938</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin A, Jimenez J, Derr J, Vera P, Manapat ML, Esvelt KM, Villanueva L, Liu DR, Chen IA. Inhibition of bacterial conjugation by phage M13 and its protein g3p: quantitative analysis and model. PLoS ONE. 2011;6(5): e19991.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3102678</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21637841</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bi L, Zhang H, Hu W, Chen J, Wu Y, Chen H, Li B, Zhang Z, Choo J, Chen L. Self-assembly of Au@AgNR along M13 framework: a SERS nanocarrier for bacterial detection and killing. Biosens Bioelectron. 2023;237: 115519.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37437455</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bardhan NM, Ghosh D, Belcher AM. Carbon nanotubes as in vivo bacterial probes. Nat Commun. 2014;5:4918.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4349414</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25230005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sattar S, Bennett NJ, Wen WX, Guthrie JM, Blackwell LF, Conway JF, Rakonjac J. Ff-nano, short functionalized nanorods derived from Ff (f1, fd, or M13) filamentous bacteriophage. Front Microbiol. 2015;6:316.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4403547</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25941520</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsedev U, Lin CW, Hess GT, Sarkaria JN, Lam FC, Belcher AM. Phage particles of controlled length and genome for In Vivo targeted glioblastoma imaging and therapeutic delivery. ACS Nano. 2022;16(8):11676–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35830573</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Specthrie L, Bullitt E, Horiuchi K, Model P, Russel M, Makowski L. Construction of a microphage variant of filamentous bacteriophage. J Mol Biol. 1992;228(3):720–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1469710</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chasteen L, Ayriss J, Pavlik P, Bradbury AR. Eliminating helper phage from phage display. Nucleic Acids Res. 2006;34(21): e145.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1693883</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17088290</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao Y, Wu N, Li HD, Xue JW, Wang R, Yang T, Wang JH. Efficient pathogen capture and sensing promoted by dynamic deformable nanointerfaces. Small. 2022;18(51): e2203962.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36328708</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zavala-Martínez AB, Grelet E. M13-phage-based star-shaped particles with internal flexibility. ACS Nano. 2024;18(1):281–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38113352</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rakonjac J, Model P. Roles of pIII in filamentous phage assembly. J Mol Biol. 1998;282(1):25–41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9733639</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoffmann-Thoms S, Jakob RP, Schmid FX. Energetic communication between functional sites of the gene-3-protein during infection by phage fd. J Mol Biol. 2014;426(8):1711–22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24440124</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lorenz SH, Jakob RP, Weininger U, Balbach J, Dobbek H, Schmid FX. The filamentous phages fd and IF1 use different mechanisms to infect Escherichia coli. J Mol Biol. 2011;405(4):989–1003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21110981</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eckert B, Martin A, Balbach J, Schmid FX. Prolyl isomerization as a molecular timer in phage infection. Nat Struct Mol Biol. 2005;12(7):619–23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15937494</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Click EM, Webster RE. Filamentous phage infection: required interactions with the TolA protein. J Bacteriol. 1997;179(20):6464–71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC179564</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9335297</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Riechmann L, Holliger P. The C-terminal domain of TolA is the coreceptor for filamentous phage infection of E. coli. Cell. 1997;90(2):351–60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9244308</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams-Jones DP, Webby MN, Press CE, Gradon JM, Armstrong SR, Szczepaniak J, Kleanthous C. Tunable force transduction through the Escherichia coli cell envelope. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2023;120(47): e2306707120.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10666116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37972066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Armstrong J, Hewitt JA, Perham RN. Chemical modification of the coat protein in bacteriophage fd and orientation of the virion during assembly and disassembly. EMBO J. 1983;2(10):1641–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC555339</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6357778</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bernard JM, Francis MB. Chemical strategies for the covalent modification of filamentous phage. Front Microbiol. 2014;5:734.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4274979</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25566240</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Litjens G, Kooi T, Bejnordi BE, Setio AAA, Ciompi F, Ghafoorian M, van der Laak J, van Ginneken B, Sánchez CI. A survey on deep learning in medical image analysis. Med Image Anal. 2017;42:60–88.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28778026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen D, Wu G, Suk HI. Deep learning in medical image analysis. Annu Rev Biomed Eng. 2017;19:221–48.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5479722</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28301734</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dotto GP, Horiuchi K. Replication of a plasmid containing two origins of bacteriophage. J Mol Biol. 1981;153(1):169–76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7040678</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greenstein D, Horiuchi K. Replication enhancer-independent mutation increases the co-operativity with which an initiator protein binds its origin. J Mol Biol. 1990;211(1):91–101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2405167</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dotto GP, Horiuchi K, Zinder ND. Initiation and termination of phage f1 plus-strand synthesis. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 1982;79(23):7122–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC347290</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6961399</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dotto GP, Horiuchi K, Zinder ND. The functional origin of bacteriophage f1 DNA replication Its signals and domains. J Mol Biol. 1984;172(4):507–21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6607361</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eckert B, Schmid FX. A conformational unfolding reaction activates phage fd for the infection of Escherichia coli. J Mol Biol. 2007;373(2):452–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17822712</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Principi N, Silvestri E, Esposito S. Advantages and limitations of bacteriophages for the treatment of bacterial infections. Front Pharmacol. 2019;10:513.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6517696</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31139086</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng H, Chen IA. Rapid colorimetric detection of bacterial species through the capture of gold nanoparticles by chimeric phages. ACS Nano. 2019;13(2):1244–52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6396317</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30586498</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pang Y, Sun M, Jiang X, Li X. Convolution in convolution for network in network. IEEE Trans Neural Netw Learn Syst. 2018;29(5):1587–97.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28328517</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>