<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39361130</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>06</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1432-0614</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>108</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>03</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Applied microbiology and biotechnology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Applications of Pythium- and Phytophthora-produced volatiles in plant disease control.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>479</StartPage><MedlinePgn>479</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">479</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s00253-024-13312-1</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Volatile organic compounds (VOCs) mediate biological interactions and are produced by Pythium and Phytophthora species. These VOCs are biotechnologically relevant because the genera include important plant pathogens, whereby VOCs can aid in disease detection, and biological control agents, whereby VOCs contribute to disease control. Studies on VOC production, identification, and characterization of individual VOCs produced by Pythium and Phytophthora species are reviewed. VOCs detected in plants infected with Phytophthora species are also reviewed as potentially oomycete-derived VOCs. The Pythium- and Phytophthora-produced VOCs are compared with other microorganisms, and the main effects of these VOCs on microbial inhibition and plant-mediated effects are reviewed. These effects are summarized from direct demonstration studies and inferences based on the known functions of the identified Pythium- and Phytophthora-produced VOCs. There are two main applications of VOCs to plant disease control: the use of VOCs to detect pathogenic Pythium and Phytophthora species, e.g., e-nose detecting systems, and the use of VOC-producing biological control agents, e.g., Pythium oligandrum. Future research could understand how the VOCs are produced to engineer VOC levels in strains, analyze more oomycete species and strains, accurately quantify the VOCs produced, and exploit recent developments in analytical chemistry technology. KEY POINTS: • Compiled inventory of volatiles produced by Phytophthora and Pythium species • Volatilomes contain microbe-inhibiting and plant growth-promoting compounds • Volatile potential in disease detection and control supports analyzing more species.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sheikh</LastName><ForeName>Taha Majid Mahmood</ForeName><Initials>TMM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Lab of Food Quality and Safety of Jiangsu Province-State Key Laboratory Breeding Base, Institute of Plant Protection, Jiangsu Academy of Agricultural Sciences, 50 Zhongling St, Nanjing, 210014, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cell Biology and Genetics, Shantou University Medical College, Shantou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Jinhao</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food and Bioengineering, Henan University of Science and Technology, Luoyang, Henan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Lunji</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food and Bioengineering, Henan University of Science and Technology, Luoyang, Henan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Dongmei</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Lab of Food Quality and Safety of Jiangsu Province-State Key Laboratory Breeding Base, Institute of Plant Protection, Jiangsu Academy of Agricultural Sciences, 50 Zhongling St, Nanjing, 210014, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Deng</LastName><ForeName>Sheng</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Lab of Food Quality and Safety of Jiangsu Province-State Key Laboratory Breeding Base, Institute of Plant Protection, Jiangsu Academy of Agricultural Sciences, 50 Zhongling St, Nanjing, 210014, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Velasco de Castro Oliveira</LastName><ForeName>Juliana</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>SENAI Innovation Institute for Biotechnology, São Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Raza</LastName><ForeName>Waseem</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Jiangsu Provincial Key Lab for Organic Solid Waste Utilization, National Engineering Research Center for Organic-Based Fertilizers, Jiangsu Collaborative Innovation Center for Solid Organic Waste Resource Utilization, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wei</LastName><ForeName>Lihui</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Lab of Food Quality and Safety of Jiangsu Province-State Key Laboratory Breeding Base, Institute of Plant Protection, Jiangsu Academy of Agricultural Sciences, 50 Zhongling St, Nanjing, 210014, China. weilihui@jaas.ac.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Daly</LastName><ForeName>Paul</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6863-2536</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Lab of Food Quality and Safety of Jiangsu Province-State Key Laboratory Breeding Base, Institute of Plant Protection, Jiangsu Academy of Agricultural Sciences, 50 Zhongling St, Nanjing, 210014, China. paul4594@hotmail.co.uk.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>CARS-24-C-01</GrantID><Agency>Agriculture Research System of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>CX(22)3022</GrantID><Agency>Jiangsu Provincial Agricultural Science and Technology Independent Innovation Fund</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>FAPESP 2022/00474-1</GrantID><Agency>Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de São Paulo</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8406612</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0175-7598</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D055549">Volatile Organic Compounds</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D061046">Biological Control Agents</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011775" MajorTopicYN="Y">Pythium</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010838" MajorTopicYN="Y">Phytophthora</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055549" MajorTopicYN="Y">Volatile Organic Compounds</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010935" MajorTopicYN="Y">Plant Diseases</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000469" MajorTopicYN="N">parasitology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D061046" MajorTopicYN="Y">Biological Control Agents</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010944" MajorTopicYN="N">Plants</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Phytophthora</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pythium</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Biocontrol</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Disease detection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Volatile</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>LW and DZ are co-inventors on a patent application for <i>Py. oligandrum</i> (Patent application number CN201910757035.2) relating to the biocontrol of plant diseases using the <i>Py. oligandrum</i> GAQ1 isolate. The other authors do not have a competing interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39361130</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11450046</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00253-024-13312-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s00253-024-13312-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Almeida OAC, de Araujo NO, Dias BHS, de Sant’Anna Freitas C, Coerini LF, Ryu C-M, de Castro Oliveira JV (2022) The power of the smallest: the inhibitory activity of microbial volatile organic compounds against phytopathogens. Front Microbiol 13:951130. 10.3389/fmicb.2022.951130</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9845590</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36687575</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Angle C, Waggoner LP, Ferrando A, Haney P, Passler T (2016) Canine detection of the volatilome: a review of implications for pathogen and disease detection. Front Vet Sci 3:47. 10.3389/fvets.2016.00047</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4919317</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27446935</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bailey KL (2014) The bioherbicide approach to weed control using plant pathogens. In: Abrol DPBT (ed) Integrated pest management. Elsevier, San Diego, pp 245–266</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bělonožníková K, Hýsková V, Chmelík J, Kavan D, Čeřovská N, Ryšlavá H (2022) Pythium oligandrum in plant protection and growth promotion: Secretion of hydrolytic enzymes, elicitors and tryptamine as auxin precursor. Microbiol Res 258:126976. 10.1016/j.micres.2022.126976</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35158298</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benhamou N, Bélanger RR, Rey P, Tirilly Y (2001) Oligandrin, the elicitin-like protein produced by the mycoparasite Pythium oligandrum, induces systemic resistance to Fusarium crown and root rot in tomato plants. Plant Physiol Biochem 39:681–696. 10.1016/S0981-9428(01)01283-9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borowik P, Adamowicz L, Tarakowski R, Wacławik P, Oszako T, Ślusarski S, Tkaczyk M (2021) Application of a low-cost electronic nose for differentiation between pathogenic oomycetes Pythium intermedium and Phytophthora plurivora. Sensors (Basel) 21:1326. 10.3390/s21041326</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7918289</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33668511</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borowik P, Tarakowski R, Tkaczyk M, Ślusarski S, Oszako T (2022) Application of a low-cost electronic nose to detect of forest tree pathogens: Fusarium oxysporum and Phytophthora plurivora. IEEE Access 10:93475–93487. 10.1109/ACCESS.2022.3203390</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bradshaw-Smith RP, Whalley WM, Craig GD (1991) Interactions between Pythium oligandrum and the fungal footrot pathogens of peas. Mycol Res 95:861–865. 10.1016/S0953-7562(09)80050-6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brasier C, Scanu B, Cooke D, Jung T (2022) Phytophthora: an ancient, historic, biologically and structurally cohesive and evolutionarily successful generic concept in need of preservation. IMA Fungus 13:12. 10.1186/s43008-022-00097-z</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9235178</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35761420</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bruisson S, Alfiky A, L’Haridon F, Weisskopf L (2023) A new system to study directional volatile-mediated interactions reveals the ability of fungi to specifically react to other fungal volatiles. Front Ecol Evol 11:1128514</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carter ZT, McNaughton EJ, Fea MP, Horner I, Johnson K, Killick S, McLay J, Shields B, Stanley MC, Glen AS (2023) Evaluating scent detection dogs as a tool to detect pathogenic Phytophthora species. Conserv Sci Pract 5:e12997. 10.1111/csp2.12997</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daly P, Chen S, Xue T, Li J, Sheikh TMM, Zhang Q, Wang X, Zhang J, FitzPatrick DA, McGowan J, Shi X, Sheng D, Jiu M, Zhou D, Druzhinina IS, Wei L (2021) Dual-transcriptomic, microscopic, and biocontrol analyses of the interaction between the bioeffector Pythium oligandrum and the Pythium soft-rot of ginger pathogen Pythium myriotylum. Front Microbiol 12:765872. 10.3389/fmicb.2021.765872</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8637047</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34867897</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Lacy Costello BPJ, Evans P, Ewen RJ, Gunson HE, Jones PRH, Ratcliffe NM, Spencer-Phillips PTN (2001) Gas chromatography–mass spectrometry analyses of volatile organic compounds from potato tubers inoculated with Phytophthora infestans or Fusarium coeruleum. Plant Pathol 50:489–496. 10.1046/j.1365-3059.2001.00594.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>El Jaddaoui I, Rangel DEN, Bennett JW (2023) Fungal volatiles have physiological properties. Fungal Biol 127:1231–1240. 10.1016/j.funbio.2023.03.005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37495313</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Katatny MH, Abdelzaher HMA, Shoulkamy MA (2006) Antagonistic actions of Pythium oligandrum and Trichoderma harzianum against phytopathogenic fungi (Fusarium oxysporum and Pythium ultimum var. ultimum). Arch Phytopathol Plant Prot 39:289–301. 10.1080/03235400500222396</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garbeva P, Weisskopf L (2020) Airborne medicine: bacterial volatiles and their influence on plant health. New Phytol 226:32–43. 10.1111/nph.16282</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31651035</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garbeva P, Hordijk C, Gerards S, de Boer W (2014) Volatile-mediated interactions between phylogenetically different soil bacteria. Front Microbiol 5:289. 10.3389/fmicb.2014.00289</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4052926</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24966854</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Geiser DM, Martin FN, Espindola AS, Brown JK, Bell TH, Yang Y, Kang S (2023) Knowledge gaps, research needs, and opportunities in plant disease diagnostic assay development and validation. PhytoFrontiers 3:51–63. 10.1094/PHYTOFR-05-22-0057-FI</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo H, Qin X, Wu Y, Yu W, Liu J, Xi Y, Dou G, Wang L, Xiao H (2019) Biocontrol of gray mold of cherry tomatoes with the volatile organic monomer from Hanseniaspora uvarum, trans-cinnamaldehyde. Food Bioprocess Technol 12:1809–1820</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo Y, Jud W, Ghirardo A, Antritter F, Benz JP, Schnitzler J-P, Rosenkranz M (2020) Sniffing fungi - phenotyping of volatile chemical diversity in Trichoderma species. New Phytol 227:244–259. 10.1111/nph.16530</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32155672</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ho H (2018) The Taxonomy and biology of Phytophthora and Pythium. J Bacteriol Mycol Open Access 6:40–45. 10.15406/jbmoa.2018.06.00174</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang Y, Xu C, Ma L, Zhang K, Duan C, Mo M (2010) Characterisation of volatiles produced from Bacillus megaterium YFM3.25 and their nematicidal activity against Meloidogyne incognita. Eur J Plant Pathol 126:417–422. 10.1007/s10658-009-9550-z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Inamdar AA, Morath S, Bennett JW (2020) Fungal volatile organic compounds: more than just a funky smell? Annu Rev Microbiol 74:101–116. 10.1146/annurev-micro-012420-080428</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32905756</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamoun S, Furzer O, Jones JDG, Judelson HS, Ali GS, Dalio RJD, Roy SG, Schena L, Zambounis A, Panabières F, Cahill D, Ruocco M, Figueiredo A, Chen X-R, Hulvey J, Stam R, Lamour K, Gijzen M, Tyler BM, Grünwald NJ, Mukhtar MS, Tomé DFA, Tör M, Van Den Ackerveken G, McDowell J, Daayf F, Fry WE, Lindqvist-Kreuze H, Meijer HJG, Petre B, Ristaino J, Yoshida K, Birch PRJ, Govers F (2015) The Top 10 oomycete pathogens in molecular plant pathology. Mol Plant Pathol 16:413–434. 10.1111/mpp.12190</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6638381</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25178392</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kenney DS (1986) DeVine®—the way it was developed—an industrialist’s view. Weed Sci 34:15–16. 10.1017/S0043174500068302</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kurzawińska H, Mazur S (2007) The effect of Pythium oligandrum and chitosan used in control of potato against late blight and the occurrence of fungal diseases on tuber peel. Commun Agric Appl Biol Sci 72:967–971</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18396836</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Le Floch G, Rey P, Benizri E, Benhamou N, Tirilly Y (2003) Impact of auxin-compounds produced by the antagonistic fungus Pythium oligandrum or the minor pathogen Pythium group F on plant growth. Plant Soil 257:459–470. 10.1023/A:1027330024834</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lemfack MC, Gohlke B-O, Toguem SMT, Preissner S, Piechulla B, Preissner R (2018) mVOC 2.0: a database of microbial volatiles. Nucleic Acids Res 46:D1261–D1265. 10.1093/nar/gkx1016</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5753297</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29106611</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li S, Hu M, Tong Y, Xia Z, Tong Y, Sun Y, Cao J, Zhang J, Liu J, Zhao S, He P (2023) A review of volatile compounds in edible macroalgae. Food Res Int 165:112559. 10.1016/j.foodres.2023.112559</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36869543</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang D, Andersen CB, Vetukuri RR, Dou D, Grenville-Briggs LJ (2020) Horizontal gene transfer and tandem duplication shape the unique CAZyme complement of the mycoparasitic oomycetes Pythium oligandrum and Pythium periplocum. Front Microbiol 11:581698. 10.3389/fmicb.2020.581698</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7720654</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33329445</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lochmann F, Flatschacher D, Speckbacher V, Zeilinger S, Heuschneider V, Bereiter S, Schiller A, Ruzsanyi V (2024) Demonstrating the applicability of proton transfer teaction mass spectrometry to quantify volatiles emitted by the mycoparasitic fungus Trichoderma atroviride in real time: monitoring of Trichoderma-based biopesticides. J Am Soc Mass Spectrom 35:1168–1177. 10.1021/jasms.3c00456</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11157538</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38708575</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loulier J, Lefort F, Stocki M, Asztemborska M, Szmigielski R, Siwek K, Grzywacz T, Hsiang T, Ślusarski S, Oszako T, Klisz M, Tarakowski R, Nowakowska JA (2020) Detection of fungi and oomycetes by volatiles using e-nose and SPME-GC/MS platforms. Molecules 25:1–27. 10.3390/molecules25235749</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7730677</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33291490</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>MacDougall S, Bayansal F, Ahmadi A (2022) Emerging methods of monitoring volatile organic compounds for detection of plant pests and disease. Biosensors 12(4):239</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9025064</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35448299</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Massawe VC, Hanif A, Farzand A, Mburu DK, Ochola SO, Wu L, Tahir HAS, Gu Q, Wu H, Gao X (2018) Volatile compounds of endophytic Bacillus spp. have biocontrol activity against Sclerotinia sclerotiorum. Phytopathology 108:1373–1385. 10.1094/PHYTO-04-18-0118-R</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29927356</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCartney MM, Roubtsova TV, Yamaguchi MS, Kasuga T, Ebeler SE, Davis CE, Bostock RM (2018) Effects of Phytophthora ramorum on volatile organic compound emissions of Rhododendron using gas chromatography–mass spectrometry. Anal Bioanal Chem 410:1475–1487. 10.1007/s00216-017-0789-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29247382</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Montejano-Ramírez V, Ávila-Oviedo JL, Campos-Mendoza FJ, Valencia-Cantero E (2024) Microbial volatile organic compounds: insights into plant defense. Plants (Basel, Switzerland) 13. 10.3390/plants13152013</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11314544</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39124131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nolvachai Y, Amaral MSS, Herron R, Marriott PJ (2023) Solid phase microextraction for quantitative analysis – expectations beyond design? Green Anal Chem 4:100048. 10.1016/j.greeac.2022.100048</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paul B (1999) Pythium periplocum, an aggressive mycoparasite of Botrytis cinerea causing the gray mould disease of grape-vine. FEMS Microbiol Lett 176:25–30. 10.1016/S0378-1097(99)00213-X</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10585549</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pellan L, Dieye CA, Durand N, Fontana A, Strub C, Schorr-Galindo S (2021) Biocontrol agents: toolbox for the screening of weapons against mycotoxigenic Fusarium. J Fungi 7:446</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8226957</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34205071</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phan J, Kapcia J III, Rodriguez CI, Vogel VL, Dunham SJ, Whiteson K (2022) Capturing actively produced microbial volatile organic compounds from human-associated samples with vacuum-assisted sorbent extraction. JoVE 184:e62547. 10.3791/62547</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35723496</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pisarčik M, Hakl J, Szabó O, Nerušil P (2022) Efficacy of Pythium oligandrum on improvement of lucerne yield, root development and disease score under field conditions. Front Plant Sci 13:1045225. 10.3389/fpls.2022.1045225</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9774032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36570933</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poveda J (2021) Beneficial effects of microbial volatile organic compounds (MVOCs) in plants. Appl Soil Ecol 168:104118. 10.1016/j.apsoil.2021.104118</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiu R, Qu D, Trengove R, Agarwal M, Hardy GESJ, Ren Y (2014) Headspace solid-phase microextraction and gas chromatography-mass spectrometry for analysis of VOCs produced by Phytophthora cinnamomi. Plant Dis 98:1099–1105. 10.1094/PDIS-01-14-0049-RE</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30708787</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>R4P-Network (2016) Trends and challenges in pesticide resistance detection. Trends Plant Sci 21:834–853. 10.1016/j.tplants.2016.06.006</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27475253</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rani A, Rana A, Dhaka RK, Singh AP, Chahar M, Singh S, Nain L, Singh KP, Minz D (2023) Bacterial volatile organic compounds as biopesticides, growth promoters and plant-defense elicitors: current understanding and future scope. Biotechnol Adv 63:108078. 10.1016/j.biotechadv.2022.108078</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36513315</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sánchez-Fernández RE, Diaz D, Duarte G, Lappe-Oliveras P, Sánchez S, Macías-Rubalcava ML (2016) Antifungal volatile organic compounds from the endophyte nodulisporium sp. strain GS4d2II1a: a qualitative change in the intraspecific and interspecific interactions with Pythium aphanidermatum. Microb Ecol 71:347–364. 10.1007/s00248-015-0679-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26408189</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sánchez-Ortiz BL, Sánchez-Fernández RE, Duarte G, Lappe-Oliveras P, Macías-Rubalcava ML (2016) Antifungal, anti-oomycete and phytotoxic effects of volatile organic compounds from the endophytic fungus Xylaria sp. strain PB3f3 isolated from Haematoxylon brasiletto. J Appl Microbiol 120:1313–1325. 10.1111/jam.13101</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26920072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schoen HR, Peyton BM, Knighton WB (2016) Rapid total volatile organic carbon quantification from microbial fermentation using a platinum catalyst and proton transfer reaction-mass spectrometry. AMB Express 6:90. 10.1186/s13568-016-0264-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5052237</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27709547</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheikh TMM, Zhou D, Ali H, Hussain S, Wang N, Chen S, Zhao Y, Wen X, Wang X, Zhang J, Wang L, Deng S, Feng H, Raza W, Fu P, Peng H, Wei L, Daly P (2023a) Volatile organic compounds emitted by the biocontrol agent Pythium oligandrum contribute to ginger plant growth and disease resistance. Microbiol Spectr 11:e0151023. 10.1128/spectrum.01510-23</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10433877</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37534988</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheikh TMM, Zhou D, Haider MS, Hussain S, Wang N, Chen S, Zhao Y, Wen X, Feng H, Wang X, Zhang J, Wang L, Deng S, Raza W, Wei L, Daly P (2023b) Volatile organic compounds from Pythium oligandrum play a role in its parasitism on plant-pathogenic Pythium myriotylum. Appl Environ Microbiol 89:e0203622. 10.1128/aem.02036-22</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9973004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36744963</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen D, Tang Z, Wang C, Wang J, Dong Y, Chen Y, Wei Y, Cheng B, Zhang M, Grenville-Briggs LJ, Tyler BM, Dou D, Xia A (2019) Infection mechanisms and putative effector repertoire of the mosquito pathogenic oomycete Pythium guiyangense uncovered by genomic analysis. PLoS Genet 15:e1008116. 10.1371/journal.pgen.1008116</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6502433</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31017897</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sherwood P, Nordström I, Woodward S, Bohman B, Cleary M (2024) Detecting pathogenic Phytophthora species using volatile organic compounds. Molecules 29:1749</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11052055</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38675569</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Splivallo R, Novero M, Bertea CM, Bossi S, Bonfante P (2007) Truffle volatiles inhibit growth and induce an oxidative burst in Arabidopsis thaliana. New Phytol 175:417–424. 10.1111/j.1469-8137.2007.02141.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17635217</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stenberg JA, Sundh I, Becher PG, Björkman C, Dubey M, Egan PA, Friberg H, Gil JF, Jensen DF, Jonsson M, Karlsson M, Khalil S, Ninkovic V, Rehermann G, Vetukuri RR, Viketoft M (2021) When is it biological control? A framework of definitions, mechanisms, and classifications. J Pest Sci 94:665–676. 10.1007/s10340-021-01354-7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Swiecki T, Quinn M, Sims L, Bernhardt E, Oliver L, Popenuck T, Garbelotto M (2018) Three new Phytophthora detection methods, including training dogs to sniff out the pathogen, prove reliable. Calif Agric 72:217–225. 10.3733/ca.2018a0026</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tholl D, Hossain O, Weinhold A, Röse USR, Wei Q (2021) Trends and applications in plant volatile sampling and analysis. Plant J 106:314–325. 10.1111/tpj.15176</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33506558</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tilocca B, Cao A, Migheli Q (2020) Scent of a killer: microbial volatilome and its role in the biological control of plant pathogens. Front Microbiol 11:41. 10.3389/fmicb.2020.00041</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7018762</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32117096</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ulloa-Benítez Á, Medina-Romero YM, Sánchez-Fernández RE, Lappe-Oliveras P, Roque-Flores G, Duarte Lisci G, Herrera Suárez T, Macías-Rubalcava ML (2016) Phytotoxic and antimicrobial activity of volatile and semi-volatile organic compounds from the endophyte Hypoxylon anthochroum strain Blaci isolated from Bursera lancifolia (Burseraceae). J Appl Microbiol 121:380–400. 10.1111/jam.13174</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27159426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wenke K, Wanke D, Kilian J, Berendzen K, Harter K, Piechulla B (2012) Volatiles of two growth-inhibiting rhizobacteria commonly engage AtWRKY18 function. Plant J 70:445–459. 10.1111/j.1365-313X.2011.04891.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22188129</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilson AD (2018) Applications of electronic-nose technologies for noninvasive early detection of plant, animal and human diseases. Chemosensors 6:45</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou X, Wang Z, Li S, Rong X, Bu J, Liu Q, Ouyang Z (2024) Differentiating enantiomers by directional rotation of ions in a mass spectrometer. Science 383:612–618. 10.1126/science.adj8342</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38330101</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>