<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39362970</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>06</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2045-2322</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>14</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>03</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Scientific reports</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Sci Rep</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Production of eco composites based on natural rubber and recycled sugarcane bagasse waste to be utilised as a type of food contact.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>22996</StartPage><MedlinePgn>22996</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">22996</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1038/s41598-024-73296-w</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Natural fibres are abundant, renewable, and biodegradable, which has inspired numerous academics worldwide to investigate their possible applications in various industrial fields. The food packaging sector is seeking bio-based and biodegradable substitutes to increase sustainability. In this study, new composites were prepared from natural rubber (NR) and sugarcane bagasse fibres (SCB) with different concentrations of SCB (0, 2.5, 5, 10 &amp;20 phr). The effect of SCB on the properties of natural rubber was studied before and after the alkaline treatment of the fibres. The biocomposites are characterized using Fourier transmission infrared spectroscopy, thermogravimetric analysis, scanning electron microscope, transmission electron microscope, and dielectric measurements in addition to rheological and mechanical analysis. The overall migration test for biocomposites loaded with 20phr SCB was performed to assess the biocomposite's safety as food contact materials. The study's results indicated that, adding SCB improved the conductivity, tensile strength, and elongation at break of natural rubber. Alkaline treatment strengthened the bonding between the filler and matrix and improved biocomposites' thermal dielectric and mechanical properties. The overall migration test indicated that the alkaline treatment increased the overall migration to simulants. Accordingly, alkaline-treated NR-SCB biocomposites are effective eco-friendly food packaging candidates for certain types of food such as aqueous non-acidic products.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kamel</LastName><ForeName>Nagwa A</ForeName><Initials>NA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Microwave Physics and Dielectrics Department, Physics Research Institute, National Research Centre, Giza, Egypt. nagwakamel@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shafik</LastName><ForeName>E S</ForeName><Initials>ES</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Polymers and Pigments Department, Chemical Industrial Research Institute, National Research Centre, Giza, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nabil</LastName><ForeName>Y M</ForeName><Initials>YM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Central Laboratory of Residue Analysis of Pesticides and Heavy Metals in Food (QCAP), Agricultural Research Center (ARC), Cairo, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>El Messeih</LastName><ForeName>Salwa L Abd</ForeName><Initials>SLA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Microwave Physics and Dielectrics Department, Physics Research Institute, National Research Centre, Giza, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Sci Rep</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101563288</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2045-2322</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>9006-04-6</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D012408">Rubber</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>9006-97-7</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="C027433">bagasse</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>9004-34-6</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D002482">Cellulose</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D031786" MajorTopicYN="Y">Saccharum</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012408" MajorTopicYN="Y">Rubber</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002482" MajorTopicYN="Y">Cellulose</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018857" MajorTopicYN="Y">Food Packaging</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D059027" MajorTopicYN="N">Recycling</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013718" MajorTopicYN="N">Tensile Strength</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017550" MajorTopicYN="N">Spectroscopy, Fourier Transform Infrared</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013818" MajorTopicYN="N">Thermogravimetry</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Food contact</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Natural rubber</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Physical properties</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Polymer composites</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sugar cane bagasse</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>25</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39362970</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11450146</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-73296-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1038/s41598-024-73296-w</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Barbier, E. B. The role of Natural Resources in Economic Development (October, 2002).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Auty, R. M. Natural resources, development models and sustainable development. (2003).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamel, N. A., Abd El-messieh, S. L. &amp; Saleh, N. M. Chitosan/banana peel powder nanocomposites for wound dressing application: Preparation and characterization. Mater. Sci. Engineering: C. 72, 543–550 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28024620</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamel, N. A., Wissa, D. &amp; Abd-El-Messieh, S. L. Novel nano composites from Citrus limon and Citrullus colocynthis agricultural wastes for biomedical applications. Sci. Rep.14 (1), 17343 (2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11284205</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39069554</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khalid, M. Y. et al. Natural fiber reinforced composites: sustainable materials for emerging applications. Results Eng.11, 100263 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koul, B., Yakoob, M. &amp; Shah, M. P. Agricultural waste management strategies for environmental sustainability. Environ. Res.206, 112285 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34710442</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Forrest, M. Food Contact Rubbers 2: Products, Migration and RegulationVol. 2 (ISmithers Rapra Publishing, 2006).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nooun, P. et al. Fabrication and properties of natural rubber/rice starch/activated carbon biocomposite-based packing foam sheets and their application to shelf life extension of ‘Hom Thong’banana. Ind. Crops Prod.195, 116409 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papadopoulou, E. L. et al. Sustainable active food packaging from poly (lactic acid) and cocoa bean shells. ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces. 11 (34), 31317–31327 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31373784</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pant, R. et al. Development of FRP composites using natural fibres for food packaging. In E3S Web of Conferences. EDP Sciences. (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamouda, T. Sustainable packaging from coir fibers. In Biopolymers and Biocomposites from Agro-waste for Packaging Applications (Woodhead Publishing, 2021), pp. 113–126.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahmud, M. A. &amp; Anannya, F. R. Sugarcane bagasse-A source of cellulosic fiber for diverse applications. Heliyon, 7 (8), e07771 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8379461</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34458615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loh, Y. et al. Sugarcane bagasse—the future composite material: a literature review. Resour. Conserv. Recycl.75, 14–22 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hernández-Salas, J. et al. Comparative hydrolysis and fermentation of sugarcane and agave bagasse. Bioresour. Technol.100 (3), 1238–1245 (2009).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19000863</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al Bakri, A. M. et al. Mechanical properties of polymer composites with sugarcane bagasse filler. Adv. Mater. Res.740, 739–744 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jumaidin, R. et al. Effect of sugarcane bagasse on thermal and mechanical properties of thermoplastic cassava starch/beeswax composites. Phys. Sci. Reviews. 9 (1), 1–15 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bartos, A. et al. Reinforcement of polypropylene with alkali-treated sugarcane bagasse fibers: mechanism and consequences. Compos. Sci. Technol.200, 108428 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mente, P. et al. Natural rubber and reclaimed rubber composites – a systematic review. Polym. Sci.2 (1) (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balaji, A. et al. Effect of filler content of chemically treated short bagasse fiber-reinforced cardanol polymer composites. J. Nat. Fibers (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santos, R. J. et al. Sugarcane bagasse ash: new filler to natural rubber composite. Polímeros. 24, 646–653 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khaleefa, M. R. &amp; Kumar, P. Study on Wear Behaviour of Bagasse Filler Reinforced Vinyl Ester Composites.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Testing, A. A. S. &amp; Materials ASTM D3182-21a: Standard Practice for rubber—materials, Equipment, and Procedures for Mixing Standard Compounds and Preparing Standard Vulcanized Sheets (ASTM West Conshohocken, 2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ASTM, D. 5289; Standard Test Method for Rubber Property—Vulcanization Using Rotorless Cure Meters (West Conshohocken, PA, USA,, 2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abd-El Messieh, S. L., Rozik, N. N. &amp; Youssef, N. F. Eco‐friendly composites based on ceramic tiles industrial wastes and acrylonitrile butadiene rubber. Polym. Compos.40 (2), 544–552 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheets, S. V. &amp; Products, P. Standard test methods for Vulcanized Rubber and Thermoplastic Elastomers—. Annu. B ASTM Stand.1, 1–14 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Motawie, A. et al. Study on the properties of carbon reinforced unsaturated thermoset polyester resin nanocomposites. Available at SSRN 2790215, (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haider, K. S. Rubber soul—The Investigation of Rubber by Vibrational Spectroscopy. Master of Sciences, Program in Polymer Science, Freie Universität Berlin (Humboldt Universität zu Berlin, Technische Universität Berlin and Universität Potsdam, 2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brant, A. J. C. et al. Cellulose nanoparticles extracted from sugarcane bagasse and their use in biodegradable recipients for improving physical properties and water barrier of the latter. Mater. Sci. Appl.11 (1), 81–133 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmad, S., Wong, Y. &amp; Veloo, K. Sugarcane bagasse powder as biosorbent for reactive red 120 removals from aqueous solution. in IOP Conference Series: Earth and Environmental Science. IOP Publishing. (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mtibe, A. et al. Sequential extraction of carbohydrates and lignin from agricultural waste and their structural characterization. (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prabhakar, M. et al. Mechanical and thermal properties of epoxy composites reinforced with waste peanut shell powder as a bio-filler. Fibers Polym.16, 1119–1124 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kathiresan, S. &amp; Meenakshisundaram, O. Effect of alkali treated and untreated cellulose fibers and human hair on FTIR and tensile properties for composite material applications. SN Appl. Sci.4 (3), 74 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zarina, S. &amp; Ahmad, I. Biodegradable Composite films based on κ-carrageenan reinforced by cellulose nanocrystal from kenaf fibers. BioResources10 (1), 256–271 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naik, J. et al. Synthesis and characterization of multifunctional ZnBr2/PVA Polymer dielectrics. J. Adv. Dielectr.6 (04), 1650028 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sangeetha, M. et al. Dielectric studies and AC conductivity of PVDF-HFP: LiBF4: EC plasticized polymer electrolytes. Materials Today: Proceedings, 44: pp. 2168–2172. (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abd-El‐Messieh, S. &amp; Abd‐El‐Nour, K. Effect of curing time and sulfur content on the dielectric relaxation of styrene butadiene rubber. J. Appl. Polym. Sci.88 (7), 1613–1621 (2003).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saied, M. et al. Eco-friendly Polymer Composite Films Based on Waste Polyvinyl chloride/sunflower seed cake for Antimicrobial and Antistatic Applications (Pigment &amp; Resin Technology, 2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abd-El-Messieh, S. et al. Investigations on NBR/EPDM–Materials loaded with nano scaled Carbon Black with the applicability of conductivity models and mechanical properties. Gummi Kunst. 66, 36–45 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okrasa, L. et al. Molecular relaxation in anisotropic composites based on (hydroxypropyl) cellulose and acrylic polymer. Polymer. 42 (8), 3817–3825 (2001).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang, J. C. Carbon black filled conducting polymers and polymer blends. Adv. Polym. Technology: J. Polym. Process. Inst.21 (4), 299–313 (2002).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ridhwan, J. et al. Thermal degradation and mechanical characteristics of Sugarcane Bagasse Reinforced Biodegradable Potato Starch composites. J. Adv. Res. Fluid Mech. Therm. Sci.78 (1), 157–166 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bustamante-Torres, M. et al. Interaction between Filler and Polymeric Matrix in nanocomposites: magnetic Approach and Applications. Polymers. 13 (17), 2998 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8434030</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34503038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Belgacem, M. N. &amp; Gandini, A. Natural fibre-surface modification and characterization. Natural fibre reinforced polymer composites: from macro to nanoscale, pp. 14–46. (2009).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chand, N. &amp; Fahim, M. Tribology of Natural fiber Polymer Composites (Woodhead publishing, 2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shafik, E. S., Tharwat, C. &amp; Abd-El-Messieh, S. L. Utilization study on red brick waste as novel reinforcing and economical filler for acrylonitrile butadiene rubber composite. Clean Technol. Environ. Policy. 25 (5), 1605–1615 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rozik, N. N. et al. Mechanical and electrical properties of acrylonitrile butadiene rubber filled with waste carbon. KGK Kautschuk, Gummi, Kunststoffe, 70: pp. 30–35. (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shafik, E. S. Natural rubber biocomposites based on nanocrystalline and modified nanocrystalline cellulose: curing, mechanical, thermal and electrical properties. J. Polym. Res.28 (10), 390 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yotkuna, K. et al. Effect of flame retardant on the physical and mechanical properties of natural rubber and sugarcane bagasse composites. J. Polym. Res.28, 1–13 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zafeer, M. K. et al. Mechanical characteristics of sugarcane bagasse fibre reinforced polymer composites: a review. Cogent Eng.10 (1), 2200903 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guazzotti, V. et al. Migration testing of GPPS and HIPS polymers: swelling effect caused by food simulants compared to real foods. Molecules. 27 (3), 823 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8839621</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35164087</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu, Y. et al. Sugarcane pulp take-out containers produce more microparticles in acidic foods. Foods. 12 (13), 2496 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10340730</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37444234</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Commission, E. Commission Regulation (EU) 10/2011 of 14 January 2011 on plastic materials and articles intended to come into contact with food. Off J. Eur. Union. 12, 1–89 (2011).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Popa, E. E. et al. Polylactic acid/cellulose fibres based composites for food packaging applications. Mater. Plast.54, 673–677 (2017).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>