<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39364803</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1097-0010</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>04</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of the science of food and agriculture</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Sci Food Agric</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Modification of gel properties of Meretrix meretrix (clam) with polysaccharides: physical characterization and interaction mechanism.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jsfa.13937</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">This study investigated the contribution of 11 polysaccharides (2%, w/w), including pectin (PC), κ-carrageenan (KC), ι-carrageenan (IC), gellan gum (GG), guar gum (GM), sodium alginate (SA), konjac gum (KG), gum arabic (GA), fucoidan (FC), locust bean gum (LBG), and curdlan (CD), to the gel and microstructural properties of Meretrix meretrix clam gel (MMG).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The hardness, springiness and chewiness of MMG with KC, IC, GG, SA and FC addition increased by ~10%-250%, while PC, GM, KG and LBG groups decreased by ~0.6% to 69%. KC, IC, SA, GG and FC decreased the cooking loss rate (CLR) by 69.4% to 88.7% and correspondingly enhanced the water holding capacity (WHC) by 10.2% to 21.4%, which was accompanied by an increased bound water and immobilized water area and high hydrogen proton density. The addition of KC transformed the MMG microstructure from a loose network with large pores to a compact, dense network, reducing lacunarity by 57.9%. The primary intermolecular forces in MMG with the incorporation of KC, IC, GG, SA and FC were hydrophobic interactions and disulfide bonds, which increased by 32.8%-105.3% and 45.6%-114.5% than MMG alone, respectively.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Collectively, KC, IC, GG, SA and FC could improve the gel properties of MMG and the strongest synergistic combination was found in the MMG/KC system. This study suggests that the incorporation of polysaccharides is a strategy with potential for modifying the gel properties of shellfish surimi products. © 2024 Society of Chemical Industry.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Society of Chemical Industry.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Jia-Cheng</ForeName><Initials>JC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>SKL of Marine Food Processing &amp; Safety Control, National Engineering Research Center of Seafood, Collaborative Innovation Center of Seafood Deep Processing, Key Laboratory of Aquatic Product Processing and Quality Control, School of Food Science and Technology, Dalian Polytechnic University, Dalian, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Lin-Da</ForeName><Initials>LD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>SKL of Marine Food Processing &amp; Safety Control, National Engineering Research Center of Seafood, Collaborative Innovation Center of Seafood Deep Processing, Key Laboratory of Aquatic Product Processing and Quality Control, School of Food Science and Technology, Dalian Polytechnic University, Dalian, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Yue</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>SKL of Marine Food Processing &amp; Safety Control, National Engineering Research Center of Seafood, Collaborative Innovation Center of Seafood Deep Processing, Key Laboratory of Aquatic Product Processing and Quality Control, School of Food Science and Technology, Dalian Polytechnic University, Dalian, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Tian-Qi</ForeName><Initials>TQ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>SKL of Marine Food Processing &amp; Safety Control, National Engineering Research Center of Seafood, Collaborative Innovation Center of Seafood Deep Processing, Key Laboratory of Aquatic Product Processing and Quality Control, School of Food Science and Technology, Dalian Polytechnic University, Dalian, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lai</LastName><ForeName>Bin</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>SKL of Marine Food Processing &amp; Safety Control, National Engineering Research Center of Seafood, Collaborative Innovation Center of Seafood Deep Processing, Key Laboratory of Aquatic Product Processing and Quality Control, School of Food Science and Technology, Dalian Polytechnic University, Dalian, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Ce</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>SKL of Marine Food Processing &amp; Safety Control, National Engineering Research Center of Seafood, Collaborative Innovation Center of Seafood Deep Processing, Key Laboratory of Aquatic Product Processing and Quality Control, School of Food Science and Technology, Dalian Polytechnic University, Dalian, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yan</LastName><ForeName>Jia-Nan</ForeName><Initials>JN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>SKL of Marine Food Processing &amp; Safety Control, National Engineering Research Center of Seafood, Collaborative Innovation Center of Seafood Deep Processing, Key Laboratory of Aquatic Product Processing and Quality Control, School of Food Science and Technology, Dalian Polytechnic University, Dalian, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wu</LastName><ForeName>Hai-Tao</ForeName><Initials>HT</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2652-7508</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>SKL of Marine Food Processing &amp; Safety Control, National Engineering Research Center of Seafood, Collaborative Innovation Center of Seafood Deep Processing, Key Laboratory of Aquatic Product Processing and Quality Control, School of Food Science and Technology, Dalian Polytechnic University, Dalian, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>U22A20538</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Sci Food Agric</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0376334</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-5142</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Meretrix meretrix clam gel</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">gel properties</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">intermolecular forces</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">microstructure</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">polysaccharides</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">shellfish surimi</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39364803</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jsfa.13937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Zhao YD, Wei GP, Li JJ, Tian F, Zheng B, Gao PP et al., Comparative study on the effect of different salts on surimi gelation and gel properties. Food Hydrocoll 144:108982 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu WH, Xu WT, Han ML, Bu Y, Li XP and Li JR, Preparation, characterization, and gel characteristics of nanoemulsions stabilized with dextran‐conjugated clam Meretrix meretrix Linnaeus protein isolate. Food Chem 375:131664 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang SJ, Zhang LZ, Yin T, You J, Liu R, Wang L et al., Exploring the versatility of carbohydrates in surimi and surimi products: novel applications and future perspectives. J Sci Food Agric 104:1874–1883 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu YJ and Xu XL, Modification of myofibrillar protein functional properties prepared by various strategies: a comprehensive review. Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf 20:458–500 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang YM, Bai GP, Jin GF, Wang Y, Wang JP, Puolanne E et al., Role of low molecular additives in the myofibrillar protein gelation: underlying mechanisms and recent applications. Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr 64:1–19 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Somjid P, Panpipat W, Cheong LZ and Chaijan M, Comparative effect of cricket protein powder and soy protein isolate on gel properties of Indian mackerel surimi. Foods 11:3445 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin WL, Han YX, Liu FF, Huang H, Li LH, Yang SL et al., Effect of lipid on surimi gelation properties of the three major Chinese carp. J Sci Food Agr 100:4671–4677 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cando D, Borderías AJ and Moreno HM, Influence of amino acid addition during the storage life of high pressure processed low salt surimi gels. LWT‐Food Sci Technol 75:599–607 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang JL, Ye BB, Wang W, Li JR, Yi SM, Li XP et al., Incorporation effect of inulin and microbial transglutaminase on the gel properties of silver carp (Hypophthalmichthys molitrix) surimi. J Food Meas Charact 15:1–11 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan S, Liu XH, Sang YX and Tian GF, Gel mechanism analysis of minced scallop (Patinopecten yessoensis) meat modified by three kinds of food colloids. Food Biosci 57:103541 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aiman SA, Muhammad N and Norbert J, Polysaccharides; classification, chemical properties, and future perspective applications in fields of pharmacology and biological medicine (a review of current applications and upcoming potentialities). J Polym Environ 29:2359–2371 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei QJ, Zhang WW, Wang JJ, Thakur K, Hu F, Khan MR et al., Effect of κ‐carrageenan on the quality of crayfish surimi gels. Food Chem X 22:101497 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mi HB, Li Y, Wang C, Yi SM, Li XP and Li JR, The interaction of starch‐gums and their effect on gel properties and protein conformation of silver carp surimi. Food Hydrocoll 112:106290 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng MJ, Hong JL, Chuai PJ, Chen YH, Ni H, Li QB et al., Impacts of agar gum and fucoidan on gel properties of surimi products without phosphate. Food Sci Nutr 10:3759–3771 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tanyamon P and Soottawat B, Effect of gellan incorporation on gel properties of bigeye snapper surimi. Food Hydrocoll 77:746–753 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao N, Zou H, Sun S and Yu C, The interaction between sodium alginate and myofibrillar proteins: the rheological and emulsifying properties of their mixture. Int J Biol Macromol 161:1545–1551 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen JX, Deng TY, Wang C, Mi HB, Yi SM, Li XP et al., Effect of hydrocolloids on gel properties and protein secondary structure of silver carp surimi. J Sci Food Agric 100:2252–2260 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buda U, Priyadarshini MB, Majumdar RK, Mahanand SS, Patel AB and Mehta NK, Quality characteristics of fortified silver carp surimi with soluble dietary fiber: effect of apple pectin and konjac glucomannan. Int J Biol Macromol 175:123–130 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu K, Zhao NN, Xiang CX, Li YJ, Jiang XM, Zeng MY et al., Three‐dimensional printing properties of polysaccharide hydrocolloids‐unrinsed sturgeon surimi complex hydrogels. Foods 11:952–2947 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barrera AM, Ramı́rez JA, González‐Cabriales JJ and Vázquez M, Effect of pectins on the gelling properties of surimi from silver carp. Food Hydrocoll 16:441–447 (2002).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen L and Opara UL, Texture measurement approaches in fresh and processed foods‐a review. Food Res Int 51:823–835 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin SW, Liang X, Zhang JM, Kong BH, Sun FD, Cao CN et al., Combined effect of ultrasound treatment and κ‐carrageenan addition on the enhancement of gelling properties and rheological behavior of myofibrillar protein: an underlying mechanisms study. Int J Biol Macromol 257:128569 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang JJ, Zhao X, Zhou CY, Wang C, Zheng YY, Ye KP et al., Effects of gellan gum and inulin on mixed‐gel properties and molecular structure of gelatin. Food Sci Nutr 9:1336–1346 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vasyukova A, Kononenko M, Moshkin A, Vasyukov M, Kushnarenko A and Binkovskaya O, Influence of sodium alginate on the formation of the structure of the products from chopped and minced meat, in BIO Web of Conferences, Vol. 30. EDP Sciences, France, 01023 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding YQ, Liu R, Rong JH and Xiong SB, Heat‐induced denaturation and aggregation of actomyosin and myosin from yellowcheek carp during setting. Food Chem 149:237–243 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang C, Chen L, Lu MX, Ai C, Cao H, Xiao JB et al., Effect of cellulose on gel properties of heat‐induced low‐salt surimi gels: physicochemical characteristics, water distribution and microstructure. Food Chem: X 19:100820 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lian FL, Cheng JH, Ma J and Sun DW, LF‐NMR and MRI analyses of water status and distribution in pork patties during combined roasting with steam cooking. Food Biosci 56:103325 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang XB, Liu QG, Wang PK, Song CY, Ma HT, Hong PZ et al., Tapioca starch improves the quality of Virgatus nemipterus surimi gel by enhancing molecular interaction in the gel system. Foods 13:169 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leng L, Zou H, Wang Y, Yu C and Qi H, Seaweed slurry improved gel properties and enhanced protein structure of silver carp (Hypophthalmichthys molitrix) surimi. Foods 11:3115 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu WY, Wang ZM, Pan YX, Jiang PF, Pan JF, Yu CX et al., Effect of κ‐carrageenan on quality improvement of 3D printed Hypophthalmichthys molitrix‐sea cucumber compound surimi product. LWT‐Food Sci Technol 154:112279 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toshifumi U, Gopinath M, Anand M, Rakesh KS and Kong FB, Current and emerging applications of carrageenan in the food industry. Food Res Int 173:113369 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gentile L, Protein‐polysaccharide interactions and aggregates in food formulations. Curr Opin Colloid Interface Sci 48:18–27 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li M, Li B and Zhang WJ, Rapid and non‐invasive detection and imaging of the hydrocolloid‐injected prawns with low‐field NMR and MRI. Food Chem 242:16–21 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li S, Lin SY, Jiang PF, Bao ZJ, He XQ and Sun N, Contribution of κ‐/ι‐carrageenan on the gelling properties of shrimp myofibrillar protein and their interaction mechanism exploration. J Sci Food Agric 103:524–533 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ellis AL, Mills TB, Norton IT and Norton‐Welch AB, The hydrophobic modification of kappa‐carrageenan microgel particles for the stabilisation of foams. J Colloid Interf Sci 538:165–173 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang HM, Xiong YT, Bakry AM, Xiong SB, Yin T, Zhang BJ et al., Effect of yeast β‐glucan on gel properties, spatial structure and sensory characteristics of silver carp surimi. Food Hydrocoll 88:256–264 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang T, Xu XQ, Ji L, Li ZJ, Wang YM, Xue Y et al., Phase behaviors involved in surimi gel system: effects of phase separation on gelation of myofibrillar protein and kappa‐carrageenan. Food Res Int 100:361–368 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deng X, Ni X, Han J, Yao W, Fang Y, Zhu Q et al., High‐intensity ultrasound modified the functional properties of Neosalanx taihuensis myofibrillar protein and improved its emulsion stability. Ultrason Sonochem 97:106458 (2023).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>