<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39363350</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1537-2537</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>03</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of environmental quality</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Environ Qual</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>From wastewater to feed: Understanding per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances occurrence in wastewater-irrigated crops.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jeq2.20630</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Reusing treated wastewater for irrigation is a sustainable way to recycle nutrients and reduce freshwater use. However, wastewater irrigation inadvertently introduces per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) into agroecosystems, causing concerns regarding potential adverse effects to ecosystem, animal, and human health. Therefore, a better understanding of the pathways by which PFAS accumulate in forage crops is needed. A greenhouse study was conducted to (1) quantify the contribution of root uptake versus foliar sorption of PFAS in corn (Zea mays) and orchard grass (Dactylis glomerata), (2) assess effects of PFAS-impacted wastewater irrigation on plant health, and (3) determine the potential implications for bioaccumulation. The greenhouse study was composed of four treatments for each forage crop to isolate the relative contribution of two uptake pathways. Results suggested that foliar sorption was an unlikely contributor to PFAS concentrations observed in crop tissue. Root uptake was identified as the predominant uptake pathway. PFAS were detected more frequently in orchard grass samples compared to corn silage samples. Additionally, corn exhibited a lower uptake of long-chain PFAS compared to grass. Overall, no plant health effects on growth attributable to PFAS concentrations were observed. Forage data suggest cattle exposure to PFAS would be largely short-chain PFAS or long-chain "replacement" compounds (&gt;50%). However, cattle may still be exposed to potentially harmful long-chain PFAS; levels in the forage crops exceeded the tolerable weekly intake set by the European Food Safety Authority. This study provides insights on PFAS entry into the food chain and potential implications for livestock and human health.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Journal of Environmental Quality published by Wiley Periodicals LLC on behalf of American Society of Agronomy, Crop Science Society of America, and Soil Science Society of America.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kosiarski</LastName><ForeName>Kelly</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Agricultural and Biological Engineering, The Pennsylvania State University, University Park, Pennsylvania, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Usner</LastName><ForeName>Charles Zeke</ForeName><Initials>CZ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Agricultural and Biological Engineering, The Pennsylvania State University, University Park, Pennsylvania, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Preisendanz</LastName><ForeName>Heather E</ForeName><Initials>HE</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2145-2538</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Agricultural and Biological Engineering, The Pennsylvania State University, University Park, Pennsylvania, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Sustainable, Agricultural, Food and Environmental Science, College of Agricultural Sciences, The Pennsylvania State University, University Park, Pennsylvania, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>Project PEN04726</GrantID><Agency>USDA National Institute of Food and Agriculture</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>Accession number 7000254</GrantID><Agency>USDA National Institute of Food and Agriculture</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>Project PEN04870</GrantID><Agency>USDA National Institute of Food and Agriculture</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>Accession number 7005711</GrantID><Agency>USDA National Institute of Food and Agriculture</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>G-70444-03</GrantID><Agency>USDA Natural Resources Conservation Service</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Environ Qual</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0330666</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0047-2425</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>7</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39363350</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jeq2.20630</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Agency for Toxic Substances and Disease Registry (ASTDR). (2021). Toxicological profile for perfluoroalkyls. https://www.atsdr.cdc.gov/toxprofiles/tp200.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahrens, L., Gashaw, H., Sjöholm, M., Gebrehiwot Gebreyohannis, S., Getahun, A., Derbe, E., Bishop, K., &amp; Åkerblom, S. (2016). Poly‐and perfluoroalkylated substances (PFASs) in water, sediment, and fish muscle tissue from Lake Tana, Ethiopia, and implications for human exposure. Chemosphere, 165, 352–357. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2016.09.007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahrens, L., Shoeib, M., Harner, T., Lee, C. S., Gui, R., &amp; Reiner, E. (2011). Wastewater treatment plant and landfills as sources of polyfluoroalkyl compounds to the atmosphere. Environmental Science &amp; Technology, 45(19), 8098–8105. https://doi.org/10.1021/es1036173</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arvaniti, O. S., &amp; Stasinakis, A. S. (2015). Review on the occurrence, fate, and removal of perfluorinated compounds during wastewater treatment. Science of the Total Environment, 524–525, 81–92. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2015.04.023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asselt, E. D., Kowalczyk, J., Eijkeren, J. C. H., Zeilmaker, M. J., Ehlers, S., Fürst, P., Lahrssen‐Wiederholt, M., &amp; Fels‐Klerx, H. J. (2013). Transfer of perfluorooctane sulfonic acid (PFOS) from contaminated feed to dairy milk. Food Chemistry, 141(2), 1489–1495. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2013.04.035</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ayers, R. S., &amp; Westcot, D. W. (1976). Water quality for agriculture. FAO. https://www.waterboards.ca.gov/water_issues/programs/tmdl/records/state_board/1985/ref2648.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benskin, J., Muir, D., Scott, B., Spencer, C., De Silva, A., Henrik, K., Martin, J., Morris, A., Lohmann, R., Tomy, G., Rosenberg, B., Taniyasu, S., &amp; Yamashita, N. (2012). Perfluoroalkyl acids in the Atlantic and Canadian Arctic Oceans. Environmental Science &amp; Technology, 46(11), 5815–5823. https://doi.org/10.1021/es300578x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhalsod, G. D., Chuang, Y., Jeon, S., Gui, W., Li, H., Ryser, E., Guber, A. K., &amp; Zhang, W. (2018). Uptake and accumulation of pharmaceuticals in overhead‐ and surface‐irrigated greenhouse lettuce. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 66(4), 822–830. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jafc.7b04355</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blaine, A., Rich, C., Hundal, L., Lau, C., Mills, M., Harris, K., &amp; Higgins, C. (2013). Uptake of perfluoroalkyl acids into edible crops via land applied biosolids: Field and greenhouse studies. Environmental Science &amp; Technology, 47(24), 14062–14069. https://doi.org/10.1021/es403094q</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blaine, A., Rich, C., Sedlacko, E., Hyland, K., Stushnoff, C., Dickenson, E., &amp; Higgins, C. (2014). Perfluoroalkyl acid uptake in lettuce (Lactuca sativa) and strawberry (Fragaria ananassa) irrigated with reclaimed water. Environmental Science &amp; Technology, 48(24), 14361–14368. https://doi.org/10.1021/es504150h</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bräunig, J., Baduel, C., Heffernan, A., Rotander, A., Donaldson, E., &amp; Mueller, J. F. (2017). Fate, and redistribution of perfluoroalkyl acids through AFFF‐impacted groundwater. Science of the Total Environment, 596–597, 360–368. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2017.04.095</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Che, J., Xu, C., Song, X., Ding, X., Ali, M., &amp; Chen, H. (2024). Bioaccumulation of PFASs in cabbage collected near a landfill site in China: Laboratory and field investigations. Science of the Total Environment, 906, 167578. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.167578</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coggan, T. L., Moodie, D., Kolobaric, A., Szabo, D., Shimeta, J., Crosbie, N. D., Lee, E., Fernandes, M., &amp; Clarke, B. O. (2019). An investigation into per‐ and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) in nineteen Australian wastewater treatment plants (WWTPs). Heliyon, 5(8), e02316. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2019.e02316</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Costello, M. C. S., &amp; Lee, L. S. (2020). Sources, fate, and plant uptake in agricultural systems of per‐ and polyfluoroalkyl substances. Current Pollution Reports. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40726‐020‐00168‐y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA Panel on Contaminants in the Food Chain. (2020). Risk to human health related to the presence of perfluoroalkyl substances in food. EFSA Journal, 18(9). https://doi.org/10.2903/j.efsa.2020.6223</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ernst Conservation Seeds. (2023). Pennlate. https://www.ernstseed.com/?s=pennlate</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghisi, R., Vamerali, T., &amp; Manzetti, S. (2019). Accumulation of perfluorinated alkyl substances (PFAS) in agricultural plants: A review. Environmental Research, 169, 326–341. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envres.2018.10.023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gonzalez, D., Thompson, K., Quiñones, O., Dickenson, E., &amp; Bott, C. (2021). Assessment of PFAS fate, transport, and treatment inhibition associated with a simulated AFFF release within a wastewater treatment plant. Chemosphere, 262, 127900. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.127900</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gredelj, A., Nicoletto, C., Valsecchi, S., Ferrario, C., Polesello, S., Lava, R., Zanon, F., Barausse, A., Palmeri, L., Guidolin, L., &amp; Bonato, M. (2020). Uptake and translocation of perfluoroalkyl acids (PFAA) in red chicory (Cihorium intybus L.) under various treatments with pre‐contaminated and irrigation water. Science of the Total Environment, 708, 134766. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.134766</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamid, H., &amp; Li, L. (2016). Role of wastewater treatment plant in environmental cycling of poly‐ and perfluoroalkyl substances. Ecocycles, 2(2), 43–53. https://doi.org/10.19040/ecocycles.v2i2.62</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamid, H., Li, L. Y., &amp; Grace, J. R. (2020). Effect of substrate concentrations on aerobic biotransformation of 6:2 fluorotelomer sulfonate (6:2 FTS) in landfill leachate. Chemosphere, 261, 128108. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.128108</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harding‐Marjanovic, K. C., Houtz, E. F., Yi, S., Field, J. A., Sedlak, D. L., &amp; Alvarez‐Cohen, L. (2015). Aerobic biotransformation of fluorotelomer thioether amido sulfonate (Lodyne) in AFFF‐amedned microcosms. Environmental Science &amp; Technology, 49, 7666–7674. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.5b01219</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoke, R. A., Ferrell, B. D., Ryan, T., Sloman, T. L., Green, J. W., Nabb, D. L., Mingoia, R., Buck, R. C., &amp; Korzeniowski, S. H. (2015). Aquatic hazard, bioaccumulation and screening risk assessment for 6:2 fluorotelomer sulfonate. Chemosphere, 128, 258–265. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2015.01.033</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jones, G. B., Alpuerto, J. B., Tracy, B. F., &amp; Fukao, T. (2017). Physiological effect of cutting height and high temperature on regrowth vigor in orchard grass. Frontiers in Plant Science, 8, 805. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2017.00805</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kowalczyk, J., Ehlers, S., Oberhausen, A., Tischer, M., Fürst, P., Schafft, H., &amp; Lahrssen‐Wiederholt, M. (2013). Absorption, distribution, and milk secretion of the perfluoroalkyl acids PFBS, PFHxS, PFOS, and PFOA by dairy cows fed naturally contaminated feed. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 61(12), 2903–2912. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf304680</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krippner, J., Falk, S., Brunn, H., Georgii, S., Schubert, S., &amp; Stahl, T. (2015). Accumulation potentials of perfluoroalkyl carboxylic acids (PFCAs) and perfluoroalkyl sulfonic acids (PFSAs) in maize (Zea mays). Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 63(14), 3646–3653. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jafc.5b00012</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lenka, S. P., Kah, M., &amp; Padhye, L. P. (2021). A review of the occurrence, transformation, and removal of poly‐ and perfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) in wastewater treatment plants. Water Research, 199, 117187. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.watres.2021.117187</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lesmeister, L., Lange, F., Breuer, J., Biegel‐Engler, A., Giese, E., &amp; Scheurer, M. (2021). Extending the knowledge about PFAS bioaccumulation factors for agricultural plants—A review. Science of the Total Environment, 766, 142640. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.142640</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, J., Sun, J., &amp; Li, P. (2022). Exposure routes, bioaccumulation, and toxic effects of per‐ and perfluoroalkyl substances (PFASs) on plants: A critical review. Environment International, 158, 106891. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2021.106891</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lupton, S., Huwe, J., Smith, D., Dearfield, K., &amp; Johnston, J. (2012). Absorption and excretion of 14C‐perfluorooctanoic acid (PFOA) in angus cattle (Bos taurus). Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 60(4), 1128–1134. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf2042505</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lupton, S., Smith, D., Scholljegerdes, E., Ivey, S., Young, W., Genualdi, S., DeJager, L., Snyder, A., Esteban, E., &amp; Johnston, J. (2022). Plasma and skin per‐ and polyfluoroalkyl substance (PFAS) levels in dairy cattle with lifetime exposures to PFAS‐contaminated drinking water and feed. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 70(50), 15945–15954. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jafc.2c06620</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahapatra, C. T., Damayanti, N. P., Guffey, S. C., Serafin, J. S., Irudayaraj, J., &amp; Sepúlveda, M. S. (2016). Comparative in vitro toxicity assessment of perfluorinated carboxylic acids. Journal of Applied Toxicology, 37(6), 699–708. https://doi.org/10.1002/jat.3418</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McLachlan, M., Felizeter, S., Klein, M., Kotthoff, M., &amp; Voogt, P. (2019). Fate of a perfluoroalkyl acid mixture in an agricultural soil studied in lysimeters. Chemosphere, 223, 180–187. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2019.02.012</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mroczko, O., Preisendanz, H. E., Wilson, C., Mashtare, M. L., Elliott, H. A., Veith, T. L., Soder, K. J., &amp; Watson, J. E. (2022). Spatiotemporal patterns of PFAS in water and crop tissue at a beneficial wastewater reuse site in central Pennsylvania. Journal of Environmental Quality, 51(6), 1282–1297. https://doi.org/10.1002/jeq2.20408</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Navarro, D. A., Kabiri, S., Ho, J., Bowles, K. C., Davis, G., McLaughlin, M. J., &amp; Kookana, R. S. (2023). Stabilisation of PFAS in soils: Long‐term effectiveness of carbon‐based soil amendments. Environmental Pollution, 323, 0269–7491. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2023.121249</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phong Vo, H. N., Ngo, H. H., Guo, W., Nguyen, H. T. M., Li, J., Liang, H., Deng, L., Chen, Z., &amp; Hang Nguyen, T. A. (2020). Poly‐and perfluoroalkyl substances in water and wastewater: A comprehensive review from sources to remediation. Journal of Water Process Engineering, 36, 101393. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jwpe.2020.101393</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiu, R., Liu, C., Li, F., Wang, Z., Yang, Z., &amp; Cui, N. (2019). An investigation on possible effect of leaching fractions physiological responses of hot pepper plants to irrigation water salinity. BMC Plant Biology, 19(297), Article 297. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12870‐019‐1910‐z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scheiber, S. M., Sandrock, D., Alvarez, E., &amp; Brennan, M. M. (2008). Effect of salt spray concentration on growth and appearance of ‘Gracillimus’ maiden grass and ‘Hamelin’ fountain grass. HortTech, 18(1), 34–38. https://doi.org/10.21273/HORTTECH.18.1.34</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sima, M. W., &amp; Jaffé, R. P. (2021). A critical review of modeling poly‐ and perfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) in the soil‐water environment. Science of the Total Environment, 757, 143793. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.143793</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stahl, T., Heyn, J., Thiele, H., Hüther, J., Failing, K., Georgii, S., &amp; Brunn, H. (2009). Carryover of perfluorooctanoic acid (PFOA) and perfluorooctane sulfonate (PFOS) from soil to plants. Archives of Environmental Contamination and Toxicology, 57, 289–298. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00244‐008‐9272‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>United States Environmental Protection Agency (USEPA). (2022). CWA analytical methods for per‐ and polyfluorinated alkyl substances (PFAS). https://www.epa.gov/cwa‐methods/cwa‐analytical‐methods‐and‐polyfluorinated‐alkyl‐substances‐pfas</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>United States Environmental Protection Agency (USEPA). (2024). Per‐ and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS): Final PFAS national primary drinking water regulation. https://www.epa.gov/sdwa/and‐polyfluoroalkyl‐substances‐pfas</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uresk, D. W. (2010). Cattle weights on USDA forest service lands by state with cow and calf forage consumption. Rangelands, 32, 26–29.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vestergren, R., Orata, F., Berger, U., &amp; Cousins, I. T. (2013). Bioaccumulation of perfluoroalkyl acids in dairy cows in a naturally contaminated environment. Environmental Science and Pollution Research, 20, 7959–7969. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11356-013-1722-x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wallis, I., Hutson, J., Davis, G., Kookana, R., Rayner, J., &amp; Prommer, H. (2022). Model‐based identification of vadose zone controls on PFAS mobility under semi‐arid climate conditions. Water Research, 225, 119096. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.watres.2022.119096</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, N., Liu, J., Buck, R. C., Korzeniowski, S. H., Wolstenholme, B. W., Folsom, P. W., &amp; Sulecki, L. M. (2011). 6:2 fluorotelomer sulfonate aerobic biotransformation in activated sludge of wastewater treatment plants. Chemosphere, 82(6), 853–858. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2010.11.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, W., Zhang, D., Zagorevski, D., &amp; Liang, Y. (2019). Exposure of Juncus effusus to seven perfluoroalkyl acids: Uptake accumulation and phytotoxicity. Chemosphere, 233, 300–308. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2019.05.258</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Z., Chen, Q., Tan, Y., Shuang, S., Dai, R., Jiang, X., &amp; Temuer, B. (2021). Combined transcriptome and metabolome analysis of alfalfa response to thrips infection. Genes, 12(12), 1967. https://doi.org/10.3390/genes12121967</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, H., Guan, Y., Zhang, G., Zhang, Z., Tan, F., Quan, X., &amp; Chen, J. (2013). Uptake of perfluorooctane sulfonate (PFOS) by wheat (Triticum aestivum L.) plant. Chemosphere, 91(2), 139–144. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2012.11.036</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, H., Qu, B., Guan, Y., Jiang, J., &amp; Chen, X. (2016). Influence of salinity and temperature on uptake of perfluorinated carboxylic acids (PFCAs) by hydroponically grown wheat (Triticum aestivum L.). Springerplus, 5, 541. https://doi.org/10.1186/s40064‐016‐2016‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, S., Liang, T., Zhu, L., Yang, L., Liu, T., Fu, J., Wang, B., Zhan, J., &amp; Liu, L. (2019). Fate of 6:2 fluorotelomer sulfonic acid in pumpkin (Cucurbita maxima L.) based on hydroponic culture: Uptake, translocation and biotransformation. Environmental Pollution, 252, 804–812. https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0269749119301769</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng, J., Fan, J., Zhang, F., Yan, S., &amp; Xiang, Y. (2018). Rainfall partitioning into throughfall, stemflow and interception loss by maize canopy on the semi‐arid Loess Plateau of China. Agricultural Water Management, 195, 25–36. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.agwat.2017.09.013</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu, X., Song, X., &amp; Schwarzbauer, J. (2021). First insights into the formation and long‐term dynamic behaviours of perfluorooctanesulfonate and its alternative 6:2 chlorinated polyfluorinated ether sulfonate residues in a silty clay soil. Science of the Total Environment, 761, 143230. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.143230</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>