<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39369016</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2396-8370</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>8</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>05</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>NPJ science of food</Title><ISOAbbreviation>NPJ Sci Food</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Lactiplantibacillus plantarum 299V-fermented soy whey improved the safety and shelf life of Pacific oysters (Magallana gigas).</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>77</StartPage><MedlinePgn>77</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">77</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1038/s41538-024-00317-3</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>This study developed a postbiotic fermentation solution for fresh oyster preservation with the use of food waste soy whey. Lactiplantibacillus plantarum 299V was able to proliferate in soy whey within 24 h without any supplementation. Pacific oysters (Magallana gigas) were immersed in the postbiotic fermentation solution and stored at 4 °C for 12 days. Pathogenic bacteria Vibrio parahaemolyticus and Salmonella enterica introduced by bioaccumulation were suppressed to levels below the detection limit (&lt;2 log CFU/g) within 4 days. The spoilage-related microbial parameters and chemical parameters were maintained at low levels across the 12 days. Sensory evaluation revealed that the product had a positive effect on most of the participants (&gt;60%). Overall, the postbiotic fermentation solution reported in this study enhanced the shelf life and safety of oysters in a sustainable way and could also be recognized as an innovative probiotic vehicle with potential implications for human health promotion.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Lipin</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science &amp; Technology, Faculty of Science, National University of Singapore, Singapore, Singapore.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science and Engineering, Ocean University of China, Qingdao, 266003, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Food Science and Technology, Hainan University, Haikou, Hainan, 570228, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hua</LastName><ForeName>Qian</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science &amp; Technology, Faculty of Science, National University of Singapore, Singapore, Singapore.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ten</LastName><ForeName>Mei Zhen Michelle</ForeName><Initials>MZM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science &amp; Technology, Faculty of Science, National University of Singapore, Singapore, Singapore.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Zhaojie</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science and Engineering, Ocean University of China, Qingdao, 266003, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xue</LastName><ForeName>Changhu</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Food Science and Engineering, Ocean University of China, Qingdao, 266003, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Dan</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6645-2489</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Science &amp; Technology, Faculty of Science, National University of Singapore, Singapore, Singapore. dan.li@nus.edu.sg.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>NA</GrantID><Agency>NUS | Faculty of Science, National University of Singapore (NUS, FoS)</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>05</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>NPJ Sci Food</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101739627</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2396-8370</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39369016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41538-024-00317-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1038/s41538-024-00317-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11457525</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Rodezno, L. A. E. et al. Modified atmosphere packaging (MAP) on nutritional stability and quality retention of oyster meat (Crassostrea virginica) during frozen storage. J. Packag. Technol. Res.7, 11–22 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, L. et al. Identification of potential peptide markers for the shelf-life of Pacific oysters (Crassostrea gigas) during anhydrous preservation via mass spectrometry-based peptidomics. LWT134, 109922 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caron, G. et al. Campylobacter jejuni outbreak linked to raw oysters in Rhode Island, 2021. J. Food Prot.86, 100174 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37783288</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lo, Y., Wang, C., Chen, B., Hu, C. &amp; Chou, C. Prevalence and antimicrobial resistance of Salmonella in market raw oysters in Taiwan. J. Food Prot.80, 734–739 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28358258</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adams, C., Mayer, L. M., Rawson, P., Brady, D. C. &amp; Newell, C. Detrital protein contributes to oyster nutrition and growth in the Damariscotta estuary, Maine, USA. Aquac. Environ. Interact.11, 521–536 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, L. et al. Molecular mechanism of protein dynamic change in Pacific oyster (Crassostrea gigas) during depuration at different salinities uncovered by mass spectrometry-based proteomics combined with bioinformatics. Food Chem.394, 133454 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35753254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaveh, S. et al. Bio-preservation of meat and fermented meat products by lactic acid bacteria strains and their antibacterial metabolites. Sustainability15, 10154 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khubber, S., Marti-Quijal, F. J., Tomasevic, I., Remize, F. &amp; Barba, F. J. Lactic acid fermentation as a useful strategy to recover antimicrobial and antioxidant compounds for food and by-products. Curr. Opin. Food Sci.43, 189–198 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anisah, Harun, H., Jannah, H., Amelia, R. &amp; Purwati, E. Molecular identification and antimicrobial potency of probiotic lactic acid bacteria Pado (Fish Fermentation) Nagari Balingka IV Koto district-west Sumatra as a functional food. IOP Conf. Ser. Earth Environ. Sci.1188, 012039 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dejene, F., Regasa Dadi, B. &amp; Tadesse, D. In Vitro antagonistic effect of Lactic acid bacteria isolated from fermented beverage and finfish on pathogenic and foodborne pathogenic microorganism in Ethiopia. Int. J. Microbiol.2021, 1–10 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8536461</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34691185</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hua, Q., Wong, C. H. &amp; Li, D. Postbiotics enhance the functionality of a probiotic edible coating for salmon fillets and the probiotic stability during simulated digestion. Food Packag. Shelf Life34, 100954 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khouadja, S., Haddaji, N., Hanchi, M. &amp; Bakhrouf, A. Selection of lactic acid bacteria as candidate probiotics for Vibrio parahaemolyticus depuration in pacific oysters (Crassostrea gigas). Aquac. Res.48, 1885–1894 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gálvez, A., Abriouel, H., López, R. L. &amp; Omar, N. B. Bacteriocin-based strategies for food biopreservation. Int. J. Food Microbiol.120, 51–70 (2007).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17614151</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guerra, N. P., Macias, C. L., Agrasar, A. T. &amp; Castro, L. P. Development of a bioactive packaging cellophane using Nisaplin® as bio preservative agent. Lett. Appl. Microbiol.40, 106–110 (2005).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15644108</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mauriello, G., Luca, E. D., Storia, A. L., Villani, F. &amp; Ercolini, D. Antimicrobial activity of a nisin-activated plastic film for food packaging. Lett. Appl. Microbiol.41, 464–469 (2010).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16305671</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meira, S. M. M., Zehetmeyer, G., Werner, J. O. &amp; Brandelli, A. A novel active packaging material based on starch-halloysite nanocomposites incorporating antimicrobial peptides. Food Hydrocoll.63, 561–570 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu, D. et al. Soy whey as a promising substrate in the fermentation of soy sauce: a study of microbial community and volatile compounds. Int. J. Food Sci. Technol.56, 5799–5811 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou, R. Y., Huang, X., Liu, Z., Chua, J. &amp; Liu, S. Evaluating the effect of lactic acid bacterial fermentation on salted soy whey for development of a potential novel soy sauce-like condiment. Curr. Res. Food Sci.5, 1826–1836 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9579447</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36276244</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chua, J. &amp; Liu, S. Soy whey: More than just wastewater from tofu and soy protein isolate industry. Trends Food Sci. Technol.91, 24–32 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitra, D. et al. Value-added production of Nisin from soy whey. Appl. Biochem. Biotechnol.162, 1819–1833 (2010).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20853068</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun, P. et al. Antimicrobial activity of tofu whey and steam blanching pea water for enhancement of shelf-life of 3D printed mashed potatoes. Food Biosci.50, 102049 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdelazez, A., Abdelmotaal, H., Zhu, Z. T., Fang-Fang, J. &amp; Meng, X. C. Potential benefits of Lactobacillus plantarum as probiotic and its advantages in human health and industrial applications: a review. Adv. Environ. Biol.12, 16–27 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barssoum, R. et al. Biochemical limitations of Bacillus thuringiensis based biopesticides production in a wheat bran culture medium. Res. Microbiol.174, 104043 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36764472</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, R., Sun, J., Lassabliere, B., Yu, B. &amp; Liu, S. Q. UPLC-Q-TOF-MS based metabolomics and chemometric analyses for green tea fermented with Saccharomyces boulardii CNCM I-745 and Lactiplantibacillus plantarum 299V. Curr. Res. Food Sci.5, 471–478 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8892000</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35252880</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koistinen, V. M. et al. Metabolite pattern derived from Lactiplantibacillus plantarum - Fermented rye foods and in Vitro gut fermentation synergistically inhibits bacterial growth. Mol. Nutr. Food Res.66, 2101096 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9787878</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35960594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, J. et al. Isolation, purification, identification, and discovery of the antibacterial mechanism of LD-phenyllactic acid produced by Lactiplantibacillus plantarum CXG9 isolated from a traditional Chinese fermented vegetable. Food Control132, 108490 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brillhart, C. D. &amp; Joens, L. A. Prevalence and characterization of Salmonella Serovars isolated from oysters served raw in restaurants. J. Food Prot.74, 1025–1029 (2011).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21669086</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xi, D., Liu, C. &amp; Su, Y. Effects of green tea extract on reducing Vibrio parahaemolyticus and increasing shelf life of oyster meats. Food Control25, 368–373 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong, C. H. &amp; Li, D. Comparison of two strategies enhancing the antagonistic effect of lactic acid bacteria in edible coating against Listeria monocytogenes on fresh-cut apple slices. LWT182, 114923 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, Y., Ten, M. M. Z., Zwe, Y. H. &amp; Li, D. Lactiplantibacillus plantarum 299v as starter culture suppresses Enterobacteriaceae more efficiently than spontaneous fermentation of carrots. Food Microbiol.103, 103952 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35082069</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sorée, M. et al. Screening of marine lactic acid bacteria for Vibrio parahaemolyticus inhibition and application to depuration in Pacific oysters (Crassostrea gigas). J. Appl. Microbiol.134, lxac081 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36626775</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Swieca, M. et al. Lactobacillus plantarum 299V improves the microbiological quality of legume sprouts and effectively survives in these carriers during cold storage and in vitro digestion. PLoS ONE13, e0207793 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6248997</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30462723</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee, R., Lovatelli, A. &amp; Ababouch, L. Bivalve Depuration: Fundamental and Practical aspects (FAO Fisheries Technical Paper, 2008).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, C., Rui, X., Lu, Z., Li, W. &amp; Dong, M. Enhanced shelf-life of tofu by using bacteriocinogenic Weissella hellenica D1501 as bioprotective cultures. Food Control46, 203–209 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borch, E., Kantmuermans, M. L. &amp; Blixt, Y. Bacterial spoilage of meat and cured meat products. Int. J. Food Microbiol.33, 103 (1996).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8913812</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mol, S., Erkan, N., Ücok, D. &amp; Tosun, Y. Effect of psychrophilic bacteria to estimate fish quality. J. Muscle Foods18, 120–128 (2007).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Odeyemi, O. A., Burke, C. M., Bolch, C. C. J. &amp; Stanley, R. Seafood spoilage microbiota and associated volatile organic compounds at different storage temperatures and packaging conditions. Int. J. Food Microbiol.280, 87–99 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29478710</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andreani, N. A. &amp; Fasolato, L. The Microbiological Quality of Food 25–59 (Woodhead Publishing, 2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, H., Liu, Z., Shi, Y. &amp; Ding, H. H. Microbiological analysis and microbiota in oyster: a review. Invertebr. Surviv. J.13, 374–388 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bekhit, A. E. A., Holman, B. W. B., Giteru, S. G. &amp; Hopkins, D. L. Total volatile basic nitrogen (TVB-N) and its role in meat spoilage: A review. Trends Food Sci. Technol.109, 280–302 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, T. H. &amp; Bechtel, P. J. Ammonia, dimethylamine, trimethylamine, and trimethylamine oxide from raw and processed fish by-products. J. Aquat. Food Prod. Technol.17, 27–38 (2008).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, S. et al. Applications of colorimetric sensors for non-destructive predicting total volatile basic nitrogen (TVB-N) content of Fujian oyster (Crassostrea angulata). Food Control153, 109914 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alvarez, M. A. &amp; Moreno-Arribas, M. V. The problem of biogenic amines in fermented foods and the use of potential biogenic amine-degrading microorganisms as a solution. Trends Food Sci. Technol.39, 146–155 (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qu, Y., Wang, J., Liu, Z., Wang, X. &amp; Zhou, H. Effect of storage temperature and time on biogenic amines in canned seafood. Foods11, 2743 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9497643</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36140871</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baixas Nogueras, S., Bover Cid, S., Veciana Nogues, M. T., Marine Font, A. &amp; Vidal Carou, M. C. Biogenic amine index for freshness evaluation in iced Mediterranean hake (Merluccius merluccius). J. Food Prot.68, 2433–2438 (2005).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16300084</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, M., Mah, J. &amp; Hwang, H. Biogenic amine formation and bacterial contribution in fish, squid and shellfish. Food Chem.116, 87–95 (2009).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Omer, A. K., Mohammed, R. R., Ameen, P. S. M., Abas, Z. A. &amp; Ekici, K. Presence of biogenic amines in food and their public health implications: A review. J. Food Prot.84, 1539–1548 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34375430</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balamatsia, C. C., Paleologos, E. K., Kontominas, M. G. &amp; Savvaidis, I. N. Correlation between microbial flora, sensory changes and biogenic amines formation in fresh chicken meat stored aerobically or under modified atmosphere packaging at 4°C: possible role of biogenic amines as spoilage indicators. Antonie Van Leeuwenhoek89, 9–17 (2006).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16528580</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, J. H. et al. Effects of gamma irradiation on the biogenic amines in pepperoni with different packaging conditions. Food Chem.89, 199–205 (2005).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halsz, A., Bar Th, G., Simon-Sarkadi, L. &amp; Holzapfel, W. Biogenic amines and their production by microorganisms in food. Trends Food Sci. Technol.5, 42–49 (1994).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lekjing, S. &amp; Venkatachalam, K. Effects of modified atmospheric packaging conditions on the quality changes of pasteurized oyster (Crassostrea belcheri) meat during chilled storage. J. Aquat. Food Prod. Technol.27, 1106–1119 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, J. &amp; Lee, J. Korean consumers’ acceptability of commercial food products and usage of the 9‐point hedonic scale. J. Sens. Stud.33, e12467 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng, Y. &amp; O’Mahony, M. Comparison between American and Chinese consumers in the use of verbal and numerical 9-point hedonic scales and R-Index ranking for food and personal products. Food Qual. Prefer.60, 138–144 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chung, W. H., Howieson, J. &amp; Chaklader, M. R. The ameliorative effects of low-temperature pasteurization on physicochemical and microbiological quality of raw Akoya pearl oyster (Pinctada fucata). Food Control129, 108241 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma, X., Mei, J. &amp; Xie, J. Effects of multi-frequency ultrasound on the freezing rates, quality properties and structural characteristics of cultured large yellow croaker (Larimichthys crocea). Ultrason. Sonochem.76, 105657 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8261011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34229120</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang, S., Zeng, M. &amp; Zhao, Y. Thermal processed Crassostrea gigas impact the mouse gut microbiota. J. Funct. Foods75, 104254 (2020).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>