<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39364389</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>05</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2688-1152</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>5</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of the American College of Emergency Physicians open</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Am Coll Emerg Physicians Open</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Efficacy and safety of two Antivenoms in the treatment of eastern copperhead (<i>Agkistrodon contortrix</i>) envenomations in Southeast Texas.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e13310</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e13310</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e13310</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/emp2.13310</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">There are two Food and Drug Administration-approved antivenoms for the treatment of North American pitviper envenomations: Crotalidae polyvalent immune fab (ovine) (CroFab, henceforth FabAV) and Crotalidae immune F(ab')<sub>2</sub> (equine) (Anavip, henceforth Fab2AV). This study compared the effectiveness and safety of the two products in eastern copperhead envenomations.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">We retrospectively reviewed eastern copperhead bites on which our toxicology service consulted between January 1, 2021 and November 1, 2023. Collected data included patient demographics, bite location, clinical features, antivenom use, response to treatment, and adverse reactions to antivenom.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">There were 134 patients with confirmed copperhead envenomations. We administered antivenom to 89 patients, of which 36 (40%) were female. The median age was 42 years old (range: 2-89 years). Fifty-nine patients received Fab2AV and 30 were treated with FabAV. Initial control was achieved in 30 (100%) patients treated with FabAV. In the Fab2AV group, 53 (89.8%) achieved control; six patients with acute adverse reactions declined further treatment despite persistent symptoms. The median FabAV dose required for initial control was six vials (range: 4-6). A median dose of 10 vials (range: 10-30) was used in the Fab2AV group. Repeat doses of Fab2AV were required in 15 (25.4%) cases. There were no acute adverse reactions to FabAV. Acute adverse reactions were seen in seven (11.9%) of patients treated with Fab2AV.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Fewer patients treated with FabAV required repeat antivenom dosing to attain initial control following eastern copperhead envenomation. A higher percentage of patients treated with Fab2AV developed acute adverse reactions.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Journal of the American College of Emergency Physicians Open published by Wiley Periodicals LLC on behalf of American College of Emergency Physicians.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Greene</LastName><ForeName>Spencer</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1119-5582</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Houston College of Medicine Houston Texas USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>HCA Houston Healthcare Kingwood Houston USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Teshon</LastName><ForeName>Alexander</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Houston College of Medicine Houston Texas USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emergency Medicine Residency Program HCA Houston Healthcare Kingwood Houston USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>02</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Am Coll Emerg Physicians Open</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101764779</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2688-1152</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Agkistrodon</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antivenom</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">copperhead</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">envenomation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">snakebite</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Dr. Greene has served as a paid consultant and speaker for BTG International. The other author has no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>10</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>9</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39364389</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11447194</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/emp2.13310</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">EMP213310</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Gummin DD, Mowry JB, Beuhler MC, et al. 2020 Annual report of the American Association of Poison Control Centers’ National Poison Data System (NPDS): 38th annual report. Clin Toxicol. 2021;59(12):1282‐1501.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34890263</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gummin DD, Mowry JB, Beuhler MC, et al. 2021 annual report of the National Poison Data System© (NPDS) from America's poison centers: 39th annual report. Clin Toxicol. 2022;60(12):1381‐1643.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36602072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jones LLC . Venomous Animals of the United States and Canada. Rio Nuevo Publishers; 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anavip® package insert. Laboratorios Silanes S.A. de C.V. Accessed December 25, 2023. https://www.fda.gov/media/92139/download
</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
FDA
. CroFab® package insert. Accessed December 25, 2023. https://www.fda.gov/media/74683/download
</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bush SP, Ruha AM, Seifert SA, et al. Comparison of F(ab’)2 versus Fab antivenom for pit viper envenomation: a prospective, blinded, multicenter, randomized clinical trial. Clin Toxicol. 2015;53(1):37‐45.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4364250</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25361165</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mascarenas DN, Fullerton L, Smolinske SC, et al. Comparison of F (ab') 2 and Fab antivenoms in rattlesnake envenomation: first year's post‐marketing experience with F (ab’) 2 in New Mexico. Toxicon. 2020;186:42‐45.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32763251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruha AM, Kleinschmidt KC, Greene S, et al. The epidemiology, clinical course, and management of snakebites in the North American Snakebite Registry. J Med Toxicol. 2017;13:309‐320.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5711762</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28975491</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali AJ, Horwitz DA, Mullins ME. Lack of coagulopathy after copperhead snakebites. Ann Emerg Med. 2015;65(4):404‐409.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25199611</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wills BK, Billet M, Rose SR, et al. Prevalence of hematologic toxicity from copperhead envenomation: an observational study. Clin Toxicol. 2020;58(4):262‐265.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31342795</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walker JP, Morrison RL. Current management of copperhead snakebite. J Am Coll Surgeons. 2011;212(4):470‐474.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21463771</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gale SC, Peters JA, Allen L, et al. FabAV antivenin use after copperhead snakebite: clinically indicated or knee‐jerk reaction? J Venom Anim Toxins Incl Trop Dis. 2016;22:2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4711107</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26766940</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roth B, Sharma K, Onisko N, Chen T. Prospective evaluation of pain, swelling, and disability from copperhead envenomation. Clin Toxicol. 2016;54(3):271‐276.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26795406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gerardo CJ, Quackenbush E, Lewis B, et al. The efficacy of Crotalidae polyvalent immune Fab (Ovine) antivenom versus placebo plus optional rescue therapy on recovery from copperhead snake envenomation: a randomized, double‐blind, placebo‐controlled, clinical trial. Ann Emerg Med. 2017;70(2):233‐244.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28601268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryan E, Atti S, Marshall S, Rivera J, Rushton W. Repeat antivenom administration following crotalidae immune F (ab’) 2 antivenom in Agkistrodon species: a case series. Toxicol Commun. 2023;7(1):2280893.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lavonas EJ, Ruha AM, Banner W, et al. Unified treatment algorithm for the management of crotaline snakebite in the United States: results of an evidence‐informed consensus workshop. BMC Emerg Med. 2011;11(1):1‐6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3042971</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21291549</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greene S, Cheng D, Vilke GM, Winkler G. How should native crotalid envenomation be managed in the emergency department? J Emerg Med. 2021;61(1):41‐48.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33622584</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thorson A, Lavonas EJ, Rouse AM, Kerns WP. Copperhead envenomations in the Carolinas. J Toxicol Clin Toxicol. 2003;41(1):29‐35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12645965</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spiller HA, Bosse GM. Prospective study of morbidity associated with snakebite envenomation. J Toxicol Clin Toxicol. 2003;41(2):125‐130.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12733849</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freiermuth CE, Lavonas EJ, Anderson VE, et al. Antivenom treatment is associated with fewer patients using opioids after copperhead envenomation. West J Emerg Med. 2019;20(3):497.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6526891</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31123552</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corbett B, Otter J, Masom CP, Clark RF. Prevalence of acute hypersensitivity reactions in pediatric patients receiving Crotalidae polyvalent immune fab. J Med Toxicol. 2021;17:48‐50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7785595</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32710249</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khobrani M, Huckleberry Y, Boesen KJ, et al. Incidence of allergic reactions to Crotalidae polyvalent immune Fab. Clin Toxicol. 2019;57(3):164‐167.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30260274</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kleinschmidt K, Ruha AM, Campleman S, et al. Acute adverse events associated with the administration of Crotalidae polyvalent immune Fab antivenom within the North American Snakebite Registry. Clin Toxicol. 2018;56(11):1115‐1120.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29688079</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schaeffer TH, Khatri V, Reifler LM, Lavonas EJ. Incidence of immediate hypersensitivity reaction and serum sickness following administration of crotalidae polyvalent immune Fab antivenom: a meta‐analysis. Acad Emerg Med. 2012;19(2):121‐131.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22320362</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>