<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39379291</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1541-4337</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>23</Volume><Issue>6</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Comprehensive reviews in food science and food safety</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Prioritization of chemical food safety hazards in the European feed supply chain.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70025</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70025</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1541-4337.70025</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Extensive monitoring programs of chemical hazards in the animal feed chain are in place, both organized by public and private organizations. The objective of this review was to prioritize chemical hazards for monitoring in the European animal feed supply chain. A step-wise approach was designed for the prioritization, based on: historical occurrence of the chemicals in animal feed ingredients and animal feeds (in relation to European guidance values or maximum limits in feed); information on transfer of the chemical to edible animal products, and; the extent of human dietary intake of the products and possible adverse human health effects of the chemical. Possible prioritization outcomes were: high (H), medium (M), or low (L) priority for monitoring, or classification not possible (NC) because of limited available data on the transfer of the chemical to edible animal tissues. The selection of chemicals included (with results in parentheses): dioxins and polychlorinated biphenyls (H); brominated flame retardants (H); per- and polyfluorinated alkyl substances (H); the heavy metals arsenic (H) and cadmium (H) as well as lead (M) and mercury (M); aflatoxins (H), ochratoxin A (NC), and other mycotoxins (L); pyrrolizidine alkaloids (H) and other plant toxins (NC); organochlorine pesticides (H) and other pesticides (L); pharmaceutically active substances (M); hormones (NC); polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (L), heat-induced processing contaminants (NC), and mineral oils (NC). Results of this study can be used to support risk-based monitoring by food safety authorities and feed-producing companies in Europe.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety published by Wiley Periodicals LLC on behalf of Institute of Food Technologists.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>van der Fels-Klerx</LastName><ForeName>H J</ForeName><Initials>HJ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7801-394X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wageningen Food Safety Research, Wageningen, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>van Asselt</LastName><ForeName>E D</ForeName><Initials>ED</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4653-4123</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wageningen Food Safety Research, Wageningen, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>van Leeuwen</LastName><ForeName>S P J</ForeName><Initials>SPJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wageningen Food Safety Research, Wageningen, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dorgelo</LastName><ForeName>F O</ForeName><Initials>FO</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wageningen Food Safety Research, Wageningen, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hoek-van den Hil</LastName><ForeName>E F</ForeName><Initials>EF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wageningen Food Safety Research, Wageningen, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>WOT-02-004-012</GrantID><Agency>Ministerie van Landbouw, Natuur en Voedselkwaliteit</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101305205</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1541-4337</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D005411">Flame Retardants</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>DFC2HB4I0K</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D011078">Polychlorinated Biphenyls</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D004147">Dioxins</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D019216">Metals, Heavy</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000821" MajorTopicYN="Y">Animal Feed</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D059022" MajorTopicYN="Y">Food Safety</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005506" MajorTopicYN="Y">Food Contamination</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005060" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Europe</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005411" MajorTopicYN="N">Flame Retardants</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011078" MajorTopicYN="N">Polychlorinated Biphenyls</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004147" MajorTopicYN="N">Dioxins</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019216" MajorTopicYN="N">Metals, Heavy</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">animal feed</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">chemical compounds</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">contaminants</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">prioritization</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">risk ranking</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39379291</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.70025</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Abrahams, P. W., &amp; Steigmajer, J. (2003). Soil ingestion by sheep grazing the metal enriched floodplain soils of mid‐Wales. Environmental Geochemistry and Health, 25(1), 17–24.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adamse, P., Van der Fels‐Klerx, H. J., &amp; de Jong, J. (2017). Cadmium, lead, mercury and arsenic in animal feed and feed materials—Trend analysis of monitoring results. Food Additives &amp; Contaminants: Part A, 34(8), 1298‐1311. https://doi.org/10.1080/19440049.2017.1300686</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali, H., &amp; Khan, E. (2018). What are heavy metals? Long‐standing controversy over the scientific use of the term ‘heavy metals’–Proposal of a comprehensive definition. Toxicological &amp; Environmental Chemistry, 100(1), 6–19.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allen, H. K. (2014). Antibiotic resistance gene discovery in food‐producing animals. Current Opinion in Microbiology, 19, 25–29.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amlund, H., Berntssen, M., Lunestad, B., &amp; Lundebye, A.‐K. (2012). Aquaculture feed contamination by persistent organic pollutants, heavy metals, additives and drug residues. In Animal feed contamination (pp. 205–229), J Fink‐Gremmels (Ed.). Woodhead Publishing.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aust, V., Knappstein, K., Kunz, H. J., Kaspar, H., Wallmann, J., &amp; Kaske, M. (2013). Feeding untreated and pasteurized waste milk and bulk milk to calves: Effects on calf performance, health status and antibiotic resistance of faecal bacteria. Journal of Animal Physiology and Animal Nutrition, 97(6), 1091–1103.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azanu, D., Mortey, C., Darko, G., Weisser, J. J., Styrishave, B., &amp; Abaidoo, R. C. (2016). Uptake of antibiotics from irrigation water by plants. Chemosphere, 157, (Supplement C), 107–114. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2016.05.035</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bacanli, M., &amp; Başaran, N. (2019). Importance of antibiotic residues in animal food. Food and Chemical Toxicology, 00, 00–00.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Battacone, G., Nudda, A., &amp; Pulina, G. (2010). Effects of ochratoxin A on livestock production. Toxins, 2(7), 1796–1824. https://doi.org/10.3390/toxins2071796</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Battilani, P., Rossi, V., Giorni, P., Pietri, A., Gualla, A., Van der Fels‐Klerx, H. J., Booij, C. J. H., Moretti, A., Logrieco, A., Miglietta, F., Toscano, P., Miraglia, M., De Sanits, B., &amp; Brera, C. (2012). Scientific report submitted to EFSA modelling, predicting and mapping the emergence of aflatoxins in cereals in the EU due to climate change. EFSA, MODMAP‐AFLA.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benford, D., De Boer, J., Carere, A., Di Domenico, A., Johansson, N., Schrenk, D., Schoeters, G., De Voogt, P., &amp; Dellatte, E. (2008). Opinion of the Scientific Panel on contaminants in the food chain on perfluorooctane sulfonate (PFOS), perfluorooctanoic acid (PFOA) and their salts. EFSA Journal, 6(53), 1–131.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berendsen, B., Pikkemaat, M., Römkens, P., Wegh, R., van Sisseren, M., Stolker, L., &amp; Nielen, M. (2013). Occurrence of chloramphenicol in crops through natural production by bacteria in soil. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 61(17), 4004–4010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berntssen, M. H. G., Valdersnes, S., Rosenlund, G., Torstensen, B. E., Zeilmaker, M. J., &amp; van Eijkeren, J. C. H. (2011). Toxicokinetics and carry‐over model of α‐hexabromocyclododecane (HBCD) from feed to consumption‐sized Atlantic salmon (Salmo salar). Food Additives &amp; Contaminants: Part A, 28(9), 1274–1286. https://doi.org/10.1080/19440049.2011.587029</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bertocchi, L., Ghidini, S., Fedrizzi, G., &amp; Lorenzi, V. (2015). Case‐study and risk management of dioxins and PCBs bovine milk contaminations in a high industrialized area in Northern Italy. Environmental Science and Pollution Research, 22(13), 9775–9785.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Binder, E. M., Tan, L. M., Chin, L. J., Handl, J., &amp; Richard, J. (2007). Worldwide occurrence of mycotoxins in commodities, feeds and feed ingredients. Animal Feed Science and Technology, 137(3/4), 265–282. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2007.06.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blanco, S. L., Martínez, A., Porro, C., &amp; Vieites, J. M. (2011). Dietary uptake of polybrominated diphenyl ethers (PBDEs), occurrence and profiles, in aquacultured turbots (Psetta maxima) from Galicia, Spain. Chemosphere, 85(3), 441–447. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2011.07.072</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brera, C., Peduto, A., Debegnach, F., Pannunzi, E., Prantera, E., Gregori, E., De Giacomo, M., &amp; De Santis, B. (2013). Study of the influence of the milling process on the distribution of deoxynivalenol content from the caryopsis to cooked pasta. Food Control, 32(1), 309–312. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2012.12.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brühl, L. (2016). Occurrence, determination, and assessment of mineral oils in oilseeds and vegetable oils. European Journal of Lipid Science and Technology, 118(3), 361–372. https://doi.org/10.1002/ejlt.201400528</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buck, R. C., Franklin, J., Berger, U., Conder, J. M., Cousins, I. T., De Voogt, P., Jensen, A. A., Kannan, K., Mabury, S. A., &amp; van Leeuwen, S. P. (2011). Perfluoroalkyl and polyfluoroalkyl substances in the environment: Terminology, classification, and origins. Integrated Environmental Assessment and Management, 7(4), 513–541.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bulder, A., Hoogenboom, L., Kan, C., Van Raamsdonk, L., Traag, W., &amp; Bouwmeester, H. (2006). Initial risk assessment of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) in feed (materials).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chenchen, W., Wenlong, W., Xiaoxue, L., Feng, M., Dandan, C., Xiaowen, Y., Shanshan, W., Pengshuai, G., Hao, L., &amp; Baoyu, Z. (2014). Pathogenesis and preventive treatment for animal disease due to locoweed poisoning. Environmental Toxicology and Pharmacology, 37(1), 336–347. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.etap.2013.11.013</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chételat, J., Amyot, M., Arp, P., Blais, J. M., Depew, D., Emmerton, C. A., Evans, M., Gamberg, M., Gantner, N., &amp; Girard, C. (2015). Mercury in freshwater ecosystems of the Canadian Arctic: Recent advances on its cycling and fate. Science of the Total Environment, 509, 41–66.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cook, D., Oliveira, C. A., Gardner, D. R., Pfister, J. A., Riet‐Correa, G., &amp; Riet‐Correa, F. (2015). Changes in swainsonine, calystegine, and nitrogen concentrations on an annual basis in Ipomoea carnea [Toxicon]. Toxicon, 95, 62–66. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.toxicon.2015.01.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Jong, J., López, P., Mol, H., Baeten, V., Fernández Pierna, J. A., Vermeulen, P., Vincent, U., Boix, A., von Holst, C., Tomaniova, M., Hajslova, J., Yang, Z., Han, L., MacDonald, S., Haughey, S. A., &amp; Elliott, C. T. (2016). Analytical strategies for the early quality and safety assurance in the global feed chain: Approaches for nitrogen adulterants in soybean meal and mineral and transformer oils in vegetable oils. Trends in Analytical Chemistry, 76, 203–215. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.trac.2015.11.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Rijk, T. C., van Egmond, H. P., van der Fels‐Klerx, H. J., Herbes, R., de Nijs, M., Samson, R. A., Slate, A. B., &amp; van der Spiegel, M. (2015). A study of the 2013 Western European issue of aflatoxin contamination of maize from the Balkan area. World Mycotoxin Journal, 8(5), 641–651. https://doi.org/10.3920/Wmj2015.1903</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Vries, M., Kwakkel, R. P., &amp; Kijlstra, A. (2006). Dioxins in organic eggs: A review. NJAS‐Wageningen Journal of Life Sciences, 54(2), 207–221.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Death, C., Bell, C., Champness, D., Milne, C., Reichman, S., &amp; Hagen, T. (2021). Per‐ and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) in livestock and game species: A review. Science of the Total Environment, 774, 144795. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.144795</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Devanaboyina, N., Rao, S. V. R., Panda, A. K., &amp; Sastry, V. R. B. (2007). Cottonseed meal in poultry diets: A review. Journal of Poultry Science, 44(2), 119–134. https://doi.org/10.2141/jpsa.44.119</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diaz, G. J., Almeida, L. X., &amp; Gardner, D. R. (2014). Effects of dietary Crotalaria pallida seeds on the health and performance of laying hens and evaluation of residues in eggs. Research in Veterinary Science, 97(2), 297–303. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.rvsc.2014.06.011</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dickinson, J. O., Cooke, M. P., King, R. R., &amp; Mohamed, P. A. (1976). Milk transfer of pyrrolizidine alkaloids in cattle. Journal of the American Veterinary Medical Association, 169(11), 1192–1196. &lt;Go to ISI&gt;://WOS:A1976CN75200004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dierengezondheidszorg_Vlaanderen_(DGZ). (2013). Een bijzonder geval van schapensterfte. http://www.dgz.be/nieuwsbericht/een‐bijzonder‐geval‐van‐schapensterfte http://www.boerderij.nl/Rundveehouderij/Nieuws/2013/2/Dertig‐schapen‐dood‐door‐vergiftiging‐1175377W/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dominguez‐Romero, E., Cariou, R., Omer, E., Marchand, P., Dervilly‐Pinel, G., Le Bizec, B., Travel, A., &amp; Jondreville, C. (2016). Tissue distribution and transfer to eggs of ingested α‐hexabromocyclododecane (α‐HBCDD) in laying hens (Gallus domesticus). Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 64(10), 2112–2119. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jafc.5b05574</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drejer‐Storm, I. M. L., Rasmussen, R. R., &amp; Rasmussen, P. H. (2014). Occurrence of pre‐ and post‐harvest mycotoxins and other secondary metabolites in Danish maize silage. Toxins, 6(8), 2256–2269. https://doi.org/10.3390/toxins6082256</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA. (2008). Mercury as undesirable substance in animal feed—Scientific Opinion of the Panel on Contaminants in the Food Chain. EFSA Journal, 6(4), 654. https://doi.org/10.2903/j.efsa.2008.654</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA. (2009). Scientific Opinion of the Panel on Contaminants in the Food Chain on a request from the European Commission on cadmium in food. EFSA Journal, 980, 1–139.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA. (2012a). Cadmium dietary exposure in the European population. EFSA Journal, 10(1), 2551. http://www.efsa.europa.eu/sites/default/files/scientific_output/files/main_documents/2551.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA. (2012b). Lead dietary exposure in the European population. EFSA Journal, 10(7), 2831. https://doi.org/10.2903/j.efsa.2012.2831</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA. (2012c). Scientific opinion on mineral oil hydrocarbons in food. EFSA Journal, 10(6), 2704.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA. (2012d). Scientific opinion on the risk for public health related to the presence of mercury and methylmercury in food. EFSA Journal, 10(12), 2985. https://doi.org/10.2903/j.efsa.2012.2985</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA. (2012e). Update of the monitoring of levels of dioxins and PCBs in food and feed. EFSA Journal, 10(7), 2832. https://efsa.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/epdf/10.2903/j.efsa.2012.2832</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA. (2014). Dietary exposure to inorganic arsenic in the European population. EFSA Journal, 12(3), 3597. http://www.efsa.europa.eu/sites/default/files/scientific_output/files/main_documents/3597.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA. (2016). Appropriateness to set a group health‐based guidance value for zearalenone and its modified forms. EFSA Panel on Contaminants in the Food Chain. EFSA Journal, 14(4), e04425.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA. (2017). Human and animal dietary exposure to ergot alkaloids. EFSA Journal, 15(7), e04902. https://doi.org/10.2903/j.efsa.2017.4902</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA. (2018). Risk for animal and human health related to the presence of dioxins and dioxin‐like PCBs in feed and food. EFSA Journal, 16(11), e05333. https://doi.org/10.2903/j.efsa.2018.5333</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA. (2020a). Risk assessment of aflatoxins in food. EFSA Journal, 18(3), e06040. https://doi.org/10.2903/j.efsa.2020.6040</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA. (2020b). Risk to human health related to the presence of perfluoroalkyl substances in food. EFSA Journal, 18(9), e06223. https://doi.org/10.2903/j.efsa.2020.6223</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA. (2021). Update of the risk assessment of hexabromocyclododecanes (HBCDDs) in food. EFSA Journal, 19(3), e06421. https://doi.org/10.2903/j.efsa.2021.6421</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA. (2023). Risks for animal health related to the presence of ochratoxin A (OTA) in feed. EFSA Journal, 21(11), e08375. https://doi.org/10.2903/j.efsa.2023.8375</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA. (2024a). Update of the risk assessment of inorganic arsenic in food. EFSA Journal, 22(1), e8488. https://doi.org/10.2903/j.efsa.2024.8488</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA. (2024b). Update of the risk assessment of polybrominated diphenyl ethers (PBDEs) in food. EFSA Journal, 22(1), e8497. https://doi.org/10.2903/j.efsa.2024.8497</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA. (2011a). Scientific opinion on hexabromocyclododecanes (HBCDDs) in food. EFSA Journal, 9(7): 2156.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA. (2011b). Scientific opinion on polybrominated diphenyl ethers (PBDEs) in food. EFSA Journal, 9(5): 2296.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elliott, S., Frio, A., &amp; Jarman, T. (2017). Heavy metal contamination of animal feedstuffs—A new survey. Journal of Applied Animal Nutrition, 5, e8, Article e8. https://doi.org/10.1017/jan.2017.7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission (1990). Council Directive 90/167/EEC of 26 March 1990 laying down the conditions governing the preparation, placing on the market and use of medicated feeding stuffs in the community (pp. 42–48). http://data.europa.eu/eli/dir/1990/167/oj</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission (2002a). Directive 2002/32/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 7 May 2002 on undesirable substances in animal feed (pp. 10–22). http://data.europa.eu/eli/dir/2002/32/oj</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission (EC) (2002b). Regulation (EC) No 178/2002 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 28 January 2002 laying down the general principles and requirements of food law, establishing the European Food Safety Authority and laying down procedures in matters of food safety (pp. 1–24). http://data.europa.eu/eli/reg/2002/178/oj</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission (EC) (2003). Regulation (EC) No 1831/2003 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 22 September 2003 on additives for use in animal nutrition (pp. 29–43). http://data.europa.eu/eli/reg/2003/1831/oj</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>(2005). Regulation (EC) No 396/2005 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 23 February 2005 on maximum residue levels of pesticides in or on food and feed of plant and animal origin and amending Council Directive 91/414/EEC Text with EEA relevance (pp. 1–16). http://data.europa.eu/eli/reg/2005/396/oj</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission (EC) (2006a). Commission Regulation (EC) No 1881/2006 of 19 December 2006 setting maximum levels for certain contaminants in foodstuffs (Text with EEA relevance) (pp. 5–24). http://data.europa.eu/eli/reg/2006/1881/oj</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission (EC) (2006b). Recommendation of 17 August 2006 on the presence of deoxynivalenol, zearalenone, ochratoxin A, T‐2 and HT‐2 and fumonisins in products intended for animal feeding (2006/576/EC) (pp. 7–10). http://data.europa.eu/eli/reco/2006/576/2016‐08‐02</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission (EC) (2009a). Regulation (EC) No 767/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 13 July 2009 on the placing on the market and use of feed, amending European Parliament and Council Regulation (EC) No 1831/2003 and repealing Council Directive 79/373/EEC, Commission Directive 80/511/EEC, Council Directives 82/471/EEC, 83/228/EEC, 93/74/EEC, 93/113/EC and 96/25/EC and Commission Decision 2004/217/EC (pp. 1–28). http://data.europa.eu/eli/reg/2009/767/oj</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission (EC) (2009b). Regulation (EC) No 1069/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 21 October 2009 laying down health rules as regards animal by‐products and derived products not intended for human consumption and repealing Regulation (EC) No 1774/2002 (Animal by‐products Regulation) (pp. 1–33). http://data.europa.eu/eli/reg/2009/1069/oj</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission (EC) (2009c). Regulation (EC) No 1107/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 21 October 2009 concerning the placing of plant protection products on the market and repealing Council Directives 79/117/EEC and 91/414/EE (pp. 1–50). http://data.europa.eu/eli/reg/2009/1107/oj</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission (EC) (2010). Commission Regulation (EU) No 37/2010 of 22 December 2009 on pharmacologically active substances and their classification regarding maximum residue limits in foodstuffs of animal origin (Text with EEA relevance) (pp. 1–72). http://data.europa.eu/eli/reg/2010/37(1)/oj</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission (EC) (2011). Regulation (EU) No 142/2011 of 25 February 2011 implementing Regulation (EC) No 1069/2009 of the European Parliament and of the Council laying down health rules as regards animal by‐products and derived products not intended for human consumption and implementing Council Directive 97/78/EC as regards certain samples and items exempt from veterinary checks at the border under that Directive (Text with EEA relevance) (pp. 1–254). http://data.europa.eu/eli/reg/2011/142/oj</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission (EC) (2023a). Commission Regulation (EU) 2023/915 of 25 April 2023 on maximum levels for certain contaminants in food and repealing Regulation (EC) No 1881/2006 (pp. 103–157). http://data.europa.eu/eli/reg/2023/915/2023‐08‐10</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission (EC) (2023b). Regulation (EU) 2023/915 of 25 April 2023 on maximum levels for certain contaminants in food and repealing Regulation (EC) No 1881/2006 (Text with EEA relevance) (pp. 103–157). http://data.europa.eu/eli/reg/2023/915/oj</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Union (EU). (2024). RASFF: Entire database. https://bigdata‐wfsr.wur.nl/2020/09/18/rasff‐entire‐database‐2/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAO. (2011). Report of the Joint FAO/WHO Expert Consultation on the Risks and Benefits of Fish 37 Consumption. FAO Fisheries and Aquaculture Report No 978 38.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FEFAC. (2019). Annual Report 2018−2019. European Commission Register of Interest Representatives ID Number 77105321408−83. https://old.fefac.eu/files/89251.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernandes, A. R., Mortimer, D., Rose, M., Smith, F., Panton, S., &amp; Garcia‐Lopez, M. (2016). Bromine content and brominated flame retardants in food and animal feed from the UK. Chemosphere, 150, 472–478. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2015.12.042</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferrario, J., Byrne, C., Winters, D., Boone, T., Vigo, C., &amp; Dupuy, A. (2003). Chlorinated dioxins and furans from kelp and copper sulfate: Initial investigations of dioxin formation in mineral feed supplements. Organohalogen Compounds, 63, 183–186.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fink‐Gremmels, J. (2012a). Introduction to animal feed contamination. In J. Fink‐Gremmels (Ed.), Animal feed contamination (pp. 1–10). Woodhead Publishing Limited.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fink‐Gremmels, J. (2012b). Introduction to animal feed contamination Chapter 1. In Animal feed contamination ‐ Effects on livestock and food safety. Woodhead Publishing Limited. ISBN:978‐1‐84569‐725‐9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frohne, D., &amp; Pfänder, H. (2005). Poisonous plants: A handbook for doctors, pharmacists, toxicologists, biologists and veterinarians (2nd ed.).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galimova, E., Amirova, Z., &amp; Galimov, S. N. (2015). Dioxins in the semen of men with infertility. Environmental Science and Pollution Research, 22(19), 14566–14569.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gatta, D., Russo, C., Giuliotti, L., Mannari, C., Picciarelli, P., Lombardi, L., Giovannini, L., Ceccarelli, N., &amp; Mariotti, L. (2013). Influence of partial replacement of soya bean meal by faba beans or peas in heavy pigs diet on meat quality, residual anti‐nutritional factors and phytoestrogen content. Archives of Animal Nutrition, 67(3), 235–247. https://doi.org/10.1080/1745039x.2013.801137</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gebbink, W. A., van der Lee, M. K., Peters, R. J. B., Traag, W. A., Dam, G. T., Hoogenboom, R. L. A. P., &amp; van Leeuwen, S. P. J. (2019). Brominated flame retardants in animal derived foods in the Netherlands between 2009 and 2014. Chemosphere, 234, 171–178. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2019.06.046</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gill, T. A. (2000). Waste from processing aquatic animals and animal products: Implications on aquatic animal pathogen transfer. FAO Fisheries Circular (FAO).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glüge, J., Scheringer, M., Cousins, I. T., DeWitt, J. C., Goldenman, G., Herzke, D., Lohmann, R., Ng, C. A., Trier, X., &amp; Wang, Z. (2020). An overview of the uses of per‐ and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS). Environmental Science: Processes &amp; Impacts, 22(12), 2345–2373. https://doi.org/10.1039/D0EM00291G</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>GMP+ I. (2016). GMP+ International.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Granby, K., Ersbøll, B. K., Olesen, P. T., Christensen, T., &amp; Sørensen, S. (2024). Per‐ and poly‐fluoroalkyl substances in commercial organic eggs via fishmeal in feed. Chemosphere, 346, 140553. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2023.140553</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grob, K., Vass, M., Biedermann, M., &amp; Neukom, H.‐P. (2001). Contamination of animal feed and food from animal origin with mineral oil hydrocarbons. Food Additives &amp; Contaminants, 18(1), 1–10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grova, N., Feidt, C., Crépineau, C., Laurent, C., Lafargue, P. E., Hachimi, A., &amp; Rychen, G. (2002). Detection of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon levels in milk collected near potential contamination sources. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 50(16), 4640–4642. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf0201071</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grundböck, F., Fiselier, K., Schmid, F., &amp; Grob, K. (2010). Mineral oil in sunflower seeds: The sources. European Food Research and Technology, 231(2), 209–213. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00217‐010‐1264‐0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo, Y., Yu, H.‐Y., Zhang, B.‐Z., &amp; Zeng, E. Y. (2009). Persistent halogenated hydrocarbons in fish feeds manufactured in South China. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 57(9), 3674–3680. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf803868b</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halle, I., Ihling, M., Lahrssen‐Wiederholt, M., Klaffke, H., &amp; Flachowsky, G. (2006). Carry‐over of acrylamide from feed (heated potato product) to eggs and body tissues of laying hens. Journal Für Verbraucherschutz Und Lebensmittelsicherheit, 1(4), 290–293. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00003‐006‐0050‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamscher, G., Pawelzick, H. T., Höper, H., &amp; Nau, H. (2005). Different behavior of tetracyclines and sulfonamides in sandy soils after repeated fertilization with liquid manure. Environmental Toxicology and Chemistry: An International Journal, 24(4), 861–868.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heres, L., Hoogenboom, R., Herbes, R., Traag, W., &amp; Urlings, B. (2010). Tracing and analytical results of the dioxin contamination incident in 2008 originating from the Republic of Ireland. Food Additives &amp; Contaminants. Part A, Chemistry, Analysis, Control, Exposure &amp; Risk Assessment, 27(12), 1733–1744. https://doi.org/10.1080/19440049.2010.522598</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoogenboom, L., Kan, C., Zeilmaker, M. J., Van Eijkeren, J., &amp; Traag, W. A. (2006). Carry‐over of dioxins and PCBs from feed and soil to eggs at low contamination levels–Influence of mycotoxin binders on the carry‐over from feed to eggs. Food Additives and Contaminants, 23(05), 518–527.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoogenboom, L. A., Mulder, P. P., Zeilmaker, M. J., van den Top, H. J., Remmelink, G. J., Brandon, E. F., Klijnstra, M., Meijer, G. A., Schothorst, R., &amp; Van Egmond, H. P. (2011). Carry‐over of pyrrolizidine alkaloids from feed to milk in dairy cows. Food Additives &amp; Contaminants. Part A, Chemistry, Analysis, Control, Exposure &amp; Risk Assessment, 28(3), 359–372. https://doi.org/10.1080/19440049.2010.547521</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoogenboom, L. A., Van Eijkeren, J. C., Zeilmaker, M. J., Mengelers, M. J., Herbes, R., Immerzeel, J., &amp; Traag, W. A. (2007). A novel source for dioxins present in recycled fat from gelatin production. Chemosphere, 68(5), 814–823. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2007.02.032</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoogenboom, L. A. P. (2012). Animal feed contamination by dioxins, polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs) and brominated flame retardants. In Animal feed contamination (pp. 131–182). Elsevier.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoogenboom, L. A. P. R., Zeilmaker, M., van Eijkeren, J., Kan, K., Mengelers, M., Luykx, D., &amp; Traag, W. (2010). Kaolinic clay derived PCDD/Fs in the feed chain from a sorting process for potatoes. Chemosphere, 78(2), 99–105.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoogenboom, L. A. P, Klop, A., Herbes, R., van Eijkeren, J. C., Zeilmaker, M. J., van Vuuren, A. M., &amp; Traag, W. A. (2015). Carry‐over of polychlorinated dibenzo‐p‐dioxins and dibenzofurans (PCDD/Fs) and polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs) in dairy cows fed smoke contaminated maize silage or sugar beet pulp. Chemosphere, 137, 214–220. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2015.07.040</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoogenboom, L. A. P., Malisch, R., van Leeuwen, S. P. J., Vanderperren, H., Hove, H., Fernandes, A., Schächtele, A., &amp; Rose, M. (2020). Congener patterns of polychlorinated dibenzo‐p‐dioxins, dibenzofurans and biphenyls as a useful aid to source identification during a contamination incident in the food chain. Science of the Total Environment, 746, 141098. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.141098</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hughes, M. F., Beck, B. D., Chen, Y., Lewis, A. S., &amp; Thomas, D. J. (2011). Arsenic exposure and toxicology: A historical perspective. Toxicological Sciences, 123(2), 305–332.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hussein, H. S., &amp; Brasel, J. M. (2001). Toxicity, metabolism, and impact of mycotoxins on humans and animals. Toxicology, 167(2), 101–134. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0300‐483X(01)00471‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Isidori, M., Lavorgna, M., Nardelli, A., Pascarella, L., &amp; Parrella, A. (2005). Toxic and genotoxic evaluation of six antibiotics on non‐target organisms. Science of the Total Environment, 346(1), 87–98. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2004.11.017</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Isosaari, P., Lundebye, A. K., Ritchie, G., Lie, Ø., Kiviranta, H., &amp; Vartiainen, T. (2005). Dietary accumulation efficiencies and biotransformation of polybrominated diphenyl ethers in farmed Atlantic salmon (Salmo salar). Food Additives &amp; Contaminants, 22(9), 829–837. https://doi.org/10.1080/02652030500195205</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jobst, H., &amp; Aldag, R. (2000). Dioxine in Lagerstätten‐Tonen. Umweltwissenschaften Und Schadstoff‐Forschung, 12(1), 2–4. https://doi.org/10.1007/bf03037783</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jondreville, C., Cariou, R., Méda, B., Dominguez‐Romero, E., Omer, E., Dervilly‐Pinel, G., Le Bizec, B., Travel, A., &amp; Baéza, E. (2017). Accumulation of Α‐hexabromocyclododecane (Α‐HBCDD) in tissues of fast‐ and slow‐growing broilers (Gallus domesticus). Chemosphere, 178, 424–431. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2017.03.064</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kan, C. A., &amp; Meijer, G. A. L. (2007). The risk of contamination of food with toxic substances present in animal feed. Animal Feed Science and Technology, 133(1–2), 84–108. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2006.08.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kan, C. A., Traag, W. A., &amp; Hoogenboom, L. A. P. (2003). Voorkomen van PAK's in voer, omgeving van dieren, melken zuivelproducten alsmede een oriënterende studie in melkvee. http://edepot.wur.nl/27783</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan, Z., Ahmad, K., Bayat, A., Mukhtar, M., &amp; Sher, M. (2013). Evaluation of lead concentration in pasture and milk: A possible risk for livestock and public health. Pakistan Journal of Zoology, 45, 79–84.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kierkegaard, A., Asplund, L., de Wit, C. A., McLachlan, M. S., Thomas, G. O., Sweetman, A. J., &amp; Jones, K. C. (2007). Fate of higher brominated PBDEs in lactating cows. Environmental Science &amp; Technology, 41(2), 417–423.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kierkegaard, A., De Wit, C. A., Asplund, L., McLachlan, M. S., Thomas, G. O., Sweetman, A. J., &amp; Jones, K. C. (2009). A mass balance of tri‐hexabrominated diphenyl ethers in lactating cows. Environmental Science &amp; Technology, 43(7), 2602–2607.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kotthoff, M., Müller, J., Jürling, H., Schlummer, M., &amp; Fiedler, D. (2015). Perfluoroalkyl and polyfluoroalkyl substances in consumer products. Environmental Science and Pollution Research, 22(19), 14546–14559.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kowalczyk, J., Ehlers, S., Oberhausen, A., Tischer, M., Fürst, P., Schafft, H., &amp; Lahrssen‐Wiederholt, M. (2013). Absorption, distribution, and milk secretion of the perfluoroalkyl acids PFBS, PFHxS, PFOS, and PFOA by dairy cows fed naturally contaminated feed. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 61(12), 2903–2912. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf304680j</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leggieri, M. C., Bertuzzi, T., Pietri, A., &amp; Battilani, P. (2015). Mycotoxin occurrence in maize produced in Northern Italy over the years 2009–2011: Focus on the role of crop related factors. Phytopathologia Mediterranea, 54(2), 212–221. &lt;Go to ISI&gt;://WOS:000361471700002.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, J., Xu, Y., Wang, L., &amp; Li, F. (2019). Heavy metal occurrence and risk assessment in dairy feeds and manures from the typical intensive dairy farms in China. Environmental Science and Pollution Research, 00, 00–00.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, X., Dong, S., Wang, P., Su, X., &amp; Fu, J. (2019). Polychlorinated biphenyls are still alarming persistent organic pollutants in marine‐origin animal feed (fishmeal) [Article]. Chemosphere, 233, 355–362. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2019.05.250</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, X., Dong, S., Wang, R., Wang, P., Ruan, Z., Sun, X., Rao, Q., Liu, Z., &amp; Su, X. (2019). Novel brominated flame retardant (NBFR) concentrations and spatial distributions in global fishmeal. Ecotoxicology and Environmental Safety, 170, 306–313. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecoenv.2018.11.112</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, X., Dong, S., Zhang, W., Fan, X., Li, Y., Wang, R., &amp; Su, X. (2018). Global occurrence of polybrominated diphenyl ethers and their hydroxylated and methoxylated structural analogues in an important animal feed (fishmeal). Environmental Pollution, 234, 620–629. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2017.11.059</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, X., Dong, S., Zhang, W., Fan, X., Wang, R., Wang, P., &amp; Su, X. (2019). The occurrence of perfluoroalkyl acids in an important feed material (fishmeal) and its potential risk through the farm‐to‐fork pathway to humans. Journal of Hazardous Materials, 367, 559–567. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhazmat.2018.12.103</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, X., Rezaei, R., Li, P., &amp; Wu, G. (2011). Composition of amino acids in feed ingredients for animal diets. Amino Acids, 40(4), 1159–1168. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00726‐010‐0740‐y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, Z., &amp; Fantke, P. (2023). Framework for defining pesticide maximum residue levels in feed: Applications to cattle and sheep. Pest Management Science, 79(2), 748–759. https://doi.org/10.1002/ps.7241</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, J., &amp; Applegate, T. (2020). Zearalenone (ZEN) in livestock and poultry: Dose, toxicokinetics, toxicity and estrogenicity. Toxins, 12(6), 377. https://doi.org/10.3390/toxins12060377</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>López‐Alonso, M. (2012). Animal feed contamination by toxic metals. In Animal feed contamination (pp. 183–204). Elsevier.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Love, D. C., Halden, R., Davis, M., &amp; Nachman, K. (2012). Feather meal: A previously unrecognized route for reentry into the food supply of multiple pharmaceuticals and personal care products (PPCPs). Environmental Science &amp; Technology, 46(7), 3795–3802.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lutz, S., Feidt, C., Monteau, F., Rychen, G., Le Bizec, B., &amp; Jurjanz, S. (2006). Effect of exposure to soil‐bound polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons on milk contaminations of parent compounds and their monohydroxylated metabolites. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 54(1), 263–268. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf0522210</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma, Y., Shi, L., Liu, Y., &amp; Lu, Q. (2017). Effects of neutralization, decoloration, and deodorization on polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons during laboratory‐scale oil refining process. Journal of Chemistry, 2017, 7824761. https://doi.org/10.1155/2017/7824761</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>MacLachlan, D. J. (2011). Estimating the transfer of contaminants in animal feedstuffs to livestock tissues, milk and eggs: A review. Animal Production Science, 51(12), 1067–1078. https://doi.org/10.1071/AN11112</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maes, J., &amp; De Meulenaer, B., Van Heerswynghels, P., De Greyt, W., Eppe, G., De Pauw, E., Huyghebaert, A. (2005). Journal of the American Oil Chemists Society. 82(8). p.593‐597.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malir, F., Ostry, V., Pfohl‐Leszkowicz, A., Malir, J., &amp; Toman, J. (2016). Ochratoxin A: 50 years of research. Toxins, 8(7), 191. https://www.mdpi.com/2072‐6651/8/7/191</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marnane, I. (2012). Comprehensive environmental review following the pork PCB/dioxin contamination incident in Ireland. Journal of Environmental Monitoring, 14(10), 2551–2556. https://doi.org/10.1039/c2em30374d</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mauro, A., Battilani, P., &amp; Cotty, P. J. (2015). Atoxigenic Aspergillus flavus endemic to Italy for biocontrol of aflatoxins in maize. Biocontrol, 60(1), 125–134. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10526‐014‐9624‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mulder, P. P. J., Beumer, B., Oosterink, E., &amp; de Jong, J. (2009). Dutch survey pyrrolizidine alkaloids in animal forage. RIKILT Report, 018, 1–45.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mulder, P. P. J., Lopez, P., These, A., Preiss‐Weigert, A., &amp; Castellari, M. (2015). Occurrence of pyrrolizidine alkaloids in food. EFSA Supporting publication EN‐859, p. 114.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ng, C. A., Ritscher, A., Hungerbuehler, K., &amp; Von Goetz, N. (2018). Polybrominated diphenyl ether (PBDE) accumulation in farmed salmon evaluated using a dynamic sea‐cage production model. Environmental Science and Technology, 52(12), 6965–6973. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.8b00146</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nisha, A. R. (2008). Antibiotic residues—A global health hazard. Veterinary World, 1(12), 375–377.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nøstbakken, O. J., Duinker, A., Rasinger, J. D., Nilsen, B. M., Sanden, M., Frantzen, S., Hove, H. T., Lundebye, A. K., Berntssen, M. H. G., Hannisdal, R., Madsen, L., &amp; Maage, A. (2018). Factors influencing risk assessments of brominated flame‐retardants; Evidence based on seafood from the North East Atlantic Ocean. Environment International, 119, 544–557. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2018.04.044</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>NVWA. (2014). Resultaten van het NVWA Nationaal Plan Diervoeders 2014 ‐ Monitoringsprogramma voor ongewenste stoffen in diervoeder en diervoederingrediënten (vertrouwelijk).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>NVWA. (2015). Resultaten van het NVWA Nationaal Plan Diervoeders 2015 ‐ Monitoringsprogramma voor ongewenste stoffen in diervoeder en diervoederingrediënten (vertrouwelijk).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>OECD. (2021). Portal on per and poly fluorinated chemicals. https://www.oecd.org/chemicalsafety/portal‐perfluorinated‐chemicals/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ortiz, X., Guerra, P., Díaz‐Ferrero, J., Eljarrat, E., &amp; Barceló, D. (2011). Diastereoisomer‐ and enantiomer‐specific determination of hexabromocyclododecane in fish oil for food and feed. Chemosphere, 82(5), 739–744. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2010.10.088</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pabst, K., Mathar, W., Palavinskas, R., Meisel, H., Bluthgen, A., &amp; Klaffke, H. (2005). Acrylamide‐occurrence in mixed concentrate feed for dairy cows and carry‐over into milk. Food Additives &amp; Contaminants: Part A, 22(3), 210–213. https://doi.org/10.1080/02652030500110964</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parikka, P., Hakala, K., &amp; Tiilikkala, K. (2012). Expected shifts in Fusarium species' composition on cereal grain in Northern Europe due to climatic change. Food Additives and Contaminants Part A, 29(10), 1543–1555. https://doi.org/10.1080/19440049.2012.680613</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pfister, J. A., Cook, D., &amp; Gardner, D. R. (2011). Cattle grazing toxic Delphinium andersonii in South‐Central Idaho, Rangeland. Ecology and Management, 64(6), 664–668. https://doi.org/10.2111/rem‐d‐11‐00001.1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piskorska‐Pliszczynska, J., Maszewski, S., Mikolajczyk, S., Pajurek, M., Strucinski, P., &amp; Olszowy, M. (2017). Elimination of dioxins in milk by dairy cows after the long‐term intake of contaminated sugar beet pellets. Food Additives &amp; Contaminants: Part A, 34(5), 842–852.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piskorska‐Pliszczynska, J., Struciński, P., &amp; Kan, C. A. (2019). Contaminants in eggs: Dioxins/PCBs and other toxic substances and their possible health implications. In Chemical hazards in foods of animal origin (pp. 415–441). https://doi.org/10.3920/978‐90‐8686‐877‐3_17</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pulina, G., Battacone, G., Brambilla, G., Cheli, F., Danieli, P. P., Masoero, F., Pietri, A., &amp; Ronchi, B. (2014). An update on the safety of foods of animal origin and feeds. Italian Journal of Animal Science, 13(4), 3571. https://doi.org/10.4081/ijas.2014.3571</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rajaganapathy, V., Xavier, F., Sreekumar, D., &amp; Mandal, P. (2011). Heavy metal contamination in soil, water and fodder and their presence in livestock and products: A review. Journal of Environmental Science and Technology, 4(3), 234–249.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>RIVM, W. (2020). Feed‐food transfer models. National Institute for Public Health and the Environment and Wageningen University &amp; Research. https://www.feedfoodtransfer.nl/en</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosas‐Castor, J., Guzmán‐Mar, J., Hernández‐Ramírez, A., Garza‐González, M., &amp; Hinojosa‐Reyes, L. (2014). Arsenic accumulation in maize crop (Zea mays): A review. Science of the Total Environment, 488, 176–187.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rose, M. D., Mortimer, D. N., Gem, M. G., Petch, R. G., Fernandes, A. R., &amp; Livesey, C. T. (2010). Considerations for the regulation of polychlorinated dibenzodioxins, furans (PCDD/Fs) and biphenyls (PCBs) in liver. Quality Assurance and Safety of Crops &amp; Foods, 2(2), 72–77. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1757‐837X.2010.00058.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadowska‐Rociek, A. (2020). Monochloropropanediol esters and glycidyl esters in dietary supplements based on fish oils. Food Additives &amp; Contaminants: Part B, 13(4), 305–312. https://doi.org/10.1080/19393210.2020.1803419</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saha Turna, N., &amp; Wu, F. (2021). Aflatoxin M1 in milk: A global occurrence, intake, &amp; exposure assessment. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 110, 183–192. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2021.01.093</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>SCF. (2002). Opinion of the Scientific Committee on food on the risks to human health of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in food. Reportnr. SCF/CS/CNTM/PAH/29 final.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schimming, T., Jenett‐Siems, K., Mann, P., Tofern‐Reblin, B., Milson, J., Johnson, R. W., Deroin, T., Austin, D. F., &amp; Eich, E. (2005). Calystegines as chemotaxonomic markers in the convolvulaceae. Phytochemistry, 66(4), 469–480. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2004.12.024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schwarz, M., Buchmann, A., Stinchcombe, S., Kalkuhl, A., &amp; Bock, K.‐W. (2000). Ah receptor ligands and tumor promotion: Survival of neoplastic cells. Toxicology Letters, 112, 69–77.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi, Y., Wang, J., Pan, Y., &amp; Cai, Y. (2012). Tissue distribution of perfluorinated compounds in farmed freshwater fish and human exposure by consumption. Environmental Toxicology and Chemistry, 31(4), 717–723. https://doi.org/10.1002/etc.1758</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Srogi, K. (2008). Levels and congener distributions of PCDDs, PCDFs and dioxin‐like PCBs in environmental and human samples: A review. Environmental Chemistry Letters, 6(1), 1–28.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stolker, A., Manti, V., Zuidema, T., Van Egmond, H., Deckers, E., Herbes, R., Hooglugt, J., Olde Heuvel, E., &amp; De Jong, J. (2013). Carry‐over of veterinary drugs from medicated to non‐medicated feeds in commercial feed manufacturing plants. Food Additives &amp; Contaminants: Part A, 30(6), 1100–1107.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun, Y., &amp; Wu, S. (2020). Analysis of PAHs in oily systems using modified QuEChERS with EMR‐Lipid clean‐up followed by GC‐QqQ‐MS. Food Control, 109, 106950. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2019.106950</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tittlemier, S. A., Roscoe, M., Trelka, R., Patrick, S. K., Bamforth, J. M., Grafenhan, T., Schlichting, L., &amp; Fu, B. X. (2014). Fate of moniliformin during milling of Canadian Durum wheat, processing, and cooking of spaghetti. Canadian Journal of Plant Science, 94(3), 555–563. https://doi.org/10.4141/Cjps2013‐096</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tlustos, C., Sheridan, M., O'Sullivan, D., Anderson, W., &amp; Flynn, A. (2012). The dioxin contamination incident in Ireland, 2008: Analytical results and congener patterns. Food Additives &amp; Contaminants: Part A, 29(1), 128–138.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tolosa, J., Rodríguez‐Carrasco, Y., Ruiz, M. J., &amp; Vila‐Donat, P. (2021). Multi‐mycotoxin occurrence in feed, metabolism and carry‐over to animal‐derived food products: A review. Food and Chemical Toxicology, 158, Article 112661. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fct.2021.112661</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Traag, W., Kotz, A., van der Weg, G., Malisch, R., &amp; Hoogenboom, R. (2009). Bioassay directed detection of brominated dioxins in the feed additive cholin chloride. Organohalogen Compounds, 71, 210‐213.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. FDA. (2023). CFR—Code of Federal Regulations Title 21. U.S. Food &amp; Drug Administration. https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/scripts/cdrh/cfdocs/cfcfr/CFRSearch.cfm?CFRPart=556&amp;showFR=1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ünüsan, N. (2019). Systematic review of mycotoxins in food and feeds in Turkey. Food Control, 97, 1–14. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2018.10.015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Asselt, E., Meeuwissen, M., Van Asseldonk, M., Sterrenburg, P., Mengelers, M., &amp; Van der Fels‐Klerx, H. (2011). Approach for a pro‐active emerging risk system on biofuel by‐products in feed. Food Policy, 36(3), 421–429.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Asselt, E. D., van der Fels‐Klerx, H. J., Marvin, H. J. P., van Bokhorst‐van de Veen, H., &amp; Groot, M. N. (2017). Overview of food safety hazards in the European dairy supply chain. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 16(1), 59–75. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.12245</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Fels‐Klerx, H. J., Romkens, P., Franz, E., &amp; van Raamsdonk, L. (2011). Modeling cadmium in the feed chain and cattle organs. Biotechnology, Agronomy, Society and Environment, 15(Special issue 1), 53–59.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Fels‐Klerx, H. J., van Asselt, E. D., Adamse, P., Nijkamp, M., van Leeuwen, S. P. J., Pikkemaat, M., de Nijs, M., Mol, H., van Raamsdonk, L., &amp; Hoogenboom, R. (2019). Chemische en fysische gevaren in de Nederlandse diervoederketen.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Fels‐Klerx, H. J., &amp; Booij, C. J. H. (2010). Perspectives for geographically oriented management of Fusarium mycotoxins in the cereal supply chain. Journal of Food Protection, 73(6), 1153–1159. &lt;Go to ISI&gt;://WOS:000278789500022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Fels‐Klerx, H. J., &amp; Camenzuli, L. (2016). Effects of milk yield, feed composition, and feed contamination with aflatoxin B1 on the aflatoxin M1 concentration in dairy cows' milk investigated using Monte Carlo simulation modelling. Toxins, 8(10):, 290. https://doi.org/10.3390/toxins8100290</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Fels‐Klerx, H. J., van Asselt, E. D., Adamse, P., Nijkamp, M. N., van Leeuwen, S. P. J., Pikkemaat, M., de Nijs, M., Mol, H., van Raamsdonk, L., Hoogenboom, R., &amp; de Jong, J. (2019). Chemische en fysische gevaren in de Nederlandse diervoederketen [Report]. RIKILT. https://doi.org/10.18174/470704</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Eijkeren, J. C., Zeilmaker, M. J., Kan, C. A., Traag, W. A., &amp; Hoogenboom, L. A. P. (2006). A toxicokinetic model for the carry‐over of dioxins and PCBs from feed and soil to eggs. Food Additives &amp; Contaminants: Part A, 23(5), 509–517. https://doi.org/10.1080/02652030500512045</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Heyst, A., Vanlancker, M., Vercammen, J., Van den Houwe, K., Mertens, B., Elskens, M., &amp; Van Hoeck, E. (2018). Analysis of mineral oil in food: Results of a Belgian market survey. Food Additives &amp; Contaminants: Part A, 35(10), 2062–2075. https://doi.org/10.1080/19440049.2018.1512758</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Leeuwen, S., Van Velzen, M., Swart, C., Van der Veen, I., Traag, W., &amp; De Boer, J. (2009). Halogenated contaminants in farmed salmon, trout, tilapia, pangasius, and shrimp. Environmental Science &amp; Technology, 43(11), 4009–4015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Leeuwen, S. P. J., van Velzen, M. J. M., Swart, C. P., van der Veen, I., Traag, W. A., &amp; de Boer, J. (2009). Halogenated contaminants in farmed salmon, trout, tilapia, pangasius, and shrimp. Environmental Science &amp; Technology, 43(11), 4009–4015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vandenberge, V., Delezie, E., Delahaut, P., Pierret, G., De Backer, P., Daeseleire, E., &amp; Croubels, S. (2012). Transfer of flubendazole and tylosin at cross contamination levels in the feed to egg matrices and distribution between egg yolk and egg white. Poultry Science, 91(5), 1248–1255.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vénisseau, A., Bichon, E., Brosseaud, A., Vaccher, V., Lesquin, E., Larvor, F., Durand, S., Dervilly‐Pinel, G., Marchand, P., &amp; Le Bizec, B. (2018). Occurrence of legacy and novel brominated flame retardants in food and feed in France for the period 2014 to 2016. Chemosphere, 207, 497–506. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2018.05.122</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vrkoslavová, J., Demnerová, K., Macková, M., Zemanová, T., Macek, T., Hajšlová, J., Pulkrabová, J., Hrádková, P., &amp; Stiborová, H. (2010). Absorption and translocation of polybrominated diphenyl ethers (PBDEs) by plants from contaminated sewage sludge. Chemosphere, 81(3), 381–386. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2010.07.010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wallinga, D., &amp; Burch, D. G. S. (2013). Does adding routine antibiotics to animal feed pose a serious risk to human health? BMJ, 347(7917), Article f4214. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.f4214</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, J. X., Bao, L. J., Luo, P., Shi, L., Wong, C. S., &amp; Zeng, E. Y. (2017). Intake, distribution, and metabolism of decabromodiphenyl ether and its main metabolites in chickens and implications for human dietary exposure. Environmental Pollution, 231, 795–801. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2017.08.084</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, J. X., Bao, L. J., Shi, L., Liu, L. Y., &amp; Zeng, E. Y. (2019). Characterizing PBDEs in fish, poultry, and pig feeds manufactured in China. Environmental Science and Pollution Research, 00, 00–00. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11356‐018‐04057‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weber, R., Herold, C., Hollert, H., Kamphues, J., Blepp, M., &amp; Ballschmiter, K. (2018). Reviewing the relevance of dioxin and PCB sources for food from animal origin and the need for their inventory, control and management. Environmental Sciences Europe, 30(1), 42. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12302‐018‐0166‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Welch, K. D., Lee, S. T., Panter, K. E., &amp; Gardner, D. R. (2014). A study on embryonic death in goats due to Nicotiana glauca ingestion. Toxicon, 90, 64–69. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.toxicon.2014.07.020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wenzl, T., Lachenmeier, D. W., &amp; Gökmen, V. (2007). Analysis of heat‐induced contaminants (acrylamide, chloropropanols and furan) in carbohydrate‐rich food. Analytical and Bioanalytical Chemistry, 389(1), 119–137. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00216‐007‐1459‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. (2018). Global antimicrobial resistance surveillance system (GLASS) report: Early implementation, 2017–2018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wocławek‐Potocka, I., Mannelli, C., Boruszewska, D., Kowalczyk‐Zieba, I., Waśniewski, T., &amp; Skarzyński, D. J. (2013). Diverse effects of phytoestrogens on the reproductive performance: Cow as a model. International Journal of Endocrinology, 2013, 650984. https://doi.org/10.1155/2013/650984</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yingliang, J., Pei, L., Yongning, W., Jie, M., Cannan, W., Jinfang, S., &amp; Yafei, Z. (2014). A systematic review on food lead concentration and dietary lead exposure in China. Chinese Medical Journal, 127(15), 2844–2849.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zafeiraki, E., Costopoulou, D., Vassiliadou, I., Leondiadis, L., Dassenakis, E., Hoogenboom, R. L., &amp; van Leeuwen, S. P. (2016a). Perfluoroalkylated substances (PFASs) in home and commercially produced chicken eggs from the Netherlands and Greece. Chemosphere, 144, 2106–2112.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zafeiraki, E., Gebbink, W. A., Hoogenboom, R. L. A. P., Kotterman, M., Kwadijk, C., Dassenakis, E., &amp; van Leeuwen, S. P. J. (2019). Occurrence of perfluoroalkyl substances (PFASs) in a large number of wild and farmed aquatic animals collected in the Netherlands. Chemosphere, 232, 415–423. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2019.05.200</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zafeiraki, E., Vassiliadou, I., Costopoulou, D., Leondiadis, L., Schafft, H. A., Hoogenboom, R. L., &amp; van Leeuwen, S. P. J. (2016b). Perfluoroalkylated substances in edible livers of farm animals, including depuration behaviour in young sheep fed with contaminated grass. Chemosphere, 156, 280–285.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, L., &amp; Wong, M. H. (2007). Environmental mercury contamination in China: Sources and impacts. Environment International, 33(1), 108–121.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, Y., Krishnadasan, A., Kennedy, N., Morgenstern, H., &amp; Ritz, B. (2005). Estimated effects of solvents and mineral oils on cancer incidence and mortality in a cohort of aerospace workers. American Journal of Industrial Medicine, 48(4), 249–258. https://doi.org/10.1002/ajim.20216</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng, X., Qiao, L., Sun, R., Luo, X., Zheng, J., Xie, Q., Sun, Y., &amp; Mai, B. (2017). Alteration of diastereoisomeric and enantiomeric profiles of hexabromocyclododecanes (HBCDs) in adult chicken tissues, eggs, and hatchling chickens. Environmental Science and Technology, 51(10), 5492–5499. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.6b06557</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu, Y., Xie, S., Chen, D., Pan, Y., Qu, W., Wang, X., Liu, Z., Peng, D., Huang, L., &amp; Tao, Y. (2016). Targeted analysis and determination of β‐agonists, hormones, glucocorticoid and psychiatric drugs in feed by liquid chromatography with electrospray ionization tandem mass spectrometry. Journal of Separation Science, 39(13), 2584–2594.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zuidema, T., van Holthoon, F., van Egmond, H., Bikker, P., Aarts, H., &amp; Heuvel, E. O. (2010). Omvang en implicaties van antibiotica‐versleping in mengvoeders voor varkens.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>