<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39379293</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1541-4337</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>23</Volume><Issue>6</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Comprehensive reviews in food science and food safety</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A 10-year (2014-2023) review of complementary food development in sub-Saharan Africa and the impact on child health.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70022</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70022</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1541-4337.70022</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Complementary foods (CFs) commonly consumed by infants and young children (IYC) in sub-Saharan Africa (SSA) are processed using either single or multi-grain ingredients through simple technologies such as fermentation, malting and roasting. Interestingly, CFs (e.g., ogi, kunu, and dabo) are prepared and fed to infants alongside breastmilk until they are completely weaned up to the infant's second birthday. The grains used for preparing CFs can be contaminated with bacterial and chemical contaminants as a result of poor harvesting, handling or storage practices. The stage at which IYC are introduced to CFs is of utmost importance as it aids in addressing malnutrition and improving their overall health and well-being. Complementary feeding practices across SSA are influenced by socio-economic, cultural and geographical factors such that improper introduction can result in dire health consequences including immune suppression, severe foodborne diseases, poor child growth and development, and sometimes death from malnutrition. Malnutrition often occurs from inadequacies of nutrient intakes and assimilation which affect the ability to maintain normal body functions such as growth, learning abilities, resistance to and recovery from diseases. In SSA, IYC malnutrition still poses an enormous concern, therefore indicating the need for intervention strategies such as the promotion of indigenous crops and elevating traditional knowledge and technologies for formulating CFs. This paper clearly highlights the diversity of CFs in SSA, ingredients utilized, processing techniques, contamination by bacteria and chemicals, and demonstrates the consequences of consuming contaminated CFs, and their influence on IYC health as well as approaches to ensuring safety and scaling up indigenous CFs.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety published by Wiley Periodicals LLC on behalf of Institute of Food Technologists.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ogunniran</LastName><ForeName>Oluwabunmi P</ForeName><Initials>OP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, School of Science and Technology, Babcock University, Ilishan Remo, Ogun State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ayeni</LastName><ForeName>Kolawole I</ForeName><Initials>KI</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, School of Science and Technology, Babcock University, Ilishan Remo, Ogun State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Vienna, Faculty of Chemistry, Department of Food Chemistry and Toxicology, Vienna, Austria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shokunbi</LastName><ForeName>Olutayo S</ForeName><Initials>OS</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3020-8852</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biochemistry, School of Basic Medical Sciences, Babcock University, Ilishan Remo, Ogun State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Krska</LastName><ForeName>Rudolf</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6843-9755</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>BOKU University, Department of Agrobiotechnology, IFA-Tulln, Institute of Bioanalytics and Agro-Metabolomics, Tulln, Austria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Global Food Security, School of Biological Sciences, Queen´s University Belfast, Belfast, Northern Ireland, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ezekiel</LastName><ForeName>Chibundu N</ForeName><Initials>CN</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2113-2948</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, School of Science and Technology, Babcock University, Ilishan Remo, Ogun State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>BOKU University, Department of Agrobiotechnology, IFA-Tulln, Institute of Bioanalytics and Agro-Metabolomics, Tulln, Austria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101305205</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1541-4337</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017954" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Africa South of the Sahara</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007223" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000067576" MajorTopicYN="Y">Child Health</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002675" MajorTopicYN="N">Child, Preschool</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007227" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant Nutritional Physiological Phenomena</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007225" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant Food</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005511" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Handling</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">complementary food contaminants</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food processing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">infants and young children</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">malnutrition</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39379293</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.70022</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Aayushi, T., Surbhi, S., &amp; Priya, Y. (2018). Effect of blanching on green vegetables. University Research Resource Journal, 1(2), 218–225.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdulkadir, M., &amp; Danjuma, J. B. (2015). Microbial profile and nutritional quality during the fermentation of cereal‐based weaning food fortified with soybean and tiger‐nut using starter culture. World Scientific News, 24(285), 103–115.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abeshu, M. A., Lelisa, A., &amp; Geleta, B. (2016). Complementary feeding: Review of recommendation, feeding practices and adequacy of homemade complementary food preparation in developing countries—Lessons from Ethiopia. Frontiers in Nutrition, 3, 41. https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2016.00041</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abinash, V., Rahul, T., Antoniraj, M. G., Moses, J. A., &amp; Anandharamakrishnan, C. (2021). Nanotechnology approaches for food fortification. In K. Pal, I. Banerjee, P. Sarkar, A. Bit, D. Kim, A. Anis, &amp; S. Maji (Eds.), Food, medical, and environmental applications of polysaccharides (pp. 161–186). Elsevier. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978‐0‐12‐819239‐9.00007‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abiose, S. H., Ikujenlola, A. V., &amp; Aboderin, F. I. (2015). Nutritional quality assessment of complementary foods produced from fermented and malted quality protein maize fortified with soybean flour. Polish Journal of Food Nutrition Sciences, 65(1), 49–56. https://doi.org/10.1515/pjfns‐2015‐0004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Achaglinkame, M. A., Opoku, N., &amp; Amagloh, F. K. (2017). Aflatoxin contamination in cereal and legumes to reconsider usage as complementary food ingredients for Ghanian infants: A review. Journal of Nutrition and Intermediary Metabolism, 10, 1–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adamcova, A., Laursen, K. H., &amp; Ballin, N. Z. (2021). Lectin activity in commonly consumed plant‐based foods: Calling for method harmonization and risk assessment. Foods, 10(11), 2796. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods10112796</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adebiyi, J. A., Kayitesi, E., Adebo, O. A., Changwa, R., &amp; Njobeh, P. B. (2019). Food fermentation and mycotoxin detoxification: An African perspective. Food Control, 106, 106731. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2019.106731</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adebowale, A. A., Awolala, F. M., Fetuga, G. O., Sanni, S. A., &amp; Adegunwa, M. O. (2013). Effect of soaking pre‐treatments on nutritional composition and functional properties of bambara groundnut (Vigna subterranea) flour. Proc. 2nd International Symposium on Underutilized Plants Species, 139–146.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adedeji, B. S., Ezeokoli, O. T., Ezekiel, C. N., Obadina, A. O., Somorin, Y. M., Sulyok, M., Adeleke, R. A., Warth, B., Nwangburuka, C. C., Omemu, A. M., Oyewole, O. B., &amp; Krska, R. (2017). Bacterial species and mycotoxin contamination associated with locust bean, melon and their fermented products in south‐western Nigeria. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 258, 73–80. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2017.07.014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ademola, O. M., Adeyemi, T. E., Ezeokoli, O. T., Ayeni, K. I., Obadina, A. O., Somorin, Y. M., Omemu, A. M., Adeleke, R. A., Nwangburuka, C. C., Oluwafemi, F., Oyewole, O. B., &amp; Ezekiel, C. N. (2018). Phylogenetic analyses of bacteria associated with the processing of iru and ogiri condiments. Letters in Applied Microbiology, 67(4), 354–362. https://doi.org/10.1111/lam.13040</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adesulu‐Dahunsi, A. T., Dahunsi, S. O., &amp; Ajayeoba, T. A. (2022). Co‐occurrence of Lactobacillus spp. during fermentation of African indigenous foods: Impact on food safety and shelf‐life extension. Frontiers in Microbiology, 13, 684730. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2022.684730</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adetola, O., Onabanjo, O., &amp; Stark, A. (2020). The search for sustainable solutions: Producing a sweet potato based complementary food rich in vitamin A, zinc and iron for infants in developing countries. Scientific African, 8, e00363. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.sciaf.2020.e00363</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adu‐Afarwuah, S., Lartey, A., Brown, K. H., Zlotkin, S., Briend, A., &amp; Dewey, K. G. (2008). Home fortification of complementary foods with micronutrient supplements is well accepted and has positive effects on infant iron status in Ghana. American Journal of Clinical Nutrition, 87, 929–938. https://doi.org/10.1093/ajcn/87.4.929</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agarwal, S., &amp; Chauhan, E. S. (2019). Extrusion processing: The effect on nutrients and based products. The Pharma Innovation Journal, 8(4), 464–470.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agbemafle, I., Hadzi, D., Amagloh, F. K., Zotor, F. B., &amp; Reddy, M. B. (2020). Nutritional, microbial, and sensory evaluation of complementary foods made from blends of orange‐fleshed sweet potato and edible insects. Foods, 9(9), 1225. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods9091225</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agrawal, P. (2016). Potential prospects of future medicine: Nano medicine. Journal of Pharmacovigilance, 4(1), 1000e149. https://doi.org/10.4172/2329‐6887.1000e149</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agredo‐Campos, A. S., Fernandez‐Silva, J. A., &amp; Ramirez‐Vasquez, N. F. (2023). Staphylococcus aureus, Escherichia coli and Klebsiella spp. prevalence in bulk tank milk of Colombian herds and associated milking practices. Veterinary World, 16(4), 869–881. https://doi.org/10.14202/vetworld.2023.869‐881</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agume, N. A. S., Njintang, Y. N., &amp; Mbofung, C. M. F. (2017). Effect of soaking and roasting on the physicochemical and pasting properties of soybean flour. Foods, 6(12), 1–10. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods6020012</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ajayeoba, T. A., Awosika, O. O., &amp; Atolagbe, J. E. (2022). The approach and health challenges of complementary foods and feeding practices. Adeleke University Journal of Science, 1(2), 507–529. https://aujs.adelekeuniversity.edu.ng</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akingbala, J. O., Rooney, L. W., &amp; Faubion, J. M. (1981). Physical, chemical and sensory evaluation of ogi from sorghum of differing kernel characteristics. Journal of Food Science, 46, 1523–1526. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365‐2621.1981.tb04214.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akinsola, A. O., Idowu, M. A., Babajide, J., Oguntona, C. R. B., &amp; Shittu, T. (2018). Production and functional property of maize‐millet based complementary food blended with soybean. African Journal of Food Science, 12(12), 360–366.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akinsola, A. O., Idowu, M. A., Karim, O., Segilola, V. O., &amp; Obisesan, D. O. (2017). Effects of processing methods II: Anti‐nutritional, microbial and sensory quality of maize–millet–soybean complementary food. Annals Food Science and Technology, 18(4), 686–695.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akinsola, A. O., Onabanjo, O. O., Idowu, M. A., &amp; Ade‐Omowaye, B. I. O. (2017). Traditional complementary foods: A critical review. Greener Journal of Agricultural Sciences, 7(9), 226–242.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akinyemi, M. O., Ayeni, K. I., Ogunremi, O. R., Adeleke, R. A., Oguntoyinbo, F. A., Warth, B., &amp; Ezekiel, C. N. (2021). A review of microbes and chemical contaminants in dairy products in sub‐Saharan Africa. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 20, 1188–1220. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.12712</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akombi, B. J., Agho, K. E., Merom, D., Renzaho, A. M., &amp; Hall, J. J. (2017). Child malnutrition in sub‐Saharan Africa: A meta‐analysis of demographic and health surveys (2006–2016). PLoS ONE, 12(5), e0177338. https://doi.org/10.1371/Journal.pone.0177338</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allen, L., de Benoist, B., Dary, O., Hurrell, R., Horton, S., Lewis, J., Parvanta, C., Rahmani, M., Ruel, M., &amp; Thompson, B. (2006). Guidelines on food fortification with micronutrients. World Health Organization, Food and Agricultural Organization of the United Nations.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almendares Calderón, L., Garcia Mena, V. A., &amp; Roman Miranda, J. M. (2021). Development of an extruded food product similar to fried potatoes, based on by‐products of potatoes and rice. Physicochemical and microbiological evaluation. Food Science and Technology, 41(2), 359–364. https://doi.org/10.1590/fst.03820</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alowo, D., Muggaga, C., &amp; Ongeng, C. (2018). The effect of traditional malting technology practiced by an ethnic community in Northern Uganda on in‐vitro nutrient bioavailability and consumer sensory preference for locally formulated complementary food formula. Food Science and Nutrition, 6(8), 2491–2498. https://doi.org/10.1002/fsn3.856</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Altemimi, A. B., Farag, H. A. M., Salih, T. H., Awlqadr, F. H., Al‐Manhel, A. J. A., Vieira, I. R. S., &amp; Conte‐Junior, C. A. (2024). Application of nanoparticles in human nutrition: A review. Nutrients, 16, 636. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu16050636</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alum, E. A., Urom, S. M. O., &amp; Ben, C. M. A. (2016). Microbiological contamination of food: The mechanisms, impacts and prevention. International Journal of Scientific &amp; Technology Research, 5(3), 65–78.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amagloh, F. K., Mutukumira, A. N., Brough, L., Weber, J. L., Hardacre, A., &amp; Coad, J. (2013). Carbohydrate composition, viscosity, solubility, and sensory acceptance of sweet potato‐ and maize‐based complementary foods. Food and Nutrition Research, 57, 1–9. https://doi.org/10.3402/fnr.v57i0.18717</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amod, R., Pillay, K., Siwela, M., &amp; Kolanisi, U. (2016). Acceptance of a complementary food based on provitamin A‐biofortified maize and chicken stew. Journal of Human Ecology, 55(3), 152–159. https://doi.org/10.1080/09709274.2016.11907019</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amusa, N. A., &amp; Odunbaku, O. A. (2009). Microbiological and nutritional quality of hawked kunu‐zaki (a sorghum‐based non‐alcoholic beverage) widely consumed in Nigeria. Pakistan Journal of Nutrition, 8, 20–25.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Araro, T., Gemechu, F., Wotango, A., &amp; Esho, T. (2020). Chemical formulation and characterization of complementary foods from blends of orange‐fleshed sweet potato, brown teff, dark kidney beans. International Journal of Food Science, 2020, 4803839. https://doi.org/10.1155/2020/4803839</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arce‐Lopez, B., Lizarraga, E., Vettorazzi, A., &amp; Gonzalez‐Penas, E. (2020). Human biomonitoring of mycotoxins in blood, plasma and serum in recent years: A review. Toxins, 12, 1–43. https://doi.org/10.3390/toxins12030147</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arshad, R., Gulshad, L., Haq, I. U., Farooq, M. A., Al‐Farga, A., Siddique, R., Manzoor, M. F., &amp; Karrar, E. (2021). Nanotechnology: A novel tool to enhance the bioavailability of micronutrients. Food Science &amp; Nutrition, 9(6), 3354–3361. https://doi.org/10.1002/fsn3.2311</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashby, J., Tinwell, H., Stevens, J., Pastoor, T., &amp; Breckenridge, C. B. (2002). The effects of atrazine on the early maturation of female rats. Regulatory Toxicology Pharmacology, 35(3), 468–473. https://doi.org/10.1006/rtph.2002.1571</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Assi, M. A., Hezmee, M. N., Haron, A. W., Sabri, M. Y., &amp; Rajion, M. A. (2016). The detrimental effects of lead on human and animal health. Veterinary World, 9(6), 660–671. https://doi.org/10.14202/vetworld.2016.660‐67</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ayelign, A., Woldegiorgis, A. Z., Adish, A., &amp; De Saeger, S. (2018). Total aflatoxins in complementary foods produced at community levels using locally available ingredients in Ethiopia. Food Additives and Contaminants: Part B, 11(2), 111–118. https://doi.org/10.1080/19393210.2018.1437784</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ayeni, K. I., Berry, D., Wisgrill, L., Warth, B., &amp; Ezekiel, C. N. (2022). Early‐life chemical exposome and gut microbiome development: African research perspectives within a global environmental health context. Trends in Microbiology, 30(11), 1084–1100. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tim.2022.05.008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ayeni, K. I., Seki, D., Pjevac, P., Hausmann, B., Krausová, M., Braun, D., Wisgrill, L., Berry, D., Warth, B., &amp; Ezekiel, C. N. (2024). Biomonitoring of dietary mycotoxin exposure and associated impact on the gut microbiome in Nigerian infants. Environmental Science &amp; Technology, 58(5), 2236–2246. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.3c07786</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ayeni, K. I., Sulyok, M., Krska, R., Warth, B., &amp; Ezekiel, C. N. (2023). Mycotoxins in complementary foods consumed by infants and young children within the first 18 months of life. Food Control, 144, 109328. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2022.109328</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bartelt, L. A., Bolick, D. T., &amp; Guerrant, R. L. (2019). Disentangling microbial mediators of malnutrition: Modeling environmental enteric dysfunction. Cellular and Molecular Gastroenterology and Hepatology, 7(3), 692–707. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcmgh.2018.12.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Battilani, P., Rossi, V., Giorni, P., Pietri, A., Gualla, A., van der Fels‐Klerx, H. J., Booij, C. J. H., Moretti, A., Logrieco, A., Miglietta, F., Toscano, P., Miraglia, M., &amp; De Santis, B. (2012). Modelling, predicting and mapping the emergence of aflatoxins in cereals in the EU due to climate change. EFSA Support Publications, 9(1), 1–172. https://doi.org/10.2903/sp.efsa.2012.EN‐223</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bekele, R., &amp; Shiferaw, L. (2020). Development and nutritional evaluation of instant complementary food formulated from vitamin A, iron and zinc rich crops. Journal of Food Processing and Technology, 11, 854.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Belay, A., Awoke, T., Woldeyohannes, M., &amp; Debella (2022). Evaluation of the nutritional quality of complementary food formulated from locally available grains and Moringa stenopetala in Southern Ethiopia. African Journal of Food, Agriculture, Nutrition and Development, 22(7), 20849–20870.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berger, S., Oesterle, I., Ayeni, K. I., Ezekiel, C. N., Rompel, A., &amp; Warth, B. (2024). Polyphenol exposure of mothers and infants assessed by LC–MS/MS based biomonitoring in breast milk. Analytical and Bioanalytical Chemistry, 416(7), 1759–1774. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00216‐024‐05179‐y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berhanu, L., Mereta, S. T., Gume, B., Kassa, T., Berihun, G., Dadi, L. S., Suleman, S., Tegegne, D., Getaneh, A., &amp; Bedru, H. (2021). Effect of microbial quality of washing water on hand hygiene status of food handlers in Jimma town: Implication for food hygiene and safety. Journal of Multidisciplinary Healthcare, 14, 1129–1134. https://doi.org/10.2147/JMDH.S306359</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhattacharjee, J., &amp; Goswami, P. (2018). Heavy metals (As, Cd &amp; Pb) toxicity &amp; detection of these metals in ground water sample: A review on different techniques. International Journal of Engineering Science Invention, 7(1), 12–21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blanco‐Rojo, R., Pérez‐Granados, A. M., Toxqui, L., González‐Vizcayno, C., Delgado, M. A., &amp; Vaquero, M. P. (2011). Efficacy of a microencapsulated iron pyrophosphate‐fortified fruit juice: A randomised, double‐blind, placebo‐controlled study in Spanish iron‐deficient women. British Journal of Nutrition, 105(11), 1652–1659. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0007114510005490</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blankson, G. K., &amp; Mills‐Robertson, F. C. (2015). Aflatoxin contamination and exposure in processed cereal based complementary foods for infants and young children in greater Accra. Food Control, 64, 212–217. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2015.12.032</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bokulich, N. A., &amp; Bamforth, C. W. (2013). The microbiology of malting and brewing. Microbiology and Molecular Reviews, 77(2), 157–172. https://doi.org/10.1128/MMBR.00060‐12</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bolarinwa, I. F., Olajide, J. O., Oke, M. O., Olaniyan, S. A., &amp; Faromiki, O. G. (2016). Production and quality evaluation of complementary food from malted millet, plantain and soybean blends. International Journal of Scientific and Engineering Research, 7(5), 663–674.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bolor, V. K., Boadi, N. O., Borquaye, L. S., &amp; Afful, S. (2018). Human risk assessment of organochlorine pesticide residues in vegetables from Kumasi, Ghana. Journal of Chemistry, 2018, 3269065. https://doi.org/10.1155/2018/3269065</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bouis, H. E., &amp; Saltzman, A. (2017). Improving nutrition through biofortification: A review of evidence from HarvestPlus, 2003 through 2016. Global Food Security, 12, 49–58. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gfs.2017.01.009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bourke, C. D., Berkeley, J. A., &amp; Prendergast, A. J. (2016). Immune dysfunction as a cause and consequence of malnutrition. Trends in Immunology, 37(6), 386–398. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.it.2016.04.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brander, S. M., &amp; Gabler, M. K., Fowler, N. L., Connon, R. E., &amp; Schlenk, D. (2016). Pyrethroid pesticides as endocrine disruptors: Molecular mechanisms in vertebrates with a focus on fishes. Environmental Science &amp; Technology, 50(17), 8977–8992. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.6b02253</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Camacho, J. C., Shieh, C. Y., Redan, B. W., &amp; Koontz, J. L. (2023). Antiviral activity of copper contact surfaces against MS2 coliphage and hepatitis A virus. Journal of Applied Microbiology, 134(8), 1–9. https://doi.org/10.1093/jambio/lxad160</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chadare, F. J., Madode, Y. E., Fanou‐Fogny, N., Kindossi, J. M., Ayosso, J. O., Honfo, S. H., Kayode, A. P., Linnemann, A. R., &amp; Hounhougian, D. J. (2018). Indigenous food ingredients for complementary food formulations to combat infant malnutrition in Benin: A review. Journal of the Science of Food and Agriculture, 98(2), 439–455. https://doi.org/10.1002/jsfa.8568</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chandran, L., &amp; Cataldo, R. (2010). Lead poisoning: Basics and new developments. Pediatrics in Review, 31(10), 399–405. https://doi.org/10.1542/pir.31‐10‐399</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chattopadhauay, N., &amp; Saumitra, M. (2016). Development outcome in children with malnutrition. Journal of Nepal Pediatrics Society, 36(2), 170–177. https://doi.org/10.3126/jnps.v36i2.14619</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaves‐Lopez, C., Serio, A., Grande‐Tovar, C. D., Cueiro‐Mulet, R., Delgado‐Ospina, J., &amp; Paparella, A. (2014). Traditional fermented foods and beverages from a microbiological and nutritional perspective: The Colombian heritage. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 13(5), 1031–1048. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.12098</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chekol, F. A., Melak, M. F., Belew, A. K., &amp; Zeleke, E. G. (2019). Food handling practice and associated factors among food handlers in public food establishments, Northwest Ethiopia. BMC Research Notes, 12(1), 20. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13104‐019‐4047‐0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, Y., Graziano, J. H., Parvez, F., Liu, M., Slavkovich, V., Kalra, T., Argos, M., Islam, T., &amp; Ahmed, A. (2011). Arsenic exposure from drinking water and mortality from cardiovascular disease in Bangladesh: Prospective cohort study. British Medical Journal, 342, d2431. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.d2431</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chisti, M. J., Pietroni, M. A., Smith, J. H., Bardhan, P. K., &amp; Salam, M. A. (2011). Predictors of death in under‐five children with diarrhoea admitted to a critical care ward in an urban hospital in Bangladesh. Acta Paediatrica, 100(12), e275–e279. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1651‐2227.2011.02368.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choton, S., Gupta, N., Bandral, J. D., Anjum, N., &amp; Choudary, A. (2020). Extrusion technology and its application in food processing: A review. The Pharma Innovation Journal, 9(2), 162–168. https://doi.org/10.22271/tpi.2020.v9.i2d.4367</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clark, L. F., &amp; Hobbs, J. E. (2018). Informational barriers, quality assurance and scaling up of complementary food supply chains in sub‐Saharan Africa. Outlook on Agriculture, 47(1), 11–18. https://doi.org/10.1177/0030727018760601</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CODEX. (2006). Codex Alimentarius Commission: CODEX STAN 074‐1981, REV.1‐2006‐Standards for processed cereal‐based foods for infants and young children (pp. 1–8). CODEX.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Colin, W., Ian, B., &amp; Diarne, M. (2017). Cereal grains, assessing and managing quality (2nd ed.). https://www.google.com.ng/search?tbo=p&amp;tbm=bks&amp;q=bibliogroup:%22Woodhead+Publishing+Series+in+Food+Science,+Technology+and+Nutrition%22&amp;source=gbs_metadata_r&amp;cad=3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Covic, N., &amp; Hendriks, S. L. (2015). Achieving a nutrition revolution in Africa: The road to healthier diets and optimal nutrition. ReSKASS Annual Trends and Outlook Report, pp. 256. https://doi.org/10.2499/9780896295933</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cudjoe, D. C., Balali, G. I., Titus, O. O., Osafo, R., &amp; Taufiq, M. (2022). Food safety in sub‐Sahara Africa, an insight into Ghana and Nigeria. Environmental Health Insights, 16, 1–18. https://doi.org/10.1177/11786302221142484</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Degaga, B., Girma, G., Woyessa, D., &amp; Batcha, K. (2015). Microbiological quality and safety of weaning foods of in‐patient infants in Jimma University specialized hospital, Jimma town, South‐west Ethiopia. Journal of Biochemical and Chemical Research, 32(2), 673–682. http://10.140.5.162//handle/123456789/1087</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Demissie, G. D., Yeshaw, Y., Aleminew, W., &amp; Akalu, Y. (2021). Diarrhea and associated factors among under five children in sub‐Saharan Africa: Evidence from demographic and health surveys of 34 sub‐Saharan countries. PLoS ONE, 16(9), e0257522. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0257522</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dendegh, T. A., Enefola, O. S., Akpapunam, S. O., Yelmi, B. M., &amp; Abdullahi, M. J. B. (2022). Extrusion technology and its application in food processing—An overview. Tropical Journal of Engineering, Science and Technology, 1(2), 25–53.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Onis, M. (2017). Child growth and development. In S. de Pee, D. Taren, &amp; M. Bloem (Eds.), Nutrition and health in a developing world (pp. 119–141). Humana Press. https://doi.org/10.1007/978‐3‐319‐43739‐2_6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Onis, M., Blössner, M., &amp; Borghi, B. (2010). Global prevalence and trends of overweight and obesity among preschool children. American Journal of Clinical Nutrition, 92(5), 1257–1264. https://doi.org/10.3945/ajcn.2010.29786</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Onis, M., &amp; Branca, F. (2016). Childhood stunting: A global perspective. Maternal &amp; Child Nutrition, 12(Suppl 1), 12–26. https://doi.org/10.1111/mcn.12231</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Development Initiatives. (2018). Global nutrition report: Shining a light to spur action on nutrition (p. 161). Development Initiatives.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Devers, K. G., &amp; Nine, J. S. (2010). Autopsy findings in botulinum toxin poisoning. Journal of Forensic Sciences, 55(6), 1649–1651. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1556‐4029.2010.01470.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dewey, K. G. (2001). Nutrition, growth, and complementary feeding of the breastfed infant. Pediatrics Clinic North America, 48(1), 87–104. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0031‐3955(05)70287‐X</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dewey, K. G., Cohen, R. J., &amp; Rollins, N. C. (2004). Informal working group on feeding of non‐breastfed children. WHO technical background paper: Feeding of non‐breastfed children from 6 to 24 months of age in developing countries. Food and Nutrition Bulletin, 25(4), 377–402. https://doi.org/10.1177/156482650402500407</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dhliwayo, T. C., Nyanga, L. K., Chopera, P., Matsungo, T. M., &amp; Chidewe, C. (2022). A review of traditional grain‐based complementary foods for children aged 6–23 months in selected African countries. The North African Journal of Food Nutrition and Research, 6(14), 115–125. https://doi.org/10.51745/najfnr.6.14.115‐125</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dossa, R., Ahouandjinou, E., &amp; Houngbe, F. (2011). Evaluation of the suitability and acceptability of newly designed infant flour for infant feeding in the district of Bopa in south of Benin. African Journal of Food, Agriculture, Nutrition and Development, 11(4), 4934–4952. https://doi.org/10.4314/ajfand.v11i4.69177</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du Plessis, L. M., Kruger, H. S., &amp; Sweet, L. (2013). Complementary feeding: A critical window of opportunity from six months onwards. South African Journal of Clinical Nutrition, 26, (3 Supplement), S129–S140.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EC (European Commission). (2006). Commission Regulation (EC) No 1881/2006 of 19 December 2006 setting maximum levels for certain contaminants in foodstuffs. 364. OJ L (pp. 5–24). EC (European Commission). https://eur‐lex.europa.eu/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Economist Impact. (2023). Breaking the cycle of chronic child malnutrition in sub‐Saharan Africa (pp. 1–29). Economist Impact.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA. (2010). Scientific opinion on Bisphenol A: Evaluation of a study investigating its neurodevelopmental toxicity review of recent scientific literature on its toxicity and advice on the Danish∖risk assessment of Bisphenol A. The EFSA Journal, 8(9), 182. http://www.efsa.europa.eu/en/efsajournal/pub/1829</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Egbujie, A. E., &amp; Okoye, J. J. (2019). Quality characteristics of complementary foods formulated from sorghum, African yam bean and crayfish flours. Science World Journal, 14(2), 16–22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eskenazi, B., Marks, A. R., Bradman, A., Fenster, L., Johnson, C., Barr, D. B., &amp; Jewell, N. P. (2006). In utero exposure to dichlorodiphenyltrichloroethane (DDT) and dichlorodiphenyldichloroethylene (DDE) and neurodevelopment among Mexican American children. Pediatrics, 118(1), 233–241. https://doi.org/10.1542/peds.2005‐3117</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ezekiel, C. N., Ayeni, K. I., Misihairabgwi, J. M., Somorin, Y. M., Chibuzor‐Onyeama, I. E., Oyedele, O. A., Abia, W. A., Sulyok, M., Shephard, G. S., &amp; Krska, R. (2018). Traditionally processed beverages in Africa: A review of the mycotoxin occurrence in patterns and exposure assessment. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 17, 334–351. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.12329</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ezekiel, C. N., Sulyok, M., Ogara, I. M., Abia, W. A., Warth, B., Sarkanj, B., Turner, P. C., &amp; Krska, R. (2019). Mycotoxins in uncooked and plate‐ready household food from rural northern Nigeria. Food and Chemical Toxicology, 128, 171–179. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fct.2019.04.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ezeocha, V. C., &amp; Onwuka, G. I. (2010). Effect of processing methods on the physic‐chemical and nutritional quality of maize and soybean based complementary blends. Nigerian Food Journal, 28(2), 210–216. https://doi.org/10.4314/nifoj.v28i2.62654</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan, Y. M., Oikarinen, S., Lehto, K. M., Nurminen, N., Juuti, R., Mangani, C., Maleta, K., Hyöty, H., &amp; Ashorn, P. (2019). High prevalence of selected viruses and parasites and their predictors in Malawian children. Epidemiology and Infection, 147(e90), 1–9. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0950268819000025</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fanzo, J. (2012). The nutrition challenge in sub‐Saharan Africa. In UNDP Africa Policy Notes 2012‐012. United Nations Development Programme. Regional Bureau for Africa. https://www.undp.org/sites/g/files/zskgke326/files/migration/africa/Nutrition‐Challenge.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAO (Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations). (2015). Regional overview of food insecurity: Africa. African food security prospects brighter than ever. FAO. https://www.fao.org/documents/card/en/c/9186338b‐3fe6‐427c‐b805‐fe81be23a676/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAO (Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations). (2017a). Nutrition‐sensitive agriculture and food systems in practice. Options for intervention: In Nutrition‐sensitive agriculture and food systems in practice. Options for intervention. FAO. https://www.fao.org/documents/card/en/c/9ca3cf89‐6109‐4a38‐855f‐6e218eae543b</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAO (Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations). (2017b). The future of food and agriculture—Trends and challenges. FAO. https://www.fao.org/3/i6583e/i6583e.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAO /WHO (Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations/World Health Organization). (1991). Guidelines on formulated complementary foods for older infants and young Children. Codex Alimentarius. In International Food Standards. CAC/GL 8‐1991. FAO. https://www.fao.org/fao‐who‐codexalimentarius/sh‐proxy/en/?lnk=1&amp;url=https%253A%252F%252Fworkspace.fao.org%252Fsites%252Fcodex%252FStandards%252FCXG%2B8‐1991%252FCXG_008e.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAO, IFAD, UNICEF, WFP &amp; WHO (Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations, the International Fund for Agricultural Development, the United Nations Children's Fund, the World Food Programme, and the World Health Organization). (2018). The state of food security and nutrition in the world 2018: Building climate resilience for food security and nutrition. FAO. https://www.fao.org/3/i9553en/i9553en.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAO/INFOODS/IZiNCG (Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations and International Zinc Nutrition Consultative Group). (2018). Global food composition database for Phytate Version 1.0—PhyFoodComp1.0. FAO. https://www.fao.org/3/i8542en/I8542EN.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fenga, C., Gangemi, S., Salvatore, V. D., Falzone, L., &amp; Libra, M. (2017). Immunological effects of occupational exposure to lead (review). Molecular Medicine Reports, 15(5), 3355–3360. https://doi.org/10.3892/mmr.2017.6381</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feyera, M. (2020). Review on some cereal and legume based composite biscuits. International Journal of Agricultural Science and Food Technology, 6(2), 101–109. https://doi.org/10.17352/2455‐815X.000062</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Filli, K. B., Jideani, A. I. O., &amp; Jideani, V. A. (2014). Extrusion bolsters food security in Africa. Food Technology Magazine, 68(4), 46–55. https://www.ift.org/news‐and‐publications/food‐technology‐magazine/issues/2014/april/features/extrusioncooking</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Forsido, S. F., Duguma, H. T., Lema, T. B., Sturm, B., &amp; Hensel, O. (2018). Nutritional and sensory quality of composite extruded complementary food. Food Science &amp; Nutrition, 7(2), 882–889. https://doi.org/10.1002/fsn3.940</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fredrick, R., Martin, H., Snapp, S., &amp; Kassim, N. (2021). Monotonous cereal‐based complementary feeding contributes to aflatoxin exposure in children. International Journal of Biosciences, 18(6), 204–216. https://doi.org/10.12692/ijb/18.6.204‐216</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frias, J., Miranda, M. L., Doblado, R., &amp; Vidal‐Valverde, C. (2005). Effect of germination and fermentation on the antioxidant vitamin content and antioxidant capacity of Lupinus albus L. var. multolupa. Food Chemistry, 92(2), 211–220. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2004.06.049</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garg, M., Sharma, N., Sharma, S., Kapoor, P., Kumar, A., Chunduri, V., &amp; Arora, P. (2018). Biofortified crops generated by breeding, agronomy and transgenic approaches are improving lives of millions of people around the world. Frontiers in Nutrition, 5, 12. https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2018.00012</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gawande, A. V., &amp; Babar, K. P. (2018). Effect of malting and fermentation on the functional and rheological properties of sorghum flour. Asian Food Science Journal, 1(1), 1–4. https://doi.org/10.9734/AFSJ/2018/38184</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gbashi, S., Adebo, O., Adebiyi, J. A., Targuma, S., Tebele, S., Areo, O. M., Olopade, B., Odukoya, J. O., &amp; Njobeh, P. (2021). Food safety, food security and genetically modified organisms in Africa: A current perspective. Biotechnology and Genetic Engineering Reviews, 37(1), 30–63. https://doi.org/10.1080/02648725.2021.1940735</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gemede, H. F. (2020). Nutritional and anti‐nutritional evaluation of complementary food formulated from maize, pea, and anchote flours. Food Science and Nutrition, 8(4), 2156–2164. https://doi.org/10.1002/fsn3.1516</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghosh, S., Tano‐Debrah, K., Aaron, G. J., Otoo, G., Strutt, N., Bomfeh, K., Kitamura, S., Suri, D. J., Murakami, H., Funita, C., Sarpong, D., Saalia, F., Nakao, S. Y., Amonoo‐Kuofi, H., Uauy, R., &amp; Toride, Y. (2014). Improving complementary feeding in Ghana: Reaching the vulnerable through innovative business—The case of KOKO Plus. Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences, 1331(1), 76–89. https://doi.org/10.1111/nyas.12596</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gibson, R. S., Bailey, K. B., Gibbs, M., &amp; Ferguson, E. L. (2010). A review of phytate, iron, zinc, and calcium concentrations in plant‐based complementary foods used in low‐income countries and implications for bioavailability. Food and Nutrition Bulletin, 31(2), S134–S146. https://doi.org/10.1177/15648265100312S206</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gilbert, G. S., Diaz, A., &amp; Bregoff, H. A. (2023). Seed disinfestation practices to control seed‐borne fungi and bacteria in home production of sprouts. Foods, 12(4), 747. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods12040747</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gilbert, R., Subedi, B., Wallingford, J., Wilson, N., &amp; Masters, W. A. (2019). Nutrient and mycotoxin content of commercially‐sold premixed infant cereals in Malawi. MaSSP Working Paper 28 (pp. 1–25). International Food Policy Research Institute (IFPRI). https://doi.org/10.2499/p15738coll2.133335</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grosshagauer, S., Milani, P., Kraemer, K., Mukabutera, A., Burkon, A., Pignitter, M., Bayer, S., &amp; Somoza, V. (2020). Inadequacy of nutrients and contaminants found in porridge‐type complementary foods in Rwanda. Maternal and Child Nutrition, 16(1), e12856. https://doi.org/10.1111/mcn.12856</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta, C., Chawla, P., Arora, S., Tomar, S. K., &amp; Singh, A. K. (2015). Iron microencapsulation with blend of gum arabic, maltodextrin and modified starch using modified solvent evaporation method—Milk fortification. Food Hydrocolloids, 43, 622–628. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodhyd.2014.07.021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hackett, K. M., Mukta, U. S., Jalal, C. S., &amp; Sellen, D. W. (2015). Knowledge, attitudes and perceptions on infant and young child nutrition and feeding among adolescent girls and young mothers in rural Bangladesh. Maternal and Child Nutrition, 11(2), 173–189. https://doi.org/10.1111/mcn.12007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>HarvestPlus &amp; Food and Agricultural Organization of the United Nations (FAO). (2019). Biofortification: A food systems solution to help end hidden hunger (p. 22) HarvestPlus. https://www.ifpri.org/publication/biofortification‐food‐systems‐solution‐help‐end‐hidden‐hunger</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hotz, C. (2013). Biofortification. In B. Caballero (Ed.), Encyclopedia of human nutrition (3rd ed., pp. 175–181). Academic Press. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978‐0‐12‐375083‐9.00025‐8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hotz, C., &amp; Gibson, R. S. (2001). Assessment of home‐based processing methods to reduce phytate content and phytate/zinc molar ratios of white maize (Zea mays). Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 49(2), 692–698. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf000462w</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hotz, C., &amp; Gibson, R. S. (2007). Traditional food‐processing and preparation practices to enhance the bioavailability of micronutrients in plant‐based diets. Journal of Nutrition, 137(4), 1097–100. https://doi.org/10.1093/jn/137.4.1097</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hubner, F., &amp; Arendt, E. K. (2013). Germination of cereal grains as a way to improve the nutritional value: A review. Critical Reviews in Food, Science and Nutrition, 53(8), 853–861. https://doi.org/10.1080/10408398.2011.562060</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hunger Notes. (2018). World hunger and poverty facts and statistics. Hunger Notes. https://www.worldhunger.org/world‐hunger‐and‐poverty‐facts‐and‐statistics/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>IARC (International Agency for Research on Cancer). (1993). IARC monographs on the evaluation of carcinogenic risks to humans. Some naturally occurring substances: Food items and constituents, heterocyclic aromatic amines and mycotoxins. International Agency for Research on Cancer, Lyon, 56, 445–466.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>IARC (International Agency for Research on Cancer). (2015). Mycotoxin control in low‐and‐middle‐income countries. In C. P. Wild, J. D. Miller, &amp; J. D. Groopman (Eds.), IARC Working Group Reports, No. 9. International Agency for Research on Cancer. https://publications.iarc.fr/Book‐And‐Report‐Series/Iarc‐Working‐Group‐Reports/Mycotoxin‐Control‐In‐Low–And‐Middle‐income‐Countries‐2015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Igyor, M. A., Yusufu, P. A., &amp; Sengev, I. A. (2010). Evaluation of physicochemical, functional and sensory properties of fermented fura powder supplemented with soy. Nigerian Food Journal, 28(2), 454–462. https://doi.org/10.4314/nifoj.v28i2.62679</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Issaka, A. I., Agho, K. E., Page, A. N., Burns, P. L., Stevens, G. J., &amp; Dibley, M. J. (2015). The problem of suboptimal complementary feeding practices in West Africa: What is the way forward? Maternal and Child Nutrition, 11, 53–60. https://doi.org/10.1111/mcn.12195</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Itaman, V. O., &amp; Okeniyi, C. A. (2022). Comparative evaluation of the microflora and biochemical constituents of sorghum–African breadfruit blends for complementary foods. Stamford Journal of Microbiology, 12(1), 8–14. https://doi.org/10.3329/sjm.v121i1.63337</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jafari, S. M. (2017). Nanoencapsulation of food bioactive ingredients: Principles and applications (p. 2017). Academic Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaffee, S., Spencer, H., Laurian, U., Delia, G., &amp; Emilie, C. (2019). The safe food imperative: Accelerating progress in low‐ and middle‐income countries. Agriculture and Food Series. World Bank. http://hdl.handle.net/10986/30568</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jamkhande, P. G., Ghule, N. W., Bamer, A. H., &amp; Kalaskar, M. G. (2019). Metal nanoparticles synthesis: An overview on methods of preparation, advantages and disadvantages, and applications. Journal of Drug Delivery Science and Technology, 53, 101174. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jddst.2019.101174</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jan, A. T., Azam, M., Siddiqui, K., Ali, A., Choi, I., &amp; Haq, Q. M. (2015). Heavy metals and human Health: Mechanistic insight into toxicity and counter defense system of antioxidants. International Journal of Molecular Science, 16(12), 29592–29630. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms161226183</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joye, I. J., Davidov‐Pardo, G., &amp; McClements, D. J. (2014). Nanotechnology for increased micronutrient bioavailability. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 40(2), 168–182. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2014.08.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Juke, M., Mcguire, J., Method, F., &amp; Sternberg, R. (2002). Nutrition and education. In Nutrition: A foundation for development. ACC/SCN.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamala, A., Shirima, C., Jani, B., Bakari, M., Sillo, H., Rusibamayila, N., De Saeger, S., Kimanya, M., Gong, Y. Y., &amp; Simba, A. (2018). Outbreak of acute aflatoxicosis in Tanzania during 2016. World Mycotoxin Journal, 11(3), 311–320. https://doi.org/10.3920/WMJ2018.2344</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karlovsky, P., Suman, M., Berthiller, F., De Meester, J., Eisenbrand, G., Perrin, I., Oswald, I. P., Speijers, G., Chiodini, A., Recker, T., &amp; Dussort, P. (2016). Impact of food processing and detoxification treatments on mycotoxin contamination. Mycotoxin Research, 32(4), 179–205. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12550‐016‐0257‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaur, T., Rana, K. L., Kour, D., Sheikh, I., Neelam, Y., Kumar, V., Yadav, A. N., Dhaliwal, H. S., &amp; Saxena, A. K. (2020). Microbe‐mediated biofortification for micronutrients: Present status and future challenges. In A. A. Rastegari, A. N. Yadav, &amp; N. Yadav (Eds.). New and future developments in microbial biotechnology and bioengineering (pp. 1–17) Elsevier. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978‐0‐12‐820528‐0.00002‐8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaushik, G., Satya, S., &amp; Naik, S. (2010). Effect of domestic processing techniques on the nutritional quality of the soybean. Mediterranean Journal of Nutrition and Metabolism, 3, 39–46. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12349‐009‐0079‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan, S., Cao, Q., Zheng, Y., Huang, Y., &amp; Zhu, Y. (2008). Health risks of heavy metals in contaminated soils and food crops irrigated with wastewater in Beijing, China. Environmental Pollution, 152(3), 686–692. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2007.06.056</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kimanya, M. E., De Meulenaer, B., Roberfroid, D., Lachat, C., &amp; Kolsteren, P. (2010). Fumonisin exposure through maize in complementary foods is inversely associated with linear growth of infants in Tanzania. Molecular Nutrition and Food Research, 54(11), 1659–1667. https://doi.org/10.1002/mnfr.200900483</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kinkese, D. M., Hang'ombe, M. B., Toure, O., Kinkese, T., &amp; Kangua, E. (2018). Contamination of complementary weaning foods for children with Escherichia coli and Salmonella species in Lusaka District, Zambia. Journal of Preventive and Rehabilitative Medicine, 1(1), 19–31. https://doi.org/10.21617/jprm.2018.0101.3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kouton, S. E., Amoussa‐Hounkpatin, W., Ballogou, V. Y., &amp; Soumanou, M. M. (2017). Nutritional, microbiological and rheological characteristics of porridges prepared from infant flours based on germinated and fermented cereals fortified with soybean. International Journal of Current Microbiology and Applied Sciences, 6(10), 4838–4852. https://doi.org/10.20546/ijcmas.2017.610.452</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumi, J., Mitchell, N. J., &amp; Ankrah, N. A. (2014). Aflatoxins and fumonisins contamination of home‐made food (weanimix) from cereal‐legume blends for children. Ghana Medical Journal, 48(3), 121–126. https://doi.org/10.4314/gmj.v48i3.1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kusn, F., &amp; Suyatma, N. E. (2017). Iron fortification of soya based infant cereal and its stability during storage. Journal of Food Technology and Preservation, 1(2), 16–21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leroy, J. L., Ruel, M., Habitcht, J. P., &amp; Frongillo, E. A. (2014). Linear growth deficit continues to accumulate beyond the first 1000 days in low‐and‐middle income countries: Global evidence from 51 national surveys. Journal of Nutrition, 144(9), 1460–1466. https://doi.org/10.3945/jn.114.191981</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, S., Tayie, F. A. K., Young, M. F., Rocheford, T., &amp; White, W. S. (2007). Retention of provitamin A carotenoids in high β‐carotene maize (Zea mays) during traditional African household processing. Journal of Agriculture and Food Chemistry, 55(26), 10744–10750. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf071815v</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lobato, L. P., Anibal, D., Lazaretti, M. M., &amp; Grossmann, M. V. E. (2011). Extruded puffed functional ingredient with oat bran and soy flour. LWT—Food Science and Technology, 44(4), 933–939. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2010.11.013</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lucke, F. K. (1996). Lactic acid bacteria involved in food fermentations and their present and future uses in the food industry. In T. Faruk Bozoğlu, &amp; B. Ray (Eds,), Lactic acid bacteria. NATO‐ASI Series (Vol. 98). Springer. https://doi.org/10.1007/978‐3‐642‐61462‐0_5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ly, M., Kane, C., Ayessou, N., Cissé, M., &amp; Mar, C. (2015). Amélioration des farines infantiles par incorporation des feuilles de Moringa oleifera. Ecole Supérieure Polytechnique/UCAD‐ DAKAR (pp. 1–18). Université Cheikh Anta Diop de Dakar.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Macharia, I. (2015). Pesticides and health in vegetable production in Kenya. Biomedical Research International, 2015, 241516. https://doi.org/10.1155/2015/241516</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malik, S., Krishnaswamy, K., &amp; Mustapha, A. (2021). Hazard analysis and risk‐based preventive controls (HARPC): Current food safety and quality standards for complementary foods. Foods, 10(9), 2199. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods10092199</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manandhar, A., Milindi, P., &amp; Shah, A. (2018). An overview of the post‐harvest grain storage practices of smallholder farmers in developing countries. Agriculture, 8(4), 57. https://doi.org/10.3390/agriculture8040057</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manzoor, M., Singh, D., Aseri, G. K., Sohal, J. S., Vij, S., &amp; Sharma, D. (2021). Role of lacto‐fermentations in reduction of anti‐nutrients in plant‐based foods. Journal of Applied Biology &amp; Biotechnology, 9(3), 7–16. https://doi.org/10.7324/JABB.2021.9302</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martha, W., &amp; Wenaty, A. (2023). Nutritional quality of complementary porridge for feeding children aged 6–24 months from selected local food ingredients. Asian Journal of Food Research and Nutrition, 2(3), 140–149.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin, H., Laswai, H., &amp; Kulwa, K. (2010). Nutrient content and acceptability of soybean based complementary food. African Journal of Food, Agriculture, Nutrition and Development, 10(1), 1684–5358. https://doi.org/10.4314/ajfand.v10i1.51482</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mastanjevi´c, K., Krstanović, V., Mastanjevi´c, K., &amp; Šarkanj, B. (2018). Malting and brewing industries encounter Fusarium spp. related problems. Fermentation, 4(1), 3. https://doi.org/10.3390/fermentation4010003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matheisen, L., Buerki‐Thurnherr, T., Pastuschek, Y., Aengenheister, L., &amp; Knudsen, L. E. (2021). Fetal exposure to environmental chemicals: Insights from placental perfusion studies. Placenta, 106, 58–66. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.placenta.2021.01.025</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matumba, L., Van Poucke, C., Ediage, E. N., Jacobs, B., &amp; De Saeger, S. (2015). Effectiveness of hand sorting, flotation/washing, dehulling and combinations thereof on the decontamination of mycotoxin‐contaminated white maize. Food Additives and Contaminants Part A, 32(6), 960–969. https://doi.org/10.1080/19440049.2015.1029535</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mbame, M. C., Tiencheu, B., Feumba, R., Tiepma, F. D., Ashu, A. O., Ufuan, A. D., Azantsa, B. G. K., &amp; Oben, J. (2021). Formulation of adequate complementary food for children 6–24 months using local staple foods in the South‐west region of Cameroon. European Journal of Nutrition and Food Safety, 13(12), 89–108. https://doi.org/10.9734/EJNFS/2021/v13i1230471</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McClements, D. J. (2020). Recent advances in the production and application of nano‐enabled bioactive food ingredients. Currents Opinion in Food Science, 33, 85–90. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cofs.2020.02.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mekuria, S. A., Kinyuru, J. N., Mokua, B. K., &amp; Tenagashaw, M. W. (2021). Nutritional quality and safety of complementary foods developed from blends of staple grains and honey bee larvae (Apis mellifera). International Journal of Food Science, 2021, 5581585. https://doi.org/10.1155/2021/5581585</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mensah, P., &amp; Tomkins, A. (2003). A household‐level technologies to improve the availability and preparation of adequate and safe complementary foods. Food and Nutrition Bulletin, 24(1), 104–125. https://doi.org/10.1177/156482650302400106</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mensa‐Wilmot, Y., Phillips, R. D., Lee, J., &amp; Eitenmiller, R. R. (2003). Formulation and evaluation of cereal/legume‐based weaning food supplements. Plant Foods for Human Nutrition, 58(3), 1–14. https://doi.org/10.1023/B:QUAL.0000040324.04977.dd</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohammed, A. U., Bolade, M. K., &amp; James, S. (2016). Functional properties of weaning food blends from selected sorghum (Sorghum bicolor (L.) Moench) varieties and soybean (Glycine max). African Journal of Food Science, 10(8), 112–121. https://doi.org/10.5897/AJFS2015.1406</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohammed, Z. K., Petrol, B. B., &amp; Ahmad, U. (2021). Formulation and nutritional evaluation of a complementary food blend made from fermented yellow maize (improved variety), soybean and African catfish meal. Nigerian Journal of Biotechnology, 38(1), 98–108. https://doi.org/10.4314/njb.v38i1.12</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moodley, S. S. (2019). Optimization of the production of motoho, a fermented sorghum beverage (p. 104) (Thesis, submitted). University of Witwatersrand. https://wiredspace.wits.ac.za</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moroni, P., Nydam, D. V., Ospina, P. A., Scillieri‐Smith, J. C., Virkler, P. D., Watters, R. D., Welcome, F. L., Zurakowski, M. J., Ducharme, N. G., &amp; Yeager, A. E. (2018). Diseases of the teats and udder. Rebhun's diseases of dairy cattle ((3rd ed., pp. 389–465). Elsevier. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978‐0‐323‐39055‐2.00008‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Msheliza, E. A., Ilesanmi, J. O. Y., Hussein, J. B., &amp; Nkama, I. (2018). Effects of pretreatments on the microbial and sensory quality of weaning food produced from blends of sorghum and soybean. African Journal of Food Science, 12(12), 353–359. https://doi.org/10.5897/AJFS2018.1691</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Msuya, J. (2016). Food safety of homemade complementary foods in Morogoro Municipality—Tanzania [MSc thesis]. Ohio State University.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mugalavai, V. K., Oyalo, J. O., &amp; Onkware, A. O. (2020). Characterization of the nutritional properties of sorghum composite flours using different food to food fortification approaches. European Journal of Agriculture and Food Sciences, 2(6), 1–7. https://doi.org/10.24018/ejfood.2020.2.6.84</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muhimbula, H. S., &amp; Issa‐Zacharia, A. (2010). Persistent child malnutrition in Tanzania: Risks associated with traditional complementary foods (a review). African Journal of Food Science, 4(11), 679–692.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mukherjee, S., &amp; Chattopadhyay, P. K. (2007). Whirling bed blanching of potato cubes and its effects on product quality. Journal of Food Engineering, 78(1), 52–60. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2005.09.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muyanja, C. M., Narvhus, J. A., &amp; Langsrud, T. (2012). Organic acids and volatile organic compounds produced during traditional and starter culture fermentation of bushera, a Ugandan fermented cereal beverage. Food Biotechnology, 26(1), 1–28. https://doi.org/10.1080/08905436.2011.617252</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mwangi, W. W., Nguta, C. M., &amp; Muruiki, B. G. (2014). Aflatoxin contamination in selected spice preparations in the Nyahururu retail market, Kenya. Journal of Scientific Research &amp; Reports, 3(7), 917–923. https://doi.org/10.9734/JSRR/2014/7948</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nantongo, S. (2019). Non‐cancer health risks associated with pesticides residues and heavy metal exposures in locally manufactured cereal‐based baby foods in Kampala city (MSc thesis). Kyambogo University.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nationalfoody. (2017). National dish of Ethiopia—Fit fit. Nationalfoody. https://nationalfoods.org/recipe/national‐dish‐of‐ethiopia‐fit‐fit/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ngadze, R. T., Linnemann, A. R., &amp; Fogliano, V. (2023). Nexus of local context and technology in child complementary feeding. Global Food Security, 38, 100714. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gfs.2023.100714</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ngaha, W. D., Ejoh, R. A., Fombang, E. N., &amp; Tedom, W. D. (2020). Nutritional quality of formulated complementary foods and their biological effects for tackling malnutrition in Sub‐Saharan Africa (SSA) countries. European Journal of Nutrition and Food Safety, 12(12), 91–103. https://doi.org/10.9734/ejnfs/2020/v12i1230339</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nnebue, C. C., Adogu, P., Ifeadike, C. O., &amp; Ironkwe, O. C. (2014). Assessment of the food hygiene practices of food handlers in the Federal Capital Territory of Nigeria. Tropical Journal of Medical Research, 17(1), 10–15. https://doi.org/10.4103/1119‐0388.130175</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nobosse, P., Fombang, N. E., &amp; Mbofung, C. M. F. (2017). The effect of steam blanching and drying method on nutrients, phytochemicals and antioxidant activity of moringa (Moringa oleifera L.) leaves. American Journal of Food Science and Technology, 5(2), 53–60. https://doi.org/10.12691/ajfst‐5‐2‐4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nonogaki, H., Bassel, G. W., &amp; Bewley, J. D. (2010). Germination—Still a mystery. Plant Science, 179(6), 574–581. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.plantsci.2010.02.010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nout, M. J. R., &amp; Ngoddy, P. O. (1997). Technological aspects of preparing affordable fermented complementary foods. Food Control, 8(5–6), 279–287. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0956‐7135(97)00001‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ntila, S., Ndhlala, A. R., Kolanisi, U., Abdelgadir, H., &amp; Siwela, M. (2019). Acceptability of a moringa‐added complementary soft porridge to caregivers in Hammanskraal, Gauteng province and Lebowakgomo, Limpopo province, South Africa. South African Journal of Clinical Nutrition, 32(3), 51–57. https://doi.org/10.1080/16070658.2018.1449377</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nwadi, O. M. M., &amp; Uvere, P. O. (2019). Mineral bioavailability and chemical composition of cereal‐based complementary food. Sky Journal of Food Science, 6(4), 040–045.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nzewi, D., &amp; Egbuonu, A. C. C. (2011). Effect of boiling and roasting on the proximate properties of Asparagus bean (Vignases quipedalis). African Journal of Biotechnology, 10(54), 11239–11244. https://doi.org/10.5897/AJB11.452</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Obafemi, Y. D., Oranusi, S. U., Ajanaku, K. O., Akinduti, P. A., Leech, J., &amp; Cotter, P. D. (2022). African fermented foods: Overview, emerging benefits and novel approaches to microbiome profiling. NPJ Science of Food, 6, 15. https://doi.org/10.1038/S41538‐022‐00130‐W</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Obinna‐Echem, P. C. (2017). Effect of processing method on pasting, morphological and sensory properties of akamu—A Nigerian fermented maize product. American Journal of Food Science and Technology, 5(3), 101–108. https://doi.org/10.12691/ajfst‐5‐3‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Odunfa, S. A., &amp; Adeyele, S. (1985). Microbiological changes during the traditional production of ogi‐baba, a West African fermented sorghum gruel. Journal of Cereal Science, 3(2), 173–180. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0733‐5210(85)80027‐8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Odunfa, S. A., &amp; Oyewole, O. B. (1998). African fermented foods. In: Wood, B.J.B. (eds) Microbiology of fermented foods (pp. 713–752). Boston, MA: Springer. https://doi.org/10.1007/978‐1‐4613‐0309‐1_23</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oduro, I., Ellis, W. O., Abodakpi, V. D., &amp; Eleblu, S. E. (2007). Effect of soaking, autoclaving and repeated boiling on oligosaccharides in cowpea. Nigerian Food Journal, 25(2), 88–94. https://doi.org/10.4314/nifoj.v25i2.50844</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oesterle, I., Ayeni, K. I., Ezekiel, C. N., Berry, D., Rompel, A., &amp; Warth, B. (2023). Insights into the early‐life chemical exposome of Nigerian infants and potential correlations with the developing gut microbiome. Envionment International, 188, 108766. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2024.108766</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ogbo, F. A., Nguyen, H., Naz, S., Agho, K. E., &amp; Page, A. (2018). The association between infant and young child feeding practices and diarrhoea in Tanzanian children. Tropical Medicine and Health, 46(2), 1–9. https://doi.org/10.1186/s41182‐018‐0084‐y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ogbonnaya, J. A., Ketiku, A. O., Mojekwu, C. N., &amp; Ogbonnaya, J. A. (2012). Energy, iron, zinc densities of commonly consumed traditional complementary foods in Nigeria. British Journal of Applied Science and Technology, 2(1), 48–57. https://doi.org/10.9734/BJAST/2012/553</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oh, S., Cave, G., &amp; Lu, C. (2021). Vitamin B12 (cobalamin) and micronutrient fortification in food crops using nanoparticle technology. Frontiers in Plant Science, 12, 668819. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2021.668819</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ohanenye, I. C., Emenike, C. U., Mensi, A., Medina‐Godoy, S., Jin, J., Ahmed, T., Sun, X., &amp; Udenigwe, C. C. (2021). Food fortification technologies: Influence on iron, zinc and vitamin A bioavailability and potential implications on micronutrient deficiency in sub‐Saharan Africa. Scientific African, 11, e0067. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.sciaf.2020.e00667</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ojha, P., Adhikari, R., Karki, R., Mishra, A., Subedi, U., &amp; Karki, T. B. (2017). Malting and fermentation effects on anti‐nutritional components and functional characteristics of sorghum flour. Food Science and Nutrition, 6(1), 47–53. https://doi.org/10.1002/fsn3.525</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ojokoh, A. O., Yimin, W., &amp; Eromosele, O. S. (2015). Effect of some extrusion variables on fermented maize‐soybean blend. Journal of Food Science and Technology, 52(9), 5763–5771. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13197-014-1689-8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ojuri, O. T., Ezekiel, C. N., Eskola, M. K., Šarkanj, B., Babalola, A. D., Sulyok, M., Hajšlová, J., Elliott, C. T., &amp; Krska, R. (2019). Mycotoxin co‐exposures in infants and young children consuming household‐ and industrially‐processed complementary foods in Nigeria and risk management advice. Food Control, 98, 312–322. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2018.11.049</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ojuri, O. T., Ezekiel, C. N., Sulyok, M., Ezeokoli, O. T., Oyedele, O. A., Ayeni, K. I., Eskola, M. K., Sarkanj, B., Hajslova, J., Adeleke, R. A., Nwagburuka, C. C., Elliot, C. T., &amp; Krska, R. (2018). Assessing the mycotoxicological risk from consumption of complementary foods by infants and young children in Nigeria. Food and Chemical Toxicology, 121, 37–50. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fct.2018.08.025</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okafor, U. I., Omemu, A. M., Obadina, A. O., Bankole, M. O., &amp; Adeyeye, S. A. O. (2018). Nutritional composition and antinutritional properties of maize ogi co‐fermented with pigeon pea. Food Science and Nutrition, 6(2), 424–439. https://doi.org/10.1002/fsn3.571</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oke, K. E., Adeyeye, S. A. O., &amp; Olorode, O. O. (2022). Complementary foods and its processing methods: A review. Croatian Journal of Food Science and Technology, 14(1), 1–13. https://doi.org/10.17508/CJFST.2022.14.1.05</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okeke, C. A., Ezekiel, C. N., Nwangburuka, C. C., Sulyok, M., Ezeamagu, C. O., Adeleke, R. A., Dike, S. K., &amp; Krska, R. (2015). Bacterial diversity and mycotoxin reduction during maize fermentation (steeping) for ogi production. Frontiers in Microbiology, 6, 1402. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2015.01402</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okeke, C. A., Ezekiel, C. N., Sulyok, M., Ogunremi, O. R., Ezeamagu, C. O., Sarkanj, B., Warth, B., &amp; Krska, R. (2018). Traditional processing impacts mycotoxin levels and nutritional value of ogi—A maize‐based complementary food. Food Control, 86, 224–233. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2017.11.021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okeyo, D. O. (2018). Impact of food fortification on child growth and development during complementary feeding. Annals of Nutrition and Metabolism, 73(1), 7–13. https://doi.org/10.1159/000490087</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okpalanma, E. F., Ukpong, E. S., Chude, O. C., &amp; Abah, C. R. (2022). Production of maize‐soybean complementary foods fortified with crayfish, bonga fish and carrots flour rich in essential nutrients. African Journal of Food Science, 16(12), 319–325. https://doi.org/10.5897/AJFS2021.2165</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oladeji, B. S., Akanbi, C. T., &amp; Ibironke, S. I. (2014). Physico‐chemical and nutritional evaluation of co‐processed fermented yellow maize ogi (an infant diet) and carrot blends. Annals Food Science and Technology, 15(1), 82–91.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oladiran, D. A., &amp; Emmambux, N. M. (2020). Locally available African complementary foods: Nutritional limitations and processing technologies to improve nutritional quality—A review. Food Reviews International, 38(5), 1033–1063. https://doi.org/10.1080/87559129.2020.1762640</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olisah, C., Okoh, O. O., &amp; Okoh, A. I. (2020). Occurrence of organochlorine pesticide residues in biological and environmental matrices in Africa: A two‐decade review. Heliyon, 6(3), e03518. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2020.e03518</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ombeni, B. J., &amp; Munyuli, T. (2019). Nutritional quality evaluation of complementary foods flour based on edible caterpillars: Bunaeopsis aurantiaca, Imbrasia oyemensis and Cirina forda in South Kivu province, Eastern D. R. Congo. Annals Food Science and Technology, 20(2), 362–379. https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.8950433</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Omenna, E. C., Olanipekun, I. O. T., &amp; Ogunwale, I. F. J. (2018). Nutritional and sensory properties of co‐fermented maize, millet and sorghum/soybean pap‐(ogi). MOJ Food Processing and Technology, 6(1), 159–164. https://doi.org/10.15406/mojfpt.2018.06.00159</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Omosebi, M. O., Osundahunsi, O. F., &amp; Fagbemi, T. N. (2018). Effect of extrusion on protein quality, antinutritional factors, and digestibility of complementary diet from quality protein maize and soybean protein concentrate. Journal of Food Biochemistry, 42(4), e12508. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfbc.12508</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Onabanjo, O. O., Akinyemi, C. O., &amp; Agbon, C. A. (2009). Characteristics of complementary foods produced from sorghum, sesame, carrot and crayfish. Journal of Natural Sciences, Engineering and Technology, 8(1), 71–83.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Onofiok, N. O., &amp; Nnanyelugo, D. O. (2007). Weaning foods in West Africa: Nutritional problems and possible solutions. Food and Nutrition Bulletin, 19(1), 27–33. https://doi.org/10.1177/156482659801900105</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Onyango, C., Henle, T., Hofmann, T., &amp; Bley, T. (2004). Production of high energy density fermented uji using a commercial alpha‐amylase or by single‐screw extrusion. LWT—Food Science and Technology, 37(4), 401–407. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2003.10.010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ortega‐Beltran, A., &amp; Bandyopadhyay, R. (2023). Addressing another threat to food safety: Conflict. Plants People Planet, 5(3), 317–323. https://doi.org/10.1002/ppp3.10351</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osagie, A. U., &amp; Eka, O. U. (1998). Nutritional quality of plant foods. Post‐Harvest Research Unit, Department of Biochemistry, University of Benin.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osman, M. A. (2011). Effect of traditional fermentation process on the nutrient and anti‐nutrient contents of pearl millet during preparation of Lohoh. Journal of Saudi Society of Agricultural Sciences, 10(1), 450–456. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jssas.2010.06.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oyegoke, T. G., Adedayo, E. O., Fasuyi, F. O., &amp; Oyegoke, D. A. (2020). Vitamin and mineral composition of complementary food formulated from yellow maize, soybean, millet and carrot composite flours. International Journal of Science and Research, 9(2), 450–456. https://doi.org/10.21275/ART20204521</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Öztürk, B. (2017). Nano emulsions for food fortification with lipophilic vitamins: Production challenges, stability and bioavailability. European Journal of Lipid Science Technology, 119(7), 1–18. https://doi.org/10.1002/ejlt.201500539</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papageorgiou, M., &amp; Skendi, A. (2018). Introduction to cereal processing and by‐products. In C. M. Galanakis (Ed.), Sustainable recovery and reutilization of cereal processing by‐products (pp. 1–25). Woodhead Publishing Series in Food Science, Technology and Nutrition, Woodhead Publishing. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978‐0‐08‐102162‐0.00001‐0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pathak, N., &amp; Kochhar, A. (2018). Extrusion technology: Solution to develop quality snacks for malnourished generation. International Journal of Current Microbiology and Applied Sciences, 7(1), 1293–1307. https://doi.org/10.20546/ijcmas.2018.701.158</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perlas, L., &amp; Gibson, R. S. (2002). Use of soaking to enhance the bioavailability of Fe and Zn from rice‐based complementary foods used in the Philippines. Journal of the Science of Food and Agriculture, 82(10), 1115–1121. https://doi.org/10.1002/jsfa.1156</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pristner, M., &amp; Warth, B. (2020). Drug–exposome interactions: The next frontier in precision medicine. Trends in Pharmacological Sciences, 41(12), 994–1005. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tips.2020.09.012</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramadas, S., Vellaichmy, S., Ramasundaram, P., Kumar, A., &amp; Singh, S. (2020). Biofortification for enhancing nutritional outcomes and policy imperatives. In O. P. Gupta, V. Pandey, S. Narwal, P. Sharma, S. Ram, &amp; G. P. Singh (Eds.), Wheat and barley grain biofortification. (pp. 309–327). Woodhead Publishing Series in Food Science, Technology and Nutrition, Woodhead Publishing. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978‐0‐12‐818444‐8.00013‐4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rao, C. K., &amp; Annadana, S. (2017). Nutrient biofortification of staple food crops: Technologies, products and prospects. In N. Benkeblia (Ed), Phytonutritional improvement of crops (pp. 113–183). Wiley &amp; Sons. https://doi.org/10.1002/9781119079972.ch3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rather, I. A., Koh, W. Y., Paek, W. K., &amp; Lim, J. (2017). The sources of chemical contaminants in food and their health implications. Frontiers in Pharmacology, 8(830), 1–8. https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2017.00830</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rivera, J. A., Hotz, C., González‐Cossío, T., Neufeld, L., &amp; Garcia‐Guerra, A. (2003). The effect of micronutrient deficiencies on child growth: A review of results from community‐based supplementation trials 1. Journal of Nutrition, 133(11 Suppl 2), 4010S–4020S. https://doi.org/10.1093/jn/133.11.4010S</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robertson, R. C., Manges, A. R., Finlay, B. B., &amp; Prendergast, A. J. (2018). The human microbiome and child growth—First 1000 days and beyond. Trends in Microbiology, 27(2), 131–147. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tim.2018.09.008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sakala, N. (2021). Dietary, quality of complementary foods for children aged 6–23 months in biofortified intervention areas of Chipata District, Zambia. (Thesis and dissertations). University of Zambia.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saltzman, A., Birol, E., Bouis, H., Boy, E., De Moura, F., Islam, Y., &amp; Pfeiffer, W. (2013). Biofortification: Progress towards a more nourishing future. Global Food Security, 2(1), 9–17. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gfs.2012.12.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Samtiya, M., Aluko, R. E., &amp; Dhewa, T. (2020). Plant food anti‐nutritional factors and their reduction strategies: An overview. Food Production, Processing and Nutrition, 2(6), 1–14. https://doi.org/10.1186/s43014‐020‐0020‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santillán‐Urquiza, E., Méndez‐Rojas, M. A., &amp; Vélez‐Ruiz, J. F. (2017). Fortification of yogurt with nano‐ and micro‐sized calcium, iron and zinc, effect on the physicochemical and rheological properties. LWT Food Science and Technology, 80(5), 462–469. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2017.03.025</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Severini, C., Giuliani, R., De Filippis, A., Derossi, A., &amp; De Pilli, T. (2016). Influence of different blanching methods on colour, ascorbic acid and phenolics content of broccoli. Journal of Food Science and Technology, 53(1), 501–510. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13197‐015‐1878‐0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shiota, M., Saitou, K., Mizumoto, H., Matsusaka, M., Agata, N., Nakayama, M., Kage, M., Tatsumi, S., Okamoto, A., Yamaguchi, S., Ohta, M., &amp; Hata, D. (2010). Rapid detoxification of cereulide in Bacillus cereus food poisoning. Pediatrics, 125(4), e951–e955. https://doi.org/10.1542/peds.2009‐2319</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shiriki, D., Igyor, M. A., &amp; Gernah, D. I. (2015). Nutritional evaluation of complementary food formulations from maize, soybean and peanut fortified with moringa oleifera leaf powder. Food and Nutrition Sciences, 6(5), 494–500. https://doi.org/10.4236/fns.2015.65051</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shoham, J., &amp; Duffield, A. (2009). Proceedings of the World Health Organization/UNICEF/World Food Programme/United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees Consultation on the management of moderate malnutrition in children under 5 years of age. Food and Nutrition Bulletin, 30, (3 Suppl), S464–S474. https://doi.org/10.1177/15648265090303S306</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shuaib, F. M., Jolly, P. E., Ehiri, J. E., Yatich, N., Jiang, Y., Funkhouser, E., Person, S. D., Wilson, C., Ellis, W. O., Wang, J. S., &amp; Williams, J. H. (2010). Associations between birth outcomes and aflatoxin B1 biomarker blood levels in pregnant women in Kumasi, Ghana. Tropical Medicine and International Health, 15(2), 160–167. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365‐3156.2009.02435.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shubham, K., Anukiruthika, T., Dutta, S., Kashyap, A. V., Moses, J. A., &amp; Anandharamakrishnan, C. (2020). Iron deficiency anemia: A comprehensive review on iron absorption, bioavailability and emerging food fortification approaches. Trends in Food Science and Technology, 99, 58–75. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2020.02.021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh, J., Dartois, A., &amp; Kaur, L. (2010). Starch digestibility in food matrix: A review. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 21(4), 168–180. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2009.12.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh, T., Shukla, S., Kumar, P., Wahla, V., Bajpai, V. K., &amp; Rather, I. A. (2017). Application of nanotechnology in food science: Perception and overview. Frontiers in Microbiology, 8, 1501. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2017.01501</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sobowale, S. S., Adebo, O. A., &amp; Adebiyi, J. A. (2017). Development of a twin‐screw extruder. Agricultural Engineering International: CIGR Journal, 19(4), 181–186.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Solomon, N. (2007). Malnutrition and infection: An update. British Journal of Nutrition, 98(1), S5–S10. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0007114507832879</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soro, S., Elleingand, F. E., Koffi, M. G., &amp; Koffi, E. (2014). Evaluation des propriétés antioxydants et biologiques de farines infantiles à base d'igname/soja/sources végétales de minéraux. Journal of Applied Biosciences, 80(1), 7031–7047. https://doi.org/10.4314/jab.v80i1.12</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sosan, M. B., Adeleye, A. O., Oyekunle, J. A. O., Udah, O., Oloruntunbi, P. M., Daramola, M. O., &amp; Saka, W. T. (2020). Dietary risk assessment of organochlorine pesticide residues in maize‐based complementary breakfast food products in Nigeria. Heliyon, 6(12), e05803. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2020.e05803</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steinkraus, K. (2018). Handbook of indigenous fermented foods: Revised and expanded. CRC Press. https://doi.org/10.1201/9780203752821</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steinkraus, K. H. (1997). Classification of fermented foods: World‐wide review of household fermentation techniques. Food Control, 85(5–6), 311–317.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suchdev, P. S., Jefferds, M. E. D., Ota, E., da Silva Lopes, K., &amp; De‐Regil, L. M. (2020). Home fortification of foods with multiple micronutrient powders for health and nutrition in children under two years of age. Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews, 2(2), CD008959. https://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.CD008959.pub3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sule, S., Okafor, G. I., Momoh, O. C., Gbaa, S. T., &amp; Amonyeze, A. O. (2024). Applications of extrusion technology. MOJ Food Processing and Technology, 12(1), 78–84. https://doi.org/10.15406/mojfpt.2024.12.00301</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Symes, S., &amp; Goldsmith, P. (2015). Microbiological safety, H. H. food handling practices of seed sprout products in the Australian State of Victoria. Journal of Food Protection, 78(7), 1387–1391. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362‐028X.JFP‐14‐566</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tacer‐caba, Z., Nilufer‐Erdil, D., &amp; Ai, Y. (2015). Chemical composition of cereals and their products. Handbook of food chemistry (pp. 323–325). Springer. https://doi.org/10.1007/978‐3‐642‐36605‐5_33</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tamano, E. (2022). Dabo (Ethiopian bread). Jewish Food Society. https://www.jewishfoodsociety.org/recipes/dabo/‐ethiopian‐bread‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tanyikitu, M. N., &amp; Petcheu, I. C. N. (2022). Formulation and nutritional analysis of processed sorghum, soybeans and mango complementary food. Journal of Food Research, Canadian Center of Science and Education, 11(3), 1–11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tedom, D. W., Fombang, N. E., Ejoh, A. R., &amp; Ngaha, D. W. (2020). Optimal conditions of steam blanching of spinach (Spinacia oleracea), a leafy vegetable consumed in Cameroon. International Journal of Nutritional Science &amp; Food Technology, 6(4), 1–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Temesgen, M. (2013). Nutritional status of Ethiopian weaning and complementary foods: A review. Open Access Scientific Reports, 2(2), 1–9. https://doi.org/10.4172/scientificreports.621</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tenagashaw, M. W., Kenji, G. M., Melaku, E. T., Huyskens‐Keil, S., &amp; Kinyuru, J. N. (2017). Teff‐based complementary food fortified with soybean and orange‐fleshed sweet potato. Journal of Food Research, 6(1), 112–122. https://doi.org/10.5539/jfr.v6n1p112</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tenna, A., Tesfahhun, E., Derseh, D., Yenehun, G., &amp; Negussie, T. (2023). Microbial quality of home prepared complementary foods in slum households with children of age 6–24 months in Addis Ababa: A community based cross‐sectional study. Open Journal of Food and Nutrition, 1(1), 40–50. https://doi.org/10.31586/ojfn.2023.595</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Terefe, N. S. (2016). Emerging trends and opportunities in food fermentation (pp. 1–9). Elsevier Publishers. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978‐0‐08‐100596.21087‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tiemann, U. (2008). In vivo and in vitro effects of the organochlorine pesticides DDT, TCPM, methoxychior and lindane on the female reproductive tract of mammals: A review. Reproductive Toxicology, 25(3), 316–326. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.reprotox.2008.03.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tou, E. H., Mouquet‐Rivier, C., Picq, C., Traorè, A. S., Trèche, S., &amp; Guyot, J. P. (2007). Improving the nutritional quality of ben‐saalga, a traditional fermented millet‐based gruel, by co‐fermenting millet with groundnut and modifying the processing method. LWT—Food Science and Technology, 40(9), 1561–1569. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2006.12.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tufa, M., Urga, K., Weledesemayat, G. T., &amp; Mitiku, B. G. (2016). Development and nutritional assessment of complementary foods from fermented cereals and soybean. Journal of Food Science and Nutrition, 2(14), 1–8. https://doi.org/10.24966/FSN‐1076/100014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tura, D. C., Belachew, F., Tamiru, D., &amp; Abate, K. H. (2023). Optimization of dabi teff‐field pea‐based energy and protein dense novel complementary food with improved sensory acceptability using D‐optimal mixture design. Heliyon, 9(8), e19029. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e19029</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uauy, R., &amp; Kain, J. (2002). The epidemiological transition: Need to incorporate obesity prevention into nutrition programmes. Public Health Nutrition, 5(1A), 223–229. https://doi.org/10.1079/PHN2001297</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uauy, R., Maass, A., &amp; Araya, M. (2008). Estimating risk from copper excess in human populations. American Journal of Clinical Nutrition, 88(3), 867S–871S. https://doi.org/10.1093/ajcn/88.3.867S</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uchegbu, N. N., Onwurafor, E. U., &amp; Nwadi, O. M. M. (2019). Microbial status and quality assessment of complementary food produced from co‐fermentation of sorghum and pumpkin seed fortified with carrot. Saudi Journal of Pathology and Microbiology, 4(12), 884–894. https://doi.org/10.36348/SJPM.2019.v04i12.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UN (United Nations). (2015). Transforming our world: The 2030 agenda for sustainable development. UN (United Nations). https://sdgs.un.org/2030agenda</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNICEF (United Nations Children's Fund). (2011). United Nations Children's Fund Programming Guide: Infant and young child feeding. UNICEF.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNICEF (United Nations Children's Fund). (2013). The state of the world's children; children with disabilities. UNICEF. https://doi.org/10.18356/6a978726‐en</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNICEF (United Nations Children's Fund). (2016a). The state of the world's children 2016. A fair chance for every child. UNICEF. https://www.unicef.org/media/50076/file/UNICEF_SOWC_2016‐ENG.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNICEF (United Nations Children's Fund). (2016b). One is too many: Ending child deaths from pneumonia and diarrhoea. UNICEF. https://data.unicef.org/resources/one‐many‐ending‐child‐deaths‐pneumonia‐diarrhoea/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNICEF (United Nations Children's Fund). (2023). Home fortification with multiple micronutrient powders for the prevention of iron deficiency anaemia in early childhood. Brief guidance note. UNICEF. https://www.unicef.org/media/145741/file/Home%20Fortification%20with%20Multiple%20Micronutrient%20Powders%20for%20the%20Prevention%20of%20Iron%20Deficiency%20Anaemia%20in%20Early%20Childhood.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>United Nations Children's Fund (UNICEF), World Health Organization, International Bank for Reconstruction and Development/The World Bank. (2021). Levels and trends in child malnutrition: UNICEF/WHO/The World Bank Group joint child malnutrition estimates: Key findings of the 2021 edition. United Nations Children's Fund. https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240025257</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>United Nations Children's Fund (UNICEF), World Health Organization (WHO), International Bank for Reconstruction and Development/The World Bank. (2023). Levels and trends in child malnutrition: UNICEF/WHO/World Bank Group Joint Child Malnutrition Estimates: Key findings of the 2023 edition. UNICEF and WHO. https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240073791</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>United States Department of Agriculture (USDA). (2008). USDA National Food and Nutrient Analysis Program Wave. USDA.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vincent, M., Duval, R. E., Hartemann, P., &amp; Engels‐Deutsch, M. (2018). Contact killing and antimicrobial properties of copper. Journal of Applied Microbiology, 124(5), 1032–1046. https://doi.org/10.1111/jam.13681</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, J., &amp; Fung, D. Y. (1996). Alkaline‐fermented foods: A review with emphasis on pidan fermentation. Critical Reviews in Microbiology, 22(2), 101–38. https://doi.org/10.3109/10408419609106457</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ware, L. Y., Noel, D., Nikiema, P. A., Alter, P., Fontana, A., Montet, D., &amp; Barro, N. (2017). Occurrence of mycotoxins in commercial infant formulas locally produced in Ouagadougou (Burkina Faso). Food Control, 73, 518–523. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2016.08.047</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Warth, B., Priendl, K., Manser, P., Wick, P., Marko, D., &amp; Buerki‐Thurnherr, T. (2019). Transfer and metabolism of the xenoestrogen zearalenone in human perfused placenta. Environmental Health Perspectives, 127(10), 107004. https://doi.org/10.1289/EHP4860</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watson, S., Moore, S. E., Darboe, M. K., Chen, G., Tu, Y. K., Huang, Y. T., Eriksen, K. G., Bernstein, R. M., Prentice, A. M., Wild, C. P., Xu, Y., Routledge, M. N., &amp; Gong, Y. Y. (2018). Impaired growth in rural Gambian infants exposed to aflatoxin: A prospective cohort study. BMC Public Health [Electronic Resource], 18(1), 1247. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889‐018‐6164‐4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>United Nations. (2015). Millennium Development Goals Report (p. 75) (edited by C. Way). United Nations. https://www.un.org/millenniumgoals/2015_MDG_Report/pdf/MDG%202015%20rev%20(July%201).pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>White, J. M., Beal, T., Arsenault, J. E., Okronipa, H., Hinnouho, G. M., Chimanya, K., Matji, J., &amp; Garg, A. (2021). Micronutrient gaps during the complementary feeding period in 6 countries in Eastern and Southern Africa: A comprehensive nutrient gap assessment. Nutrition Reviews, 79(S1), 16–25. https://doi.org/10.1093/nutrit/nuaa142</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>White, J. M., Begin, F., Kumapley, R., Murray, C., &amp; Krasevec, J. (2017). Complementary feeding practices: Current global and regional estimates. Maternal &amp; Child Nutrition, 13(Suppl 2), e12505. https://doi.org/10.1111/mcn.12505</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO &amp; FAO (The World Health Organization and Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations). (2018). Pesticide residues in food—2018: Toxicological evaluations. World Health Organization and Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations. https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789241655330</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO &amp; UNICEF (The World Health Organization and United Nations Children's Fund). (2003). Global strategy for infant and young child feeding. WHO &amp; UNICEF. https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9241562218</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO (The World Health Organization). (2001). The optimal duration of exclusive breastfeeding: A systematic review. WHO. https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/WHO‐NHD‐01.08</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO (The World Health Organization). (2002). The World Health Report: Reducing risks, promoting healthy life. WHO. https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9241562072</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO (The World Health Organization). (2009). WHO child growth standards and the identification of severe acute malnutrition in infants and children. WHO. https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789241598163</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO (The World Health Organization). (2011). Guideline: Use of multiple micronutrient powders for home fortification of foods consumed by infants and children 6–23 months of age. World Health Organization. https://www.who.int/publications/who‐guidelines</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO (The World Health Organization). (2013). Updates on the management of severe acute malnutrition in infants and children. World Health Organization. https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789241506328</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO (The World Health Organization). (2015). Estimates of the global burden of foodborne diseases: foodborne disease burden epidemiology reference group 2007–2015. World Health Organization. https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789241565165</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO (The World Health Organization). (2018). Reducing stunting in children: Equity considerations for achieving the global nutrition targets 2025. World Health Organization. https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789241513647</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO (The World Health Organization). (2023). Multiple micronutrient powders for point‐of‐use fortification of foods consumed by children 6–23 months of age. e‐Library of Evidence for Nutrition Actions (eLENA). World Health Organization. https://www.who.int/tools/elena/interventions/micronutrientpowder‐infants</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO (The World Health Organization). (2024). Infant and young child feeding. Nutritional Landscape Information System (NLiS). World Health Organization. https://www.who.int/data/nutrition/nlis/info/infant‐and‐young‐child‐feeding</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO Multicentre Growth Reference Study Group. (2006). Child growth standards based on length /height, weight and age. WHO Multicenter Reference Study Group. Acta Paediatrica, 450, 76–85. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1651‐2227.2006.tb02378.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wild, C. P. (2005). Complementing the genome with an exposome: The outstanding challenge of environmental exposure measurement in molecular epidemiology. Cancer Epidemiology Biomarkers &amp; Prevention, 14(8), 1847–1850. https://doi.org/10.1158/1055‐9965.EPI‐05‐0456</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wild, C. P. (2012). The exposome: From concept to utility. International Journal of Epidemiology, 41(1), 24–32. https://doi.org/10.1093/ije/dyr236</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wild, C. P., &amp; Gong, Y. Y. (2010). Mycotoxins and human disease: A largely ignored global health issue. Carcinogenesis, 31(1), 71–82. https://doi.org/10.1093/carcin/bgp264</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Bank. (2005). Repositioning nutrition as central to development: A strategy for large scale action. The World Bank. https://doi.org/10.1596/978‐0‐8213‐6399‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Bank, FAO, &amp; NRI. (2011). Missing food: The case of post‐harvest grain losses in sub‐Saharan Africa economic sector work report No. 60371‐AFR. The World Bank. https://documents1.worldbank.org/curated/zh/358461468194348132/pdf/603710SR0White0W110Missing0Food0web.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Food Program. (2018). Nutritional guidance for complementary food. World Food Program. https://www.wfp.org/publications/nutritional‐guidance‐complementary‐food</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Assembly. (2012). Comprehensive implementation plan on maternal, infant and young child nutrition. World Health Assembly. https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/WHO‐NMH‐NHD‐14.1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao, H. W., Zhongli, P., Deng, L. Z., El‐Mashad, H. M., Yang, X. H., Mujumdar, A. S., Gao, Z. J., &amp; Zhang, Q. (2017). Recent developments and trends in thermal blanching—A comprehensive review. Information Processing in Agriculture, 4(2), 101–127. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.inpa.2017.02.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yao, K. N., N'guessan, K. F., Zinzendorf, N. Y., Kouassi, K. A., Kouassi, C. K., Loukou, Y. G., &amp; Kouame, P. L. (2016). Isolation and characterization of Cronobacter spp from indigenous infant flours sold in public health centres within Abidjan, Cote d'Ivoire. Food Control, 62, 224–230. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodcont.2015.10.041</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yohannes, T. G., Makokha, A. O., Okoth, J. K., &amp; Tenagashaw, M. W. (2020). Developing and nutritional quality evaluation complementary diets produced from selected cereals and legumes cultivated in Gondar province, Ethiopia. Current Research in Nutrition and Food Science, 8(1), 291–302. https://doi.org/10.12944/CRNFSJ.8.1.27</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, H., Wu, F., Xu, D., &amp; Xu, X. (2021). Effects of milling methods on the properties of glutinous rice flour and sweet dumplings. Journal of Food Science and Technology, 58(5), 1848–1857. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13197‐020‐04696‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, Y., Lv, H., &amp; Li, Y. (2023). Grain storage: Theory, technology and equipment. Foods, 12(20), 3792. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods12203792</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>