<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39374421</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1541-4337</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>23</Volume><Issue>6</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Comprehensive reviews in food science and food safety</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Frozen dough steamed products: Deterioration mechanism, processing technology, and improvement strategies.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70028</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70028</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1541-4337.70028</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Fresh dough products lead to instability in product quality, high production costs, and more production time, which seriously affects the industrial production of the food industry. The frozen dough technology mitigates the problems of short shelf-life and easy deterioration of quality during storage and transportation. It has shown a series of advantages in large-scale industrialization, high-quality standardization, and chain operation. However, the further development of frozen dough is restricted by the deterioration of the main components (gluten, starch, and yeast) caused by freezing. This review summarizes the main production process of frozen steamed bread and buns, and the deterioration reasons for the main component of frozen dough. The improvement mechanisms of raw ingredients, processing technology, processing equipment, and additives on frozen dough quality were analyzed from the perspective of improving gluten network integrity and yeast freeze tolerance. From prefermented frozen raw to steamed products without thawing has become the preferred production process to improve production efficiency. Wheat flour mixed with other flour can maintain the gluten network continuity of frozen dough. The freeze tolerance of yeast was improved by treatment with yeast suspension, yeast cell encapsulation, screening hybridization, and genetic engineering. Process optimization and new technology-assisted fermentation and freezing effectively reduce freezing damage. Various additives improve the freeze resistance of the gluten-starch matrix by promoting protein cross-linking and inhibiting water migration. In addition, ice structural proteins and ice nucleating agents have been proven to change the growth morphology and formation temperature of ice crystals. More new technologies and additive synergies need to be further explored.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Institute of Food Technologists®.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Meng-Li</ForeName><Initials>ML</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Food Science and Resources, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Food Science and Technology, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Guo</LastName><ForeName>Xiao-Na</ForeName><Initials>XN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Food Science and Resources, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Food Science and Technology, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sun</LastName><ForeName>Xiao-Hong</ForeName><Initials>XH</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2346-0347</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Plant, Food and Environmental Sciences, Faculty of Agriculture, Dalhousie University, Truro, Nova Scotia, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhu</LastName><ForeName>Ke-Xue</ForeName><Initials>KX</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7606-6813</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>State Key Laboratory of Food Science and Resources, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Food Science and Technology, Jiangnan University, Wuxi, PR China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Collaborative Innovation Center of Food Safety and Quality Control in Jiangsu Province</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>32072253</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Qing Lan Project</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101305205</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1541-4337</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>8002-80-0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D005983">Glutens</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>9005-25-8</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D013213">Starch</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005615" MajorTopicYN="Y">Freezing</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005433" MajorTopicYN="Y">Flour</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005511" MajorTopicYN="Y">Food Handling</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001939" MajorTopicYN="Y">Bread</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014908" MajorTopicYN="N">Triticum</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005983" MajorTopicYN="N">Glutens</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013213" MajorTopicYN="N">Starch</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005285" MajorTopicYN="N">Fermentation</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">frozen dough products</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">gluten network</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">processing technology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">versatile additives</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">yeast freeze tolerance</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>15</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39374421</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.70028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Acker, J. P., &amp; McGann, L. E. (2003). Protective effect of intracellular ice during freezing? Cryobiology, 46(2), 197–202. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0011‐2240(03)00025‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bae, W., Lee, B., Hou, G. G., &amp; Lee, S. (2014). Physicochemical characterization of whole‐grain wheat flour in a frozen dough system for bake off technology. Journal of Cereal Science, 60(3), 520–525. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcs.2014.08.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baier‐Schenk, A., Handeschin, S., &amp; Conde‐Petit, B. (2005). Ice in prefermented frozen bread dough–An investigation based on calorimety and microscopy. Cereal Chemistry, 82(3), 251–255. https://doi.org/10.1094/CC‐82‐0251</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao, H., Zheng, X. Z., Liu, H., Yuan, M., Ye, T., Wu, X. X., Yin, F. Q., Li, Y., Yu, J. S., &amp; Xu, F. (2020). Cryo‐protective effect of ice‐binding peptides derived from collagen hydrolysates on the frozen dough and its ice‐binding mechanisms. LWT‐Food Science and Technology, 131, 109678. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2020.109678</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao, Y. F., Jiang, L. J., Suo, W. J., Deng, Y. X., Zhang, M., Dong, S., Guo, P., Chen, S. F., &amp; Li, H. J. (2021). Influence of emulsifiers and enzymes on dough rheological properties and quality characteristics of steamed bread enriched with potato pulp. Food Chemistry, 360, 130015. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2021.130015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chavan, R. S., &amp; Chavan, S. R. (2011). Sourdough technology—A traditional way for wholesome foods: A review. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 10(3), 169–182. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1541‐4337.2011.00148.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, J. R., Xiao, J. H., Tu, J., Yu, L. L., &amp; Niu, L. Y. (2023). The alleviative effect of sweet potato protein hydrolysates on the quality deterioration of frozen dough bread in comparison to trehalose. LWT‐Food Science and Technology, 175, 114505. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2023.114505</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, N., Yang, Q., Zhang, C. C., &amp; Chen, H. Q. (2023). Impact of basil seed gum on the textural, rheological properties, water state, gluten depolymerization and microstructure of frozen dough. Journal of Cereal Science, 112, 103728. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcs.2023.103728</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, X., Wu, J. H., Cai, X. X., &amp; Wang, S. Y. (2021). Production, structure−function relationships, mechanisms, and applications of antifreeze peptides. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 20(1), 542–562. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.12655</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, X., Wu, J. H., Li, L., &amp; Wang, S. Y. (2016). The cryoprotective effects of antifreeze peptides from pigskin collagen on texture properties and water mobility of frozen dough subjected to freeze‐thaw cycles. European Food Research and Technology, 243(7), 1149–1156. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00217‐016‐2830‐x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, X., Wu, J. H., Li, L., &amp; Wang, S. Y. (2019). Cryoprotective activity and action mechanism of antifreeze peptides obtained from tilapia scales on Streptococcus thermophilus during cold stress. Journal of Agricultural Food Chemistry, 67(7), 1918–1926. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jafc.8b06514</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui, M. L., Wang, F. X., Li, X. H., Yu, J., Huang, Y. Q., &amp; Liu, Y. L. (2023). Investigation of the cryoprotective mechanisms of silver carp muscle hydrolysate for frozen dough exposed to multiple freeze‐thaw cycles. LWT‐Food Science and Technology, 187, 115321. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2023.115321</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Decock, P., &amp; Cappelle, S. (2005). Bread technology and sourdough technology. Trends in Food Science and Technology, 16, 113–120. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2004.04.012</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delcour, J. A., Joye, I. J., Pareyt, B., Wilderjans, E., Brijs, K., &amp; Lagrain, B. (2012). Wheat gluten functionality as a quality determinant in cereal‐based food products. Annual Review of Food Science and Technology, 3, 469–492. https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev‐food‐022811‐101303</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding, X. L., Li, T. T., Zhang, H., Guan, C. R., Qian, J. Y., &amp; Zhou, X. Y. (2020). Effect of barley antifreeze protein on dough and bread during freezing and freeze‐thaw cycles. Foods, 9(11), 1698. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods9111698</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dong, J., Chen, D., Wang, G., Zhang, C., Du, L., Liu, S., Zhao, Y., &amp; Xiao, D. (2016). Improving freeze‐tolerance of baker's yeast through seamless gene deletion of NTH1 and PUT1. Journal of Industrial Microbiology and Biotechnology, 43(6), 817–828. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10295‐016‐1753‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>El‐Hady, E., El‐Samahy, S., &amp; Brummer, J. (1999). Effects of oxidants, sodium‐stearoyl‐2‐lactylate and their mixtures on rheological and baking properties on nonprefermented frozen doughs. LWT‐Food Science and Technology, 32(7), 446–454. https://doi.org/10.1006/fstl.1999.0569</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng, W., Ma, S., Huang, J., Li, L., Wang, X., &amp; Bao, Q. (2022). Recent advances in the technology of quick‐frozen baozi: A review. International Journal of Food Science and Technology, 57(3), 1493–1507. https://doi.org/10.1111/ijfs.15540</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng, W., Ma, S., Wang, F., &amp; Wang, X. (2022). Effect of black rice flour with different particle sizes on frozen dough and steamed bread quality. International Journal of Food Science and Technology, 57(3), 1748–1762. https://doi.org/10.1111/ijfs.15551</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng, W., Ma, S., &amp; Wang, X. (2020a). Quality deterioration and improvement of wheat gluten protein in frozen dough. Grain &amp; Oil Science and Technology, 3(1), 29–37. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gaost.2020.02.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng, W., Ma, S., &amp; Wang, X. (2020b). Recent advances in quality deterioration and improvement of starch in frozen dough. Grain &amp; Oil Science and Technology, 3(4), 154–163. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gaost.2020.07.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frauenlob, J., Moriano, M. E., Innerkofler, U., D'Amico, S., Lucisano, M., &amp; Schoenlechner, R. (2017). Effect of physicochemical and empirical rheological wheat flour properties on quality parameters of bread made from pre‐fermented frozen dough. Journal of Cereal Science, 77, 58–65. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcs.2017.06.021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao, D., &amp; Critser, J. K. (2000). Mechanisms of cryoinjury in living cells. Institute for Laboratory Animal Research Journal, 41(4), 187–196. https://doi.org/10.1093/ilar.41.4.187</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao, H., Liu, Y., Meng, K., &amp; Zeng, J. (2022). Study on moisture migration mechanism of dough during subfreezing storage. Cereal Chemistry, 99(6), 1308–1317. https://doi.org/10.1002/cche.10593</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gélinas, P., Fiset, G., Willemot, C., &amp; Goulet, J. (1991). Lipid content and cryotolerance of bakers' yeast in frozen dough. Applied and Environmental Microbiology, 57(2), 463–468. https://doi.org/10.1128/AEM.57.2.463‐468.1991</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giannou, V., Kessoglou, V., &amp; Tzia, C. (2003). Quality and safety characteristics of bread made from frozen dough. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology, 14(3), 99–108. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0924‐2244(02)00278‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grenier, A., Lucas, T., Collewet, G., &amp; Le‐Bail, A. (2003). Assessment by MRI of local porosity in dough during proving. Theoretical considerations and experimental validation using a spin‐echo sequence. Magnetic Resonance Imaging, 21(9), 1071–1086. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0730‐725X(03)00194‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo, W. T., Yang, X. F., Ji, Y. S., Hu, B., Li, W. G., Zhong, X. Y., Jiang, S. T., &amp; Zheng, Z. (2023). Effects of transglutaminase and glucose oxidase on the properties of frozen dough: Water distribution, rheological properties, and microstructure. Journal of Cereal Science, 111, 103689. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcs.2023.103689</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassas‐Roudsari, M., &amp; Goff, H. D. (2012). Ice structuring proteins from plants: Mechanism of action and food application. Food Research International, 46(1), 425–436. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2011.12.018</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Havet, M., Mankai, M., &amp; Le‐Bail, A. (2000). Influence of the freezing condition on the baking performances of French frozen dough. Journal of Food Engineering, 45, 139–145.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsu, K. H., Hoseney, R. C., &amp; Seib, P. A. (1979). Frozen dough. II. Effects of freezing and storing conditions on the stability of yeasted doughs. Cereal Chemistry, 56(5), 424–426.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang, S., &amp; Miskelly, D. (2019). Steamed bread—A review of manufacturing, flour quality requirements, and quality evaluation. Cereal Chemistry, 96(1), 8–22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Inoue, Y., &amp; Bushuk, W. (1991). Studies on frozen bread doughs. I: Effects of frozen storage and freeze‐thaw cycles on baking and rheological properties. Cereal Chemistry, 68(6), 627–631. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365‐2125.1992.tb04111.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>James, C., Purnell, G., &amp; James, S. J. (2015). A review of novel and innovative food freezing technologies. Food Bioprocess Technology, 8, 1616–1634. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11947‐015‐1542‐8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jia, C., Huang, W., Wu, C., Zhong, J., Rayas‐Duarte, P., &amp; Guo, C. (2012). Frozen bread dough properties modified by thermostable ice structuring proteins extract from Chinese Privet (Ligustrum vulgare) leaves. Cereal Chemistry, 89(3), 162–167. https://doi.org/10.1094/cchem‐11‐11‐0136</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jia, C., Yang, W., Yang, Z., &amp; Ojobi, O. J. (2017). Study of the mechanism of improvement due to waxy wheat flour addition on the quality of frozen dough bread. Journal of Cereal Science, 75, 10–16. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcs.2017.03.007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jia, G., Du, Z., Chen, Y., &amp; Sun, A. (2023). Quantitative analysis perspective: Ice growth and super‐chilling state of frozen dough under quick freezing. LWT‐Food Science and Technology, 179, 114652. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2023.114652</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jirasatid, S., &amp; Nopharatana, M. (2018). Product development of sweet fermented rice (Khoa‐Mak) supplemented with red yeast rice. International Journal of Agricultural Technology, 14(4), 521–534.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keeratipibul, S., &amp; Luangsakul, N. (2012). Chinese steamed buns. In Y. H. Hui, &amp; E.Ö. Evranuz (Eds.), Handbook of plant‐based fermented food and beverage technology (pp. 543–556). CRC Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, H. J., &amp; Yoo, S. H. (2020). Effects of combined α‐amylase and endo‐xylanase treatments on the properties of fresh and frozen doughs and final breads. Polymers, 12(6), 1349. https://doi.org/10.3390/polym12061349</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kondakci, T., Ang, A. M. Y., &amp; Zhou, W. (2015). Impact of sodium alginate and xanthan gum on the quality of steamed bread made from frozen dough. Cereal Chemistry, 92(3), 236–245. https://doi.org/10.1094/CCHEM‐03‐14‐0036‐R</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kondakci, T., Zhang, J. W., &amp; Zhou, W. (2015). Impact of flour protein content and freezing conditions on the quality of frozen dough and corresponding steamed bread. Food and Bioprocess Technology, 8(9), 1877–1889. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11947‐015‐1544‐6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kontogiorgos, V., &amp; Goff, H. D. (2006). Calorimetric and microstructural investigation of frozen hydrated gluten. Food Biophysics, 1(4), 202–215. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11483‐006‐9021‐4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuninori, T., &amp; Sullivan, B. (1968). Disulfide‐sulfhydryl interchange studies of wheat flour. II. Reaction of glutathione. Cereal Chemistry, 45(5), 486–495.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Le‐Bail, A., Grinand, C., LeCleach, S., Martinez, S., &amp; Quilin, E. (1999). Influence of storage conditions on frozen French bread dough. Journal of Food Engineering, 39, 289–291.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Le‐Bail, A., Nicolitch, C., &amp; Vuillod, C. (2010). Fermented frozen dough: Impact of pre‐fermentation time and of freezing rate for a pre‐fermented frozen dough on final volume of the bread. Food and Bioprocess Technology, 3(2), 197–203. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11947‐008‐0142‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, K., Zhang, M., Bhandari, B., Li, L. L., &amp; Yang, C. H. (2020). Effect of pre‐emulsified soybean oil as a fat replacer on the physical and sensory attributes of reduced‐fat filling in steamed buns. Journal of Food Process Engineering, 43(2), 1–8. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfpe.13306</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, M., Hasjim, J., Xie, F., Halley, P. J., &amp; Gilbert, R. G. (2014). Shear degradation of molecular, crystalline, and granular structures of starch during extrusion. Starch/Stärke, 66, 595–605. https://doi.org/10.1002/star.201300201</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, Y., Zhang, Y., Liu, X., Wang, H., &amp; Zhang, H. (2019). Effect of ultrasound‐assisted freezing on the textural characteristics of dough and the structural characterization of wheat gluten. Journal of Food Science and Technology, 56(7), 3380–3390. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13197‐019‐03822‐6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, Y., Zhao, F., Li, C., Ban, X., Gu, Z., &amp; Li, Z. (2023). Mechanistic insights into the improvement of yeast viability by adding short‐clustered maltodextrin during long‐term frozen storage. Food Hydrocolloids, 134, 108092. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodhyd.2022.108092</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, Y., Zhao, F., Li, C., Xie, X., Ban, X., Gu, Z., &amp; Li, Z. (2023). Short‐clustered maltodextrin provides cryoprotection by maintaining cell membrane homeostasis of yeast during frozen storage. Food Chemistry, 405, 134729. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2022.134729</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Limtong, S., Sintara, S., Suwanarit, P., &amp; Lotong, N. (2002). Yeast diversity in Thai traditional fermentation starter (Loog‐pang). Kasetsart Journal Natural Sciences, 36, 149–158.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, M., Liang, Y., Wang, Y., Zhang, H., Wu, G., Wang, L., &amp; Qi, X. (2018). Effects of recombinant carrot antifreeze protein from Pichia pastoris GS115 on the physicochemical properties of hydrated gluten during freeze‐thawed cycles. Journal of Cereal Science, 83, 245–251. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcs.2018.08.016</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, M., Liu, X., &amp; Li, Y. (2020). Soybean peptides’ cryoprotective effects on Saccharomyces cerevisiae fermenting power in frozen dough and maintenance of the Chinese steamed bread qualities. Journal of Food Processing and Preservation, 44(8), 1–9. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfpp.14572</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, X., Zhao, S., Wei, Q., Zhao, X., &amp; Zhang, H. (2019). Effects of vacuum degree on the water status, physicochemical properties and microstructure of fast frozen dumpling wrappers. International Journal of Food Science &amp; Technology, 54(6), 2075–2083. https://doi.org/10.1111/ijfs.14108</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, Y., Gao, J., Wu, H., Gou, M., Jing, L., Zhao, K., Zhang, B., Zhang, G., &amp; Li, W. (2019). Molecular, crystal and physicochemical properties of granular waxy corn starch after repeated freeze‐thaw cycles at different freezing temperatures. International Journal of Biological Macromolecule, 133, 346–353. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2019.04.111</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lou, X., Yue, C., Luo, D., Li, P., Zhao, Y., Xu, Y., Wang, L., &amp; Bai, Z. (2023). Effects of natural inulin on the rheological, physicochemical and structural properties of frozen dough during frozen storage and its mechanism. LWT‐Food Science and Technology, 184, 114973. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2023.114973</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu, L., Xing, J. J., Guo, X. N., Sun, X. H., &amp; Zhu, K. X. (2020). Enhancing the freezing‐thawing tolerance of frozen dough using ε‐poly‐L‐lysine treated yeast. Food Bioscience, 37, 100699. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fbio.2020.100699</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu, L., &amp; Zhu, K. X. (2023). Physicochemical and fermentation properties of pre‐fermented frozen dough: Comparative study of frozen storage and freeze‐thaw cycles. Food Hydrocolloids, 136, 108253. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodhyd.2022.108253</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu, W., &amp; Grant, L. A. (1999). Effects of prolonged storage at freezing temperatures on starch and baking quality of frozen doughs. Cereal Chemistry, 76(5), 656–662.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lucas, T., Grenier, D., Bornert, M., Challois, S., &amp; Quellec, S. (2010). Bubble growth and collapse in pre‐fermented doughs during freezing, thawing and final proving. Food Research International, 43, 1041–1048. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres,2010.01.014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo, W., Sun, D. W., Zhu, Z., &amp; Wang, Q. J. (2018). Improving freeze tolerance of yeast and dough properties for enhancing frozen dough quality—A review of effective methods. Trends in Food Science and Technology, 72, 25–33. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2017.11.017</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma, W. J., Shan, J. L., Wang, M. Y., Xie, J. H., Chen, Y., Liang, L. X., Feng, J. Z., Hu, X. B., &amp; Yu, Q. (2024). Effects of improver on the quality of frozen Chinese sweet rice wine dough: Water status, protein structure and flavor properties. Food Chemistry, 445, 138713. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2024.138713</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Magalhães, F., Calton, A., Heiniö, R. L., &amp; Gibson, B. (2021). Frozen‐dough baking potential of psychrotolerant Saccharomyces species and derived hybrids. Food Microbiology, 94, 103640. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fm.2020.103640</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Majzoobi, M., Raissjalali, A., Jamalian, J., &amp; Farahnaky, A. (2015). Effect of white wheat flour substitution with whole oat flour on physical properties of part‐baked frozen bread. Journal of Texture Studies, 46(6), 411–419. https://doi.org/10.1111/jtxs.12139</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martínez, M. M., Rosell, C. M., &amp; Gómez, M. (2014). Modification of wheat flour functionality and digestibility through different extrusion conditions. Journal of Food Engineering, 143, 74–79. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2014.06.035</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meng, K., Gao, H., Zeng, J., Li, G., &amp; Su, T. (2021). Effect of subfreezing storage on the quality and shelf life of frozen fermented dough. Journal of Food Processing and Preservation, 45(3), e15249. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfpp.15249</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meric, L., Lambert, G. S., Neyreneuf, O., &amp; Richard, M. D. (1995). Cryoresistance of baker's yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae in frozen dough: Contribution of cellular trehalose. Cereal Chemistry, 72(6), 609–615.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mihaly Cozmuta, A., Jastrzębska, A., Apjok, R., Petrus, M., Mihaly Cozmuta, L., Peter, A., &amp; Nicula, C. (2021). Immobilization of baker's yeast in the alginate‐based hydrogels to impart sensorial characteristics to frozen dough bread. Food Bioscience, 42, 101143. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fbio.2021.101143</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Montemurro, M., Coda, R., &amp; Rizzello, C. G. (2019). Recent advances in the use of sourdough biotechnology in pasta making. Foods, 8(4), 129. https://doi.org/10.3390/foods8040129</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakagawa, Y., Ogihara, H., Mochizuki, C., Yamamura, H., Iimura, Y., &amp; Hayakawa, M. (2017). Development of intra‐strain self‐cloning procedure for breeding baker's yeast strains. Journal of Bioscience and Bioengineering, 123(3), 319–326. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jbiosc.2016.10.008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neyreneuf, O., &amp; Delpuech, B. (1993). Freezing experiments on yeasted dough slabs. Effects of cryogenic temperatures on the baking performance. Cereal Chemistry, 70(1), 109–111.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nur, B. M., &amp; Nilda, C. (2019). A review: Advance in frozen dough improver technology of bread. Jurnal Agriovet, 1(2), 165–184.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Öhgren, C., Fabregat, N., &amp; Langton, M. (2016). Quality of bread baked from frozen dough—Effects of rye, and sugar content, kneading time and proofing profile. LWT‐Food Science and Technology, 68, 626–633. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2015.12.069</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Omedi, J. O., Huang, W., Zhang, B., Li, Z., &amp; Zheng, J. (2019). Advances in present‐day frozen dough technology and its improver and novel biotech ingredients development trends–A review. Cereal Chemistry, 96(1), 34–56. https://doi.org/10.1002/cche.10122</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ortolan, F., Brites, L. T. G., Montenegro, F. M., Schmiele, M., Steel, C. J., Clerici, M. T. P. S., Almeida, E. L., &amp; Chang, Y. K. (2015). Effect of extruded wheat flour and pre‐gelatinized cassava starch on process and quality parameters of French‐type bread elaborated from frozen dough. Food Research International, 76, 402–409. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2015.07.010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ouyang, B., Duan, M., Zhu, S., Zhou, X., &amp; Zhou, Y. (2023). Effect of tartary buckwheat sourdough fermented by different exogenous lactic acid bacteria on antifreeze property of frozen dough. Food Chemistry Advances, 2, 100182. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.focha.2023.100182</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Öztürk, S., Cerit, İ., Mutlu, S., &amp; Demirkol, O. (2017). Enrichment of cookies with glutathione by inactive yeast cells (Saccharomyces cerevisiae): Physicochemical and functional properties. Journal of Cereal Science, 78, 19–24. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcs.2017.06.019</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phimolsiripol, Y., Siripatrawan, U., Tulyathan, V., &amp; Cleland, D. J. (2008). Effects of freezing and temperature fluctuations during frozen storage on frozen dough and bread quality. Journal of Food Engineering, 84(1), 48–56. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2007.04.016</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rasanen, J., Harkonen, H., &amp; Autio, K. (1995). Freeze‐thaw stability of prefermented frozen lean wheat doughs: Effect of flour quality and fermentation time. Cereal Chemistry, 72(6), 637–642. https://doi.org/10.1021/bp00036a018</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rasanen, J., Laurikainen, T., &amp; Autio, K. (1997). Fermentation stability and pore size distribution of frozen prefermented lean wheat doughs. Cereal Chemistry, 74(1), 56–62. https://doi.org/10.1094/CCHEM.1997.74.1.56</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ribotta, P. D., Perez, G. T., Leon, A. E., &amp; Anon, M. C. (2004). Effect of emulsifier and guar gum on micro structural, rheological and baking performance of frozen bread dough. Food Hydrocolloids, 18, 305–313. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0268‐005X(03)00086‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scott, G., &amp; Awika, J. M. (2023). Effect of protein−starch interactions on starch retrogradation and implications for food product quality. Comprehensive Reviews in Food Science and Food Safety, 22(3), 2081–2111. https://doi.org/10.1111/1541‐4337.13141</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sethuraman, A., Vedantham, G., Imoto, T., Przybycien, T., &amp; Belfort, G. (2004). Protein unfolding at interfaces: Slow dynamics of α‐helix to β‐sheet transition. Proteins: Structure, Function and Genetics, 56(4), 669–678. https://doi.org/10.1002/prot.20183</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharadanant, R., &amp; Khan, K. (2006). Effect of hydrophilic gums on the quality of frozen dough: Electron microscopy, protein solubility, and electrophoresis studies. Cereal Chemistry, 83(4), 411–417. https://doi.org/10.1094/CC‐83‐0411</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi, K., Yu, H., Jin, J., &amp; Lee, T.‐C. (2013). Improvement to baking quality of frozen bread dough by novel zein‐based ice nucleation films. Journal of Cereal Science, 57(3), 430–436. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcs.2013.01.010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stecchini, M. L., Maltini, E., Venir, E., Del‐Torre, M., &amp; Prospero, L. (2002). Properties of wheat dough at sub‐zero temperatures and freeze tolerance of a baker's yeast (Saccharomyces cerevisiae). Journal of Food Science, 67(6), 2196–2201.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stromeck, A., Hu, Y., Chen, L., &amp; Gäzle, M. G. (2011). Proteolysis and bioconversion of cereal proteins to glutamate and γ‐aminobutyrate (GABA) in rye malt sourdoughs. Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry, 59(4), 1392–1399. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf103546t</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun, J., Chen, M., Hou, X. X., Li, T. T., Qian, H. F., Zhang, H., Li, Y., Qi, X. G., &amp; Li, W. (2021). Effect of phosphate salts on the gluten network structure and quality of wheat noodles. Food Chemistry, 358, 129895. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun, X., Zhang, C. Y., Wu, M. Y., Fan, Z. H., Liu, S. N., &amp; Zhu, W. B. (2016). Deletion enhance the freezing tolerance and fermentation capacity of the baker's yeast in lean dough. Microbial Cell Factories, 15(54), 1–8. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12934‐016‐0453‐3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Surojanametakul, V., Panthavee, W., Satmalee, P., Phomkaivon, N., &amp; Yoshihashi, T. (2019). Effect of traditional dried starter culture on morphological, chemical and physicochemical properties of sweet fermented glutinous rice products. Journal of Agricultural Science, 11(6), 43. https://doi.org/10.5539/jas.v11n6p43</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takasaki, S., &amp; Karasawa, K. (1992). Effect of storage period on survival of freeze tolerant yeast and on the rheological properties of frozen dough. Journal of Japanese Society of Food Science and Technology (Nippon Shokuhin Kogyo Gakkaishi), 39(9), 813–820.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan, H., Dong, J., Wang, G., Xu, H., Zhang, C., &amp; Xiao, D. (2014). Enhanced freeze tolerance of baker's yeast by overexpressed trehalose‐6‐phosphate synthase gene (TPS1) and deleted trehalase genes in frozen dough. Journal of Industrial Microbiology and Biotechnology, 41(8), 1275–1285. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10295‐014‐1467‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan, J. M., Li, B., Han, S. Y., &amp; Wu, H. (2023). Use of a compound modifier to retard the quality deterioration of frozen dough and its steamed bread. Food Research International, 172, 113229. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2023.113229</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang, X., Wang, F., Huang, W., Zou, Q., Jia, C., Jin, D., Omedi, J.‐O., &amp; Li, Z. (2016). The combination of Rhizopus chinensis lipase and transglutaminase affects the rheology and glutenin macropolymer properties of frozen dough. Cereal Chemistry, 93(4), 377–385. https://doi.org/10.1094/cchem‐08‐15‐0179‐r</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tao, H., Wang, P., Wu, F., Jin, Z., &amp; Xu, X. (2016). Particle size distribution of wheat starch granules in relation to baking properties of frozen dough. Carbohydrate Polymers, 137, 147–153. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.carbpol.2015.10.063</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tao, H., Xiao, Y., Wu, F., &amp; Xu, X. (2018). Optimization of additives and their combination to improve the quality of refrigerated dough. LWT‐Food Science and Technology, 89, 482–488. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2017.11.028</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Theóphilo Galvão, A. M. M., de Oliveira Araújo, A. W., Carneiro, S. V., Zambelli, R. A., &amp; do Socorro Rocha Bastos, M. (2018). Coating development with modified starch and tomato powder for application in frozen dough. Food Packaging and Shelf Life, 16, 194–203. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fpsl.2018.04.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tochampa, W., Jittrepotch, N., Kongbangkerd, T., Kraboun, K., &amp; Rojsuntornkitti, K. (2011). The study of microwave heating time on chemical and microbiological properties and sensory evaluation in sweet fermented glutinous rice (Khao‐Mark). International Food Research Journal, 18(1), 239–248.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsolmonbaatar, A., Hashida, K., Sugimoto, Y., Watanabe, D., Furukawa, S., &amp; Takagi, H. (2016). Isolation of baker's yeast mutants with proline accumulation that showed enhanced tolerance to baking‐associated stresses. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 238, 233–240. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2016.09.015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verheyen, C., Albrecht, A., Herrmann, J., Strobl, M., Jekle, M., &amp; Becker, T. (2015). The contribution of glutathione to the destabilizing effect of yeast on wheat dough. Food Chemistry, 173, 243–249. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2014.10.021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, P., Jin, Z., &amp; Xu, X. (2015). Physicochemical alterations of wheat gluten proteins upon dough formation and frozen storage—A review from gluten, glutenin and gliadin perspectives. Trends in Food Science and Technology, 46(2), 189–198. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2015.10.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, P., Lee, T. C., Xu, X., &amp; Jin, Z. (2016). The contribution of glutenin macropolymer depolymerization to the deterioration of frozen steamed bread dough quality. Food Chemistry, 211, 27–33. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2016.05.031</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, P., Xu, L., Nikoo, M., Ocen, D., Wu, F. F., Yang, N., Jin, Z. Y., &amp; Xu, X. M. (2014). Effect of frozen storage on the conformational, thermal and microscopic properties of gluten: Comparative studies on gluten‐, glutenin‐ and gliadin‐rich fractions. Food Hydrocolloids, 35, 238–246. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodhyd.2013.05.015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, P., Yang, R., Gu, Z., Xu, X., &amp; Jin, Z. (2017). Comparative study on the freeze stability of yeast and chemical leavened steamed bread dough. Food Chemistry, 221, 482–488. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2016.10.108</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, P., Zou, M., Gu, Z., &amp; Yang, R. (2018). Heat‐induced polymerization behavior variation of frozen‐stored gluten. Food Chemistry, 255, 242–251. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2018.02.047</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, X., Pei, D., Teng, Y., &amp; Liang, J. (2018). Effects of enzymes to improve sensory quality of frozen dough bread and analysis on its mechanism. Journal Food Science Technology, 55(1), 389–398. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13197‐017‐2950‐8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei, X. R., Wu, T., &amp; Zhao, J. (2022). Fermentation characteristics and bread baking attributes of bread dough fermented with glutinous rice. Food Science &amp; Applied Microbiology Reports, 1(1), 32–38. https://finessepublishing.com/fsamr</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wieser, H., Vermeulen, N., Gaertner, F., &amp; Vogel, R. F. (2008). Effects of different Lactobacillus and Enterococcus strains and chemical acidification regarding degradation of gluten proteins during sourdough fermentation. European Food Research and Technology, 226(6), 1495–1502. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00217‐007‐0681‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, G., Liu, X., Hu, Z., Wang, K., &amp; Zhao, L. (2022). Impact of xanthan gum on gluten microstructure and bread quality during the freeze‐thaw storage. LWT‐Food Science and Technology, 162, 113450. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2022.113450</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, J., Chen, L., Guo, B., Zhang, B., Zhang, Y., &amp; Li, M. (2022). Elucidation of rheological properties of frozen non‐fermented dough with different thawing treatments: The view from protein structure and water mobility. Journal of Cereal Science, 108, 103572. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcs.2022.103572</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, S., Jeong, S., &amp; Lee, S. (2020). Elucidation of rheological properties and baking performance of frozen doughs under different thawing conditions. Journal of Food Engineering, 284, 110084. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2020.110084</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, Y., Zheng, S., Li, Z., Pan, Z., Huang, Z., Zhao, J., &amp; Ai, Z. (2021). Influence of three types of freezing methods on physicochemical properties and digestibility of starch in frozen unfermented dough. Food Hydrocolloids, 115, 106619. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodhyd.2021.106619</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, B., Omedi, J. O., Zheng, J., Huang, W., Jia, C., Zhou, L., Zou, Q., Li, N., &amp; Gao, T. (2021). Exopolysaccharides in sourdough fermented by Weissella confusa QS813 protected protein matrix and quality of frozen gluten‐red bean dough during freeze‐thaw cycles. Food Bioscience, 43, 101180. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fbio.2021.101180</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, L., Zeng, J., Gao, H., Zhang, K., &amp; Wang, M. (2022). Effects of different frozen storage conditions on the functional properties of wheat gluten protein in nonfermented dough. Food Science and Technology, 42, e97821. https://doi.org/10.1590/fst.97821</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Y., Li, Y., Wang, H., Oladejo, A. O., Zhang, H., &amp; Liu, X. (2020). Effects of ultrasound‐assisted freezing on the water migration of dough and the structural characteristics of gluten components. Journal of Cereal Science, 94, 102893. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcs.2019.102893</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Y., Wang, W., Liu, Y., Liu, X., Wang, H., &amp; Zhang, H. (2022). Cryoprotective effect of wheat gluten enzymatic hydrolysate on fermentation properties of frozen dough. Journal of Cereal Science, 104, 103423. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcs.2022.103423</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Y., Zhang, S., Yang, X., Wang, W., Liu, X., Wang, H., &amp; Zhang, H. (2022). Enhancing the fermentation performance of frozen dough by ultrasonication: Effect of starch hierarchical structures. Journal of Cereal Science, 106, 103500. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcs.2022.103500</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, B., Fu, S., Li, H., Li, H., Wang, Y., Li, Z., &amp; Liu, C. (2021). Quality evaluation of steam reheated frozen steamed bread. LWT‐Food Science and Technology, 150, 112074. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lwt.2021.112074</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou, B., Dai, Y., Guo, D., Zhang, J., Liang, H., Li, B., Sun, J., &amp; Wu, J. (2022). Effect of desalted egg white and gelatin mixture system on frozen dough. Food Hydrocolloids, 132, 107889. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodhyd.2022.107889</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu, F. (2014). Influence of ingredients and chemical components on the quality of Chinese steamed bread. Food Chemistry, 163, 154–162. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2014.04.067</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zounis, S., Quail, K. J., Wootton, M., &amp; Dickson, M. R. (2002a). Studying frozen dough structure using low‐temperature scanning electron microscopy. Journal of Cereal Science, 35(2), 135–147. https://doi.org/10.1006/jcrs.2001.0406</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zounis, S., Quail, K. J., Wootton, M., &amp; Dickson, M. R. (2002b). Effect of final dough temperature on the microstructure of frozen bread dough. Journal of Cereal Science, 36, 135–146. https://doi.org/10.1006/jcrs.2001.0407</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>