<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39370054</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1873-4596</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>225</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>05</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Free radical biology &amp; medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Free Radic Biol Med</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>CCCP induces hepatic stellate cell activation and liver fibrogenesis via mitochondrial and lysosomal dysfunction.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>181</StartPage><EndPage>192</EndPage><MedlinePgn>181-192</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2024.10.259</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0891-5849(24)00960-2</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Hepatic stellate cells (HSCs) are primary cells for development and progression of liver fibrosis. Mitophagy is an essential lysosomal process for mitochondrial homeostasis, which can be activated by carbonyl cyanide m-chlorophenyl hydrazone (CCCP), a representative mitochondrial uncoupler. However, little information is available on the role of CCCP-mediated mitophagy in HSC activation and liver fibrogenesis. In this study, we showed that CCCP treatment in HSCs caused mitochondrial dysfunction proved by decreased mitochondrial membrane potential, mitochondrial DNA, and ATP contents and increased mitochondrial ROS. Moreover, CCCP induced mitophagy and impaired mitophagy flux at the later stage. This blockade of mitophagic flux effect was mediated by suppression of lysosomal activity; CCCP decreased expression of lysosomal markers and cathepsin B activity, and increased lysosomal pH. Intriguingly, CCCP treatment in LX-2 cells or primary HSCs elevated plasminogen activator inhibitor-1 (PAI-1), a typical fibrogenic marker of HSCs which was attenuated by mitochondrial division inhibitor 1, a mitophagy inhibitor. The up-regulation of PAI-1 by CCCP was not due to altered transcriptional activity but lysosomal dysfunction. In vivo acute or sub-chronic treatment of CCCP to mice induced mitophagy and fibrogenesis of liver. Hepatic fibrogenic marker (PAI-1) was incremented with mitophagy markers (parkin and PTEN-induced putative kinase 1) in the livers of CCCP injected mice. Furthermore, we found that 5-aminoimidazole-4-carboxyamide ribonucleoside reversed CCCP-mediated mitophagy and subsequent HSC activation. To conclude, CCCP facilitated HSC activation and hepatic fibrogenesis via mitochondrial dysfunction and lysosomal blockade, implying that attenuation of CCCP-related signaling molecules may contribute to treat liver fibrosis.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lee</LastName><ForeName>Ji Hyun</ForeName><Initials>JH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MRC-OSTRC, Research Institute of Pharmaceutical Sciences, College of Pharmacy, Chosun University, Gwangju, 61452, South Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Seo</LastName><ForeName>Kyu Hwa</ForeName><Initials>KH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>General for Narcotics Safety Planning, Pharmaceutical Safety Bureau, Ministry of Food and Drug Safety (MFDS), Cheongju, South Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Ji Hye</ForeName><Initials>JH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Korean Medicine, Dongshin University, Naju, Jeollanam-do, 58245, South Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cho</LastName><ForeName>Sam Seok</ForeName><Initials>SS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MRC-OSTRC, Research Institute of Pharmaceutical Sciences, College of Pharmacy, Chosun University, Gwangju, 61452, South Korea; Non-Clinical Evaluation Center, Biomedical Research Institute, Chonbuk National University Hospital, Jeonju, Chonbuk, South Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kim</LastName><ForeName>Na Yeon</ForeName><Initials>NY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MRC-OSTRC, Research Institute of Pharmaceutical Sciences, College of Pharmacy, Chosun University, Gwangju, 61452, South Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kim</LastName><ForeName>Ji Hye</ForeName><Initials>JH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MRC-OSTRC, Research Institute of Pharmaceutical Sciences, College of Pharmacy, Chosun University, Gwangju, 61452, South Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kim</LastName><ForeName>Kyu Min</ForeName><Initials>KM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Science, College of Natural Science, Chosun University, Gwangju, 61452, South Korea; Institute of Well-Aging Medicare &amp; Chosun University LAMP Project Group, Chosun University, Gwangju, 61452, South Korea; Department of Integrative Biological Sciences &amp; BK21 FOUR Educational Research Group for Age-associated Disorder Control Technology, Chosun University, Gwangju, 61452, South Korea. Electronic address: kmkim@chosun.ac.kr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ki</LastName><ForeName>Sung Hwan</ForeName><Initials>SH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MRC-OSTRC, Research Institute of Pharmaceutical Sciences, College of Pharmacy, Chosun University, Gwangju, 61452, South Korea. Electronic address: shki@chosun.ac.kr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>05</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Free Radic Biol Med</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8709159</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0891-5849</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">AICAR</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">CCCP</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Hepatic stellate cell</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Liver fibrosis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Lysosome</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>35</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>35</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39370054</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2024.10.259</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0891-5849(24)00960-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>