<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39377767</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1613-6829</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>08</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Small (Weinheim an der Bergstrasse, Germany)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Small</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Triboelectric Nanogenerator for Self-Powered Gas Sensing.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e2406964</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e2406964</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/smll.202406964</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>With the continuous acceleration of industrialization, gas sensors are evolving to become portable, wearable and environmentally friendly. However, traditional gas sensors rely on external power supply, which severely limits their applications in various industries. As an innovative and environmentally adaptable power generation technology, triboelectric nanogenerators (TENGs) can be integrated with gas sensors to leverage the benefits of both technologies for efficient and environmentally friendly self-powered gas sensing. This paper delves into the basic principles and current research frontiers of the TENG-based self-powered gas sensor, focusing particularly on innovative applications in environmental safety monitoring, healthcare, as well as emerging fields such as food safety assurance and smart agriculture. It emphasizes the significant advantages of TENG-based self-powered gas sensor systems in promoting environmental sustainability, achieving efficient sensing at room temperature, and driving technological innovations in wearable devices. It also objectively analyzes the technical challenges, including issues related to performance enhancement, theoretical refinement, and application expansion, and provides targeted strategies and future research directions aimed at paving the way for continuous progress and widespread applications in the field of self-powered gas sensors.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Wiley‐VCH GmbH.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Dongzhi</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9238-4176</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Control Science and Engineering, China University of Petroleum (East China), Qingdao, 266580, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Lina</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Control Science and Engineering, China University of Petroleum (East China), Qingdao, 266580, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wu</LastName><ForeName>Yan</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Control Science and Engineering, China University of Petroleum (East China), Qingdao, 266580, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Chunqing</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Control Science and Engineering, China University of Petroleum (East China), Qingdao, 266580, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Hao</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Control Science and Engineering, China University of Petroleum (East China), Qingdao, 266580, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>52475580</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>tsqn202211077</GrantID><Agency>Special Foundation of the Taishan Scholar Project</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>ZR2023ME118</GrantID><Agency>Shandong Provincial Natural Science Foundation</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>23-2-1-219-zyyd-jch</GrantID><Agency>Natural Science Foundation of Qingdao City</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>SKLCS-2024020</GrantID><Agency>Open Project of State Key Laboratory of Chemical Safety</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>24CX02014A</GrantID><Agency>Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Fund of State Key Laboratory of Deep Oil and Gas, China University of Petroleum</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Small</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101235338</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1613-6810</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">environmental monitoring</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">healthcare</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">self‐powered gas sensors</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">triboelectric nanogenerators</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>25</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>25</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39377767</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/smll.202406964</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>X. Huang, Z. Gong, Y. Lv, TrAC, Trends Anal. Chem. 2022, 153, 116644.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J.‐M. Jung, T. Lee, S. Jung, Y. F. Tsang, A. Bhatnagar, S. S. Lee, H. Song, W.‐K. Park, E. E. Kwon, Chem. Eng. J. 2022, 442, 136358.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Maeng, S. Kim, H. An, D. Jung, Sens. Actuators, B 2023, 394, 134420.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Zhao, Q. Wei, S. Wang, X. Ren, Sci. Total Environ. 2021, 799, 149437.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Bin, C. A. Rahman, S. Rogers, Z. Liu, IEEE Trans. Ind. Inf. 2021, 17, 8122.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Zhong, M. Hu, S. Deetman, B. Steubing, H. X. Lin, G. A. Hernandez, C. Harpprecht, C. Zhang, A. Tukker, P. Behrens, Nat. Commun. 2021, 12, 6126.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Parthiban, A. A. R. Gopal, P. Siwayanan, K. W. Chew, J. Hazard. Mater. 2021, 417, 126107.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. P. Ravikumar, E. E. Tullos, D. T. Allen, B. Cahill, S. P. Hamburg, D. Zimmerle, T. A. Fox, M. Caltagirone, L. Owens, R. Stout, A. J. Grimes, T. M. Fernandez, C. Jenks, R. Duren, A. Halff, M. D. Bazilian, S. Rucker, Nat. Geosci. 2023, 8, 1174.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Zhang, X. Yang, Y. Wang, Z. Yang, H. Zhao, Y. Ding, Sci. Total Environ. 2024, 947, 174523.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Zou, A. D. Ziegler, D. Chen, G. McNicol, P. Ciais, X. Jiang, C. Zheng, J. Wu, J. Wu, Z. Lin, X. He, L. E. Brown, J. Holden, Z. Zhang, S. J. Ramchunder, A. Chen, Z. Zeng, Nat. Geosci. 2022, 15, 627.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Song, W. Tang, Z. Chen, Z. a. Wan, C. L. J. Chan, C. Wang, W. Ye, Z. Fan, Small 2022, 18, 2203212.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Gu, A. Guenther, C. Faiola, Environ. Sci. Technol. 2021, 55, 12191.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. R. Mohammadzadeh, A. Hasani, K. Jaferzadeh, M. Fawzy, T. De Silva, A. Abnavi, R. Ahmadi, H. Ghanbari, A. Askar, F. Kabir, R. K. N. D. Rajapakse, M. M. Adachi, Adv. Sci. 2023, 10, 2205458.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Yuan, M. Bariya, H. M. Fahad, J. Wu, R. Han, N. Gupta, A. Javey, Adv. Mater. 2020, 32, 1908385.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Jung, J. Kim, S. Hong, H. Shin, Y. Jeong, W. Shin, D. Kwon, W. Y. Choi, J.‐H. Lee, Adv. Sci. 2023, 10, 2302506.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Q. Duan, W. Zhang, L. Li, B. Ying, T. Li, B. Chen, H.‐Y. Li, H. Liu, Chem. Eng. J. 2024, 479, 147748.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Lu, T. Ji, S. He, F. Ai, L. Yan, J. Hu, Adv. Funct. Mater. 2024, https://doi.org/10.1002/adfm.202309111.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Barandun, L. Gonzalez‐Macia, H. S. Lee, C. Dincer, F. Guder, ACS Sens. 2022, 7, 2804.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. M. Majhi, A. Mirzaei, H. W. Kim, S. S. Kim, T. W. Kim, Nano Energy 2021, 79, 105369.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Wang, Y. Cheng, S. Gopalan, F. Luo, K. Amreen, R. K. Singh, S. Goel, Z. Lin, R. Naidu, ACS Sens. 2023, 8, 1373.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Zhai, J. Ye, Y. Zhang, K. Zhang, E. Zhan, X. Zhang, Y. Yang, Chem. Eng. J. 2024, 484, 149286.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Si, Y. Xu, C. Shen, H. Jiang, M. Lei, X. Guo, S. Xie, S. Gao, S. Zhang, ACS Sens. 2024, 9, 674.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Lim, Y.‐M. Jo, J.‐W. Yoon, J.‐S. Kim, D.‐J. Lee, Y. K. Moon, J. W. Yoon, J.‐H. Kim, H. J. Choi, J.‐H. Lee, Small 2021, 17, 2100438.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Shauloff, A. Morag, K. Yaniv, S. Singh, R. Malishev, O. Paz‐Tal, L. Rokach, R. Jelinek, Nano‐Micro Lett. 2021, 13, 112.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M.‐X. Xu, P. Tang, Y.‐X. Wang, J.‐G. Liang, Y.‐F. Jiang, P.‐P. Yu, T. Qiang, Sens. Actuators, B 2024, 404, 135248.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. Ding, J. Yu, F. Tsow, L. R. Jaishi, B. S. Lamsal, R. Kittelson, S. Ahmed, P. Kharel, Y. Zhou, X. Xian, NPJ 2D Mater. Appl. 2024, 8, 18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Sousa, C. M. Simon, ACS Sens. 2020, 5, 4035.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Liu, Y.‐N. Zhang, S. Liu, B. Shi, L. Wang, Y. Zhao, Sens. Actuators, B 2024, 399, 134814.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Zhao, Y. Liu, B. Han, M. Wang, Q. Wang, Y.‐N. Zhang, Coord. Chem. Rev. 2023, 493, 215297.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Hoang Si, H. Nguyen Hai, T. Dao Duc, N. Nguyen Hoang, H. Nguyen Thanh, H. Nguyen Thi, H. Tran Vinh, Nano Energy 2021, 87, 106165.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Niu, J. Zeng, X. Liu, J. Li, Q. Wang, H. Li, N. F. de Rooij, Y. Wang, G. Zhou, Adv. Sci. 2021, 8, 2100472.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Wei, Z. Li, K. Murugappan, Z. Li, F. Zhang, A. G. Saraswathyvilasam, M. Lysevych, H. H. Tan, C. Jagadish, A. Tricoli, L. Fu, Adv. Mater. 2023, 35, 202207199.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Liu, L. Wang, L. Zhao, X. Yu, Y. Zi, Infomat 2020, 2, 318.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Zhao, M. Xu, M. Shu, J. An, W. Ding, X. Liu, S. Wang, C. Zhao, H. Yu, H. Wang, C. Wang, X. Fu, X. Pan, G. Xie, Z. L. Wang, Nat. Commun. 2022, 13, 3325.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. J. Zhao, H. L. Wang, Z. L. Wang, J. Wang, Small 2024, 20, 2310023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Jaiswal, S. Singh, B. Sharma, S. Choudhary, R. Kumar, S. K. Sharma, Small 2024, 20, 2403699.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Hao, Y. Liu, C. Cai, Y. Shao, X. Meng, G. Du, B. Luo, Z. Wei, J. Wang, S. Wang, S. Nie, Nano Energy 2024, 122, 109335.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Meng, H. Li, L. Zhao, J. Lu, C. Pan, Y. Zhang, Z. Li, Nano Lett. 2020, 20, 4968.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Cai, J. Mo, Y. Lu, N. Zhang, Z. Wu, S. Wang, S. Nie, Nano Energy 2021, 83, 105833.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C.‐Y. Chang, Y.‐H. Cheng, C.‐Y. Ho, J. Mater. Chem. A 2022, 10, 22373.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Y. Chang, H. Meng, C. S. Li, J. M. Gao, S. Q. Chen, Q. Hu, H. Li, L. Feng, Adv. Mater. Technol. 2020, 5, 1901087.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. He, M. Zhang, T. Zhao, H. Zeng, L. Xing, X. Xue, Sci. China Mater. 2019, 62, 1433.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Zhang, Y. Yang, Y. Su, J. Chen, C. Hu, Z. Wu, Y. Liu, C. P. Wong, Y. Bando, Z. L. Wang, Nano Energy 2013, 2, 693.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Wang, D. Zhang, H. Zhang, Z. Wang, J. Wang, G. Xi, Sens. Actuators, B 2024, 417, 136101.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Zhang, D. Zhang, Y. Yang, L. Zhou, Y. Liu, W. Liu, Y. Sun, Y. Guo, Y. Ji, Nano Energy 2024, 128, 109978.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Joo, K. Y. Lee, J.‐H. Lee, Energy Technol. 2022, 10, 2200113.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Lu, X. Guo, X. Liao, Y. Liu, C. Cai, X. Meng, Z. Wei, G. Du, Y. Shao, S. Nie, Z. Wang, Nano Energy 2024, 126, 109672.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. Deng, Y. Zhou, X. Zhao, S. Zhang, Y. Zou, J. Xu, M.‐H. Yeh, H. Guo, J. Chen, ACS Nano 2020, 14, 9050.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. L. Sun, S. Q. Lin, W. Tang, X. Chen, Z. L. Wang, ACS Nano 2020, 14, 17354.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Hu, M. Iwamoto, X. Chen, Nano‐Micro Lett. 2024, 16, 7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. L. Wang, Adv. Energy Mater. 2020, 10, 2000137.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Zhang, D. Wang, Z. Xu, X. Zhang, Y. Yang, J. Guo, B. Zhang, W. Zhao, Coord. Chem. Rev. 2021, 427, 213597.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Zhou, M. Shen, X. Cui, Y. Shao, L. Li, Y. Zhang, Nano Energy 2021, 84, 105887.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Wen, J. Chen, M.‐H. Yeh, H. Guo, Z. Li, X. Fan, T. Zhang, L. Zhu, Z. L. Wang, Nano Energy 2015, 16, 38.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Chen, W. Li, C. Chen, H. Tai, G. Xie, Y. Jiang, Y. Su, Appl. Phys. Lett. 2021, 119, 230504.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Liu, Y. Jiang, G. Xie, Z. Duan, Z. Yuan, Y. Zhang, Q. Zhao, Z. Cao, F. Dong, H. Tai, Chem. Eng. J. 2023, 471, 144795.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Wang, D. Zhang, X. Chen, H. Zhang, M. Tang, J. Wang, Nano Energy 2022, 102, 107711.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Yang, J. Liu, C. Hu, W. Zhang, J. Jiao, N. Cui, L. Gu, J. Mater. Chem. A 2023, 11, 21937.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H.‐Z. Ma, C. Luo, J.‐N. Zhao, Y. Shao, Y.‐H. Zhang, X. Liu, S. Li, B. Yin, K. Zhang, K. Ke, L. Zhou, M.‐B. Yang, ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces 2023, 15, 37563.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. Zhang, Q. Liu, S. Chao, R. Liu, X. Cui, Y. Sun, H. Ouyang, Z. Li, ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces 2021, 13, 42966.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Mudgal, M. Tiwari, D. Bharti, Nano Energy 2024, 123, 109388.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. S. Sadanandan, Z. Saadi, C. Murphy, I. Grikalaite, M. F. Craciun, A. I. S. Neves, Nano Energy 2023, 116, 108797.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Q. Zhou, J.‐N. Kim, K.‐W. Han, S.‐W. Oh, S. Umrao, E. J. Chae, I.‐K. Oh, Nano Energy 2019, 59, 120.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Liu, G. Yuan, Y. Zhang, L. Xie, Q. Shen, H. Lei, Z. Wen, X. Sun, Adv. Mater. Technol. 2021, 6, 2100310.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. He, Y. Gui, Y. Wang, J. Yang, Nano Energy 2023, 107, 108132.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Oh, J.‐K. Kim, J. Gao, S. Jung, W. Kim, G. Park, J. Park, J. M. Baik, C. Yang, ACS Nano 2024, 18, 12146.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Veeralingam, S. Badhulika, Sens. Actuators, B 2023, 380, 133346.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Rodrigues, A. Gomes, A. Ghosh, A. Pereira, J. Ventura, Nano Energy 2019, 62, 660.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Zhang, Y. Wang, Y. Yang, Adv. Funct. Mater. 2019, 29, 1806435.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeeshan, B. K. Panigrahi, R. Ahmed, M. U. Mehmood, J. C. Park, Y. Kim, W. Chun, Appl. Energy 2021, 285, 116385.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Wang, Z. Wen, H. Guo, C. Wu, X. He, L. Lin, X. Cao, Z. L. Wang, ACS Nano 2016, 10, 11369.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Pang, Y. Cao, M. Derakhshani, Y. Fang, Z. L. Wang, C. Cao, Matter 2021, 4, 116.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Gui, W. Zhang, S. Liu, Y. Li, J. Yang, G. Jin, H. Huang, P. Yang, M. Gao, Nano Energy 2024, 124, 109498.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Su, M. Yao, G. Xie, H. Pan, H. Yuan, M. Yang, H. Tai, X. Du, Y. Jiang, Appl. Phys. Lett. 2019, 115, 073504.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. S. Barbosa, P. H. Suman, J. J. Kim, H. L. Tuller, M. O. Orlandi, Sens. Actuators, B 2019, 301, 127055.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Wang, Y. Li, C. Wang, Y. Li, J. Bai, Y. Liu, L. Zhou, F. Liu, K. Shimanoe, G. Lu, Sens. Actuators, B 2021, 339, 129888.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. He, W. Liu, T. Lv, M. Ma, Z. Liu, A. Vasiliev, X. Li, Sens. Actuators, B 2021, 329, 129275.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Ma, J. Xu, J. Mater. Chem. A 2023, 11, 23742.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Yang, S. Lv, Y. Zhang, J. Wang, L. Jiang, X. Jia, C. Wang, X. Yan, P. Sun, Y. Duan, F. Liu, G. Lu, Nano‐Micro Lett. 2022, 14, 56.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. S. Niavol, M. Budde, A. Papadogianni, M. Heilmann, H. M. Moghaddam, C. M. Aldao, G. Ligorio, E. J. W. List‐Kratochvil, J. M. J. Lopes, N. Barsan, O. Bierwagen, F. Schipani, Sens. Actuators, B 2020, 325, 128797.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Jiang, Y. Zhang, Q. Shen, Q. Zhu, X. Ge, Y. Liu, Z. Wen, X. Sun, Nano Energy 2021, 89, 106453.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Liu, X. Liu, Z. Yuan, Y. Jiang, Y. Su, J. Ma, H. Tai, Sens. Actuators, B 2019, 295, 86.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. G. Stanford, K. Yang, Y. Chyan, C. Kittrell, J. M. Tour, ACS Nano 2019, 13, 3474.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Wang, J. Chang, H. Zhi, C. Li, L. Feng, Sens. Actuators, B 2022, 356, 131292.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Sardana, H. Kaur, B. Arora, D. K. Aswal, A. Mahajan, ACS Sens. 2022, 7, 312.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Hang, T. Jiang, G. Liu, T. Xiao, L. Xu, W. Li, F. Xi, C. Zhang, Z. L. Wang, Adv. Funct. Mater. 2019, 29, 1807241.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Wen, X. Pan, H. Fu, B. Xu, Matter 2023, 6, 2153.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. Du, S. Zhuo, J. Wang, Z. Luo, Y. Chen, Z. Wang, N. Lin, H. Cheng, G. Shen, S. Tao, Environ. Pollut. 2021, 291, 118138.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. D. Weller, S. P. Hamburg, J. C. von Fischer, Environ. Sci. Technol. 2021, 55, 806.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Liu, H. Cao, C. Hu, M. Wu, S. Zhang, J. He, C. Jiang, Npj Clim. Atmos. Sci. 2023, 6, 6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Guo, L. Yan, Y. He, H. Li, S. S. Lam, W. Peng, C. Sonne, Environ. Pollut. 2023, 322, 121130.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Holton, Y. Guo, H. Luo, P. Dahlen, K. Gorder, E. Dettenmaier, P. C. Johnson, Environ. Sci. Technol. 2018, 52, 10637.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Kristensen, D. M. Lunderberg, Y. Liu, P. K. Misztal, Y. Tian, C. Arata, W. W. Nazaroff, A. H. Goldstein, Environ. Sci. Technol. 2023, 57, 3260.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Chang, C. Zhu, Z. Wang, Y. Wang, C. Li, Q. Hu, R. Xu, T. Du, M. Xu, L. Feng, Nano Energy 2022, 98, 107271.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. E. Wyer, D. B. Kelleghan, V. Blanes‐Vidal, G. Schauberger, T. P. Curran, J. Environ. Manag. 2022, 323, 116285.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Wang, D. Zhang, M. Tang, H. Zhang, T. Sun, C. Yang, R. Mao, K. Li, J. Wang, Nano Energy 2022, 100, 107509.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. He, C. Dong, Y. Fu, W. Han, T. Zhao, L. Xing, X. Xue, Sens. Actuators, B 2018, 267, 392.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. Li, L. Lu, X. Fu, C. Zhang, K. Loos, Y. Pei, ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces 2022, 14, 51018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Chen, S. Gong, T. Gong, X. Yang, H. Guo, Adv. Energy Mater. 2023, 13, 2203689.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Zhu, Z. Sun, J. Xu, R. D. Walczak, J. A. Dziuban, C. Lee, Sci. Bull. 2021, 66, 1176.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Z. Berna, A. R. O. John, Clin. Chem. 2022, 68, 43.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Gao, J. Wang, Y. Feng, N. Cao, H. Li, N. F. de Rooij, A. Umar, P. J. French, Y. Wang, G. Zhou, Small 2022, 18, 2103259.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Jiang, Q. Li, S. Lv, B. Wang, S. Pan, P. Sun, J. Zheng, F. Liu, G. Lu, ACS Sens. 2024, 9, 1575.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Liu, T. Fei, X. Guan, H. Zhao, T. Zhang, Sens. Actuators, B 2021, 334, 129625.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Vasilescu, B. Hrinczenko, G. M. Swain, S. F. Peteu, Biosens. Bioelectron. 2021, 182, 113193.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Zhu, M. Yao, Environ. Sci. Technol. 2024, 58, 4522.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Wang, G. Xie, H. Tai, Y. Su, B. Yang, Q. Zhang, X. Du, Y. Jiang, Nano Energy 2018, 51, 231.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Wang, Y. Jiang, H. Tai, B. Liu, Z. Duan, Z. Yuan, H. Pan, G. Xie, X. Du, Y. Su, Nano Energy 2019, 63, 103829.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Su, S. Chen, B. Liu, H. Lu, X. Luo, C. Chen, W. Li, Y. Long, H. Tai, G. Xie, Y. Jiang, Mater. Today Phys. 2023, 30, 100951.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Mohamadbeigi, L. Shooshtari, S. Fardindoost, M. Vafaiee, A. I. Zad, R. Mohammadpour, Sci. Rep. 2024, 14, 1562.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Tian, F. Wang, Y. Ding, R. Lei, Y. Shi, X. Tao, S. Li, Y. Yang, X. Chen, Research 2021, 2021, 8564780.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. H. Guo, Y. C. Jiao, H. L. Wang, C. Zhang, F. Liang, J. L. Liu, H. D. Yu, C. M. Li, G. Zhu, Z. L. Wang, Adv. Funct. Mater. 2019, 29, 1808974.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Du, C. Jiao, C. Li, Y. Tao, J. Lu, Y. Cheng, X. Xia, M. Tan, H. Wang, Nano Energy 2023, 116, 108803.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. Meng, Y. Yang, R. Zhang, Z. Wu, X. Xiao, Chem. Eng. J. 2023, 473, 145465.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Dai, X. Li, C. Jiang, J. Ping, Y. Ying, Infomat 2023, 5, 12391.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Jiang, X. Li, Y. Ying, J. Ping, Nano Energy 2020, 74, 104863.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. T. Rahman, S. M. S. Rana, P. Maharjan, M. Salauddin, T. Bhatta, H. Cho, C. Park, J. Y. Park, Nano Energy 2021, 85, 105974.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O. A. Odeyemi, O. O. Alegbeleye, M. Strateva, D. Stratev, Compr. Rev. Food Sci. Food Saf. 2020, 19, 311.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. B. Snyder, N. Martin, M. Wiedmann, Nat. Rev. Microbiol. 2024, 22, 528.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Joshi, G. Pransu, C. Adam Conte‐Junior, Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 2023, 63, 10536.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Shao, S. Chen, Z. Ning, X. Xu, H. Wang, Food Chem. 2023, 410, 135457.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Zhao, J. P. Ndayambaje, X. Liu, X. Xia, Food Rev. Int. 2022, 38, 225.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Jayababu, D. Kim, Nano Energy 2021, 89, 106355.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Gil, Nature Food 2022, 3, 978.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. He, F. E. Loffler, Nature 2024, 630, 310.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S.‐Y. Pan, K.‐H. He, K.‐T. Lin, C. Fan, C.‐T. Chang, Npj Clim. Atmos. Sci. 2022, 5, 43.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Wang, Y. Gui, S. He, J. Yang, Compos. Part A Appl. Sci. Manuf. 2023, 173, 107692.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. H. Hsu, X. Zhang, K. Xu, Y. Wang, Q. Wang, G. Luo, M. Xing, W. Zhong, Chem. Eng. J. 2021, 422, 129499.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Jing, B. Xu, Y. Yang, Nano Energy 2021, 84, 105867.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. M. Rani, S. M. Ghoreishian, R. Umapathi, V. Vivekananthan, Y. S. Huh, Nano Energy 2024, 128, 109899.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Ye, Q. Xu, J. Ren, S. Ling, Adv. Fiber Mater. 2020, 2, 24.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Zhang, H. Olin, Ecomat 2020, 2, 12062.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Qi, A. C. Wang, W. Yang, M. Zhang, C. Hou, Q. Zhang, Y. Li, H. Wang, Nano Energy 2020, 67, 104206.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Pu, J.‐W. Zha, C.‐L. Zhao, S.‐B. Gong, J.‐F. Gao, R. K. Y. Li, Chem. Eng. J. 2020, 398, 125526.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Bai, H. Guo, C. Feng, J. Wang, B. Liu, Z. Xie, F. Guo, D. Chen, R. Zhang, Y. Zheng, Sens. Actuators, B 2022, 368, 132131.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Han, X. Li, Y. Liu, X. Li, C. Shao, J. Ri, J. Ma, Y. Liu, J. Hazard. Mater. 2021, 403, 124093.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Kumar, X. Liu, J. Zhang, M. Kumar, Nano‐Micro Lett. 2020, 12, 164.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Su, J. Wang, B. Wang, T. Yang, B. Yang, G. Xie, Y. Zhou, S. Zhang, H. Tai, Z. Cai, G. Chen, Y. Jiang, L.‐Q. Chen, J. Chen, ACS Nano 2020, 14, 6067.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Zhang, Y. Liu, B. Zhang, O. Yang, W. Yuan, L. He, X. Wei, J. Wang, Z. L. Wang, ACS Energy Lett. 2021, 6, 1490.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Yong, J. Wang, L. Yang, H. Wang, H. Luo, R. Liao, Z. L. Wang, Adv. Energy Mater. 2021, 11, 2101194.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Ouyang, Y. Huang, H. Ye, Z. Zhang, H. Xue, Nano Energy 2022, 102, 107749.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>I. Goncalves, C. Rodrigues, J. Ventura, Adv. Energy Mater. 2024, 14, 2302627.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Zheng, T. Liu, J. Wu, T. Xu, X. Wang, X. Han, H. Cui, X. Xu, C. Pan, X. Li, Adv. Mater. 2022, 34, 2202238.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Wang, D. Zhang, M. Tang, H. Zhang, T. Sun, C. Yang, R. Mao, K. Li, J. Wang, Nano Energy 2022, 100, 107509.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Zhang, M. Hummelgard, J. Ortegren, M. Song, M. Olsen, H. Andersson, N. Blomquist, H. Olin, Nano Energy 2022, 94, 106959.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Zhang, Y. Yang, Z. Xu, D. Wang, C. Du, J. Mater. Chem. A 2022, 10, 10935.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Pal, A. Ganguly, P.‐H. Wei, S. R. Barman, C.‐C. Chang, Z.‐H. Lin, Adv. Sci. 2024, 11, 2307266.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Xiao, H. Wu, N. Li, X. Tan, H. Deng, X. Zhang, J. Tang, Y. Li, Adv. Sci. 2023, 10, 2207230.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Zhou, D. Liu, S. Li, Z. Zhao, C. Zhang, X. Yin, L. Liu, S. Cui, L. Wang Zhong, J. Wang, Adv. Energy Mater. 2020, 10, 2000965.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Liu, S. Qu, Z. Suo, W. Yang, Natl. Sci. Rev. 2021, 8, nwaa254.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Zhang, S. Xu, R. Wang, Y. Che, C. Han, W. Feng, C. Wang, W. Zhao, J. Mater. Sci. Technol. 2023, 162, 157.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Liu, Z. Hu, Y. Zhang, H.‐Y. Li, N. Gao, Z. Tian, L. Zhou, B. Zhang, J. Tang, J. Zhang, F. Yi, H. Liu, Nano‐Micro Lett. 2020, 12, 59.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. A. Mirabella, C. M. Aldao, ACS Sens. 2024, 9, 1938.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Yuan, Z. Guo, F. Meng, Adv. Mater. Technol. 2023, 8, 2300494.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>