<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39373938</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2168-4804</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>07</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Therapeutic innovation &amp; regulatory science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Ther Innov Regul Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Pharmacometrics-Enhanced Bayesian Borrowing for Pediatric Extrapolation - A Case Study of the DINAMO Trial.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s43441-024-00707-5</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Bayesian borrowing analyses have an important role in the design and analysis of pediatric trials. This paper describes use of a prespecified Pharmacometrics Enhanced Bayesian Borrowing (PEBB) analysis that was conducted to overcome an expectation for reduced statistical power in the pediatric DINAMO trial due to a greater than expected variability in the primary endpoint. The DINAMO trial assessed the efficacy and safety of an empagliflozin dosing regimen versus placebo and linagliptin versus placebo on glycemic control (change in HbA1c over 26 weeks) in young people with type 2 diabetes (T2D). Previously fitted pharmacokinetic and exposure-response models for empagliflozin and linagliptin based on available historical data in adult and pediatric patients with T2D were used to simulate participant data and derive the informative component of a Bayesian robust mixture prior distribution. External experts and representatives from the U.S. Food and Drug Administration provided recommendations to determine the effective sample size of the prior and the weight of the informative prior component. Separate exposure response-based Bayesian borrowing analyses for empagliflozin and linagliptin showed posterior mean and 95% credible intervals that were consistent with the trial results. Sensitivity analyses with a full range of alternative weights were also performed. The use of PEBB in this analysis combined advantages of mechanistic modeling of pharmacometric differences between adults and young people with T2D, with advantages of partial extrapolation through Bayesian dynamic borrowing. Our findings suggest that the described PEBB approach is a promising option to optimize the power for future pediatric trials.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sailer</LastName><ForeName>Martin Oliver</ForeName><Initials>MO</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Global Biostatistics &amp; Data Sciences, Boehringer Ingelheim Pharma GmbH &amp; Co. KG, Birkendorfer Strasse 65, 88397, Biberach, Germany. martin_oliver.sailer@boehringer-ingelheim.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Neubacher</LastName><ForeName>Dietmar</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Global Biostatistics &amp; Data Sciences, Boehringer Ingelheim Pharma GmbH &amp; Co. KG, Birkendorfer Strasse 65, 88397, Biberach, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Johnston</LastName><ForeName>Curtis</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Metrum Research Group, Tariffville, CT, 06081, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rogers</LastName><ForeName>James</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Metrum Research Group, Tariffville, CT, 06081, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wiens</LastName><ForeName>Matthew</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Metrum Research Group, Tariffville, CT, 06081, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pérez-Pitarch</LastName><ForeName>Alejandro</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Boehringer Ingelheim Pharma GmbH &amp; Co. KG, Ingelheim, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Regeneron Pharmaceuticals Inc, Tarrytown, NY, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tartakovsky</LastName><ForeName>Igor</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Boehringer Ingelheim Pharma GmbH &amp; Co. KG, Ingelheim, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Marquard</LastName><ForeName>Jan</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Boehringer Ingelheim Pharmaceuticals Inc, Ridgefield, CT, 06877, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Laffel</LastName><ForeName>Lori M</ForeName><Initials>LM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Joslin Diabetes Center, Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Ther Innov Regul Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101597411</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-4790</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bayesian dynamic borrowing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Empagliflozin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Linagliptin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Modeling &amp; simulation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pediatric extrapolation</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>57</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>57</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>14</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39373938</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s43441-024-00707-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s43441-024-00707-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>American Diabetes Association Professional Practice Committee. 9. Pharmacologic approaches to glycemic treatment: standards of Care in Diabetes—2024. Diabetes Care. 2024;47(Supplement 1):S158–78.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/dc24-S009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah AS, Zeitler PS, Wong J, et al. ISPAD Clinical Practice Consensus guidelines 2022: type 2 diabetes in children and adolescents. Pediatr Diabetes. 2022;23(7):872–902.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/pedi.13409</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laffel LM, Danne T, Klingensmith GJ, et al. Efficacy and safety of the SGLT2 inhibitor empagliflozin versus placebo and the DPP-4 inhibitor linagliptin versus placebo in young people with type 2 diabetes (DINAMO): a multicentre, randomised, double-blind, parallel group, phase 3 trial. Lancet Diabetes Endocrinol. 2023;11(3):169–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2213-8587(22)00387-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edwards D, Best N, Crawford J, et al. Using bayesian dynamic borrowing to maximize the use of existing data: a case-study. Ther Innov Regul Sci. 2024;58(1):1–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s43441-023-00585-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berry DA. Bayesian clinical trials. Nat Rev Drug Discov. 2006;5(1):27–36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nrd1927</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kotalik A, Vock DM, Donny EC, et al. Dynamic borrowing in the presence of treatment effect heterogeneity. Biostatistics. 2021;22(4):789–804.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/biostatistics/kxz066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>US Food and Drug Administration. BLA 125370/s-064 and BLA 761043/s-007 Multidisciplinary review and evaluation of Benlysta<sup>®</sup> (belimumab) for intravenous infusion in children 5 to 17 years of age with SLE. 2018. www.fda.gov/media/127912/download Accessed May 14, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Medicines Agency. Reflection paper on the use of extrapolation in the development of medicines for paediatrics, 17. October 2018. https://www.ema.europa.eu/en/documents/scientific-guideline/adopted-reflection-paper-use-extrapolation-development-medicines-paediatrics-revision-1_en.pdf Accessed May 14, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>US Food and Drug Administration. Guidance for Industry. Interacting with the FDA on complex innovative trial designs for drugs and biological products. 2020. https://www.fda.gov/media/130897/download . Accessed May 14, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richeldi L, Azuma A, Cottin V, et al. Trial of a preferential phosphodiesterase 4B inhibitor for idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis. N Engl J Med. 2022;386(23):2178–87.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2201737</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Travis J, Rothmann M, Thomson A. Perspectives on informative bayesian methods in pediatrics. J Biopharm Stat. 2023;33(6):830–43.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10543406.2023.2170405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sebastien B, Cheung SYA, Corriol-Rohou S, et al. Use of pharmacodynamic modeling for bayesian information borrowing in pediatric clinical trials. J Biopharm Stat. 2023;33(6):726–36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10543406.2022.2149772</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maher TM, Brown KK, Cunningham S, et al. Estimating the effect of nintedanib on forced vital capacity in children and adolescents with fibrosing interstitial lung disease using a bayesian dynamic borrowing approach. Pediatr Pulmonol. 2024;59(4):1038–46.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ppul.26882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fayette L, Sailer MO, Perez-Pitarch A. Pharmacometrics enhanced bayesian borrowing approach to improve clinical trial efficiency: case of empagliflozin in type 2 diabetes. CPT Pharmacometrics Syst Pharmacol. 2023;12(10):1386–97.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/psp4.13035</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laffel LMB, Tamborlane WV, Yver A, et al. Pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic profile of the sodium-glucose co-transporter-2 inhibitor empagliflozin in young people with type 2 diabetes: a randomized trial. Diabet Med. 2018;35(8):1096–104.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/dme.13629</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boehringer Ingelheim. Finding a safe and effective dose of linagliptin in pediatric patients with type 2 diabetes. Trial no. 1218.56. https://www.mystudywindow.com/trial/completed/192739/1218-0056 Accessed May 14, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baron KT, Macha S, Broedl UC, et al. Population pharmacokinetics and exposure-response (efficacy and safety/tolerability) of empagliflozin in patients with type 2 diabetes. Diabetes Ther. 2016;7(3):455–71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13300-016-0174-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ridderstråle M, Andersen KR, Zeller C, et al. Comparison of empagliflozin and glimepiride as add-on to metformin in patients with type 2 diabetes: a 104-week randomised, active-controlled, double-blind, phase 3 trial. Lancet Diabetes Endocrinol. 2014;2(9):691–700.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2213-8587(14)70120-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boehringer Ingelheim. A 16 week study on efficacy and safety of two doses of empagliflozin (BI 10773) (once daily versus twice daily) in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus and preexisting metformin therapy. Trial no. 1276.10. https://www.mystudywindow.com/trial/completed/192775/1276-0010 . Accessed May 14, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hadjadj S, Rosenstock J, Meinicke T, et al. Initial combination of empagliflozin and metformin in patients with type 2 diabetes. Diabetes Care. 2016;39(10):1718–28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/dc16-0522</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu T, Ghafoori P, Gobburu JV. Allometry is a reasonable choice in pediatric drug development. J Clin Pharmacol. 2017;57(4):469–75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jcph.831</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Retlich S, Duval V, Graefe-Mody U, et al. Impact of target-mediated drug disposition on Linagliptin pharmacokinetics and DPP-4 inhibition in type 2 diabetic patients. J Clin Pharmacol. 2010;50(8):873–85.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0091270009356444</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Graefe-Mody U, Retlich S, Friedrich C. Clinical pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of linagliptin. Clin Pharmacokinet. 2012;51(7):411–27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2165/11630900-000000000-00000</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Retlich S, Duval V, Graefe-Mody U, et al. Population pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of linagliptin in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus. Clin Pharmacokinet. 2015;54(7):737–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40262-014-0232-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boehringer Ingelheim. Safety, tolerability, pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of BI 1356 BS in patients with type 2 diabetes. Trial no. 1218.2. https://www.mystudywindow.com/trial/completed/192913/1218-0002 Accessed May 14, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boehringer Ingelheim. Safety, tolerability, pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of BI 1356 BS as tablet in patients with type 2 diabetes. Trial no. 1218.3. https://www.mystudywindow.com/trial/completed/192915/1218-0003 Accessed May 14, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boehringer Ingelheim. Efficacy and safety of 3 doses of BI1356 (linagliptin) in type 2 diabetes patients. Trial no. 1218.5. https://www.mystudywindow.com/trial/completed/192565/1218-0005 Accessed May 14, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boehringer Ingelheim. Efficacy and safety of BI 1356 BS (linagliptin) in combination with metformin in patients with type 2 diabetes. Trial no. 1218.6. https://www.mystudywindow.com/trial/completed/192561/1218-0006 Accessed May 14, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Del Prato S, Barnett AH, Huisman H, et al. Effect of linagliptin monotherapy on glycaemic control and markers of β-cell function in patients with inadequately controlled type 2 diabetes: a randomized controlled trial. Diabetes Obes Metab. 2011;13(3):258–67.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1463-1326.2010.01350.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gallwitz B, Rosenstock J, Rauch T, et al. 2-year efficacy and safety of linagliptin compared with glimepiride in patients with type 2 diabetes inadequately controlled on metformin: a randomised, double-blind, non-inferiority trial. Lancet. 2012;380(9840):475–83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(12)60691-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yki-Järvinen H, Rosenstock J, Durán-Garcia S, et al. Effects of adding linagliptin to basal insulin regimen for inadequately controlled type 2 diabetes: a ≥ 52-week randomized, double-blind study. Diabetes Care. 2013;36(12):3875–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/dc12-2718</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beal SL, Sheiner LB, Boeckmann AJ. NONMEM Users Guide: Part I-VII: Icon Development Solutions, Ellicott City, Maryland, USA.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bergstrand M, Hooker AC, Wallin JE, et al. Prediction-corrected visual predictive checks for diagnosing nonlinear mixed-effects models. AAPS J. 2011;13(2):143–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1208/s12248-011-9255-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Comets E, Brendel K, Mentre F. Computing normalised prediction distribution errors to evaluate nonlinear mixed-effect models: the npde add-on package for R. Comput Methods Programs Biomed. 2008;90(2):154–66.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmpb.2007.12.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tamborlane WV, Laffel LM, Weill J, et al. Randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled dose-finding study of the dipeptidyl peptidase-4 inhibitor linagliptin in pediatric patients with type 2 diabetes. Pediatr Diabetes. 2018;19(4):640–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/pedi.12616</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmidli H, Gsteiger S, Roychoudhury S, et al. Robust meta-analytic-predictive priors in clinical trials with historical control information. Biometrics. 2014;70(4):1023–32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/biom.12242</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weber K, Hemmings R, Koch A. How to use prior knowledge and still give new data a chance? Pharm Stat. 2018;17(4):329–41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/pst.1862</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neuenschwander B, Weber S, Schmidli H, et al. Predictively consistent prior effective sample sizes. Biometrics. 2020;76(2):578–87.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/biom.13252</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kopp-Schneider A, Calderazzo S, Wiesenfarth M. Power gains by using external information in clinical trials are typically not possible when requiring strict type I error control. Biom J. 2020;62:361–74.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/bimj.201800395</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Best N, Price RG, Pouliquen IJ, et al. Assessing efficacy in important subgroups in confirmatory trials: an example using bayesian dynamic borrowing. Pharm Stat. 2021;20(3):551–62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/pst.2093</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mager DE, Krzyzanski W. Quasi-equilibrium pharmacokinetic model for drugs exhibiting target-mediated drug disposition. Pharm Res. 2005;22(10):1589–96.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11095-005-6650-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gibiansky L, Gibiansky E, Kakkar T, et al. Approximations of the target-mediated drug disposition model and identifiability of model parameters. J Pharmacokinet Pharmacodyn. 2008;35(5):573–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10928-008-9102-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bauer RJ. NONMEM tutorial part II: estimation methods and advanced examples. CPT Pharmacometrics Syst Pharmacol. 2019;8(8):538–56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/psp4.12422</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>