<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39373744</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1436-5073</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>191</Volume><Issue>11</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>07</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Mikrochimica acta</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Mikrochim Acta</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Flexible SERS chips for rapid on-site detection of tricyclazole pesticide in agricultural products.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>652</StartPage><MedlinePgn>652</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s00604-024-06682-w</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>A flexible, ultrasensitive, and practical SERS chip is presented based on a paper/f-TiO<sub>2</sub>/Ag structure. The chip enhances the self-assembly of Ag nanoparticles on a cellulose fiber matrix, facilitated by smart functionalized TiO<sub>2</sub> nanomaterials (f-TiO<sub>2</sub>). This design enables superior detection of the hazardous pesticide tricyclazole (TCZ) on crops using an advanced, simple, and efficient analytical method. Despite its straightforward fabrication process via a solvent immersion method, the intrinsic smart surface properties of the TiO<sub>2</sub> bridging material - both hydrophilic and hydrophobic - enable the uniform and dense self-assembly of hydrophilic Ag nanoparticles (NPs) on the cellulose fiber paper substrate. This innovative design provides superior sensing efficiency for TCZ molecules with a detection limit reaching 2.1 × 10<sup>-9</sup> M, a remarkable improvement compared to Paper/Ag substrates lacking f-TiO<sub>2</sub> nanomaterials, which register at 10<sup>-5</sup> M. This flexible SERS substrate also exhibits very high reliability as indicated by its excellent reproducibility and repeatability with relative standard deviations (RSD) of only 5.93% and 4.73%, respectively. Characterized by flexibility and a water-attractive yet non-soluble surface, the flexible Paper/f-TiO<sub>2</sub>/Ag chips offer the convenience of direct immersion into the analytical sample, facilitating seamless target molecule collection while circumventing interference signals. Termed the "dip and dry" technique, its advantages in field analysis are indisputable, boasting in situ deployment, simplicity, and high efficiency, while minimizing interference signals to negligible levels. Through the application of this advanced technique, we have successfully detected TCZ in two high-value crops, ST25 rice and dragon fruit, achieving excellent recovery values ranging from 90 to 128%. This underscores its immense potential in ensuring food quality and safety. As a proof of concept, flexible Paper/f-TiO<sub>2</sub>/Ag SERS chips, with a simple fabrication process, advanced analytical technique, and superior sensing efficiency, bring SERS one step closer to field applications beyond the laboratory.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer-Verlag GmbH Austria, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Pham</LastName><ForeName>Anh-Tuan</ForeName><Initials>AT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Materials Science and Engineering, Phenikaa University, Hanoi, 12116, Vietnam.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Biotechnology, Chemistry and Environmental Engineering, Phenikaa University, Hanoi, 12116, Vietnam.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Bui</LastName><ForeName>Hanh Nhung</ForeName><Initials>HN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Materials Science and Engineering, Phenikaa University, Hanoi, 12116, Vietnam.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Thanh</LastName><ForeName>Nguyen Trung</ForeName><Initials>NT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Materials Science and Engineering, Phenikaa University, Hanoi, 12116, Vietnam.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bach</LastName><ForeName>Ta Ngoc</ForeName><Initials>TN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Materials Science (IMS), Vietnam Academy of Science and Technology, 18 Hoang Quoc Viet, Hanoi, 10000, Vietnam.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Mai</LastName><ForeName>Quan-Doan</ForeName><Initials>QD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Phenikaa University Nano Institute (PHENA), Phenikaa University, Hanoi, 12116, Vietnam. doan.maiquan@phenikaa-uni.edu.vn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Le</LastName><ForeName>Anh-Tuan</ForeName><Initials>AT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Phenikaa University Nano Institute (PHENA), Phenikaa University, Hanoi, 12116, Vietnam. tuan.leanh@phenikaa-uni.edu.vn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Materials Science and Engineering, Phenikaa University, Hanoi, 12116, Vietnam. tuan.leanh@phenikaa-uni.edu.vn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Austria</Country><MedlineTA>Mikrochim Acta</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7808782</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0026-3672</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>3M4G523W1G</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D012834">Silver</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>15FIX9V2JP</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="C009495">titanium dioxide</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>D1JT611TNE</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D014025">Titanium</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>R7U3MEU7VR</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="C041191">tricyclazole</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D013844">Thiazoles</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D010575">Pesticides</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012834" MajorTopicYN="Y">Silver</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013059" MajorTopicYN="Y">Spectrum Analysis, Raman</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D053768" MajorTopicYN="Y">Metal Nanoparticles</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D057230" MajorTopicYN="Y">Limit of Detection</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014025" MajorTopicYN="Y">Titanium</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010209" MajorTopicYN="Y">Paper</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013844" MajorTopicYN="Y">Thiazoles</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010575" MajorTopicYN="N">Pesticides</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018556" MajorTopicYN="N">Crops, Agricultural</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015203" MajorTopicYN="N">Reproducibility of Results</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Dragon fruit</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Flexible SERS chips</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Paper/f-TiO2/Ag</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ST25 rice</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Tricyclazole</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>58</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>57</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39373744</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00604-024-06682-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s00604-024-06682-w</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Han XX, Rodriguez RS, Haynes CL, Ozaki Y, Zhao B (2021) Surface-enhanced Raman spectroscopy. Nat Rev Methods Primers 1:87</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s43586-021-00083-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nie S, Emory SR (1997) Probing single molecules and single nanoparticles by surface-enhanced Raman scattering. Science 275:1102–1106</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.275.5303.1102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma B, Frontiera RR, Henry A-I, Ringe E, Van Duyne RP (2012) SERS: Materials, applications, and the future. Mater Today 15:16–25</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1369-7021(12)70017-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng S, Baillargeat D, Ho H-P, Yong K-T (2014) Nanomaterials enhanced surface plasmon resonance for biological and chemical sensing applications. Chem Soc Rev 43:3426–3452</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/c3cs60479a</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Langer J, Jimenez de Aberasturi D, Aizpurua J, Alvarez-Puebla RA, Auguié B, Baumberg JJ, Bazan GC, Bell SE, Boisen A, Brolo AG, Choo J (2019) Present and future of surface-enhanced Raman scattering. ACS Nano 14:28–117</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsnano.9b04224</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee S, Dang H, Moon J-I, Kim K, Joung Y, Park S, Yu Q, J Chen, Lu M, Chen L (2024) SERS-based microdevices for use as in vitro diagnostic biosensors. Chem Soc Rev 53:5394-5427</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu C, Xu D, Dong X, Huang Q (2022) A review: research progress of SERS-based sensors for agricultural applications. Trends Food Sci Technol 128:90–101</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2022.07.012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li C-Y, Tian Z-Q (2024) Sixty years of electrochemical optical spectroscopy: a retrospective. Chem Soc Rev 53:3579–3605</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding S-Y, You E-M, Tian Z-Q, Moskovits M (2017) Electromagnetic theories of surface-enhanced Raman spectroscopy. Chem Soc Rev 46:4042–4076</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C7CS00238F</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miao X, Yan L, Wu Y, Liu PQ (2021) High-sensitivity nanophotonic sensors with passive trapping of analyte molecules in hot spots. Light: Sci Appl 10:5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41377-020-00449-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mao P, Liu C, Favraud G, Chen Q, Han M, Fratalocchi A, Zhang S (2018) Broadband single molecule SERS detection designed by warped optical spaces. Nat Commun 9:5428</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-07869-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng S, Dos Santos MC, Carvalho BR, Lv R, Li Q, Fujisawa K, Elías AL, Lei Y, Perea-López N, Endo M, Pan M (2016) Ultrasensitive molecular sensor using N-doped graphene through enhanced Raman scattering. Sci Adv 2:e1600322</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/sciadv.1600322</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tao L, Chen K, Chen Z, Cong C, Qiu C, Chen J, Wang X, Chen H, Yu T, Xie W, Deng S, Xu J-B (2018) 1T′ transition metal telluride atomic layers for plasmon-free SERS at femtomolar levels. J Am Chem Soc 140:8696–8704</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/jacs.8b02972</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu K, Zhou R, Takei K, Hong M (2019) Toward flexible surface‐enhanced Raman scattering (SERS) sensors for point‐of‐care diagnostics. Adv Sci 6:1900925</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/advs.201900925</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pena-Pereira F, Duarte RM, Duarte AC (2012) Immobilization strategies and analytical applications for metallic and metal-oxide nanomaterials on surfaces. TrAC, Trends Anal Chem 40:90–105</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.trac.2012.07.015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pristinski D, Tan S, Erol M, Du H, Sukhishvili S (2006) In situ SERS study of Rhodamine 6G adsorbed on individually immobilized Ag nanoparticles. J Raman Spectrosc 37:762–770</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jrs.1496</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doan MQ, Anh NH, Quang NX, Dinh NX, Tri DQ, Huy TQ, Le A-T (2022) Ultrasensitive detection of methylene blue using an electrochemically synthesized SERS sensor based on gold and silver nanoparticles: roles of composition and purity on sensing performance and reliability. J Electron Mater 51:150–162</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11664-021-09228-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lai H, Zhang H, Li G, Hu Y (2021) Bimetallic AgNPs@ dopamine modified-halloysite nanotubes-AuNPs for adenine determination using surface-enhanced Raman scattering. Microchim Acta 188:1–11</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00604-021-04778-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lai H, Shang W, Yun Y, Chen D, Wu L, Xu F (2019) Uniform arrangement of gold nanoparticles on magnetic core particles with a metal-organic framework shell as a substrate for sensitive and reproducible SERS based assays: Application to the quantitation of Malachite Green and thiram. Microchim Acta 186:1–9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00604-019-3257-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Z, Huang X, Lu G (2020) Recent developments of flexible and transparent SERS substrates. J Mater Chem C 8:3956–3969</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D0TC00002G</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie L, Zeng H, Zhu J, Zhang Z, Sun H-B, Xia W, Du Y (2022) State of the art in flexible SERS sensors toward label-free and onsite detection: from design to applications. Nano Res 15:4374–4394</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12274-021-4017-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang D, Pu H, Huang L, Sun D-W (2021) Advances in flexible surface-enhanced Raman scattering (SERS) substrates for nondestructive food detection: Fundamentals and recent applications. Trends Food Sci Technol 109:690–701</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2021.01.058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mai QD, Nguyen HA, Dinh NX, Thuy NTT, Tran QH, Thanh PC, Pham A-T, Le A-T (2023) Versatile and high performance in-paper flexible SERS chips for simple and in-situ detection of methylene blue in river water and thiram on apple skin. Talanta 253:124114</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.talanta.2022.124114</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang C, Yi P, Peng L, Lai X, Chen J, Huang M, Ni J (2017) Continuous fabrication of nanostructure arrays for flexible surface enhanced Raman scattering substrate. Sci Rep 7:39814</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/srep39814</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou X, Li H, Yu G, Chen Y, Wang Y, Zeng Z, Chi L (2021) A highly-efficient, stable, and flexible Kapton tape-based SERS chip. Mater Chem Front 5:6471–6475</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D1QM00547B</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu X, Liu J, Wang J, Wang T, Jiang Y, Hu J, Liu Z, Chen X, Yu J (2020) Bioinspired, microstructured silk fibroin adhesives for flexible skin sensors. ACS Appl Mater Interfaces 12:5601–5609</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsami.9b21197</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mogera U, Guo H, Namkoong M, Rahman MS, Nguyen T, Tian L (2022) Wearable plasmonic paper–based microfluidics for continuous sweat analysis. Sci Adv 8:eabn1736</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/sciadv.abn1736</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu B, Pu H, Sun D-W (2021) Multifunctional cellulose based substrates for SERS smart sensing: Principles, applications and emerging trends for food safety detection. Trends Food Sci Technol 110:304–320</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2021.02.005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boobis AR, Ossendorp BC, Banasiak U, Hamey PY, Sebestyen I, Moretto A (2008) Cumulative risk assessment of pesticide residues in food. Toxicol Lett 180:137–150</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.toxlet.2008.06.004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fortuni B, Fujita Y, Ricci M, Inose T, Aubert R, Lu G, Hutchison JA, Hofkens J, Latterini L, Uji-i H (2017) A novel method for in situ synthesis of SERS-active gold nanostars on polydimethylsiloxane film. Chem Commun 53:5121–5124</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C7CC01776F</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar S, Goel P, Singh JP (2017) Flexible and robust SERS active substrates for conformal rapid detection of pesticide residues from fruits. Sens Actuators, B Chem 241:577–583</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.snb.2016.10.106</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang K, Sun D-W, Pu H, Wei Q, Huang L (2019) Stable, flexible, and high-performance SERS chip enabled by a ternary film-packaged plasmonic nanoparticle array. ACS Appl Mater Interfaces 11:29177–29186</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsami.9b09746</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mai QD, Nguyen HA, Huyen NN, Thanh PC, Thuc DQ, Son NA, Pham A-T, Le A-T (2023) Large-scale green electrochemical synthesis of smart titanium dioxide nanomaterials: controlled morphology and rotatable surface ligands via tuning electrolyte structures. J Electron Mater 52:5884–5900</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11664-023-10550-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wiley JH, Atalla RH (1987) Band assignments in the Raman spectra of celluloses. Carbohyd Res 160:113–129</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0008-6215(87)80306-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mai QD, Nguyen HA, Phung TLH, Xuan Dinh N, Tran QH, Doan TQ, Pham AT, Le A-T (2022) Photoinduced enhanced raman spectroscopy for the ultrasensitive detection of a low-cross-section chemical, urea, using silver-titanium dioxide nanostructures. ACS Appl Nano Mater 5:15518–15530</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsanm.2c03524</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deshmukh SP, Mullani SB, Koli VB, Patil SM, Kasabe PJ, Dandge PB, Pawar SA, Delekar SD (2018) Ag nanoparticles connected to the surface of TiO2 electrostatically for antibacterial photoinactivation studies. Photochem Photobiol 94:1249–1262</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/php.12983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mai Q-D, Thanh DC, Anh NT, Van Manh T, Bach TN, Nguyen H-A, Pham A-T, Le A-T (2024) Smart 3D Ag-decorated TiO2 Nanostructure: An advanced synergistic SERS substrate for trace detection of analytes with diverse natures. Sens Actuators, B Chem 410:135651</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.snb.2024.135651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li C, Chen Y, Huang L, Zhang Y, Cao N, Guo X, Yao C, Li X, Duan L, Pang S (2023) Potential toxicity and dietary risk of tricyclazole to Chinese mitten crab (Eriocheir sinensis) in the rice-crab co-culture model. Environ Pollut 316:120514</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2022.120514</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. F. S. Authority (2015) EFSA J 13:4032</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang H, Fang D, Li Q, Cao P, Geng J, Sui T, Wang X, Iqbal J, Du Y (2012) Determination of tricyclazole content in paddy rice by surface enhanced Raman spectroscopy. J Food Sci 77:T105–T109</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1750-3841.2012.02665.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hussain N, Pu H, Sun D-W (2021) Core size optimized silver coated gold nanoparticles for rapid screening of tricyclazole and thiram residues in pear extracts using SERS. Food Chem 350:129025</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2021.129025</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Q-Q, Du Y-P, Xu Y, Wang X, Ma S-Q, Geng J-P, Cao P, Sui T (2013) Rapid and sensitive detection of pesticides by surface-enhanced Raman spectroscopy technique based on glycidyl methacrylate–ethylene dimethacrylate (GMA–EDMA) porous material. Chin Chem Lett 24:332–334</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cclet.2013.02.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osawa M, Ikeda M (1991) Surface-enhanced infrared absorption of p-nitrobenzoic acid deposited on silver island films: contributions of electromagnetic and chemical mechanisms. J Phys Chem 95:9914–9919</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/j100177a056</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Willets KA (2014) Super-resolution imaging of SERS hot spots. Chem Soc Rev 43:3854–3864</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/C3CS60334B</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang S, Wu C, Wang Y, Yang X, Yuan R, Chai Y (2021) Ag/TiO<sub>2</sub> nanocomposites as a novel SERS substrate for construction of sensitive biosensor. Sens Actuators, B Chem 339:129843</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.snb.2021.129843</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>