<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39309043</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">0098-7921</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>50</Volume><Issue>Suppl 1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Jul</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Population and development review</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Popul Dev Rev</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>COVID-19 and Contraceptive Use in Two African Countries: Examining Conflicting Pressures on Women.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>395</StartPage><EndPage>419</EndPage><MedlinePgn>395-419</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/padr.12606</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Women in Africa may have experienced conflicting pressures during the COVID-19 pandemic. While the unpredictable nature of the pandemic was prompting some women to delay pregnancies, the pandemic was potentially limiting access to reproductive health services due to supply shortages, fears of virus exposure, and mobility restrictions. In this study, we used longitudinal data from Kenya and Burkina Faso and applied a multilevel perspective to better understand the factors contributing to change or persistence in contraceptive use during the early months of the pandemic. We found a marginal increase in contraceptive uptake in the early days of the pandemic. Multilevel logistic regression results revealed that interpersonal trust and accurate knowledge of COVID-19 precautions were associated with a greater likelihood of initiating contraception. These factors appeared to have provided women with confidence to navigate the complicated COVID-19 landscape. At the same time, we observed a decrease in contraceptive use in regions with high COVID-19 cases, suggesting the virus was limiting access to contraception in some contexts. These findings highlighted the need for public health officials to ensure that women have the necessary knowledge and ability to safely access contraception during public health crises, when overall demand for contraception may be increasing.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yu</LastName><ForeName>Jiao</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Social Research and Data Innovation, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN, 55455, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Grace</LastName><ForeName>Kathryn</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Geography, Environment &amp; Society, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN, 55455, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Boyle</LastName><ForeName>Elizabeth Heger</ForeName><Initials>EH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sociology Department, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN, 55455, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mikal</LastName><ForeName>Jude P</ForeName><Initials>JP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pharmaceutical Care and Health Systems, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN, 55455, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gunther</LastName><ForeName>Matthew</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>NORC at the University of Chicago, Chicago, IL, 60603, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kristiansen</LastName><ForeName>Devon</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Social Research and Data Innovation, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN, 55455, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>P2C HD041023</GrantID><Acronym>HD</Acronym><Agency>NICHD NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>R01 HD069471</GrantID><Acronym>HD</Acronym><Agency>NICHD NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>R01 HD099182</GrantID><Acronym>HD</Acronym><Agency>NICHD NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Popul Dev Rev</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7613927</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0098-7921</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement>• Conflict of interest disclosure The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>31</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39309043</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="mid">NIHMS1950547</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11412435</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/padr.12606</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Abi-Rached Joelle M., and Diwan Ishac. 2021. “Governing Life and the Economy: Exploring the Role of Trust in the Covid-19 Pandemic.” Erasmus Journal for Philosophy and Economics 14 (1): 71–88. 10.23941/ejpe.v14i1.580.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.23941/ejpe.v14i1.580</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adelekan Tsholofelo, Mihretu Belete, Mapanga Witness, Nqeketo Sithembile, Chauke Lawrence, Dwane Zuko, and -Baldwin Ragaven Laurel. 2020. “Early Effects of the COVID-19 Pandemic on Family Planning Utilisation and Termination of Pregnancy Services in Gauteng, South Africa : March–April 2020.” Wits Journal of Clinical Medicine 2 (2): 145–52. 10.18772/26180197.2020.v2n2a7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18772/26180197.2020.v2n2a7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alo Oluwafemi David, Daini Babajide Oluseyi, Omisile Olugbenga K., Ubah Ebere Joy, Adelusi Odunayo Esther, and Idoko-Asuelimhen Ochanya. 2020. “Factors Influencing the Use of Modern Contraceptive in Nigeria: A Multilevel Logistic Analysis Using Linked Data from Performance Monitoring and Accountability 2020.” BMC Women’s Health 20 (1): 191. 10.1186/s12905-020-01059-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12905-020-01059-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7650288</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32883259</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bain Luchuo Engelbert, Amu Hubert, and Tarkang Elvis Enowbeyang. 2021. “Barriers and Motivators of Contraceptive Use among Young People in Sub-Saharan Africa: A Systematic Review of Qualitative Studies.” PLOS ONE 16 (6): e0252745. 10.1371/journal.pone.0252745.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0252745</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8177623</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34086806</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bietsch Kristin, Williamson Jessica, and Reeves Margaret. 2020. “Family Planning During and After the West African Ebola Crisis.” Studies in Family Planning 51 (1): 71–86. 10.1111/sifp.12110.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/sifp.12110</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32180246</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bougma Moussa, and Rossier Clémentine. 2022. “The Role of Family Networks and Social Capital on Women’s Fertility Intentions in Ouagadougou, Burkina Faso.” Journal of Demographic Economics 88 (2): 237–55. 10.1017/dem.2021.18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/dem.2021.18</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brooks Nina, Grace Kathryn, Kristiansen Devon, Shukla Shraddhanand, and Brown Molly E.. 2023. “Investigating the Relationship between Growing Season Quality and Childbearing Goals.” Global Environmental Change 80 (May): 102677. 10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2023.102677.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2023.102677</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10209476</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37250477</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caruso Salvatore, Rapisarda Agnese Maria Chiara, and Minona Patrizia. 2020. “Sexual Activity and Contraceptive Use during Social Distancing and Self-Isolation in the COVID-19 Pandemic.” The European Journal of Contraception &amp; Reproductive Health Care 25 (6): 445–48.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33044107</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chuang Ying-Chih, Huang Ya-Li, Tseng Kuo-Chien, Yen Chia-Hsin, and Yang Lin-hui. 2015. “Social Capital and Health-Protective Behavior Intentions in an Influenza Pandemic.” Edited by Tang Julian W.. PLOS ONE 10 (4): e0122970. 10.1371/journal.pone.0122970.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0122970</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4398366</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25874625</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Connor Jade, Madhavan Sarina, Mokashi Mugdha, Amanuel Hanna, Johnson Natasha R., Pace Lydia E., and Bartz Deborah. 2020. “Health Risks and Outcomes That Disproportionately Affect Women during the Covid-19 Pandemic: A Review.” Social Science &amp; Medicine 266: 113364.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7487147</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32950924</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Culha Mehmet Gokhan, Demir Omer, Sahin Orhan, and Altunrende Fatih. 2021. “Sexual Attitudes of Healthcare Professionals during the COVID-19 Outbreak.” International Journal of Impotence Research 33 (1): 102–9. 10.1038/s41443-020-00381-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41443-020-00381-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7728577</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33311709</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ehsan Annahita, Klaas Hannah Sophie, Bastianen Alexander, and Spini Dario. 2019. “Social Capital and Health: A Systematic Review of Systematic Reviews.” SSM - Population Health 8 (August): 100425. 10.1016/j.ssmph.2019.100425.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ssmph.2019.100425</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6580321</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31431915</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elgar Frank J., Stefaniak Anna, and Wohl Michael J.A.. 2020. “The Trouble with Trust: Time-Series Analysis of Social Capital, Income Inequality, and COVID-19 Deaths in 84 Countries.” Social Science &amp; Medicine 263 (October): 113365. 10.1016/j.socscimed.2020.113365.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2020.113365</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7492158</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32981770</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fitzpatrick Anne, Beg Sabrin, Derksen Laura, Karing Anne, Kerwin Jason, Lucas Adrienne M., Reynoso Natalia Ordaz, and Squires Munir. 2021. “Health Knowledge and Non-Pharmaceutical Interventions during the Covid-19 Pandemic in Africa.” Journal of Economic Behavior &amp; Organization 190 (October): 33–53. 10.1016/j.jebo.2021.06.045.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jebo.2021.06.045</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8285265</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34305214</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grace Kathryn. 2017. “Considering Climate in Studies of Fertility and Reproductive Health in Poor Countries.” Nature Climate Change 7 (7): 479–85. 10.1038/nclimate3318.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nclimate3318</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6009846</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29937922</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassan Rahma, Bhatia Amiya, Zinke-Allmang Anja, Shipow Amy, Ogolla Concilia, Gorur Krittika, and Cislaghi Beniamino. 2022. “Navigating Family Planning Access during Covid-19: A Qualitative Study of Young Women’s Access to Information, Support and Health Services in Peri-Urban Nairobi.” SSM - Qualitative Research in Health 2 (December): 100031. 10.1016/j.ssmqr.2021.100031.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ssmqr.2021.100031</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8665648</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34927130</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Helliwell JF, and Putnam RD. 2004. “The Social Context of Well-Being.” Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences 359 (1449): 1435–46. 10.1098/rstb.2004.1522.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1098/rstb.2004.1522</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1693420</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15347534</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hossain Md., Hossain Md, Ainul Sigma, Bhuiyan Md, Hossain Sharif, Rob Ubaidur, and Bajracharya Ashish. 2020. “Trends in Family Planning Services in Bangladesh before, during and after COVID-19 Lockdowns: Evidence from National Routine Service Data.” Reproductive Health, October. 10.31899/rh14.1038.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.31899/rh14.1038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hussein Julia. 2020. “COVID-19: What Implications for Sexual and Reproductive Health and Rights Globally?” Sexual and Reproductive Health Matters 28 (1): 1746065. 10.1080/26410397.2020.1746065.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/26410397.2020.1746065</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7887905</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32191167</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jennings Will, Stoker Gerry, Bunting Hannah, Viktor Orri Valgarðsson Jennifer Gaskell, Devine Daniel, McKay Lawrence, and Mills Melinda C.. 2021. “Lack of Trust, Conspiracy Beliefs, and Social Media Use Predict COVID-19 Vaccine Hesitancy.” Vaccines 9 (6): 593. 10.3390/vaccines9060593.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/vaccines9060593</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8226842</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34204971</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karp Celia, Wood Shannon N., Guiella Georges, Gichangi Peter, Bell Suzanne O., Anglewicz Philip, Larson Elizabeth, Zimmerman Linnea, and Moreau Caroline. 2021. “Contraceptive Dynamics during COVID-19 in Sub-Saharan Africa: Longitudinal Evidence from Burkina Faso and Kenya.” BMJ Sexual &amp; Reproductive Health 47 (4): 252–60. 10.1136/bmjsrh-2020-200944.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjsrh-2020-200944</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7886665</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33579717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kiconco Arthur, Kabanda Richard, Tugume Abdulaziz, Mwagale Ritah, Kananathan Abirahmi, Bakyaita Tabley, Nabukenya Immaculate, Lwenge Mathias, and Kalenzi Prisca U.. 2022. “Coronavirus Disease Pandemic Response in Uganda: Government Trust, Risk Perception and Willingness to Adhere to Public Health Measures among Social Media Users.” Article manuscript. Uganda Martyrs University: ResearchGate. http://ir.umu.ac.ug/handle/20.500.12280/3001.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kristiansen Devon, Boyle Elizabeth Heger, Grace Kathryn, and Sobek Matthew. 2023. “IPUMS PMA:” Minneapolis, MN: IPUMS: Minneapolis, MN: IPUMS. 10.18128/D081.V8.0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18128/D081.V8.0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar Manisha, Daly Maura, De Plecker Eva, Jamet Christine, McRae Melissa, Markham Aine, and Batista Carolina. 2020. “Now Is the Time: A Call for Increased Access to Contraception and Safe Abortion Care during the COVID-19 Pandemic.” BMJ Global Health 5 (7): e003175.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7371486</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32690484</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin Tracy Kuo, Law Rachel, Beaman Jessica, and Foster Diana Greene. 2021. “The Impact of the COVID-19 Pandemic on Economic Security and Pregnancy Intentions among People at Risk of Pregnancy.” Contraception 103 (6): 380–85. 10.1016/j.contraception.2021.02.001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.contraception.2021.02.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9748659</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33587906</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lindberg Laura D., VandeVusse Alicia, Mueller Jennifer, and Kirstein Marielle. 2020. “Early Impacts of the COVID-19 Pandemic: Findings from the 2020 Guttmacher Survey of Reproductive Health Experiences,” June. 10.1363/2020.31482.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1363/2020.31482</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lone Shabir Ahmad, and Ahmad Aijaz. 2020. “COVID-19 Pandemic – an African Perspective.” Emerging Microbes &amp; Infections 9 (1): 1300–1308. 10.1080/22221751.2020.1775132.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/22221751.2020.1775132</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7473237</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32458760</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luppi Francesca, Arpino Bruno, and Rosina Alessandro. 2020. “The Impact of COVID-19 on Fertility Plans in Italy, Germany, France, Spain, and the United Kingdom.” Demographic Research 43: 1399–1412.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Majid Umair, Wasim Aghna, Bakshi Simran, and Truong Judy. 2020. “Knowledge, (Mis-)Conceptions, Risk Perception, and Behavior Change during Pandemics: A Scoping Review of 149 Studies.” Public Understanding of Science 29 (8): 777–99. 10.1177/0963662520963365.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0963662520963365</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33073717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marteleto Letícia J., Kumar Sneha, Dondero Molly, and Sereno Luiz Gustavo Fernandes. 2023. “Fertility Intentions During the Covid-19 Pandemic: An Analysis of Individual- and Municipality-Level Determinants.” Population and Development Review. 10.1111/padr.12561.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/padr.12561</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11323109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39145111</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marteleto Letícia J., Weitzman Abigail, Coutinho Raquel Zanatta, and Alves Sandra Valongueiro. 2017. “Women’s Reproductive Intentions and Behaviors during the Zika Epidemic in Brazil.” Population and Development Review 43 (2): 199–227. 10.1111/padr.12074.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/padr.12074</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6663086</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31359895</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mickler Alexandria K., Carrasco Maria A., Raney Laura, Sharma Vinit, May Ados V., and Greaney Jennie. 2021. “Applications of the High Impact Practices in Family Planning during COVID-19.” Sexual and Reproductive Health Matters 29 (1): 9–17. 10.1080/26410397.2021.1881210.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/26410397.2021.1881210</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8009015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33599196</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murayama H, Fujiwara Y, and Kawachi I. 2012. “Social Capital and Health: A Review of Prospective Multilevel Studies.” Journal of Epidemiology 22 (3): 179–87. 10.2188/jea.JE20110128.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2188/jea.JE20110128</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3798618</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22447212</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Musalia John. 2016. “Social Capital and Health in Kenya: A Multilevel Analysis.” Social Science &amp; Medicine 167 (October): 11–19. 10.1016/j.socscimed.2016.08.043.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2016.08.043</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27597538</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nobles Jenna, Frankenberg Elizabeth, and Thomas Duncan. 2015. “The Effects of Mortality on Fertility: Population Dynamics After a Natural Disaster.” Demography 52 (1): 15–38. 10.1007/s13524-014-0362-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13524-014-0362-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4411230</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25585644</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ochako Rhoune, Mbondo Mwende, Aloo Stephen, Kaimenyi Susan, Thompson Rachel, Temmerman Marleen, and Kays Megan. 2015. “Barriers to Modern Contraceptive Methods Uptake among Young Women in Kenya: A Qualitative Study.” BMC Public Health 15 (1): 118. 10.1186/s12889-015-1483-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12889-015-1483-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4336491</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25884675</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okereke Melody, Ukor Nelson Ashinedu, Ngaruiya Lilian Muthoni, Mwansa Chikwe, Alhaj Samar Mohammed, Ogunkola Isaac Olushola, Jaber Hadi Mohammed, Isa Mashkur Abdulhamid, Ekpenyong Aniekan, and Lucero-Prisno Don Eliseo. 2021. “COVID-19 Misinformation and Infodemic in Rural Africa.” The American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene 104 (2): 453–56. 10.4269/ajtmh.20-1488.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.20-1488</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7866344</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33382028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pillay Y, Pienaar S, Barron P, and Zondi T. 2021. “Impact of COVID-19 on Routine Primary Healthcare Services in South Africa.” South African Medical Journal 111 (8): 714–19. 10.7196/SAMJ.2021.v111i8.15786.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7196/SAMJ.2021.v111i8.15786</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35227349</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polis Chelsea B., Biddlecom Ann, Singh Susheela, Ushie Boniface Ayanbekongshie, Rosman Lori, and Saad Abdulmumin. 2022. “Impacts of COVID-19 on Contraceptive and Abortion Services in Low- and Middle-Income Countries: A Scoping Review.” Sexual and Reproductive Health Matters 30 (1): 2098557. 10.1080/26410397.2022.2098557.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/26410397.2022.2098557</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9351554</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35920612</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rietveld Cornelius A., van Kippersluis Hans, and Thurik A. Roy. 2015. “Self-Employment and Health: Barriers or Benefits?” Health Economics 24 (10): 1302–13. 10.1002/hec.3087.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/hec.3087</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4767688</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25048640</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Riley Taylor, Sully Elizabeth A., Ahmed Zara, and Biddlecom Ann. 2020. “Estimates of the Potential Impact of the COVID-19 Pandemic on Sexual and Reproductive Health in Low- and Middle-Income Countries.” International Perspectives on Sexual and Reproductive Health 46 (April): 73–76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32343244</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roberton Timothy, Carter Emily D, Chou Victoria B, Stegmuller Angela R, Jackson Bianca D, Tam Yvonne, Sawadogo-Lewis Talata, and Walker Neff. 2020. “Early Estimates of the Indirect Effects of the COVID-19 Pandemic on Maternal and Child Mortality in Low-Income and Middle-Income Countries: A Modelling Study.” The Lancet Global Health 8 (7): e901–8. 10.1016/S2214-109X(20)30229-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2214-109X(20)30229-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7217645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32405459</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Semaan Aline, Banke-Thomas Aduragbemi, Amongin Dinah, Babah Ochuwa, Dioubate Nafissatou, Kikula Amani, Nakubulwa Sarah, et al. 2022. “‘We Are Not Going to Shut down, Because We Cannot Postpone Pregnancy’: A Mixed-Methods Study of the Provision of Maternal Healthcare in Six Referral Maternity Wards in Four Sub-Saharan African Countries during the COVID-19 Pandemic.” BMJ Global Health 7 (2): e008063. 10.1136/bmjgh-2021-008063.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjgh-2021-008063</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8844957</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35144921</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Senderowicz Leigh, and Higgins Jenny. 2020. “Reproductive Autonomy Is Nonnegotiable, Even in the Time of COVID-19.” International Perspectives on Sexual and Reproductive Health 46: 147–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32790638</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shikuku Duncan N., Nyaoke Irene K., Nyaga Lucy N., and Ameh Charles A.. 2021. “Early Indirect Impact of COVID-19 Pandemic on Utilisation and Outcomes of Reproductive, Maternal, Newborn, Child and Adolescent Health Services in Kenya: A Cross-Sectional Study.” African Journal of Reproductive Health 25 (6): 76–87. 10.4314/ajrh.v25i6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4314/ajrh.v25i6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37585823</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sobotka Tomáš, Skirbekk Vegard, and Philipov Dimiter. 2011. “Economic Recession and Fertility in the Developed World.” Population and Development Review 37 (2): 267–306.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22066128</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tolu Lemi Belay, Hurisa Tesfaye, Abas Ferid, Daba Mekdes, Abebe Biruck, Nigatu Balkachew, and Prager Sarah. 2020. “Effect of COVID-19 Pandemic on Safe Abortion and Contraceptive Services and Mitigation Measures: A Case Study from a Tertiary Facility in Ethiopia.” Ethiopian Journal of Reproductive Health 12 (3): 6–6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trinitapoli Jenny, and Yeatman Sara. 2011. “Uncertainty and Fertility in a Generalized AIDS Epidemic.” American Sociological Review 76 (6): 935–54. 10.1177/0003122411427672.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0003122411427672</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3334314</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22536003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNECA. 2022. “COVID-19 for Africa: Lockdown Exit Strategies | United Nations Economic Commission for Africa.” 2022. https://www.uneca.org/covid-19-africa-lockdown-exit-strategies.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>VanBenschoten Hannah, Kuganantham Hamsadvani, Larsson Elin C., Endler Margit, Thorson Anna, Gemzell-Danielsson Kristina, Hanson Claudia, Ganatra Bela, Ali Moazzam, and Cleeve Amanda. 2022. “Impact of the COVID-19 Pandemic on Access to and Utilisation of Services for Sexual and Reproductive Health: A Scoping Review.” BMJ Global Health 7 (10): e009594. 10.1136/bmjgh-2022-009594.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjgh-2022-009594</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9539651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36202429</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wood Shannon N, Karp Celia, OlaOlorun Funmilola, Pierre Akilimali Z, Guiella Georges, Gichangi Peter, Zimmerman Linnea A, Anglewicz Philip, Larson Elizabeth, and Moreau Caroline. 2021. “Need for and Use of Contraception by Women before and during COVID-19 in Four Sub-Saharan African Geographies: Results from Population-Based National or Regional Cohort Surveys.” The Lancet Global Health 9 (6): e793–801. 10.1016/S2214-109X(21)00105-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2214-109X(21)00105-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8149322</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34019835</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ye Maoxin, and Lyu Zeyu. 2020. “Trust, Risk Perception, and COVID-19 Infections: Evidence from Multilevel Analyses of Combined Original Dataset in China.” Social Science &amp; Medicine 265: 113517.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7654228</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33218890</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu Jiao, Boyle Elizabeth Heger, Zhang Yaxuan, Grace Kathryn, and Sangli Gabriel. 2023. “Trust and COVID Precautionary Measures during the Early Days of the COVID-19 Pandemic: Evidence from Two African Countries.” SSM - Population Health 22 (June): 101397. 10.1016/j.ssmph.2023.101397.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ssmph.2023.101397</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10077808</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37038430</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Zhenmei, Xu Hongwei, Li Lydia W, Liu Jinyu, and Choi Seung-won Emily. 2021. “Social Relationships in Early Life and Episodic Memory in Mid- and Late Life.” The Journals of Gerontology: Series B 76 (10): 2121–30. 10.1093/geronb/gbaa179.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/geronb/gbaa179</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8599048</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33075811</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zidouemba Patrice Rélouendé, Kinda Somlanare Romuald, and Ouedraogo Idrissa Mohamed. 2020. “Could Covid-19 Worsen Food Insecurity in Burkina Faso?” The European Journal of Development Research 32 (5): 1379–1401. 10.1057/s41287-020-00324-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1057/s41287-020-00324-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7586363</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33132539</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zimmerman Linnea A., Bell Suzanne O., Li Qingfeng, Morzenti Antonia, Anglewicz Philip, PMA2020 Principal Investigators Group, and Tsui Amy O.. 2019. “Individual, Community and Service Environment Factors Associated with Modern Contraceptive Use in Five Sub-Saharan African Countries: A Multilevel, Multinomial Analysis Using Geographically Linked Data from PMA2020.” PLOS ONE 14 (6): e0218157. 10.1371/journal.pone.0218157.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0218157</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6586288</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31220114</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zimmerman Linnea A., Karp Celia, Thiongo Mary, Gichangi Peter, Guiella Georges, Gemmill Alison, Moreau Caroline, and Bell Suzanne O.. 2022. “Stability and Change in Fertility Intentions in Response to the COVID-19 Pandemic in Kenya.” PLOS Global Public Health 2 (3): e0000147. 10.1371/journal.pgph.0000147.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pgph.0000147</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10021581</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36962268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zinke-Allmang Anja, Bhatia Amiya, Gorur Krittika, Hassan Rahma, Shipow Amy, Ogolla Concilia, Keizer Kees, and Cislaghi Beniamino. 2023. “The Role of Partners, Parents and Friends in Shaping Young Women’s Reproductive Choices in Peri-Urban Nairobi: A Qualitative Study.” Reproductive Health 20 (1): 41. 10.1186/s12978-023-01581-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12978-023-01581-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9997433</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36894997</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>