<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39309994</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2277-9531</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of education and health promotion</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Educ Health Promot</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Clinical nurses' experiences about "breaking bad news" during the COVID-19 pandemic: A qualitative study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>247</StartPage><MedlinePgn>247</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">247</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4103/jehp.jehp_417_23</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Nurses have the most contact with COVID-19 patients and their families, while it is unclear how nurses react when they give bad news during pandemic disaster, particularly in the cultural and social context of Iran. So, our main purpose was to explore the experiences of clinical nurses about breaking bad news (BBN) in the context of the COVID-19 epidemic era.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIALS AND METHOD" NlmCategory="METHODS">The study was a qualitative content analysis approach. Data were collected by the purposive sampling method through in-depth interviews with 13 nurses in Isfahan University of Medical Sciences. The method of data analysis was conventional qualitative content analysis.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The participants of this study were 13 nurses. The work experience range was from 2 to 18 years, and in terms of education, one of them was Ph.D., eight had a bachelor's degree education, and four had a master's degree in nursing. Qualitative data of content analysis were obtained in four main categories such as nurses' avoidance of BBN, considering the patient's and family's beliefs in BBN, nurses' unpreparedness to deliver bad news during the pandemic crisis, and surrender of the patient and family members in the face of the COVID-19 bad news.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The results of the research showed that due to probability of occurrence of pandemic in the futureand also the nature of the nursing profession, so nurses should be familiar with the correct ways of BBN and existing protocols on crisis conditions and cultural and religious context of the society to provide a high quality of care for patients and their families.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: © 2024 Journal of Education and Health Promotion.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rafiei</LastName><ForeName>Malihe</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Master of Nursing, School of Nursing and Midwifery, Isfahan University of Medical Sciences, Isfahan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mohammadi</LastName><ForeName>Zakieh</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Master of Critical Care Nursing, School of Nursing and Midwifery, Isfahan University of Medical Sciences, Isfahan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mohamadirizi</LastName><ForeName>Shahla</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nursing and Midwifery Care Research Center, Isfahan University of Medical Sciences, Isfahan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>India</Country><MedlineTA>J Educ Health Promot</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101593794</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2277-9531</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bad news</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Iran</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">clinical</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">experiences</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nurse</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">qualitative</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>There are no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>29</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>56</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39309994</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11414847</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/jehp.jehp_417_23</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">JEHP-13-247</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Galehdar N, Kamran A, Toulabi T, Heydari H. Exploring nurses’ experiences of psychological distress during care of patients with COVID-19: A qualitative study. BMC Psychiatry. 2020;20:489.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7538040</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33023535</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soosaipillai G, Archer S, Ashrafian H, Darzi A. Breaking bad news training in the COVID-19 era and beyond. J Med Educ Curric Dev. 2020;7:2382120520938706. doi: 10.1177/2382120520938706.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7357050</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32699822</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arbabi M, Roozdar A, Taher M, Shirzad S, Arjmand M, Mohammadi MR, et al. How to break bad news: Physicians’ and nurses’ attitudes. Iran J Psychiatry. 2010;5:128–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3395928</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22952506</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Monden KR, Gentry L, Cox TR. Delivering bad news to patients. Proc (Bayl Univ Med Cent) 2016;29:101–2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4677873</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26722188</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sobczak K, Leoniuk K, Janaszczyk A. Delivering bad news: Patient’s perspective and opinions. Patient Prefer Adherence. 2018;12:2397–404.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6239094</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30519005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karim Z, Imanipour M, Bahrani N. Bad news in critical care and emeregency units and nurses’participation in the process of breaking bad news in affiliated hospitals of Tehran university of medical sciences. Nurs Midwifery J. 2015;13:377–85.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laranjeira C, Afonso C, Querido AI. Communicating bad news: Using role-play to teach nursing students. SAGE Open Nurs. 2021;7:23779608211044589.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8495521</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34632058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fontes CMB, Menezes DV de, Borgato MH, Luiz MR. Communicating bad news: An integrative review of the nursing literature. Rev Bras Enferm. 2017;70:1089–95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28977239</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agnese BL, Daniel ACQG, Pedrosa RBDS. Communicating bad news in the practice of nursing: An integrative review. Einstein (Sao Paulo) 2022;20:eRW6632.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9337845</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35894377</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadat Hoseini A, Alhani F, Khosro-panah A, Behjat Pour A. The concept analysis of health based on Islamic sources: Intellectual health. Int J Nurs Knowl. 2015;26:113–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25244669</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Graneheim UH, Lundman B. Qualitative content analysis in nursing research: concepts, procedures and measures to achieve trustworthiness. Nurse Educ Today. 2004;24:105–12. doi: 10.1016/j.nedt.2003.10.001. PMID: 14769454.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14769454</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polit DF, Beck CT. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins; 2013. Study Guide for Essentials of Nursing Research: Appraising Evidence for Nursing Practice.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polit DF, Beck CT. Philadelphia: Lippincott Williams and Wilkins; 2010. Essentials of Nursing Research, Methods, Appraisal and Utilization.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abbaszadeh A, Ehsani SR, Kaji MA, Dopolani FN, Nejati A, Mohammadnejad E. Nurses’ perspectives on breaking bad news to patients and their families: A qualitative content analysis. J Med Ethics Hist Med. 2014;7:18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4263382</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25512837</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jalali R, Jalali A, Jalilian M. Breaking bad news in medical services: A comprehensive systematic review. Heliyon. 2023:9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10070541</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37025874</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krieger T, Salm S, Dresen A, Cecon N. Cancer patients’ experiences and preferences when receiving bad news: A qualitative study. J Cancer Res Clin Oncol. 2022:1–12. doi: 10.1007/s00432-022-04311-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9398052</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35999331</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shahidi J. Not telling the truth: Circumstances leading to concealment of diagnosis and prognosis from cancer patients. Eur J Cancer Care. 2010;19:589–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20030693</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abazari P, Taleghani F, Hematti S, Malekian A, Fariborz M, Hakimian SMR, et al. Breaking bad news protocol for cancer disclosure: An Iranian version. J Med Ethics Hist Med. 2018;10:13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6164186</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30275940</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khalaf H, Almothafar B, Alhalabi N. Breaking bad news during COVID-19 time in surgical, emergency and medical specialties-what more we need to develop? Med Arch. 2022;76:131–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9233462</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35774038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>