<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39309750</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2666-5204</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>20</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Dec</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Resuscitation plus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Resusc Plus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Comparison of blended e-learning and face-to-face-only education for resuscitation training in German schools - A cluster randomized-controlled prospective study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>100767</StartPage><MedlinePgn>100767</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">100767</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.resplu.2024.100767</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND &amp; OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR) is the key for surviving cardiac arrest. Recent recommendations propose that CPR can - and should -be taught to schoolchildren. This e-learning-based study analyzes whether face-to-face CPR training can be partly substituted with e-learning by measuring CPR knowledge and self-efficacy in trainees.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">In this cluster randomized-controlled prospective, students attending grades 5 to 7 of a German secondary school volunteered to participate and were randomly assigned to one of two groups with different methods for CPR training each: a traditional instructor-led group (control) where students received face-to-face teaching by a BLS instructor (45 min), and an e-learning group (intervention) where schoolchildren were able to accomplish their theoretical CPR training using an e-learning module (15 min). CPR knowledge and self-efficacy were measured and compared before (t0) and after (t1) the training using questionnaires. Face-to-face CPR training (45 min) on manikins proceeded in both groups hereafter. The formal hypothesis was that e-learning would result in better CPR knowledge.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Overall, 375 students participated; 33 of which had to be excluded. 342 participants were included in statistical analysis (instructor-led group <i>n</i> = 109; e-learning group <i>n</i> = 233). The study was terminated early due to the Covid19 pandemic, and did not reach the required number of participants. Lacking statistical power, an analysis of the existing datasets failed to show superiority of e-learning vs. conventional training for CPR knowledge (<i>p</i> = 0.306). Both groups improved CPR knowledge (<i>p</i> &lt; 0.001) and self-efficacy (<i>p</i> &lt; 0.001) after CPR training and showed an equal, high level of satisfaction with their perceived training method (face-to-face: 4.1[4.0-4.2] vs. e-learning: 4.0[3.9-4.1]; <i>p</i> = 0.153; maximum 5 points).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This study failed to demonstrate superiority for e-learning but was terminated early and hence underpowered. Further research is necessary to prove the efficiency of e-learning tools for CPR.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wetsch</LastName><ForeName>Wolfgang A</ForeName><Initials>WA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Cologne, Faculty of Medicine, Albertus-Magnus-Platz 1, 50931 Cologne, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University Hospital of Cologne, Department of Anaesthesiology and Intensive Care Medicine, Kerpener Str. 62, 50937 Cologne, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Link</LastName><ForeName>Nikolas</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Cologne, Faculty of Medicine, Albertus-Magnus-Platz 1, 50931 Cologne, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rahe-Meyer</LastName><ForeName>Niels</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Franziskus Hospital Bielefeld, Department of Anaesthesiology and Intensive Care Medicine, Kiskerstraße 26, 33615 Bielefeld, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dumcke</LastName><ForeName>Rico</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bielefeld University, Faculty of Biology, Universitätsstrasse 25, 33615 Bielefeld, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Stock</LastName><ForeName>Jan M</ForeName><Initials>JM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>L2R GmbH, Cliev 4, 51515 Kuerten, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Böttiger</LastName><ForeName>Bernd W</ForeName><Initials>BW</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Cologne, Faculty of Medicine, Albertus-Magnus-Platz 1, 50931 Cologne, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University Hospital of Cologne, Department of Anaesthesiology and Intensive Care Medicine, Kerpener Str. 62, 50937 Cologne, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wingen</LastName><ForeName>Sabine</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University Hospital of Cologne, Department of Anaesthesiology and Intensive Care Medicine, Kerpener Str. 62, 50937 Cologne, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>FOM University of Applied Sciences, Agrippinawerft 4, 50678 Cologne, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>13</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Resusc Plus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101774410</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2666-5204</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Blended learning</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">KIDS SAVE LIVES</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Schoolchildren</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare the following financial interests/personal relationships which may be considered as potential competing interests: Wolfgang A. Wetsch, Nikolas Link, Niels Rahe-Meyer and Rico Dumcke have no conflicts of interest to declare regarding this manuscript. Jan Stock is Head of the L2R GmbH and Projekt Manager at the Hans Peter Esser GmbH. Bernd W. Böttiger is treasurer of the European Resuscitation Council (ERC), Founder of the ERC Research NET, Chairman of the German Resuscitation Council (GRC), Member of the „Advanced Life Support (ALS) Task Force of the International Liaison Committee on Resuscitation (ILCOR), Member of the Executive Committee of the German Interdisciplinary Association for Intensive Care and Emergency Medicine (DIVI), Founder of the “Deutsche Stiftung Wiederbelebung”, Federal Medical Advisor of the German Red Cross (DRK), Member of the Advisory Board of the “Deutsche Herzstiftung”, Co-Editor of “Resuscitation”, Editor of the Journal “Notfall + Rettungsmedizin”, Co-Editor of the Brazilian Journal of Anesthesiology. He received fees for lectures from the following companies: Forum für medizinische Fortbildung (FomF), Baxalta Deutschland GmbH, ZOLL Medical Deutschland GmbH, C.R. Bard GmbH, GS Elektromedizinische Geräte G. Stemple GmbH, Novartis Pharma GmbH, Philips GmbH Market DACH, Bioscience Valuation BSV GmbH, Becton Dickinson GmbH, Fundacja Polski Instytut Evidence Based Medicine. Sabine Wingen is executive personal assistant of the executive board of the German Resuscitation Council (GRC).</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>54</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39309750</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11415797</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.resplu.2024.100767</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2666-5204(24)00218-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Grasner J.T., Herlitz J., Tjelmeland I.B.M., et al. European Resuscitation Council Guidelines 2021: epidemiology of cardiac arrest in Europe. Resuscitation. 2021;161:61–79.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33773833</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J.J., Zhou Q., Huang Z.H., et al. Establishment of a prediction model for prehospital return of spontaneous circulation in out-of-hospital patients with cardiac arrest. World J Cardiol. 2023;15:508–517.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10600787</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37900904</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan S., Gan Y., Jiang N., et al. The global survival rate among adult out-of-hospital cardiac arrest patients who received cardiopulmonary resuscitation: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Crit Care. 2020;24:61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7036236</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32087741</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knapp J., Huber M., Grasner J.T., Bernhard M., Fischer M. Outcome differences between PARAMEDIC2 and the German Resuscitation Registry: a secondary analysis of a randomized controlled trial compared with registry data. Eur J Emerg Med. 2022;29:421–430.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9605191</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35791269</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berg K.M., Soar J., Andersen L.W., et al. Adult advanced life support: 2020 international consensus on cardiopulmonary resuscitation and emergency cardiovascular care science with treatment recommendations. Circulation. 2020;142:S92–S139.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33084390</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soar J., Berg K.M., Andersen L.W., et al. Adult advanced life support: 2020 international consensus on cardiopulmonary resuscitation and emergency cardiovascular care science with treatment recommendations. Resuscitation. 2020;156:A80–A119.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7576326</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33099419</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Panchal A.R., Bartos J.A., Cabanas J.G., et al. Part 3: adult basic and advanced life support: 2020 American heart association guidelines for cardiopulmonary resuscitation and emergency cardiovascular care. Circulation. 2020;142:S366–S468.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33081529</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soar J., Bottiger B.W., Carli P., et al. European resuscitation council guidelines 2021: adult advanced life support. Resuscitation. 2021;161:115–151.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33773825</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deakin C.D. The chain of survival: not all links are equal. Resuscitation. 2018;126:80–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29471008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grasner J.T., Wnent J., Herlitz J., et al. Survival after out-of-hospital cardiac arrest in Europe - Results of the EuReCa TWO study. Resuscitation. 2020;148:218–226.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32027980</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bottiger B.W., Lockey A., Aickin R., et al. “All citizens of the world can save a life” - The World Restart a Heart (WRAH) initiative starts in 2018. Resuscitation. 2018;128:188–190.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29679697</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fischer M., Wnent J., Gräsner J.T., et al. Jahresbericht des Deutschen Reanimationsregisters Außerklinische Reanimation im Notarzt- und Rettungsdienst 2022. Anasth Intensivmed. 2023;64:V161–V169.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bottiger B.W., Lockey A., Georgiou M., et al. KIDS SAVE LIVES: ERC position statement on schoolteachers' education and qualification in resuscitation. Resuscitation. 2020;151:87–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7194866</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32339597</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bottiger B.W., Semeraro F., Altemeyer K.H., et al. KIDS SAVE LIVES: School children education in resuscitation for Europe and the world. Eur J Anaesthesiol. 2017;34:792–796.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29087993</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bottiger B.W., Van Aken H. Kids save lives–Training school children in cardiopulmonary resuscitation worldwide is now endorsed by the World Health Organization (WHO) Resuscitation. 2015;94:A5–A7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26209417</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakagawa N.K., Silva L.M., Carvalho-Oliveira R., et al. KIDS SAVE LIVES BRAZIL: a successful pilot program to implement CPR at primary and high schools in Brazil resulting in a state law for a training CPR week. Resuscitation. 2019;140:81–83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31121207</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schroeder D.C., Ecker H., Wingen S., Semeraro F., Bottiger B.W. “Kids Save Lives”-resuscitation training for schoolchildren: systematic review. Anaesthesist. 2017;66:589–597.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28497243</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schroeder D.C., Semeraro F., Greif R., et al. KIDS SAVE LIVES: basic life support education for schoolchildren: a narrative review and scientific statement from the International Liaison Committee on Resuscitation. Circulation. 2023;147:1854–1868.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37194575</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wingen S., Jeck J., Schroeder D.C., Wingen-Heimann S.M., Drost R., Bottiger B.W. Facilitators and barriers for the implementation of resuscitation training programmes for schoolchildren: a systematic review. Eur J Anaesthesiol. 2022;39:711–719.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34860715</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jimenez-Fabrega X., Escalada-Roig X., Miro O., et al. Comparison between exclusively school teacher-based and mixed school teacher and healthcare provider-based programme on basic cardiopulmonary resuscitation for secondary schools. Emerg Med J. 2009;26:648–652.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19700581</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olasveengen T.M., Semeraro F., Ristagno G., et al. European Resuscitation Council Guidelines 2021: basic Life Support. Resuscitation. 2021;161:98–114.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33773835</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sugiki D., Matsushima H., Asao T., et al. A web-based self-learning system for ultrasound-guided vascular access. Medicine (Baltimore) 2022;101:e31292.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9622633</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36316890</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valverde-Berrocoso J., Garrido-Arroyo M.D., Burgos-Videla C., Morales-Cevallos M.B. Trends in educational research about e-learning: a systematic literature review (2009–2018) Sustainability-Basel. 2020;12</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaona A., Banzi R., Kwag K.H., Rigon G., Cereda D., Pecoraro V., Tramacere I., Moja L. E-learning for health professionals. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2018;1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6491176</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29355907</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reder S., Cummings P., Quan L. Comparison of three instructional methods for teaching cardiopulmonary resuscitation and use of an automatic external defibrillator to high school students. Resuscitation. 2006;69:443–453.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16678958</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Semeraro F., Greif R., Bottiger B.W., et al. European Resuscitation Council Guidelines 2021: Systems saving lives. Resuscitation. 2021;161:80–97.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33773834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Birkun A. Distant learning of BLS amid the COVID-19 pandemic: Influence of the outbreak on lay trainees' willingness to attempt CPR, and the motivating effect of the training. Resuscitation. 2020;152:105–106.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7245211</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32454084</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsieh M.J., Bhanji F., Chiang W.C., Yang C.W., Chien K.L., Ma M.H. Comparing the effect of self-instruction with that of traditional instruction in basic life support courses-A systematic review. Resuscitation. 2016;108:8–19.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27581252</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teague G., Riley R.H. Online resuscitation training. Does it improve high school students' ability to perform cardiopulmonary resuscitation in a simulated environment? Resuscitation. 2006;71:352–357.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17069951</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wingen S., Ecker H., Schroeder D.C., Bartholme B., Bottiger B.W., Wetsch W.A. Addressing the helper's and victim's gender is crucial in schoolchildren resuscitation training-a prospective, educative interventional trial. J Clin Med. 2022;11</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9103589</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35566510</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malta Hansen C., Zinckernagel L., Ersboll A.K., et al. Cardiopulmonary resuscitation training in schools following 8 years of mandating legislation in Denmark: a nationwide survey. J Am Heart Assoc. 2017;6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5523990</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28292745</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zinckernagel L., Malta Hansen C., Rod M.H., Folke F., Torp-Pedersen C., Tjornhoj-Thomsen T. What are the barriers to implementation of cardiopulmonary resuscitation training in secondary schools? A qualitative study. BMJ Open. 2016;6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4853997</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27113236</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sammet Jr, Wolf J. Vom Trainer zum agilen Lernbegleiter : So funktioniert Lehren und Lernen in digitalen Zeiten, 1. Aufl. 2019. edn. Berlin, Heidelberg: Springer; 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Birkun A. Free distance learning of cardiopulmonary resuscitation for laypeople - A reasonable way for improving cardiac arrest outcomes in low-resource settings. Resuscitation. 2021;168:91–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34571134</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Birkun A., Gautam A., Trunkwala F., Bottiger B.W. Open online courses on basic life support: availability and resuscitation guidelines compliance. Am J Emerg Med. 2022;62:102–107.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9359675</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35965163</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Draft Recommendation on Open Educational Resources. https://unesdoc.unesco.org/ark:/48223/pf0000370936.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lehren und Lernen in der digitalen Welt. Ergänzung zur Strategie der Kultusministerkonferenz „Bildung in der digitalen Welt“ (Beschluss der Kultusministerkonferenz vom 09.12.2021). https://www.kmk.org/fileadmin/veroeffentlichungen_beschluesse/2021/2021_12_09-Lehren-und-Lernen-Digi.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheeran P., Webb T.L. The intention-behavior gap. Soc Pers Psychol Compass. 2016;10:503–518.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>IT an Schulen: Ergebnisse einer Repräsentativbefragung von Lehrern in Deutschland. https://www.vbe.de/fileadmin/user_upload/VBE/Service/Meinungsumfragen/2014_11_06_IT_an_Schulen_Auswertung.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schule 2.0: Eine repräsentative Untersuchung zum Einsatz elektronischer Medien an Schulen aus Lehrersicht. https://www.bitkom.org/sites/default/files/file/import/BITKOM-Publikation-Schule-20.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Otto D. Adoption and diffusion of Open Educational Resources (OER) in education: a meta-analysis of 25 OER-projects. Int Rev Res Open Dis. 2019;20:122–140.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>