<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39309997</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2277-9531</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of education and health promotion</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Educ Health Promot</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Psychological distress and coping skills used by individuals in the crisis caused by the COVID-19 pandemic.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>261</StartPage><MedlinePgn>261</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">261</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4103/jehp.jehp_759_23</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Psychological distress, as a key indicator, describes a person's emotional problems and psychological reactions to adapt to the environment. This study aimed to investigate the relationship between psychological distress and coping strategies used by individuals during the crisis caused by COVID-19.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIALS AND METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">The current research is an analytical cross-sectional study that was designed in 2021. The sampling area included the three cities of Lar, Gerash, and Evaz in the south of Fars province in the south of Iran. The study population was the residents of these three cities during the COVID-19 pandemic. The final sample size in the present study was 384 people. Individuals were selected through available sampling. By answering questions from the self-assessment system of COVID-19 disease, the Ministry of Health and Medical Education filled out the necessary information for individual screening and registration of the symptoms of COVID-19 disease. Then, they completed the Coping Methods Questionnaire and the Psychological Distress Questionnaire.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The mean age of the participants was 40.90 years. One hundred sixty-seven (43.5%) participants were male, and 217 (56.5%) were female. The mean score of problem-oriented coping style was significantly different between the levels of education (<i>P</i> = 0.001). The mean score of problem-solving coping style for the participants suspected of being infected with COVID-19 was 6.18 scores lower than others, and the difference was statistically significant (<i>P</i> = 0.001). Multiple regression with a forward selection also showed that among the studied variables, age, problem-oriented, and emotion-oriented coping strategies were important variables affecting mental distress.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">People who were not suspected of having COVID-19 symptoms had a higher mean problem-oriented coping score than those who were suspected of having COVID-19. Therefore, early identification of suspects and the implementation of counseling and training programs can be very effective.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: © 2024 Journal of Education and Health Promotion.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bazrafshan</LastName><ForeName>Mohammad-Rafi</ForeName><Initials>MR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nursing, School of Nursing, Larestan University of Medical Sciences, Larestan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bargrizaneh</LastName><ForeName>Farshad</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Student Research Committee, Larestan University of Medical Sciences, Larestan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sarvi</LastName><ForeName>Fatemeh</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health, School of Health, Larestan University of Medical Sciences, Larestan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Parviniannasab</LastName><ForeName>Ali Mohammad</ForeName><Initials>AM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nursing, School of Nursing, Larestan University of Medical Sciences, Larestan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Niknam</LastName><ForeName>Noureddin</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health, Torbat Jam Faculty of Medical Sciences, Torbat Jam, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Soufi</LastName><ForeName>Omid</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, Shiraz University of Medical Sciences, Shiraz, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Delam</LastName><ForeName>Hamed</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Student Research Committee, Larestan University of Medical Sciences, Larestan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>PhD Student of Epidemiology, Student Research Committee, Shiraz University of Medical Sciences, Shiraz, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>India</Country><MedlineTA>J Educ Health Promot</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101593794</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2277-9531</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Coping strategy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">psychological distress</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>29</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>56</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39309997</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11414859</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/jehp.jehp_759_23</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">JEHP-13-261</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Lu H, Stratton CW, Tang YW. Outbreak of pneumonia of unknown etiology in Wuhan, China: The mystery and the miracle. J Med Virol. 2020;92:401–2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7166628</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31950516</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu H, Li M, Li Z, Xiang W, Yuan Y, Liu Y, et al. Coping style, social support and psychological distress in the general Chinese population in the early stages of the COVID-19 epidemic. BMC Psychiatry. 2020;20:426.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7450895</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32854656</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdi M. Coronavirus disease 2019 (covid-19) outbreak in Iran: Actions and problems. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol. 2020;41:754–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7137533</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32192541</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Druss BG. Addressing the COVID-19 pandemic in populations with serious mental illness. JAMA Psychiatry. 2020;77:891–2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32242888</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kontoangelos K, Economou M, Papageorgiou C. Mental health effects of COVID-19 pandemia: A review of clinical and psychological traits. Psychiatry Investig. 2020;17:491–505.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7324731</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32570296</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cullen W, Gulati G, Kelly BD. Mental health in the covid-19 pandemic. QJM. 2020;113:311–2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7184387</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32227218</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park SC, Park YC. Mental health care measures in response to the 2019 novel coronavirus outbreak in Korea. Psychiatry Investig. 2020;17:85–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7047003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32093458</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alizadeh A, Khankeh HR, Barati M, Ahmadi Y, Hadian A, Azizi M. Psychological distress among Iranian health-care providers exposed to coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19): A qualitative study. BMC Psychiatry. 2020;20:494.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7538532</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33028290</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brooks SK, Webster RK, Smith LE, Woodland L, Wessely S, Greenberg N, et al. The psychological impact of quarantine and how to reduce it: Rapid review of the evidence. Lancet. 2020;395:912–920.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7158942</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32112714</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun N, Wei L, Shi S, Jiao D, Song R, Ma L, et al. A qualitative study on the psychological experience of caregivers of covid-19 patients. Am J Infect Control. 2020;48:592–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7141468</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32334904</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dawson DL, Golijani-Moghaddam N. Covid-19: Psychological flexibility, coping, mental health, and wellbeing in the UK during the pandemic. J Contextual Behav Sci. 2020;17:126–34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7392106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32834970</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Boer SF, Buwalda B, Koolhaas JM. Untangling the neurobiology of coping styles in rodents: Towards neural mechanisms underlying individual differences in disease susceptibility. Neurosci Biobehav Rev. 2017;74:401–22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27402554</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heffer T, Willoughby T. A count of coping strategies: A longitudinal study investigating an alternative method to understanding coping and adjustment. PLoS One. 2017;12:e0186057.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5642021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28982138</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Algorani EB, Gupta V.  StatPearls [Internet] Treasure Island (FL): StatPearls Publishing; 2024. Coping Mechanisms. Available from: https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK559031 . [Last updated on 2023 Apr 24]</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32644457</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Compas BE, Jaser SS, Bettis AH, Watson KH, Gruhn MA, Dunbar JP, et al. Coping, emotion regulation, and psychopathology in childhood and adolescence: A meta-analysis and narrative review. Psychol Bull. 2017;143:939–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7310319</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28616996</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Folkman S, Lazarus RS. The relationship between coping and emotion: Implications for theory and research. Soc Sci Med. 1988;26:309–17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3279520</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alipour A, Hashemi T, Babapour J, Tousi F. Relationship between coping strategies and happiness among university students. Journal of Modern Psychological Researches. 2010;5:71–86.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kessler RC, Andrews G, Colpe LJ, Hiripi E, Mroczek DK, Normand SL, et al. Short screening scales to monitor population prevalences and trends in non-specific psychological distress. Psychol Med. 2002;32:959–76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12214795</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yaghubi H. Psychometric properties of the 10 questions version of the kessler psychological distress scale (K-10) Applied Psychological Research Quarterly. 2016;6:45–57.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daly M, Robinson E. Psychological distress and adaptation to the covid-19 crisis in the United States. J Psychiatr Res. 2021;136:603–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7588823</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33138985</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cénat JM, Blais-Rochette C, Kokou-Kpolou CK, Noorishad PG, Mukunzi JN, McIntee SE, et al. Prevalence of symptoms of depression, anxiety, insomnia, posttraumatic stress disorder, and psychological distress among populations affected by the COVID-19 pandemic: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Psychiatry Res. 2021;295:113599.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7689353</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33285346</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonati M, Campi R, Zanetti M, Cartabia M, Scarpellini F, Clavenna A, et al. Psychological distress among Italians during the 2019 coronavirus disease (COVID-19) quarantine. BMC Psychiatry. 2021;21:20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7793386</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33419391</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iasevoli F, Fornaro M, D’Urso G, Galletta D, Casella C, Paternoster M, et al. Psychological distress in patients with serious mental illness during the covid-19 outbreak and one-month mass quarantine in Italy. Psychol Med. 2021;51:1054–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7261960</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32423496</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao W, Fang Z, Hou G, Han M, Xu X, Dong J, et al. The psychological impact of the COVID-19 epidemic on college students in China. Psychiatry Res. 2020;287:112934.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7102633</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32229390</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lai AY, Sit SM, Lai TT, Wang MP, Kong CH, Cheuk JY, et al. Facemask wearing among Chinese international students from Hong Kong studying in United Kingdom universities during covid-19: A Mixed Method Study. Front Psychiatry. 2021;12:673531.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8242177</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34220582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eisazadeh F, Aliakbari Dehkordi M, Aghajanbigloo S. Psychological consequences of patients with coronavirus (COVID-19): A Qualitative Study. Biquarterly Iranian Journal of Health Psychology. 2020;2:9–20.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>