<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39309283</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2093-7911</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>15</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Safety and health at work</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Saf Health Work</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Association Between Sickness Presenteeism and Depressive Symptoms by Occupation and Employment Type During the COVID-19 Pandemic.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>338</StartPage><EndPage>344</EndPage><MedlinePgn>338-344</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.shaw.2024.06.002</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Sickness presenteeism (SP) has gained attention in occupational health. This study aimed to analyze the relationship between SP and depressive symptoms by occupation and employment type during the COVID-19 pandemic in Korea.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Community Health Survey data (August 16 to October 31, 2020-2021) were used to assess depressive symptoms and SP among workers (<i>n</i> = 221,241; mean age 46.0; 53.5% male). Depressive symptoms were measured using the Patient Health Questionnaire-9, and SP was defined by the ability to rest at home when exhibiting COVID-19 symptoms. Adjusted odds ratios (ORs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs) of depressive symptoms were estimated using multiple logistic regression analyses for each sex and year stratum. The interaction between SP and occupation on depressive symptoms was assessed using relative excess risk due to interaction (RERI).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The prevalence of depressive symptoms was higher in individuals with SP than in those without SP (4.22% [<i>n</i> = 696] vs. 1.89% [<i>n</i> = 3861], respectively). After adjusting for demographic and occupational variables, the association between SP and depressive symptoms was significant in both sexes in 2020 and 2021 (OR [95% CI]: 2.18 [1.82-2.62], 2.41 [1.97-2.93], 2.05 [1.77-2.38], 2.47 [2.11-2.88] for male-2020, male-2021, female-2020, and female-2021, respectively). A marginally significant interaction between service workers and SP on depressive symptoms was observed among male workers in 2021 (RERI = 2.37, 95% CI = [-0.04-4.78]) but not in other strata.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">SP is significantly associated with depressive symptoms in Korean workers across employment and occupational types, with a prominent association in service workers.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Occupational Safety and Health Research Institute. Published by Elsevier B.V. on behalf of Institute, Occupational Safety and Health Research Institute, Korea Occupational Safety and Health Agency.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kang</LastName><ForeName>Minkoo</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Yonsei University College of Medicine, Seoul, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lee</LastName><ForeName>Won-Tae</ForeName><Initials>WT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Disease Control, Jeollanam-do Provincial Government, Jeollanam-do, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yun</LastName><ForeName>Byungyoon</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Preventive Medicine, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Seoul, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Occupational Health, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Seoul, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Innovation in Digital Healthcare, Yonsei University Health System, Seoul, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yoon</LastName><ForeName>Jin-Ha</ForeName><Initials>JH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Preventive Medicine, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Seoul, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Occupational Health, Yonsei University College of Medicine, Seoul, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Innovation in Digital Healthcare, Yonsei University Health System, Seoul, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Korea (South)</Country><MedlineTA>Saf Health Work</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101542940</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2093-7911</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Depressive symptoms</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Employment type</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Occupation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sickness presenteeism</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors have no conflict of interest to report.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>29</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39309283</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11410493</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.shaw.2024.06.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2093-7911(24)00041-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Masuda M., Ishimaru T., Hino A., Ando H., Tateishi S., Nagata T., Tsuji M., Matsuda S., Fujino Y. A cross-sectional study of psychosocial factors and sickness presenteeism in Japanese workers during the COVID-19 pandemic. J Occup Environ Med. 2022;64:e1–e7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8715929</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34654039</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aronsson G., Gustafsson K., Dallner M. Sick but yet at work. An empirical study of sickness presenteeism. J Epidemol Community Health. 2000;54:502–509.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1731716</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10846192</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brouwer W., Verbooy K., Hoefman R., van Exel J. Production losses due to absenteeism and presenteeism: the influence of compensation mechanisms and multiplier effects. Pharmacoeconomics. 2023;41:1103–1115.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9976676</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36856941</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferreira A.I., Mach M., Martinez L.F., Miraglia M. Sickness presenteeism in the aftermath of COVID-19: is presenteeism remote-work behavior the new (Ab)normal? Front Psychol. 2022;12</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8830031</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35153891</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Skagen K., Collins A.M. The consequences of sickness presenteeism on health and wellbeing over time: a systematic review. Soc Sci Med. 2016;161:169–177.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27310723</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kivimäki M., Head J., Ferrie J.E., Hemingway H., Shipley M.J., Vahtera J., Marmot M.G. Working while ill as a risk factor for serious coronary events: the whitehall II study. Am J Public Health. 2005;95:98–102.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1449859</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15623867</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gustafsson K., Marklund S. Consequences of sickness presence and sickness absence on health and work ability: a Swedish prospective cohort study. Int J Occup Med Environ Health. 2011;24:153–165.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21526385</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ambresin G., Chondros P., Dowrick C., Herrman H., Gunn J.M. Self-rated health and long-term prognosis of depression. Ann Fam Med. 2014;12:57–65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3896539</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24445104</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim M.-S., Park J.B., Min K.-B., Lee K.-J., Kwon K. Presenteeism among self-employed workers: Korean working conditions survey. Ann Occup Environ Med. 2014;26:32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4387789</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25852942</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moussavi S., Chatterji S., Verdes E., Tandon A., Patel V., Ustun B. Depression, chronic diseases, and decrements in health: results from the World Health Surveys. Lancet. 2007;370:851–858.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17826170</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee K.-S. Association between sickness presenteeism and depressive symptoms in Korean workers during the COVID-19 pandemic: a cross-sectional study. J Affective Disord. 2022;319:344–351.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9477787</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36116605</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hwang I.C., Choi S. Health-related habits and health promotion behaviors in people with alcohol flushing. Asia Pac J Public Health. 2023;35:284–287.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37096496</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jo S., Han S.-Y., Howe N. Factors associated with handwashing behaviors during the COVID-19 pandemic: an analysis of the community health survey in Korea. SAGE Open Nurs. 2023;9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10150421</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37139169</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han C., Jo S.A., Kwak J.-H., Pae C.-U., Steffens D., Jo I., Park M.H. Validation of the patient health questionnaire-9 Korean version in the elderly population: the ansan geriatric study. Compr Psychiatry. 2008;49:218–223.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18243897</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sidebottom A.C., Harrison P.A., Godecker A., Kim H. Validation of the patient health questionnaire (PHQ)-9 for prenatal depression screening. Arch Womens Ment Health. 2012;15:367–374.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22983357</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cha W.-T., Joo H.-J., Park Y.-S., Park E.-C., Kim S.-Y. Depression before and during-COVID-19 by gender in the Korean population. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19:3477.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8953760</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35329161</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kwak GH, Baek SH, Kwak EJ. Effects of the COVID-19 pandemic on senior dental students in Korea: Examining stress, burnout, and depression. J Dent Sci. 2024 Apr;19(2):909–918.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11011050</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38618054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee M.-S., Lee H. The risk of obstructive sleep apnea is highly correlated with depressive symptoms among the Korean adults population: results from the 2020 Korea National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey. BMC Psychiatry. 2023;23:467.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10294313</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37370095</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kroenke K., Spitzer R.L., Williams J.B. The PHQ-9: validity of a brief depression severity measure. J Gen Intern Med. 2001;16:606–613.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1495268</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11556941</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoon J.-H., Jung S.J., Choi J., Kang M.-Y. Suicide trends over time by occupation in Korea and their relationship to economic downturns. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2019;16:2007.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6604014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31195664</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen J.J. Communicating complex information: the interpretation of statistical interaction in multiple logistic regression analysis. Am J Public Health. 2003;93:1376–1377. author reply 7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1447969</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12948938</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knol M.J., VanderWeele T.J. Recommendations for presenting analyses of effect modification and interaction. Int J Epidemiol. 2012;41:514–520.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3324457</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22253321</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin Y.H., Chen C.Y., Lu S.Y. Physical discomfort and psychosocial job stress among male and female operators at telecommunication call centers in Taiwan. Appl Ergon. 2009;40:561–568.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18691695</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Szymczak J.E., Smathers S., Hoegg C., Klieger S., Coffin S.E., Sammons J.S. Reasons why physicians and advanced practice clinicians work while sick: a mixed-methods analysis. JAMA Pediatr. 2015;169:815–821.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26146908</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gustafsson Sendén M., Løvseth L.T., Schenck-Gustafsson K., Fridner A. What makes physicians go to work while sick: a comparative study of sickness presenteeism in four European countries (HOUPE) Swiss Med Wkly. 2013;143</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23986177</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kinman G. Sickness presenteeism at work: prevalence, costs and management. Br Med Bull. 2019;129:69–78.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30649219</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chun H-r, Cho I., Choi Y., Cho S-i. Effects of emotional labor factors and working environment on the risk of depression in pink-collar workers. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020;17:5208.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7400525</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32707657</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tafet G.E., Nemeroff C.B. The links between stress and depression: psychoneuroendocrinological, genetic, and environmental interactions. J Neuropsychiatry Clin Neurosci. 2016;28:77–88.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26548654</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abramson L.Y., Alloy L.B., Hogan M.E., Whitehouse W.G., Donovan P., Rose D.T., Panzarella C., Raniere D. Cognitive vulnerability to depression: theory and evidence. J Cogn Psychother. 1999;13:5–20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haeffel G.J., Hershenberg R., Goodson J.T., Hein S., Square A., Grigorenko E.L., Chapman J. The hopelessness theory of depression: clinical utility and generalizability. Cogn Ther Res. 2017;41:543–555.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu R.T., Kleiman E.M., Nestor B.A., Cheek S.M. The hopelessness theory of depression: a quarter century in review. Clin Psychol (New York) 2015;22:345–365.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4689589</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26709338</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marciniak-Nuqui Z., Cabling M.L., Romanelli R.J. Culture of presenteeism: emergent perspectives from an NHS-workforce convenience sample. Occup Med (Lond) 2024 Apr 3;74(2):167–171.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38319798</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hale T., Angrist N., Goldszmidt R., Kira B., Petherick A., Phillips T., Webster S., Cameron-Blake E., Hallas L., Majumdar S., Tatlow H. A global panel database of pandemic policies (Oxford COVID-19 Government Response Tracker) Nat Hum Behav. 2021;5:529–538.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33686204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma Y., Mishra S.R., Han X.-K., Zhu D.-S. The relationship between time to a high COVID-19 response level and timing of peak daily incidence: an analysis of governments’ Stringency Index from 148 countries. Infect Dis Poverty. 2021;10:96.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8256203</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34225774</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jung S.W., Lee J.-H., Lee K.-J. Assessing the association between emotional labor and presenteeism among nurses in Korea: cross-sectional study using the 4th Korean working conditions survey. Saf Health Work. 2020;11:103–108.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7078561</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32206380</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lim S.-S., Lee W., Hong K., Jeung D., Chang S.-J., Yoon J.-H. Facing complaining customer and suppressed emotion at worksite related to sleep disturbance in Korea. jkms. 2016;31:1696–1702.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5056199</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27709845</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kucharczyk E.R., Morgan K., Hall A.P. The occupational impact of sleep quality and insomnia symptoms. Sleep Med Rev. 2012;16:547–559.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22401983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hur W.-M. Daily relationships between job insecurity and emotional labor amid COVID-19: mediation of ego depletion and moderation of off-job control and work-related smartphone use. J Occup Health Psychol. 2023;28:82–102.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37126066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shin Y., Hur W.-M. When do job-insecure employees keep performing well? The buffering roles of help and prosocial motivation in the relationship between job insecurity, work engagement, and job performance. J Bus Psychol. 2021;36:659–678.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gilbreath B., Karimi L. Supervisor behavior and employee presenteeism. Int J Leadership Stud. 2012;7:114–131.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferreira A.I., da Costa Ferreira P., Cooper C.L., Oliveira D. How daily negative affect and emotional exhaustion correlates with work engagement and presenteeism-constrained productivity. Int J Stress Manag. 2019;26:261.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Price L., Spence S.H. Burnout symptoms amongst drug and alcohol service employees: gender differences in the interaction between work and home stressors. Anxiety Stress Copin. 1994;7:67–84.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang J., Wang S., Wang W., Shan G., Guo S., Li Y. Nurses’ job insecurity and emotional exhaustion: the mediating effect of presenteeism and the moderating effect of supervisor support. Front Psychol. 2020;11</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7531262</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33071851</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeon S.H., Leem J.H., Park S.G., Heo Y.S., Lee B.J., Moon S.H., Jung D.Y., Kim H.C. Association among working hours, occupational stress, and presenteeism among wage workers: results from the second Korean working conditions survey. Ann Occup Environ Med. 2014;26:6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3994451</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24661575</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sverke M., Hellgren J., Näswall K. No security: a meta-analysis and review of job insecurity and its consequences. J Occup Health Psychol. 2002;7:242–264.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12148956</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han K.-M., Shin C., Yoon H.-K., Ko Y.-H., Kim Y.-K., Han C. Emotional labor and depressive mood in service and sales workers: interactions with gender and job autonomy. Psychiatry Res. 2018;267:490–498.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29980129</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Häusser J.A., Mojzisch A., Niesel M., Schulz-Hardt S. Ten years on: a review of recent research on the Job Demand–Control (-Support) model and psychological well-being. Work Stress. 2010;24:1–35.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee S.H., Sung J.H., Kim D.H., Sim C.S. The association between direct supervisor's behavior and employee presenteeism in Korean wage workers: findings from the fifth Korean Working Condition Survey. Ann Occup Environ Med. 2021;33</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8602819</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34868600</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>