<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39307898</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>12</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>12</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1573-3254</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>28</Volume><Issue>Suppl 1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>AIDS and behavior</Title><ISOAbbreviation>AIDS Behav</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>When Pandemics Collide: Actionable Lessons in HIV Prevention, Treatment and Care During the Era of COVID-19.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1</StartPage><EndPage>4</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1-4</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s10461-024-04482-0</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The articles in this special issue of AIDS and Behavior focus on the collision between HIV/AIDS and COVID-19 as intersecting pandemics that profoundly impacted communities globally. This editorial highlights the complex interplay between these two public health crises. The pandemic disrupted access to HIV prevention, testing, and treatment services, potentially jeopardizing decades of progress. Mental health challenges and social vulnerability among people living with HIV (PWH) were exacerbated, with preexisting health disparities amplified, disproportionately affecting marginalized populations. However, despite these challenges, the pandemic also spurred innovation and adaptation in HIV prevention and care, with increased use of telehealth and other modalities. The enduring and actionable lessons learned from the collision of HIV and COVID-19 pandemics can prepare us for the next public health challenge with two calls for action. First, we call for integrated and equitable responses that address the multifaceted challenges faced by individuals and communities affected by HIV in the post-COVID-19 era. Second, we call for a strengthened commitment to building resilient health systems and community-engaged interventions that can withstand future challenges.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer Science+Business Media, LLC, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Olatosi</LastName><ForeName>Bankole</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8295-8735</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>South Carolina SmartState Center for Healthcare Quality, Arnold School of Public Health, University of South Carolina, Columbia, SC, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Services Policy and Management, Arnold School of Public Health, University of South Carolina, Columbia, SC, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Patel</LastName><ForeName>Rena C</ForeName><Initials>RC</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9893-5856</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases, Department of Medicine, Heersink School of Medicine, University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, AL, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Xiaoming</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5555-9034</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>South Carolina SmartState Center for Healthcare Quality, Arnold School of Public Health, University of South Carolina, Columbia, SC, USA. xiaoming@mailbox.sc.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Promotion, Education, and Behavior, Arnold School of Public Health, University of South Carolina, Columbia, SC, USA. xiaoming@mailbox.sc.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016421">Editorial</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D054711">Introductory Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>AIDS Behav</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9712133</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1090-7165</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015658" MajorTopicYN="Y">HIV Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="Y">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006297" MajorTopicYN="N">Health Services Accessibility</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017216" MajorTopicYN="N">Telemedicine</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011634" MajorTopicYN="N">Public Health</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D054625" MajorTopicYN="N">Healthcare Disparities</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Disparities</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">HIV/AIDS</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mental health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Organizational resilience</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Social vulnerability</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>21</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39307898</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10461-024-04482-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s10461-024-04482-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Mi T, Yang X, Sun S, Li X, Tam CC, Zhou Y, Shen Z. Mental health problems of HIV healthcare providers during the COVID-19 pandemic: the interactive effects of stressors and coping. AIDS Behav. 2021;25:18–27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10461-020-03073-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33128108</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiao S, Li Z, Weissman S, Olatosi B, Li X, Davis C, Mansaray A. Disparity in HIV service interruption in the outbreak of COVID-19 in South Carolina. AIDS Behav. 2021;25:49–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10461-020-03013-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32856176</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tam CC, Sun S, Yang X, Li X, Zhou Y, Shen Z. Psychological distress among HIV healthcare providers during the COVID-19 pandemic in China: mediating roles of institutional support and resilience. AIDS Behav. 2021;25:9–17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10461-020-03068-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33089356</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Xie Y, Hu S, Ai W, Tao Y, Tang W. Systematic review and meta-analyses of the interaction between HIV infection and COVID-19: two years’ evidence summary. Front Immunol. 2022;13: 864838.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2022.864838</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35619709</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9128408</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Auerbach JD, Forsyth AD, Davey C, Hargreaves JR. Living with COVID-19 and preparing for future pandemics: revisiting lessons from the HIV pandemic. Lancet HIV. 2023;10(1):e62–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2352-3018(22)00301-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36370713</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lesko CR, Bengtson AM. HIV and COVID-19: intersecting epidemics with many unknowns. Am J Epidemiol. 2021;190(1):10–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/aje/kwaa158</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32696057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lohiniva AL, Zachariah R, Harries AD. The impact of COVID-19 on HIV care in low- and middle-income countries: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Int AIDS Soc. 2022;25(1): e25801.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang X, Sun J, Patel RC, Zhang J, Guo S, Li X. The role of HIV infection in the clinical spectrum of COVID-19: a population level analysis based on US National COVID Cohort Collaborative (N3C) data. Lancet HIV. 2021;8(11):e690–700.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2352-3018(21)00239-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34655550</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8514200</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kunz M, Rott KW, Hurwitz E, Kunisaki K, Sun J, Wilkins KJ, Islam JY, Patel R, Safo SE, National Covid Cohort Collaborative (N3C) Consortium. The intersections of COVID-19, HIV, and race/ethnicity: machine learning methods to identify and model risk factors for severe COVID-19 in a large US National dataset. AIDS Behav. 2024. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10461-024-04266-6 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10461-024-04266-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38326668</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Z, Qiao S, Ning H, Sun X, Zhang J, Olatosi B, Li X. Place visitation data reveals the geographic and racial disparities of COVID-19 impact on HIV service utilization in the deep south. AIDS Behav. 2023. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10461-023-04163-4 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10461-023-04163-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38109020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10896863</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiao S, Zhang J, Li Z, Olatosi B, Weissman S, Li X. The impacts of HIV-related service interruptions during the COVID-19 pandemic: protocol of a mixed methodology longitudinal study. AIDS Behav. 2023. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10461-023-04138-5 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10461-023-04138-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38091128</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10226022</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi F, Zhang J, Yang X, Gao H, Chen S, Weissman S, Olatosi B, Li X. COVID-19 testing among people with HIV: a population level analysis based on statewide data in South Carolina. AIDS Behav. 2023. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10461-023-04244-4 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10461-023-04244-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38109020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tapera T, Odimegwu C, Makoni T, Mukuwapasi W, Chitiyo V, Kadziyanike G, Willis N, Mutsinze A, Mawodzeke M, Chimberengwa P, Phiri M. Intersecting epidemics: the predictors of continued utilization of HIV care and treatment services during the COVID-19 outbreak among people living with HIV in ZIMBABWE. AIDS Behav. 2023. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10461-023-04194-x .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10461-023-04194-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoover KW, HIV services and outcomes during the COVID-19 pandemic—United States, 2019–2021. MMWR. Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report 71, 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNAIDS, Global AIDS update. Confronting in equalities — Lessons for pandemic responses from 40 years of AIDS 2021, 2021. https://www.unaids.org/en/resources/documents/2021/2021-global-aids-update .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNAIDS, In Danger: UNAIDS Global AIDS update 2022, 2022. https://www.unaids.org/en/resources/documents/2022/in-danger-global-aids-update .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiao S, Shirley C, Garrett C, Weissman S, Olatosi B, Li X. Facilitators of organizational resilience within South Carolina AIDS service organizations: lessons learned from the COVID-19 pandemic. AIDS Behav. 2023. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10461-023-04089-x .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10461-023-04089-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38091128</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10226022</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schieber E, Cottrell L, Deveaux L, Li X, Taylor M, Adderley R, Marshall S, Forbes N, Wang B. Teachers’ perceptions of the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic and their implementation of an evidence-based HIV prevention program in the Bahamas. AIDS Behav. 2024. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10461-024-04345-8 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10461-024-04345-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38642212</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Z, Chan PSF, Xin M, Fang Y, Chidgey A, Yu FY, Ip M, Chen S, Mo PKH. An online intervention promoting HIV testing service utilization among Chinese men who have sex with men during the COVID-19 pandemic: a quasi-experimental study. AIDS Behav. 2023. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10461-023-04100-5 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10461-023-04100-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37922033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10598162</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen WT, Huang F, Sun W, Zhang L. Fear of COVID and physical health among people living with HIV in China: Mediation effects of HIV stigma, social support, and substance use. AIDS Behav. 2023. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10461-023-04099-9 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10461-023-04099-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38109020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10246536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo S, Zhang J, Yang X, Weissman S, Olatosi B, Patel RC, Li X, N3C Consortium. Impact of HIV on COVID-19 outcomes: a propensity score matching analysis with varying age differences. AIDS Behav. 2023. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10461-023-04088-y .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10461-023-04088-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37289345</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10249542</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Islam JY, Hurwitz E, Li D, Camacho-Rivera M, Sun J, Safo S, Ross JM, Wilkins K, Hassan S, Hill EL, Nosyk B, Varley C, Fadul N, Madlock-Brown C, Patel RC, on behalf of N3C Consortium. Associations of county-level social determinants of health with COVID-19 related hospitalization among people with HIV: a retrospective analysis of the U.S. National COVID Cohort Collaborative (N3C). AIDS Behav. 2024. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10461-024-04466-0 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10461-024-04466-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39292319</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muno BA, Islam JY, Schwartz R, Wallace S, Camacho-Rivera M, Patel RC. Structural racism conceptualization and operationalization for research for the US HIV epidemic: findings from a scoping review and implications for advancing research for structural interventions. AIDS Behav. 2024. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10461-024-04417-9 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10461-024-04417-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39093355</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barbera LK, Kamis KF, Rowan SE, Davis AJ, Shehata S, Carlson JJ, Johnson SC, Erlandson KM. HIV and COVID-19: review of clinical course and outcomes. HIV Res Clin Pract. 2021;22(4):102–18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/25787489.2021.1975608</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34514963</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Danwang C, Noubiap JJ, Robert A, Yombi JC. Outcomes of patients with HIV and COVID-19 co-infection: a systematic review and meta-analysis. AIDS Res Ther. 2022;19(1):3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12981-021-00427-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35031068</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8759058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nkengasong J. HIV and COVID-19: juxtaposition of two pandemics. Lancet HIV. 2022;9(5):e300–1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2352-3018(22)00095-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35489372</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9045779</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>