<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39309990</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2277-9531</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of education and health promotion</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Educ Health Promot</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Evaluation of the effectiveness of the training on "Home care of COVID-19 positive/suspicious patients" given to nursing students: A quasi-experimental study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>250</StartPage><MedlinePgn>250</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">250</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4103/jehp.jehp_1574_23</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">This study aims to evaluate the effects of education on home care of infected or suspected COVID-19 patients on the levels of knowledge, anxiety, and awareness of nursing students in Turkey.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIALS AND METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">The study is in quasi-experimental design. A sample of 158 volunteer students studying nursing at a private university in Turkey was formed. Data were collected using, descriptive information form, "Coronavirus Anxiety Scale," "COVID-19 Awareness Scale," and the "Knowledge of COVID-19 Home Care Test." Pre-test was performed before the participants received education. Post-test was performed seven days after the intervention. SPSS version 25.0 was used for data analysis. "TREND checklist" was used for quasi-experimental/non-randomized evaluations to report the findings of the study.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Anxiety levels decreased and the levels of awareness and knowledge on COVID-19 increased after receiving education on home care of infected or suspected COVID-19 patients (p &lt; 0.001), indicating the effectiveness of the education. Education on home care of infected or suspected COVID-19 patients was an effective method to reduce anxiety and increase knowledge and awareness in nursing students.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">To contribute to community health, home care training can be given to nursing students, other people receiving home care, or providing home care to COVID-19 patients, infected or suspected COVID-19 patients.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: © 2024 Journal of Education and Health Promotion.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sabandüzen</LastName><ForeName>Hande</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nursing, Faculty of Health Sciences, Bahcesehir University, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kavaklı</LastName><ForeName>Öznur</ForeName><Initials>Ö</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Fundamentals of Nursing, Gulhane Faculty of Nursing, University of Health Sciences, Ankara, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>India</Country><MedlineTA>J Educ Health Promot</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101593794</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2277-9531</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Anxiety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19 pandemic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">awareness</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">education</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">home health nursing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">knowledge</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nursing students</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>There are no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>29</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>56</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39309990</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11414848</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/jehp.jehp_1574_23</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">JEHP-13-250</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Çelebi C. Covid-19 Tanılı Hastalarda Hemşirelik Bakımı. Ege Klinik Tıp Dergisi. 2020;58:35–40.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou F, Yu T, Du R, Fan G, Liu Y, Liu Z, et al. Clinical course and risk factors for mortality of adult inpatients with COVID-19 in Wuhan, China: A retrospective cohort study. Lancet. 2020;395:1054–62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7270627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32171076</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 Nedir?  Available from: https://covid19.saglik.gov.tr/TR-66300/covid-19-nedir-.html . [Last accessed on 2023 Oct 14]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Türk Toraks Derneği COVID-19 E-Kitapları. 2020.  Available from: www.toraks.org.tr . [Last accessed on 2023 Oct 14]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Republic of Turkey Ministry of Health (02.10.2021) COVID-19 Contact Follow-up, Outbreak Management, Home Patient Monitoring and Filiation.  https://covid19.saglik.gov.tr/ . Date of access: 10.03.2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Republic of Turkey Ministry of Health. COVID-19 Related Isolation and Quarantine Practices in the Current Period.  Available from: https://covid19.saglik.gov.tr/Eklenti/42333/0/covid-19gunceldonemdecovid19iliskiliizolasyonvekarintinauygulamalari-2pdf.pdf . [Last accessed on 2022 Jan 14]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hafiz TA, D’Sa JL, Zamzam S, Dionaldo MLV, Aldawood E, Madkhali N, et al. The effectiveness of an educational ıntervention on helicobacter pylori for university students: A quasi-experimental study. J Multidiscip Healthc. 2023;16:1979–88.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10361274</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37484821</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gutiérrez-Puertas L, Márquez-Hernández VV, Gutiérrez-Puertas V, Granados-Gámez G, Aguilera-Manrique G. Educational ınterventions for nursing students to develop communication skills with patients: A systematic review. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020;17:2241. doi: 10.3390/ijerph17072241.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7177717</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32225038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadafi M, Bahmanpour K, Nouri B, Valiee S. Effect of multimodal ıntervention on nursing students’ adherence to hand hygiene: An experimental study. Creat Nurs. 2021;27:209–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34493643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cırık, V. A.; Aksoy, B.; Gül, U. Psychological resilience levels of nursing students and coping strategies in the COVID-19 process: descriptive study. Turkiye Klinikleri Journal of Nursing Sciences. 2021;13(3):693–703.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Birimoglu Okuyan C, Karasu F, Polat F. Hemşirelik öğrencilerinin Covid-19’a maruz kalma korkularının sağlık kaygısı düzeyleri üzerine etkisi: Bir üniversite örneği. Van Sağlık Bilimleri Dergisi 2020, 13.COVID-19 Özel Sayı. :45–52.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen J. Statistical Power Analysis for the Behavioral Sciences. 2013 ISBN: 0-8058-0283-5. DOI: 10.4324/9780203771587.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lakens D. Calculating and reporting effect sizes to facilitate cumulative science: A practical primer for t-tests and ANOVAs. Front Psychol. 2013;4:863. doi: 10.3389/fpsyg. 2013.00863.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3840331</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24324449</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faul F, Erdfelder E, Lang AG, Buchner A. G*Power 3: A flexible statistical power analysis program for the social, behavioral, and biomedical sciences. Behav Res Methods. 2007;39:175–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17695343</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee SA. Coronavirus anxiety scale: A brief mental health screener for COVID-19 related anxiety. Death Stud. 2020;44:393–401.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32299304</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biçer İ, Çakmak C, Demir H, Kurt ME. Koronavirüs Anksiyete Ölçeği Kısa Formu: Türkçe Geçerlik ve Güvenirlik Çalışması. Anadolu Klin. 2020;25(Special Issue on COVID 19):216–25.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bilgin, O. Koronavirüs (Covid-19) Farkındalık Ölçeği Geliştirilmesi: Geçerlik ve Güvenirlik Çalışması. Electronic Turkish Studies. 2020;15:6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coronavirus disease (COVID-19): Home care for families and caregivers.  Available from: https://www.who.int/news-room/questions-and-answers/item/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-home-care-for-families-and-caregivers . [Last accessed on 2023 Oct 14]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Home care for patients with suspected or confirmed COVID-19 and management of their contacts.  Available from: https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/home-care-for-patients-with-suspected-novel-coronavirus-(ncov)-infection-presenting-with-mild-symptoms-and-management-of-contacts . [Last accessed on 2023 Oct 14]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Üçgün, AB, Yavuz C. COVID-19 Pandemisinin hatırlattıkları: temizlik ve dezenfeksiyon. Sürekli Tıp Eğitimi Dergisi. 2021;30(5):351–357.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barazzoni R, Bischoff SC, Breda J, Wickramasinghe K, Krznaric Z, Nitzan D, et al. ESPEN expert statements and practical guidance for nutritional management of individuals with SARS-CoV-2 infection. Clin Nutr. 2020;39:1631–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7138149</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32305181</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ikhlaq A, Bint-E-riaz H, Bashir I, Ijaz F. Awareness and Attitude of Undergraduate Medical Students towards 2019-novel Corona virus. Pak J Med Sci. 2020;36(COVID19-S4):S32. doi: 10.12669/pjms. 36.COVID19-S4.2636.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7306955</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32582311</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hossain MA, Jahid MIK, Amran Hossain KM, Walton LM, Uddin Z, Haque MO, et al. Knowledge, attitudes, and fear of COVID-19 during the Rapid Rise Period in Bangladesh. PLoS One. 2020;15:e0239646.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7514023</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32970769</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y, Li P, Lv Y, Hou X, Rao Q, Tan J, et al. Public awareness and anxiety during COVID-19 epidemic in China: A cross-sectional study. Compr Psychiatry. 2021;107:152235. doi: 10.1016/j.comppsych. 2021.152235.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7946536</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33765493</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Çavuşoğlu E, Yurtsever S. The relationship between health perceptions and health anxiety levels of nursing department students: A descriptive study. Turkiye Klinikleri J Nurs Sci. 2022;14:171–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akman Ö, Yildirim D, Sarikaya A, Akman Ö, Yildirim D, Sarikaya A. The effect of COVID-19 pandemic on nursing students’ anxiety levels. IGUSABDER. 2020;12:379–97.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Albaqawi HM, Alquwez N, Balay-odao E, Bajet JB, Alabdulaziz H, Alsolami F, et al. Nursing students’ perceptions, knowledge, and preventive behaviors toward COVID-19: A multi-university study. Front Public Health. 2020;8:573390. doi: 10.3389/fpubh. 2020.573390.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7786242</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33425830</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernández IAM, Moreno SC, Díaz LC, Gallegos-Torres RM, Fernández JAM, Martínez EKH. Fear, stress, and knowledge regarding COVID-19 in nursing students and recent graduates in Mexico. Invest Educ Enferm. 2021;39:1–12. doi: 10.17533/udea.iee.v39n1e05.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7987291</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33687809</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kochuvilayil T, Fernandez RS, Moxham LJ, Lord H, Alomari A, Hunt L, et al. COVID-19: Knowledge, anxiety, academic concerns and preventative behaviours among Australian and Indian undergraduate nursing students: A cross-sectional study. J Clin Nurs. 2021;30:882–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8013450</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33434378</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun Y, Wang D, Han Z, Gao J, Zhu S, Zhang H. Disease prevention knowledge, anxiety, and professional ıdentity during COVID-19 pandemic in nursing students in Zhengzhou, China. J Korean Acad Nurs. 2020;50:533–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32895340</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ayed A, Zabn K. Knowledge and attitude towards COVID-19 among nursing students: Palestinian perspective. SAGE Open Nurs. 2021;7:23779608211015150. doi: 10.1177/23779608211015150.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8127755</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34036173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olaimat AN, Aolymat I, Shahbaz HM, Holley RA. Knowledge and ınformation sources about COVID-19 among university students in Jordan: A cross-sectional study. Front Public Health. 2020;8:254.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7274134</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32574314</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gohel KH, Patel PB, Shah PM, Patel JR, Pandit N, Raut A. Knowledge and perceptions about COVID-19 among the medical and allied health science students in India: An online cross-sectional survey. Clin Epidemiol Glob Health. 2021;9:104–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7420087</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32838066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mena-Tudela D, González-Chordá VM, Andreu-Pejó L, Mouzo-Bellés VM, Cervera-Gasch Á. Spanish nursing and medical students’ knowledge, confidence and willingness about COVID-19: A cross-sectional study. Nurse Educ Today. 2021;103:104957. doi: 10.1016/j.nedt.2021.104957.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8118698</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34015678</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fakhri N, Jallal M, Belabbes S, Khudur K, Kaddar R, Oubaasri A, et al. COVID-19 and Moroccan nursing students: A multicentre cross-sectional survey on their related knowledge, attitudes and practices. Nurs Open. 2021;8:1634–41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8186718</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33675185</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aksu A, Buldum A, G Emül T, Çelebioğlu A. Nursing students’ knowledge and practices about COVID-19: A cross-sectional survey. Nurs Forum (Auckl) 2022;57:615–23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9115445</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35332534</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>