<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39307542</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>22</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1365-2923</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>22</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Medical education</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Med Educ</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Exploring institutional stratification: Minority-serving institutional pathways to medical school acceptance in the United States.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/medu.15539</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Recruiting and training a diverse pool of physicians from historically excluded groups is vital to solving complex scientific problems and increasing access to patient care. Disparate educational and health outcomes of COVID-19 amplified this need. In stratified higher education systems, underfunded institutions that serve greater numbers of underrepresented in medicine (URM) students face unique barriers to entering physician training. However, pathways from historically underfunded minority-serving institutions (MSIs) in the United States to medical school (MD) are not well understood.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHOD" NlmCategory="METHODS">A hierarchical logistic regression analysis of 328 488 de-identified applicants to US MD-granting medical schools for academic years 2017-2018 through 2022-2023 was used to determine predictors of acceptance based on MSI attendance compared to predominantly White institutions (PWI) and other literature-informed predictors. An interrupted time series analysis determined the significance in changes in observed differences in application acceptance before and after the COVID-19 pandemic.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">In model 1, MSI attendance was associated with significantly lower odds of acceptance, with a 42% to 52% chance of acceptance compared to PWI applicants. Adding MCAT and GPA significantly increased odds of acceptance for most MSI applicants in model 2. MSI attendance, MCAT, GPA and socio-economic status indicators were useful predictors, improving the acceptance model by 39% better than the null model. Although some predictors showed a change in odds over time, none changed significantly when comparing before and after COVID-19.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DISCUSSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">MSI attending students were less likely to be admitted to MD programmes, highlighting systemic stratification until other academic factors were introduced to the model that alleviated lower odds, and the COVID-19 pandemic did not substantially change these trends. Improved pathways and strengthened institutional relationships between institutions that have greater proportions of underrepresented students and medical schools may help improve MSI applicant odds furthering diversity within the physician-trained workforce.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Medical Education published by Association for the Study of Medical Education and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Burbage</LastName><ForeName>Amanda K</ForeName><Initials>AK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Macon &amp; Joan Brock Virginia Health Sciences at Old Dominion University, School of Health Professions, Eastern Virginia Medical School, Norfolk, Virginia, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hewitt</LastName><ForeName>Eushekia Y</ForeName><Initials>EY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Student Affairs in the Macon &amp; Joan Brock Virginia Health Sciences at Old Dominion University, Eastern Virginia Medical School, Norfolk, Virginia, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Med Educ</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7605655</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0308-0110</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>20</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39307542</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/medu.15539</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>United States Department of State. Understanding U.S. higher education [cited 2024 August]. https://educationusa.state.gov/foreign-institutions-and-governments/understanding-us-higher-education</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor BJ, Cantwell B. Unequal Higher Education: Wealth, Status, and Student Opportunity. Rutgers University Press; 2019. doi:10.36019/9780813593531</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Posselt JR, Jaquette O, Bielby R, Bastedo MN. Access without equity: longitudinal analyses of institutional stratification by race and ethnicity, 1972–2004. Am Educ Res J. 2012;49(6):1074‐1111. doi:10.3102/0002831212439456</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hendrickson RM, Lane JE, Harris JT, Dorman RH. Academic Leadership and Governance of Higher Education: A Guide for Trustees, Leaders, and Aspiring Leaders of Two‐ and Four‐Year Institutions. Stylus Publishing, LLC; 2013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osei Z. Low‐income and minority students are growing share of enrollments, and 2 other takeaways from new study. Chron High Educ. 2019 [cited 2024 July 4]. https://www.chronicle.com/article/low-income-and-minority-students-are-growing-share-of-enrollments-and-2-other-takeaways-from-new-study/?sra=true</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martinho AM. Becoming a doctor in Europe: objective selection systems. AMA J Ethics. 2012;14(12):984‐988.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Posselt JR, Grodsky E. Graduate education and social stratification. Annu Rev Sociol. 2017;43(1):353‐378. doi:10.1146/annurev‐soc‐081715‐074324</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sesate DB. A Matthew effect?: undergraduate institutional prestige, admission to medical school, and medically underserved communities.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marsh CD. Does Major Matter? An Examination of Undergraduate Major and Medical School Admission. Temple University; 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gay SE, Santen SA, Mangrulkar RS, Sisson TH, Ross PT, Zaidi NL. The influence of MCAT and GPA preadmission academic metrics on interview scores. Adv Health Sci Educ Theory Pract. 2018;23(1):151‐158. doi:10.1007/s10459‐017‐9779‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hanson JT, Busche K, Elks ML, et al. The validity of MCAT scores in predicting students' performance and progress in medical school: results from a multisite study. Acad Med. 2022;97(9):1374‐1384. doi:10.1097/ACM.0000000000004754</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Violato C, Gauer JL, Violato EM, Patel D. A study of the validity of the new MCAT exam. Acad Med. 2020;95(3):396‐400. doi:10.1097/ACM.0000000000003064</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perez MA, Williams C, Henderson K, et al. Association of applicant demographic factors with medical school acceptance. BMC Med Educ. 2023;23(1):960. doi:10.1186/s12909‐023‐04897‐8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weber M. Economy and society. 1922.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bourdieu P, Passeron JC. Reproduction in education, culture and society. 1977.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Triventi M. Stratification in higher education and its relationship with social inequality: a comparative study of 11 European countries. Eur Sociol Rev. 2013;29(3):489‐502. doi:10.1093/esr/jcr092</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marginson S. The worldwide trend to high participation higher education: dynamics of social stratification in inclusive systems. High Educ. 2016;72(4):413‐434. doi:10.1007/s10734‐016‐0016‐x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smeeding TM. Public policy, economic inequality, and poverty: the United States in comparative perspective. Soc Sci Q. 2005;86(s1):955‐983. doi:10.1111/j.0038‐4941.2005.00331.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Office of Postsecondary Education. Institutional service: U.S. Department of Education. 2023 [updated 2023 August 9; cited 2024 May 7]. https://www2.ed.gov/about/offices/list/ope/idues/index.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Department of Education. Title III part AS programs ‐ strengthening institutions funding status 2023. [cited 2024 May 7]. https://www2.ed.gov/programs/iduestitle3a/funding.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>About Hispanic‐Serving Institutions. [cited 2024 August 2]. www.hacu.net</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Excelencia in Education. Hispanic‐serving institutions (HSIs): 2021–22 fact sheet. 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Excelencia in Education. Diversity at HSIs. 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Postsecondary National Policy Institute. Asian American and Native American Pacific Islander serving institutions. 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fountain JH. The higher education act (HEA): A primer Congressional Research Service. 2023. Report No.: R43351 Contract No.: R43351.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elhage R, Laosebikan O, Black‐Parker K. Alumni perceptions of the educational benefits of their graduate degrees from a PBI. J Eff Teach Higher Ed. 2022;5(2):93‐122. doi:10.36021/jethe.v5i2.268</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>MSI Data Project. Msis 2023 [updated 2023 May 7; cited 2024 May 7]. https://www.msidata.org/msis</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Capers IQ, Way DP. Academic and post‐graduate performance of African American medical students by category of premed institution: historically black vs. predominantly white institutions. J Health Care Poor Underserved. 2015;26(3):617‐630. doi:10.1353/hpu.2015.0082</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin J, Samels JE. Turnaround: Leading Stressed Colleges and Universities to Excellence. 1st ed. Johns Hopkins University Press; 2009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toldson IA. The funding gap between historically black colleges and universities and traditionally white institutions needs to be addressed* (editor's commentary). J Negro Educ. 2016;85(2):97‐100. doi:10.7709/jnegroeducation.85.2.0097</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cunningham A, Park E, Engle J. Minority‐serving institutions: doing more with less. https://live-ihep-wp.pantheonsite.io/publication/minority-serving-institutions-doing-more-with-less/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sav GT. Separate and unequal: state financing of historically black colleges and universities. J Blacks High Educ. 1997;15(15):101‐104. doi:10.2307/2962709</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fischer K. When everyone goes to college: a lesson from South Korea. Chron High Educ. 2016 [cited 2024 July 4]. https://www.chronicle.com/article/when-everyone-goes-to-college-a-lesson-from-south-korea/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Espinosa L, Kelchen R, Taylor M. Minority serving institutions as engines of upward mobility. 2018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Academies of Sciences E, and Medicine. MSIs and the students they serve. In: Espinosa KM LL, Jackson LM, eds. Minority Serving Institutions: America's Underutilized Resource for Strengthening the STEM Workforce. National Academies Press; 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Espinosa LL, Turk JM, Taylor M. Pulling back the curtain: enrollment and outcomes at minority serving institutions. 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tai DBG, Sia IG, Doubeni CA, Wieland ML. Disproportionate impact of COVID‐19 on racial and ethnic minority groups in the United States: a 2021 update. J Racial Ethn Health Disparities. 2021;9(6):2334‐2339. doi:10.1007/s40615‐021‐01170‐w</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weiss J, Holaday L, Keene D, et al. Perspectives of historically black college and university advisors to premedical students during the COVID‐19 pandemic: a qualitative study. JAMA Netw Open. 2022;5(10):e2238563. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.38563</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lederer AM, Hoban MT, Lipson SK, Zhou S, Eisenberg D. More than inconvenienced: the unique needs of US college students during the COVID‐19 pandemic. Health Educ Behav. 2021;48(1):14‐19. doi:10.1177/1090198120969372</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhai Y, Du X. Addressing collegiate mental health amid COVID‐19 pandemic. Psychiatry Res. 2020;288:113003. doi:10.1016/j.psychres.2020.113003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goldrick‐Rab S, Coca V, Kienzl G, Welton CR, Dahl S, Magnelia S. #realcollege during the pandemic: new evidence on basic needs insecurity and student well‐being. 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bell T, Aubele JW, Perruso C. Digital divide issues affecting undergraduates at a Hispanic‐serving institution during the pandemic: a mixed‐methods approach. Educ Sci. 2022;12(2):115. doi:10.3390/educsci12020115</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barber PH, Shapiro C, Jacobs MS, et al. Disparities in remote learning faced by first‐generation and underrepresented minority students during COVID‐19: insights and opportunities from a remote research experience. J Microbio Biol Educ. 2021;22(1):1‐10. doi:10.1128/jmbe.v22i1.2457</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackson CS, Gracia JN. Addressing health and health‐care disparities: the role of a diverse workforce and the social determinants of health. Public Health Rep. 2014;129(1):57‐61. doi:10.1177/00333549141291S211</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilbur K, Snyder C, Essary AC, Reddy S, Will KK, Mary S. Developing workforce diversity in the health professions: a social justice perspective. Health Prof Educ. 2020;6(2):222‐229. doi:10.1016/j.hpe.2020.01.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>AAMC. Table a‐10: applicants to U.S. MD‐granting medical schools by race/ethnicity (alone) and state of legal residence, 2022–2023. In: AAMC, editor. 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>AAMC. Table a‐11: matriculants to U.S. M‐granting medical schools by race/ethnicity (alone) and state of legal residence, 2022–2023. In: AAMC, editor. 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morris DB, Gruppuso PA, McGee HA, Murillo AL, Grover A, Adashi EY. Diversity of the national medical student body—four decades of inequities. New Engl J Med. 2021;384(17):1661‐1668. doi:10.1056/NEJMsr2028487</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robinett K, Kareem R, Reavis K, Quezada S. A multi‐ pronged, antiracist approach to optimize equity in medical school admissions. Med Educ. 2021;55(12):1342‐1344. doi:10.1111/medu.14589</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gasman M, Smith T, Ye C, Nguyen T. HBCUs and the production of doctors. AIMS Public Health. 2017;4(6):579‐589. doi:10.3934/publichealth.2017.6.579</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>AAMC. Percentage of all active physicians by race/ethnicity, 2018. 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salsberg E, Richwine C, Westergaard S, et al. Estimation and comparison of current and future racial/ethnic representation in the US health care workforce. JAMA Netw Open. 2021;4(3):e213789. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.3789</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakae S, Porfeli EJ, Davis D, et al. Enrollment management in undergraduate medical school admissions: a complementary framework to holistic review for increasing diversity in medicine. Acad Med. 2021;96(4):501‐506. doi:10.1097/ACM.0000000000003866</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kreiter CD, Axelson RD. A perspective on medical school admission research and practice over the last 25 years. Teach Learn Med. 2013;25(sup1):S50‐S56. doi:10.1080/10401334.2013.842910</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kelly‐Blake K, Garrison NA, Fletcher FE, et al. Rationales for expanding minority physician representation in the workforce: a scoping review. Med Educ. 2018;52(9):925‐935. doi:10.1111/medu.13618</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Celletti F, Reynolds TA, Wright A, Stoertz A, Dayrit M. Educating a new generation of doctors to improve the health of populations in low‐ and middle‐income countries. PLoS Med. 2011;8(10):e1001108. doi:10.1371/journal.pmed.1001108</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>US Census Bureau. Quick facts [Internet]. Washington (DC): Department of Commerce (US); [reviewed 2024 Jul 17; cited 2024 Jul 17]. https://www.census.gov/quickfacts/fact/table/US/PST045223#PST045223</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pregibon D. Logistic regression diagnostics. Ann Stat. 1981;9(4):705‐724. doi:10.1214/aos/1176345513</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keith TZ. Multiple Regression and Beyond: An Introduction to Multiple Regression and Structural Equation Modeling. Routledge; 2014. doi:10.4324/9781315749099</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng C‐YJ, Lee KL, Ingersoll GM. An introduction to logistic regression analysis and reporting. J Educ Res. 2002;96(1):3‐14. doi:10.1080/00220670209598786</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bernal JL, Cummins S, Gasparrini A. Interrupted time series regression for the evaluation of public health interventions: a tutorial. Int J Epidemiol. 2017;46(1):348‐355. doi:10.1093/ije/dyw098</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nelson BK. Time series analysis using autoregressive integrated moving average (ARIMA) models. Acad Emerg Med. 1998;5(7):739‐744. doi:10.1111/j.1553‐2712.1998.tb02493.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nickerson CA, Brown NJ. Simpson's paradox is suppression, but LDord's paradox is neither: clarification of and correction to Tu, Gunnell, and Gilthorpe (2008). Emerg Themes Epidemiol. 2019;16(1):1‐11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ko M, Henderson MC, Fancher TL, London MR, Simon M, Hardeman RR. US medical school admissions leaders' experiences with barriers to and advancements in diversity, equity, and inclusion. JAMA Netw Open. 2023;6(2):e2254928. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.54928</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lucey CR, Saguil A. The consequences of structural racism on MCAT scores and medical school admissions: the past is prologue. Acad Med. 2020;95(3):351‐356. doi:10.1097/ACM.0000000000002939</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liaison Committee on Medical Education (LCME) annual questionnaire part II, 219–1010 through 2021‐2022; 2024. Pathway programs at medical school programs.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mayrath M, Fontanez D, Abdelbaset F, Lenihan B, Lenihan D. Increasing diversity in the physician workforce: pathway programs and predictive analytics. Acad Med. 2023;98(10):1154‐1158. doi:10.1097/ACM.0000000000005287</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kost A, Evans D, Dobie S, Sanders E. What is the impact of the underserved pathway program on graduates entering an underserved family medicine residency? Five‐year findings from the University of Washington School of Medicine. Acad Med. 2018;93(7):1042‐1047. doi:10.1097/ACM.0000000000002073</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freeman BK, Landry A, Trevino R, Grande D, Shea JA. Understanding the leaky pipeline: perceived barriers to pursuing a career in medicine or dentistry among underrepresented‐in‐medicine undergraduate students. Acad Med. 2016;91(7):987‐993. doi:10.1097/ACM.0000000000001020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pearson J, Giacumo LA, Farid A, Sadegh M. A systematic multiple studies review of low‐income, first‐generation, and underrepresented, STEM‐degree support programs: emerging evidence‐based models and recommendations. Educ Sci. 2022;12(5):333. doi:10.3390/educsci12050333</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Center for Science and Engineering Statistics. Diversity and STEM: women, minorities, and persons with disabilities 2023. Alexandria, VA: National Science Foundation; 2023. Contract No.: NSF 23‐315.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Students for Fair Admissions, Inc. v. President and fellows of Harvard College. 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>AAMC. Diversity in medical school admissions 2023. [cited 2024 May 7]. https://www.aamc.org/about‐us/mission‐areas/medical‐education/diversity‐medical‐school‐admissions</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gustafson CE, Johnson CJ, Beck Dallaghan GL, et al. Evaluating situational judgment test use and diversity in admissions at a southern US medical school. PLoS ONE. 2023;18(2):e0280205. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0280205</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoon H, Yang Y, Morewedge CK. Early cost realization and college choice. J Mark Res. 2022;59(1):136‐152. doi:10.1177/00222437211026337</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>