<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39307567</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>22</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1758-0854</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>22</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Applied psychology. Health and well-being</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Appl Psychol Health Well Being</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Understanding internal dynamics of state anxiety during COVID-19 pandemic: Seven-wave longitudinal findings via panel network analysis.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/aphw.12599</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Research on state anxiety has long been dominated by the traditional psychometric approach that assumes anxiety symptoms have a common cause. Yet state anxiety can be conceptualized as a network system. In this study, we utilized data from the COVID-Dynamic dataset from waves 7 to 13, collected at three-week intervals from June 6, 2020, to October 13, 2020, and included 1,042 valid participants to characterize the internal dynamics of state anxiety. Using the Gaussian graphical model along with strength centrality, we estimated three network models of state anxiety. The between-subjects and contemporaneous network showed numerous positive relations between items and some unexpected negative relations. Three communities were identified in the between-subjects network, and two communities were identified in the contemporaneous network. The temporal network showed the coexistence of positive and negative predictions between items after three weeks. Several items exhibited significant positive autocorrelations after three weeks. These findings have implications for anxiety theory and clinical interventions at between-subjects and within-subjects levels.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 International Association of Applied Psychology.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Yimei</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0007-3600-9348</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Computational Communication Collaboratory, School of Journalism and Communication, Nanjing University, Nanjing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ma</LastName><ForeName>Zhihao</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7983-4136</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Computational Communication Collaboratory, School of Journalism and Communication, Nanjing University, Nanjing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>19ZDA324</GrantID><Agency>Major Project of The National Social Science Fund of China</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Appl Psychol Health Well Being</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101502957</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1758-0854</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Gaussian graphical model</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">STAI</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">panel network analysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">state anxiety</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>21</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39307567</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/aphw.12599</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Addolorato, G., Ancona, C., Capristo, E., Graziosetto, R., Di Rienzo, L., Maurizi, M., &amp; Gasbarrini, G. (1999). State and trait anxiety in women affected by allergic and vasomotor rhinitis. Journal of Psychosomatic Research, 46(3), 283–289.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bar‐Tal, D., &amp; Jacobson, D. (1998). A psychological perspective on security. Applied Psychology, 47(1), 59–71.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beard, C., Millner, A. J., Forgeard, M. J. C., Fried, E. I., Hsu, K. J., Treadway, M. T., Leonard, C. V., Kertz, S. J., &amp; Björgvinsson, T. (2016). Network analysis of depression and anxiety symptom relationships in a psychiatric sample. Psychological Medicine, 46(16), 3,359–3,369.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Behar, E., DiMarco, I. D., Hekler, E. B., Mohlman, J., &amp; Staples, A. M. (2009). Current theoretical models of generalized anxiety disorder (GAD): Conceptual review and treatment implications. Journal of Anxiety Disorders, 23(8), 1011–1023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borsboom, D. (2017). A network theory of mental disorders. World Psychiatry, 16(1), 5–13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borsboom, D., &amp; Cramer, A. O. J. (2013). Network analysis: An integrative approach to the structure of psychopathology. Annual Review of Clinical Psychology, 9(1), 91–121.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bringmann, L. F., Albers, C., Bockting, C., Borsboom, D., Ceulemans, E., Cramer, A., Epskamp, S., Eronen, M. I., Hamaker, E., Kuppens, P., Lutz, W., McNally, R. J., Molenaar, P., Tio, P., Voelkle, M. C., &amp; Wichers, M. (2022). Psychopathological networks: Theory, methods and practice. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 149, 104011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buechner, H., Toparlak, S. M., Ostinelli, E. G., Shokraneh, F., Nicholls‐Mindlin, J., Cipriani, A., Geddes, J. R., &amp; Syed Sheriff, R. (2023). Community interventions for anxiety and depression in adults and young people: A systematic review. Australian &amp; New Zealand Journal of Psychiatry, 57(9), 1223–1242.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Christensen, H., Pallister, E., Smale, S., Hickie, I. B., &amp; Calear, A. L. (2010). Community‐based prevention programs for anxiety and depression in youth: A systematic review. The Journal of Primary Prevention, 31(3), 139–170.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Contreras, A., Blanchard, M. A., Mouguiama‐Daouda, C., &amp; Heeren, A. (2024). When eco‐anger (but not eco‐anxiety nor eco‐sadness) makes you change! A temporal network approach to the emotional experience of climate change. Journal of Anxiety Disorders, 102, 102822.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daly, M. (2021). Psychological distress and adaptation to the COVID‐19 crisis in the United States. Journal of Psychiatric Research, 136, 603–609.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davis, W. B., &amp; Thaut, M. H. (1989). The influence of preferred relaxing music on measures of state anxiety, relaxation, and physiological responses. Journal of Music Therapy, 26(4), 168–187.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doron, J., Thomas‐Ollivier, V., Vachon, H., &amp; Fortes‐Bourbousson, M. (2013). Relationships between cognitive coping, self‐esteem, anxiety and depression: A cluster‐analysis approach. Personality and Individual Differences, 55, 515–520.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elliott, D., Polman, R., &amp; McGregor, R. (2011). Relaxing music for anxiety control. Journal of Music Therapy, 48(3), 264–288.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Endler, N. S., &amp; Kocovski, N. L. (2001). State and trait anxiety revisited. Journal of Anxiety Disorders, 15(3), 231–245.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Epskamp, S. (2020). Psychometric network models from time‐series and panel data. Psychometrika, 85(1), 206–231.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Epskamp, S., Borsboom, D., &amp; Fried, E. I. (2018). Estimating psychological networks and their accuracy: A tutorial paper. Behavior Research Methods, 50(1), 18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Epskamp, S., Waldorp, L. J., Mõttus, R., &amp; Borsboom, D. (2018). The Gaussian graphical model in cross‐sectional and time‐series data. Multivariate Behavioral Research, 53(4), 453–480.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fisher, A. J., Reeves, J. W., Lawyer, G., Medaglia, J. D., &amp; Rubel, J. A. (2017). Exploring the idiographic dynamics of mood and anxiety via network analysis. Journal of Abnormal Psychology, 126(8), 1,044–1,056.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freichel, R., Veer, I., Wiers, R., McNally, R. J., &amp; Epskamp, S. (2023). Cross‐lagged panel models for studying psychopathology: A comparative overview of structural equation and panel network approaches.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fried, E. I., Papanikolaou, F., &amp; Epskamp, S. (2022). Mental health and social contact during the COVID‐19 pandemic: An ecological momentary assessment study. Clinical Psychological Science, 10(2), 340–354.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gathier, A. W., Van Tuijl, L. A., Penninx, B. W. J. H., De Jong, P. J., Van Oppen, P. C., Vinkers, C. H., &amp; Verhoeven, J. E. (2024). The role of explicit and implicit self‐esteem in the relationship between childhood trauma and adult depression and anxiety. Journal of Affective Disorders, S0165032724004518.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gou, Z., &amp; Ma, Z. (2023). Dynamic structure of posttraumatic growth among victims of the 2021 Henan floods: A 6‐month, three‐wave longitudinal study. Applied Psychology: Health and Well‐Being, 15, 1372–1390.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gruber, J., Prinstein, M. J., Clark, L. A., Rottenberg, J., Abramowitz, J. S., Albano, A. M., Aldao, A., Borelli, J. L., Chung, T., Davila, J., Forbes, E. E., Gee, D. G., Hall, G. C. N., Hallion, L. S., Hinshaw, S. P., Hofmann, S. G., Hollon, S. D., Joormann, J., Kazdin, A. E., … Weinstock, L. M. (2021). Mental health and clinical psychological science in the time of COVID‐19: Challenges, opportunities, and a call to action. American Psychologist, 76(3), 409.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han, Y., Fan, J., Wang, X., Xia, J., Liu, X., Zhou, H., Zhang, Y., &amp; Zhu, X. (2020). Factor structure and gender invariance of Chinese version state–trait anxiety inventory (form Y) in university students. Frontiers in Psychology, 11, 2228.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heeren, A., Bernstein, E. E., &amp; McNally, R. J. (2018). Deconstructing trait anxiety: A network perspective. Anxiety, Stress, &amp; Coping, 31(3), 262–276.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Helms‐Lorenz, M., &amp; Maulana, R. (2016). Influencing the psychological well‐being of beginning teachers across three years of teaching: Self‐efficacy, stress causes, job tension and job discontent. Educational Psychology, 36(3), 569–594.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoffart, A., Burger, J., Johnson, S. U., &amp; Ebrahimi, O. V. (2023). Daily dynamics and mechanisms of anxious symptomatology in the general population: A network study during the COVID‐19 pandemic. Journal of Anxiety Disorders, 93, 102658.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ilardi, C. R., Gamboz, N., Iavarone, A., Chieffi, S., &amp; Brandimonte, M. A. (2021). Psychometric properties of the STAI‐Y scales and normative data in an Italian elderly population. Aging Clinical and Experimental Research, 33(10), 2,759–2,766.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jordan, D. G., Winer, E. S., &amp; Salem, T. (2020). The current status of temporal network analysis for clinical science: Considerations as the paradigm shifts? Journal of Clinical Psychology, 76(9), 1,591–1,612.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, S., Hong, S., Park, D.‐H., Ryu, S.‐H., Ha, J. H., &amp; Jeon, H. J. (2024). Temperament clusters in patients with panic disorder in relation to character maturity. Psychiatry Investigation, 21(2), 174–180.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kvaal, K., Laake, K., &amp; Engedal, K. (2001). Psychometric properties of the state part of the Spielberger state–trait anxiety inventory (STAI) in geriatric patients. International Journal of Geriatric Psychiatry, 16(10), 980–986.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lauderdale, S. A., Martin, K. J., &amp; Moore, J. (2019). Aversive indecisiveness predicts risks for and symptoms of anxiety and depression over avoidant indecisiveness. Journal of Rational‐Emotive &amp; Cognitive‐Behavior Therapy, 37(1), 62–83.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lauderdale, S. A., &amp; Oakes, K. (2021). Factor structure of the revised indecisiveness scale and association with risks for and symptoms of anxiety, depression, and attentional control. Journal of Rational‐Emotive &amp; Cognitive‐Behavior Therapy, 39(2), 256–284.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, H. C. W., Wong, M. L. E., &amp; Lopez, V. (2008). Factorial structure of the Chinese version of the state anxiety scale for children (short form). Journal of Clinical Nursing, 17(13), 1762–1770.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, Y., Zhao, J., Ma, Z., McReynolds, L. S., Lin, D., Chen, Z., Wang, T., Wang, D., Zhang, Y., Zhang, J., Fan, F., &amp; Liu, X. (2021). Mental health among college students during the COVID‐19 pandemic in China: A 2‐wave longitudinal survey. Journal of Affective Disorders, 281, 597–604.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lian, H., Li, J., Du, C., Wu, W., Xia, Y., &amp; Lee, C. (2022). Disaster or opportunity? How COVID‐19‐associated changes in environmental uncertainty and job insecurity relate to organizational identification and performance. Journal of Applied Psychology, 107(5), 693–706.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manzoni, G. M., Pagnini, F., Castelnuovo, G., &amp; Molinari, E. (2008). Relaxation training for anxiety: A ten‐years systematic review with meta‐analysis. BMC Psychiatry, 8(1), 41.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meijer, J. (2001). Stress in the relation between trait and state anxiety. Psychological Reports, 88, 947–964.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moshagen, M., &amp; Bader, M. (2023). semPower: General power analysis for structural equation models. Behavior Research Methods, 56(4), 2,901–2,922.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mõttus, R., &amp; Rozgonjuk, D. (2021). Development is in the details: Age differences in the big five domains, facets, and nuances. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 120(4), 1,035–1,048.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mullen, R., &amp; Jones, E. S. (2021). Network analysis of competitive state anxiety. Frontiers in Psychology, 11, 586976.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oei, T. P. S., Evans, L., &amp; Crook, G. M. (1990). Utility and validity of the STAI with anxiety disorder patients. British Journal of Clinical Psychology, 29(4), 429–432.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okan, O., Bollweg, T. M., Berens, E.‐M., Hurrelmann, K., Bauer, U., &amp; Schaeffer, D. (2020). Coronavirus‐related health literacy: A cross‐sectional study in adults during the COVID‐19 Infodemic in Germany. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, 17(15), 5,503.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pons, P., &amp; Latapy, M. (2006). Computing communities in large networks using random walks. Journal of Graph Algorithms and Applications, 10(2), 191–218.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rusch, T., Han, Y., Liang, D., Hopkins, A. R., Lawrence, C. V., Maoz, U., Paul, L. K., Stanley, D. A., the COVID‐Dynamic Team, Adolphs, R., Alvarez, R. M., Camplisson, I., Harrison, L., Hien, D., Lan, T., Lin, C., Lopez‐Castro, T., Nizzic, M.‐C., Golden, A. R., … Yaffe, G. (2023). COVID‐dynamic: A large‐scale longitudinal study of socioemotional and behavioral change across the pandemic. Scientific Data, 10(1), 71.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santangelo, G., Sacco, R., Siciliano, M., Bisecco, A., Muzzo, G., Docimo, R., De Stefano, M., Bonavita, S., Lavorgna, L., Tedeschi, G., Trojano, L., &amp; Gallo, A. (2016). Anxiety in multiple sclerosis: Psychometric properties of the state–trait anxiety inventory. Acta Neurologica Scandinavica, 134(6), 458–466.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Savolainen, I., Oksa, R., Savela, N., Celuch, M., &amp; Oksanen, A. (2021). COVID‐19 anxiety—A longitudinal survey study of psychological and situational risks among Finnish workers. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, 18(2), 794.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scott, K. M., Wells, J. E., Angermeyer, M., Brugha, T. S., Bromet, E., Demyttenaere, K., De Girolamo, G., Gureje, O., Haro, J. M., Jin, R., Karam, A. N., Kovess, V., Lara, C., Levinson, D., Ormel, J., Posada‐Villa, J., Sampson, N., Takeshima, T., Zhang, M., &amp; Kessler, R. C. (2010). Gender and the relationship between marital status and first onset of mood, anxiety and substance use disorders. Psychological Medicine, 40(9), 1495–1505.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shek, D. T. L. (1988). Reliability and factorial structure of the Chinese version of the state–trait anxiety inventory. Journal of Psychopathology and Behavioral Assessment, 10(4), 303–317.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spielberger, C. D. (1983). Manual for the state–trait anxiety inventory (form Y) (“self‐evaluation questionnaire”). Consulting Psychologists Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spielberger, C. D. (Ed.). (2013). Anxiety and behavior. Academic press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang, J., &amp; Gibson, S. J. (2005). A psychophysical evaluation of the relationship between trait anxiety, pain perception, and induced state anxiety. The Journal of Pain, 6(9), 612–619.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tovilovic, S., Novovic, Z., Mihic, L., &amp; Jovanovic, V. (2009). The role of trait anxiety in induction of state anxiety. Psihologija, 42(4), 491–504.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vermote, B., Waterschoot, J., Morbée, S., Van Der Kaap‐Deeder, J., Schrooyen, C., Soenens, B., Ryan, R., &amp; Vansteenkiste, M. (2022). Do psychological needs play a role in times of uncertainty? Associations with well‐being during the COVID‐19 crisis. Journal of Happiness Studies, 23(1), 257–283.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vigneau, F., &amp; Cormier, S. (2008). The factor structure of the state–trait anxiety inventory: An alternative view. Journal of Personality Assessment, 90(3), 280–285.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vitasari, P., Wahab, M. N. A., Herawan, T., Othman, A., &amp; Sinnadurai, S. K. (2011). Re‐test of state trait anxiety inventory (STAI) among engineering students in Malaysia: Reliability and validity tests. Procedia ‐ Social and Behavioral Sciences, 15, 3,843–3,848.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Z., Luo, S., Xu, J., Wang, Y., Yun, H., Zhao, Z., Zhan, H., &amp; Wang, Y. (2021). Well‐being reduces COVID‐19 anxiety: A three‐wave longitudinal study in China. Journal of Happiness Studies, 22(8), 3,593–3,610.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wells, A. (1994). A multi‐dimensional measure of worry: Development and preliminary validation of the anxious thoughts inventory. Anxiety, Stress and Coping, 6(4), 289–299.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wells, A. (1995). Meta‐cognition and worry: A cognitive model of generalized anxiety disorder. Behavioural and Cognitive Psychotherapy, 23(3), 301–320.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wills‐Herrera, E., Orozco, L. E., Forero‐Pineda, C., Pardo, O., &amp; Andonova, V. (2011). The relationship between perceptions of insecurity, social capital and subjective well‐being: Empirical evidences from areas of rural conflict in Colombia. The Journal of Socio‐Economics, 40(1), 88–96.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, Y., Zhang, T., Ye, Z., Chen, K., Kuijp, J. V. D., Sun, X., Han, G., Zhao, Y., Liu, Y., &amp; Huang, L. (2022). Public anxiety through various stages of COVID‐19 coping: Evidence from China. PLOS One, 17(6), e0270229.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yim, Y.‐R., Lee, K.‐E., Park, D.‐J., Kim, S.‐H., Nah, S.‐S., Lee, J. H., Kim, S.‐K., Lee, Y.‐A., Hong, S.‐J., Kim, H.‐S., Lee, H.‐S., Kim, H. A., Joung, C.‐I., Kim, S.‐H., &amp; Lee, S.‐S. (2017). Identifying fibromyalgia subgroups using cluster analysis: Relationships with clinical variables. European Journal of Pain, 21(2), 374–384.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>