<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39309817</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2405-8440</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>18</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>30</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Heliyon</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Heliyon</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Clinical data and quantitative CT parameters combined with machine learning to predict short-term prognosis of severe COVID-19 in the elderly.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e37096</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e37096</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e37096</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e37096</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="RATIONALE AND OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This study aims to evaluate the effectiveness of integrating clinical data and quantitative CT parameters with machine learning techniques in forecasting the short-term outcomes of severe COVID-19 in elderly patients.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIALS AND METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">In this retrospective study, we analyzed the clinical profiles and chest quantitative CT parameters of 239 elderly patients with severe COVID-19 admitted for treatment. The cohort included 61 deceased patients (death group) and 178 who recovered and were discharged (survival group). The participants were randomly assigned into a training group (n = 167) and a validation group (n = 72). Quantitative CT parameters were measured using the 3D-Slicer software. Univariate and multivariate logistic regression analyses identified independent risk factors for mortality. Predictive models were developed employing four machine learning algorithms: Logistic Regression (LR), Random Forest (RF), Decision Tree (DT), and Support Vector Machine (SVM).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Both univariate and multivariate logistic regression analyses revealed age, hypersensitive C-reactive protein (hs-CRP), and solid organ volume percentage (SOV%) as independent predictors of mortality. The Area Under the Curve (AUC) values for the LR, RF, DT, and SVM models in the training group were 0.795, 0.726, 0.854, and 0.589, respectively; for the validation group, they were 0.817, 0.634, 0.869, and 0.754, respectively. The DT algorithm outperformed other models in both the training and validation groups, emerging as the most effective predictive model in this study.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The combination of clinical data and quantitative CT parameters with machine learning approaches is highly valuable in predicting the short-term prognosis of severe COVID-19 in the elderly. Among the various models tested, the Decision Tree algorithm-based model proved to be the most accurate and reliable in this context.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fan</LastName><ForeName>Lifang</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Medical Imageology, Wannan Medical College, Wuhu, Anhui, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wu</LastName><ForeName>Shujian</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, Yijishan Hospital of Wannan Medical College, Wuhu, Anhui, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wu</LastName><ForeName>Yimin</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Ultrasound, WuHu Hospital, East China Normal University (The Second People's Hospital, WuHu), Wuhu, Anhui, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Xiaoyan</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Medical Imageology, Wannan Medical College, Wuhu, Anhui, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Zhengyuan</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Medical Imageology, Wannan Medical College, Wuhu, Anhui, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huang</LastName><ForeName>Lei</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Medical Imageology, Wannan Medical College, Wuhu, Anhui, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Guoxian</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Clinical Medicine, Wannan Medical College, Wuhu, Anhui, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>07</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Heliyon</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101672560</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2405-8440</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Machine learning</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Quantitative CT</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>29</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>55</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39309817</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11415644</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e37096</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2405-8440(24)13127-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Wu F., Liu M., Wang A., et al. Evaluating the association of clinical characteristics with neutralizing antibody levels in patients who have recovered from mild COVID-19 in Shanghai, China. JAMA Intern. Med. 2020;180(10):1356–1362.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9377417</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32808970</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Z., Mcgoogan J. Characteristics of and important lessons from the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) outbreak in China: summary of a report of 72 314 cases from the Chinese center for disease control and prevention. JAMA Intern. Med. 2020;323(13):1239–1242.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32091533</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nikolaeva L.I., Stuchinskaya M.D., Dedova A.V., et al. Association of polymorphic variants of hemostatic system genes with the course of COVID-19. Vopr. Virusol. 2023;68(5):445–453.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38156578</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grasselli G., Greco M., Zanella A., et al. Risk factors associated with mortality among patients with COVID-19 in intensive care units in lombardy, Italy. JAMA Intern. Med. 2020;180(10):1345–1355.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7364371</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32667669</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diagnosis and Treatment Protocol for Novel Coronavirus Pneumonia (Trial Version 9) Journal of Cardiovascular and Pulmonary Diseases. 2022;41(5):449–457.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miroševič Š., Prins J., Bešić N., et al. Symptoms of anxiety and depression among slovenian breast cancer survivors post-treatment during the COVID-19 pandemic: a cross-sectional study. Zdr Varst. 2024;63(1):55–62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10751885</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38156338</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamamoto M., Kato Y., Takeuchi J. Hand function and quality of life in patients with diabetes mellitus before and during the COVID-19 pandemic. Nagoya J. Med. Sci. 2023;85(4):659–667.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10751486</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38155631</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bošnjak B., Stein S., Willenzon S., et al. Low serum neutralizing anti-SARS-CoV-2 S antibody levels in mildly affected COVID-19 convalescent patients revealed by two different detection methods. Cell. Mol. Immunol. 2021;18(4):936–944.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7604543</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33139905</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mustafić S., Jusufović E., Hukić F., et al. Early predictors of severity and mortality in COVID-19 hospitalized patients. Med. Glas. 2021;18(2):384–393.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34080405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ha S., Choi S., Park S., et al. Prognostic effect of preoperative neutrophil-lymphocyte ratio is related with tumor necrosis and tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes in hepatocellular carcinoma. Virchows Arch. 2020;477(6):807–816.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32483662</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adamstein N., Macfadyen J., Rose L., et al. The neutrophil-lymphocyte ratio and incident atherosclerotic events: analyses from five contemporary randomized trials. Eur. Heart J. 2021;42(9):896–903.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7936519</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33417682</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kerboua K. NLR: a cost-effective nomogram to guide therapeutic interventions in COVID-19. Immunol. Invest. 2021;50(1):92–100.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32482134</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang W.J., Yoon J.Y. Dental trauma trends in emergency care:a comparative analysis before, during, and after COVID-19. J Korean Assoc Oral Maxillofac Surg. 2023;49(6):339–346.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10761316</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38155087</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Del Giudice M., Gangestad S., et al. Rethinking IL-6 and CRP: why they are more than inflammatory biomarkers, and why it matters. Brain Behav. Immun. 2018;70:61–75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29499302</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gozdas H., Kayis S., Damarsoy T., et al. Multi-inflammatory index as a novel mortality predictor in critically ill COVID-19 patients. J. Intensive Care Med. 2022;37(11):1480–1485.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9096173</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35538901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prasad S., Patel S., Behera A., et al. Influence of laboratory biomarkers on inflammatory indices for assessing severity progression in COVID-19 cases. J Family Med Prim Care. 2022;11(5):2056–2072.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9254836</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35800567</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perks A., Brendt P. Pericardiocentesis for COVID-19 associated cardiac tamponade using a central venous catheter in rural Australia: a case report. Air Med. J. 2024;43(1):63–65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38154844</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fetyukov A.V., Pshennikov D.S., Zaitseva S.E. Olfactory, gustatory and auditory disorders associated with COVID-19. A systematic review of their distribution and pathogenesis. Vestn. Otorinolaringol. 2023;88(6):61–66.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38153895</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun D., Li X., Guo D., et al. CT quantitative analysis and its relationship with clinical features for assessing the severity of patients with COVID-19. Korean J. Radiol. 2020;21(7):859–868.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7289692</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32524786</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dumea E., Barbu E.C., Chiţu C.E., et al. Clinical, biochemical and pulmonary CT imaging features for hepatobiliary involvement in COVID-19. Germs. 2023;13(2):121–129.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10746343</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38144251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bidari A., Zarei E., Hassanzadeh M., et al. Development of a scoring method based on a chest CT scan to determine the outcomes of COVID-19 patients. Cureus. 2023;15(10)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10657166</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38022268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ufuk F., Demirci M., Uğurlu E., et al. Evaluation of disease severity with quantitative chest CT in COVID-19 patients. Diagn Interv Radiol. 2021;27(2):164–171.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7963378</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33044173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>