<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39307088</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>22</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1095-8630</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>370</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>20</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of environmental management</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Environ Manage</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Magnetic graphene oxide-zinc oxide nanocomposite for enhanced photocatalytic degradation of azithromycin under normal sunlight.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>122571</StartPage><MedlinePgn>122571</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.jenvman.2024.122571</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0301-4797(24)02557-X</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>During the Covid-19 pandemic and its aftermath, there has been a sudden surge in the production and consumption of macrolide antibiotics. This surge has had a significant impact on water quality, leading to concentrations exceeding acceptable limits. To address this concerning issue, a magnetic graphene oxide-zinc oxide nanocomposite (MZG) was synthesized using a straightforward wet chemical synthesis method. The synthesized catalyst was then subjected to comprehensive characterization using sophisticated techniques including HRTEM, XRD, FTIR, Raman spectroscopy, BET, XPS, VSM, DRS, and TGA. Subsequently, the MZG photocatalyst's efficacy was evaluated through a series of experiments aimed at degrading azithromycin drug residues in water. These techniques divulged substantial information about the morphology, polycrystallinity, size (in nm range), functional groups, defects, surface area (132.9 m<sup>2</sup>/g), elemental composition (C, O, Fe and Zn), super paramagnetism (Ms 69.78 emu/g), suitable bandgap (2.8 eV) and thermal stability of the material, respectively. The optimized concentration of MZG photocatalyst demonstrated remarkable potential for photocatalytic degradation, particularly towards higher concentrations of 50 ppm azithromycin. It achieved an impressive degradation efficiency of 96.04 % in water when exposed to normal sunlight for just 1 h. Kinetic studies revealed a first-order reaction rate, with a notably higher rate constant (k = 0.0533 min⁻<sup>1</sup>) compared to other photocatalysts. Furthermore, MZG had shown better recyclabilty up to four cycles with minimal loss of photocatalytic acitvity to only 9%. Thus, it proves to be both effective and cost-efficient, capable of functioning under visible radiation. This makes it suitable for industrial applications aimed at removing azithromycin drugs and promoting a safer and more sustainable environment.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Singh</LastName><ForeName>Vineeta</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biochemical Engineering Laboratory, Department of Chemical and Biochemical Engineering, Indian Institute of Technology Patna, Bihta, Patna, 801106, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Samanta</LastName><ForeName>Sujoy Kumar</ForeName><Initials>SK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biochemical Engineering Laboratory, Department of Chemical and Biochemical Engineering, Indian Institute of Technology Patna, Bihta, Patna, 801106, India. Electronic address: sksamanta@iitp.ac.in.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>20</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Environ Manage</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0401664</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0301-4797</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Azithromycin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">MZG nanocomposite</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Macrolides</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Photocatalytic degradation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Water resource</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>7</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39307088</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2024.122571</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0301-4797(24)02557-X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>