<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39309991</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2277-9531</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of education and health promotion</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Educ Health Promot</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Investigating the mode of transmission of COVID-19 through genital secretions, semen, the birth canal, and lactation: A systematic review.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>263</StartPage><MedlinePgn>263</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">263</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4103/jehp.jehp_387_23</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>In a global pandemic, the coronavirus has brought new challenges to reproductive and sexual health. This systematic review has been conducted with the aim of investigating a) the transmission of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) through female-to-male sexual secretions and vice versa, b) vertical transmission to the fetus, c) transmission to the newborn through the birth canal, and d) transmission through breast milk. In this review study, to find related articles, databases were searched using English and Persian keywords from the beginning of 2019 to the end of 2023. Based on the entry and exit criteria and the qualitative evaluation of the studies based on the STROBE criterion, the final studies were summarized. According to the initial search, 5970 articles were reviewed. After removing duplicate articles and the inappropriateness of the title, the abstract of the article was not related to the objectives of the project, there was no relevant study, and retrospective studies were excluded. Finally, 120 articles were selected as final articles. The general results show that transmission of the virus through the vagina to the blood of the fetus causing septicemia, vertical transmission from the mother to the fetus, transmission through the water bag, genital secretions, and ejaculate fluid are considered rare and ruled out. Transmission through rectal secretions during anal or oral sex requires more extensive studies. It is not possible to transmit the virus through breast milk. The long-term reproductive impact of COVID-19 on the reproductive systems of women and men is unclear.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: © 2024 Journal of Education and Health Promotion.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Meamar</LastName><ForeName>Fatemeh Z</ForeName><Initials>FZ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Midwifery and Reproductive Health, Faculty of Nursing and Midwifery, Reproductive Sciences and Sexual Health Research Center, Isfahan University of Medical Sciences, Isfahan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Farajkhoda</LastName><ForeName>Tahmineh</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Center for Nursing and Midwifery Care, Non-Communicable Diseases Research Institute, Department of Midwifery, School of Nursing and Midwifery, Shahid Sadoughi University of Medical Sciences, Yazd, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Afshani</LastName><ForeName>Seyed A</ForeName><Initials>SA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Sociology, Faculty of Social Science, Yazd University, Yazd, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ardakani</LastName><ForeName>Tayebeh S</ForeName><Initials>TS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Midwifery, Maybod Branch, Islamic Azad University, Maybod, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>India</Country><MedlineTA>J Educ Health Promot</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101593794</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2277-9531</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Birth canal</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sexual health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sexual secretions</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">transmission</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">women</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>There are no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>29</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>56</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39309991</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11414867</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/jehp.jehp_387_23</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">JEHP-13-263</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Lu C-W, Liu X-F, Jia Z-F. 2019-nCoV transmission through the ocular surface must not be ignored. Lancet (London, England) 2020;395:e39. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736 (20) 30313-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7133551</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32035510</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen H, Guo J, Wang C, Luo F, Yu X, Zhang W, et al. Clinical characteristics and intrauterine vertical transmission potential of COVID-19 infection in nine pregnant women: A retrospective review of medical records. Lancet. 2020;395:809–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7159281</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32151335</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dubey S, Biswas P, Ghosh R, Chatterjee S, Dubey MJ, Chatterjee S, et al. Psychosocial impact of COVID-19. Diabetes Metab Syndr. 2020;14:779–88.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7255207</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32526627</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tahmineh F. Letter to the Editor: Sexual and Reproductive Health Rights and Challenges of Covid 19 Diagnosis. Medical Ethics [Internet] 2021;15:0–0. Available from: https://sid.ir/paper/1019421/en .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamzehgardeshi Z, Yazdani F, Rezaei M, Kiani Z. COVID-19 as a threat to sexual and reproductive health. Iran J Public Health. 2020;49(Suppl 1):136.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8266010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34268224</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bolarinwa OA, Ahinkorah BO, Seidu A-A, Ameyaw EK, Saeed BQ, Hagan JE, Jr, et al. Mapping evidence of impacts of COVID-19 outbreak on sexual and reproductive health: A scoping review. Healthcare. 2021;9:436. doi: 10.3390/healthcare9040436.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8068100</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33917784</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding S, Liang TJ. Is SARS-CoV-2 also an enteric pathogen with potential fecal–oral transmission? A COVID-19 virological and clinical review. Gastroenterology. 2020;159:53–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7184994</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32353371</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cabello F, Sánchez F, Farré JM, Montejo AL. Consensus on recommendations for safe sexual activity during the COVID-19 coronavirus pandemic. J Clin Med. 2020;9:2297. doi: 10.3390/jcm9072297.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7408907</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32698369</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blackwell CW. Reducing sexually associated transmission of COVID-19 in men who have sex with men. J Am Assoc Nurse Pract. 2021;33:1050–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32773533</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubin ES, Sansone SA, Hirshberg A, Clement EG, Srinivas SK. Detection of COVID-19 in a vulvar lesion. Am J Perinatol. 2020;37:1183.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7516389</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32615620</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gagneur A, Dirson E, Audebert S, Vallet S, Legrand-Quillien M, Laurent Y, et al. Materno-fetal transmission of human coronaviruses: A prospective pilot study. Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis. 2008;27:863–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7087967</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18373106</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patrì A, Gallo L, Guarino M, Fabbrocini G. Sexual transmission of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2): A new possible route of infection? J Am Acad Dermatol. 2020;82:e227.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7194822</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32278800</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashraf MA, Keshavarz P, Hosseinpour P, Erfani A, Roshanshad A, Pourdast A, et al. Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19): A systematic review of pregnancy and the possibility of vertical transmission. J Reprod Infertil. 2020;21:157–68.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7362089</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32685412</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schwartz A, Yogev Y, Zilberman A, Alpern S, Many A, Yousovich R, et al.  Detection of SARS-CoV-2 in Vaginal Swabs of Women with Acute SARS-CoV-2 Infection.  Available from SSRN: https://ssrn.com/abstract=3671438.  or http://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.3671438.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7675593</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33021026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui P, Chen Z, Wang T, Dai J, Zhang J, Ding T, et al. Clinical features and sexual transmission potential of SARS-CoV-2 infected female patients: A descriptive study in Wuhan, China. MedRxiv. 2020 doi: 10.1101/2020.02.26.20028225.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aslan MM, Yuvacı HU, Köse O, Toptan H, Akdemir N, Köroğlu M, et al. SARS-CoV-2 is not present in the vaginal fluid of pregnant women with COVID-19, The Journal of Maternal-Fetal &amp; Neonatal Medicine. 2020 DOI: 10.1080/14767058.2020.1793318.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32669014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Y, Liu C, Dong L, Zhang C, Chen Y, Liu J, et al. Coronavirus disease 2019 among pregnant Chinese women: Case series data on the safety of vaginal birth and breastfeeding. BJOG. 2020;127:1109–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7383704</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32369656</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaterian N, Abdi F. Is cesarean section a safe delivery method to prevent mother to child transmission of SARS-CoV-2? Tehran Univ Med J TUMS Publications. 2020;78:337–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mor N. New Delhi: Ministry of Health and Family Welfare; 2020. Resources for primary care providers to meet patients needs during the COVID-19 epidemic.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tamimi H, Tahmasebi R, Darabi AH, Noroozi A. The predictive role of vaccine literacy and vaccine hesitancy on acceptance of COVID-19 vaccination. ISMJ. 2021;24:597–609.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hashem NM, Abdelnour SA, Alhimaidi AR, Swelum AA. Potential impacts of COVID-19 on reproductive health: Scientific findings and social dimension. Saudi Journal of Biological Sciences. 2021;28:1702–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7831751</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33519273</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saghafipour A. What are the barriers to Covid-19 vaccination coverage?(Commentary) Payesh (Health Monitor) 2022;21:321–3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mosadeghrad AH. Promote COVID-19 vaccination uptake: A letter to editor. Tehran Univ Med J TUMS Publications. 2022;80:159–60.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadrmomtaz N, Khedmati M, Babaei A. Evaluation of the performance of world countries’ health systems in the face of Covid-19 in respect of vaccination role. Depiction Health. 2022;13:33–47.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aitken RJ. COVID-19 and human spermatozoa—Potential risks for infertility and sexual transmission? Andrology. 2021;9:48–52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7404878</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32649023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tatu A, Nadasdy T, Nwabudike L. Observations about sexual and other routes of SARS-CoV-2 (COVID-19) transmission and its prevention. Clin Exp Dermatol. 2020;45:761–2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7267151</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32369619</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiu L, Liu X, Xiao M, Xie J, Cao W, Liu Z, et al. SARS-CoV-2 is not detectable in the vaginal fluid of women with severe COVID-19 infection. Clin Infect Dis. 2020;71:813–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7184332</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32241022</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohseni AH, Taghinezhad-S S, Xu Z, Fu X. Body fluids may contribute to human-to-human transmission of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2: Evidence and practical experience. Chin Med. 2020;15:1–4. doi: 10.1186/s13020-020-00337-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7273816</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32514291</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui P, Chen Z, Wang T, Dai J, Zhang J, Ding T, et al. Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 detection in the female lower genital tract. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2020;223:131–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7196539</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32376320</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmad MF, Mahakkanukrauh P, Das S. The detection of SARS-CoV-2 virus in the vaginal fluid of females with severe COVID-19 infection: Scientific facts. Clin Infect Dis. 2022;74:2262–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7665426</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33085746</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lowe B, Bopp B. COVID-19 vaginal delivery–a case report. Aust N Z J Obstet Gynaecol. 2020;60:465–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7262173</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32294229</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carosso AR, Cosma S, Benedetto C. Vaginal delivery in COVID-19 pregnant women: Anorectum as a potential alternative route of SARS-CoV-2 transmission. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2020;223:612.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7283067</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32531218</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khoiwal K, Kalita D, Shankar R, Kumari R, Dhundi D, Bahadur A, et al. Identification of SARS-CoV-2 in the vaginal fluid and cervical exfoliated cells of women with active COVID-19 infection: A pilot study. Int J Gynecol Obstet. 2021;153:551–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9087647</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33713341</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuvacı HU, Aslan MM, Köse O, Akdemir N, Toptan H, Cevrioğlu AS, et al. Evaluation of the presence of SARS-COV-2 in the vaginal fluid of reproductive-aged women. Ginekologia Polska. 2021;92:406–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33751509</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barber E, Kovo M, Leytes S, Sagiv R, Weiner E, Schwartz O, et al. Evaluation of SARS-CoV-2 in the vaginal secretions of women with COVID-19: A prospective study. J Clin Med. 2021;10:2735.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8234022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34205751</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agarwal M, Basumatary S, Bhusan D, Pati BK. Detection of severe acute respiratory syndrome corona virus 2 in cervico-vaginal secretion of COVID-19-affected female: A prospective observational study from India. SAGE Open Med. 2021;9:20503121211022993. doi: 10.1177/20503121211022993.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8182207</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34158940</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Atarod Z, Zamaniyan M, Moosazadeh M, Valadan R, Soleimanirad SM, Gordani N. Investigation of vaginal and rectal swabs of women infected with COVID-19 in two hospitals covered by Mazandaran University of Medical Sciences, 2020. J Obstet Gynaecol. 2022;42:2225–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35260029</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erdem D, Kayaaslan B, Cakir EY, Dinc B, Asilturk D, Kirca F, et al. Investigation of SARS-CoV-2 using RT-PCR in vaginal swab samples of female patients with a diagnosis of severe COVID-19. Taiwan J Obstet Gynecol. 2023;62:270–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9729648</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36965894</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta P, Choudhary A, Srigyan D, Malhotra N. SARS-CoV-2 is not detectable in cervicovaginal secretions from women with active COVID-19 infection-a pilot study. JBRA Assist Reprod. 2023;27:1–3. doi: 10.5935/1518-0557.20210103.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10065781</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34995047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khoiwal K, Kalita D, Kumari R, Dhundi D, Shankar R, Kumari R, et al. Presence of SARS-CoV-2 in the lower genital tract of women with active COVID-19 infection: A prospective study. Int J Gynaecol Obst. 2022;157:744–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9087666</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35218221</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Cillo PEC, Lafraia FM, de Souza Bonetti TC, Saldanha MG, Reis N, Sartori MGF, et al. Cross-Sectional study confirms absence of viral RNA in vaginal secretion of SARS-COV-2 infected women. AJOG Glob Rep. 2023;3:100200. doi: 10.1016/j.xagr. 2023.100200.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10011025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37123882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li D, Jin M, Bao P, Zhao W, Zhang S. Clinical characteristics and results of semen tests among men with coronavirus disease 2019. JAMA Netw Open. 2020;3:e208292. doi: 10.1001/jamanetworkopen. 2020.8292.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7206502</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32379329</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song C, Wang Y, Li W, Hu B, Chen G, Xia P, et al. Absence of 2019 novel coronavirus in semen and testes of COVID-19 patients. Biol Reprod. 2020;103:4–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7184456</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32297920</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan F, Xiao X, Guo J, Song Y, Li H, Patel DP, et al. No evidence of severe acute respiratory syndrome–coronavirus 2 in semen of males recovering from coronavirus disease 2019. Fertil Steril. 2020;113:1135–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7164916</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32482249</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo L, Zhao S, Li W, Wang Y, Li L, Jiang S, et al. Absence of SARS-CoV-2 in semen of a COVID-19 patient cohort. Andrology. 2021;9:42–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7362062</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32598557</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma L, Xie W, Li D, Shi L, Ye G, Mao Y, et al. Evaluation of sex-related hormones and semen characteristics in reproductive-aged male COVID-19 patients. J Med Virol. 2021;93:456–62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7361404</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32621617</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruan Y, Hu B, Liu Z, Liu K, Jiang H, Li H, et al. No detection of SARS-CoV-2 from urine, expressed prostatic secretions, and semen in 74 recovered COVID-19 male patients: A perspective and urogenital evaluation. Andrology. 2021;9:99–106.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33150723</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gröner MF, Carvalho RCd, Camillo J, Ferreira PRA, Fraietta R. Effects of Covid-19 on male reproductive system. Int Braz J Urol. 2020;47:185–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7712710</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33047924</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holtmann N, Edimiris P, Andree M, Doehmen C, Baston-Buest D, Adams O, et al. Assessment of SARS-CoV-2 in human semen—A cohort study. Fertil Steril. 2020;114:233–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7256599</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32650948</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paoli D, Pallotti F, Turriziani O, Mazzuti L, Antonelli G, Lenzi A, et al. SARS-CoV-2 presence in seminal fluid: Myth or reality. Andrology. 2021;9:23–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7283802</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32453494</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kayaaslan B, Korukluoglu G, Hasanoglu I, Kalem AK, Eser F, Akinci E, et al. Investigation of SARS-CoV-2 in semen of patients in the acute stage of COVID-19 infection. Urol Int. 2020;104:678–83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7490499</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32781456</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gacci M, Coppi M, Baldi E, Sebastianelli A, Zaccaro C, Morselli S, et al. Semen impairment and occurrence of SARS-CoV-2 virus in semen after recovery from COVID-19. Hum Reprod. 2021;36:1520–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7953947</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33522572</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Machado B, Barcelos Barra G, Scherzer N, Massey J, dos Santos Luz H, Henrique Jacomo R, et al. Presence of SARS-CoV-2 RNA in semen—cohort study in the United States COVID-19 positive patients. Infect Dis Rep. 2021;13:96–101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7930957</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33557147</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Temiz MZ, Dincer MM, Hacibey I, Yazar RO, Celik C, Kucuk SH, et al. Investigation of SARS-CoV-2 in semen samples and the effects of COVID-19 on male sexual health by using semen analysis and serum male hormone profile: A cross-sectional, pilot study. Andrologia. 2021;53:e13912. doi: 10.1111/and. 13912.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7744846</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33244788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta P, Choudhary A, Gopal G, Kumar R, Kumar A, Tiwari P, et al. Detection of SARS-CoV2 virus using the real-time reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction in semen and seminal plasma from men with active COVID-19 infection–A pilot study. Indian J Urol. 2021;37:331–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8555575</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34759524</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang C, Zhou S-F, Gao L-D, Li S-K, Cheng Y, Zhou W-J, et al. Risks associated with cryopreserved semen in a human sperm bank during and after the COVID-19 pandemic. Reprod BioMed Online. 2021;42:589–94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7713547</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33384268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pavone C, Giammanco GM, Cascino AP, Baiamonte D, Pinelli M, Cangelosi E, et al. Assessment of SARS-CoV-2 RNA shedding in semen of 36 males with symptomatic, asymptomatic, and convalescent infection during the first and second wave of COVID-19 pandemic in Italy. Asian J Androl. 2022;24:135–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8887102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35017385</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delaroche L, Bertine M, Oger P, Descamps D, Damond F, Genauzeau E, et al. Evaluation of SARS-CoV-2 in semen, seminal plasma, and spermatozoa pellet of COVID-19 patients in the acute stage of infection. PLoS One. 2021;16:e0260187. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone. 0260187.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8670700</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34905541</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Donders GG, Bosmans E, Reumers J, Donders F, Jonckheere J, Salembier G, et al. Sperm quality and absence of SARS-CoV-2 RNA in semen after COVID-19 infection: A prospective, observational study and validation of the SpermCOVID test. Fertil Steril. 2022;117:287–96.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8685303</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34937665</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang Z, Do DV, Beh D, Lee CK, Yan B, Foo R, et al. Effects of acute severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 infection on male hormone profile, ACE2 and TMPRSS2 expression, and potential for transmission of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 in semen of Asian men. F S Sci. 2022;3:29–34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8604798</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34841282</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dong L, Tian J, He S, Zhu C, Wang J, Liu C, et al. Possible vertical transmission of SARS-CoV-2 from an infected mother to her newborn. JAMA. 2020;323:1846–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7099527</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32215581</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu W, Wang Q, Zhang Q, Chen L, Chen J, Zhang B, et al. Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) during pregnancy: A case series. 2020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elshafeey F, Magdi R, Hindi N, Elshebiny M, Farrag N, Mahdy S, et al. A systematic scoping review of COVID-19 during pregnancy and childbirth. Int J Gynecol Obstet. 2020;150:47–52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9087748</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32330287</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rozycki HJ, Kotecha S. Covid-19 in pregnant women and babies: What pediatricians need to know. Paediatr Respir Rev. 2020;35:31–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7293440</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32709462</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trippella G, Ciarcià M, Ferrari M, Buzzatti C, Maccora I, Azzari C, et al. COVID-19 in pregnant women and neonates: A systematic review of the literature with quality assessment of the studies. Pathogens. 2020;9:485. doi: 10.3390/pathogens9060485.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7350364</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32570959</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schwartz DA. An analysis of 38 pregnant women with COVID-19, their newborn infants, and maternal-fetal transmission of SARS-CoV-2: Maternal coronavirus infections and pregnancy outcomes. Arch Pathol Lab Med. 2020;144:799–805.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32180426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mullins E, Evans D, Viner R, O’Brien P, Morris E. Coronavirus in pregnancy and delivery: Rapid review. Ultrasound Obstet Gynecol. 2020;55:586–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32180292</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carosso A, Cosma S, Serafini P, Benedetto C, Mahmood T. How to reduce the potential risk of vertical transmission of SARS-CoV-2 during vaginal delivery? Eur J Obstet Gynecol Reprod Biol. 2020;250:246–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7200385</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32418711</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y, Peng H, Wang L, Zhao Y, Zeng L, Gao H, et al. Infants born to mothers with a new coronavirus (COVID-19) Front Pediatr. 2020;8:104. doi: 10.3389/fped. 2020.00104.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7098456</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32266184</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li N, Han L, Peng M, Lv Y, Ouyang Y, Liu K, et al. Maternal and neonatal outcomes of pregnant women with coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pneumonia: A case-control study. Clin Infect Dis. 2020;71:2035–41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7184430</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32249918</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao D, Chen M, Peng M, Yin H, Sun G. Vaginal delivery in women with COVID-19: Report of two cases. BMC Pregnancy Childbirth. 2020;20:1–6. doi: 10.1186/s12884-020-03281-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7530846</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33008308</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schwartz DA, Graham AL. Potential maternal and infant outcomes from coronavirus 2019-nCoV (SARS-CoV-2) infecting pregnant women: Lessons from SARS, MERS, and other human coronavirus infections. Viruses. 2020;12:194. doi: 10.3390/v12020194.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7077337</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32050635</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duran P, Berman S, Niermeyer S, Jaenisch T, Forster T, Gomez Ponce de Leon R, et al. COVID-19 and newborn health: Systematic review. Rev Panam Salud Pública. 2020;44:e54. doi: 10.26633/RPSP. 2020.54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7241573</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32454807</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Melo GCd, Araújo KCGMd. COVID-19 infection in pregnant women, preterm delivery, birth weight, and vertical transmission: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Cad Saude Publica. 2020;36:e00087320. doi: 10.1590/0102-311×00087320.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32696830</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Juan J, Gil MM, Rong Z, Zhang Y, Yang H, Poon LC. Effect of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) on maternal, perinatal and neonatal outcome: Systematic review. Ultrasound Obstet Gynecol. 2020;56:15–27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7276742</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32430957</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed FT, Jabbar S. Neonatal outcomes and vertical transmission in Covid-19 infected pregnant women; a systematic review. J Glob Trends Pharm Sci. 2020;11:8589–95.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pettirosso E, Giles M, Cole S, Rees M. COVID-19 and pregnancy: A review of clinical characteristics, obstetric outcomes and vertical transmission. Aust N Z J Obstet Gynaecol. 2020;60:640–59.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7436616</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32779193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marim F, Karadogan D, Eyuboglu TS, Emiralioglu N, Gurkan CG, Toreyin ZN, et al. Lessons learned so far from the pandemic: A review on pregnants and neonates with COVID-19. Eurasian J Med. 2020;52:202.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7311134</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32612432</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zimmermann P, Curtis N. COVID-19 in children, pregnancy and neonates: A review of epidemiologic and clinical features. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2020;39:469–77.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7363381</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32398569</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alzamora MC, Paredes T, Caceres D, Webb CM, Valdez LM, La Rosa M. Severe COVID-19 during pregnancy and possible vertical transmission. Am J Perinatol. 2020;37:861–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7356080</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32305046</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu X, Gao J, Luo X, Feng L, Liu W, Chen J, et al. Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) vertical transmission in neonates born to mothers with coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pneumonia. Obstet Gynecol. 2020;136:65–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7219851</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32332320</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheth S, Shah N, Bhandari V. Outcomes in COVID-19 positive neonates and possibility of viral vertical transmission: A narrative review. Am J Perinatol. 2020;37:1208–16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7645816</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32736407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dumitriu D, Emeruwa UN, Hanft E, Liao GV, Ludwig E, Walzer L, et al. Outcomes of neonates born to mothers with severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 infection at a large medical center in New York City. JAMA Pediatr. 2021;175:157–67.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7551222</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33044493</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joma M, Fovet C-M, Seddiki N, Gressens P, Laforge M. COVID-19 and pregnancy: Vertical transmission and inflammation impact on newborns. Vaccines. 2021;9:391.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8071483</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33921113</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He Z, Fang Y, Zuo Q, Huang X, Lei Y, Ren X, et al. Vertical transmission and kidney damage in newborns whose mothers had coronavirus disease 2019 during pregnancy. Int J Antimicrob Agents. 2021;57:106260. doi: 10.1016/j.ijantimicag. 2020.106260.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7834320</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33309765</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farhadi R, Mehrpisheh S, Ghaffari V, Haghshenas M, Ebadi A. Clinical course, radiological findings and late outcome in preterm infant with suspected vertical transmission born to a mother with severe COVID-19 pneumonia: A case report. J Med Case Rep. 2021;15:1–5. doi: 10.1186/s13256-021-02835-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8063577</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33892788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palalioglu RM, Mahammadaliyeva A, Erbiyik HI, Muhcu M. COVID-19 in third trimester may not be as scary as you think, it can be innocent: Evaluating vertical transmission from a COVID-19 positive asymptomatic pregnant woman with early membrane rupture. J Obstet Gynaecol Res. 2021;47:838–42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7753417</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33258171</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jing H, Ackerman IV WE, Zhao G, El Helou Y, Buhimschi CS, Buhimschi IA. Connecting the dots on vertical transmission of SARS-CoV-2 using protein-protein interaction network analysis–potential roles of placental ACE2 and ENDOU. Placenta. 2021;104:16–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7649632</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33197855</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumari K, Yadav R, Mittra S, Kumar A, Singh J, Bajpai PK, et al. Pregnancy consequences and vertical transmission potential of SARS-CoV-2 infection: Seeking answers from a preliminary observation. J Reprod Infertil. 2021;22:144.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8143008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34041012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Douglass KM, Strobel KM, Richley M, Mok T, de St Maurice A, Fajardo V, et al. Maternal-neonatal dyad outcomes of maternal COVID-19 requiring extracorporeal membrane support: A case series. Am J Perinatol. 2021;38:82–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7869039</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33069171</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rabiei M, Soori T, Abiri A, Farsi Z, Shizarpour A, Pirjani R. Maternal and fetal effects of COVID-19 virus on a complicated triplet pregnancy: A case report. J Med Case Rep. 2021;15:1–4. doi: 10.1186/s13256-020-02643-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7890395</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33602315</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdelazim IA, AbuFaza M, Al-Munaifi S. COVID-19 positive woman presented with preterm labor: Case report. Gynecol Obstet Reprod Med. 2021;27:294–6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pereira PCADA, Rodrigues DND, Rodrigues AMDS, Ferreira TM, Coelho BM, Do Nascimento MD, et al. Preventive measures against COVID-19 in pregnancy and neonates. J Young Pharm. 2021;13:31.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oncel MY, Akın IM, Kanburoglu MK, Tayman C, Coskun S, Narter F, et al. A multicenter study on epidemiological and clinical characteristics of 125 newborns born to women infected with COVID-19 by Turkish Neonatal Society. Eur J Pediatr. 2021;180:733–42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7416592</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32776309</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sukhikh G, Petrova U, Prikhodko A, Starodubtseva N, Chingin K, Chen H, et al. Vertical transmission of SARS-CoV-2 in second trimester associated with severe neonatal pathology. Viruses. 2021;13:447. doi: 10.3390/v13030447.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7999228</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33801923</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goh XL, Low YF, Ng CH, Amin Z, Ng YPM. Incidence of SARS-CoV-2 vertical transmission: A meta-analysis. Arch Dis Child Fetal Neonatal Ed. 2021;106:112–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32586828</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thapa B, Acharya S, Karki S. Vertical transmission of COVID-19: A case report and review of literature. J Nepal Health Res Counc. 2021;19:203–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33934161</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elósegui JH, García AC, Risquez AF, Quintana MB, Montes JE. Does the maternal-fetal transmission of SARS-CoV-2 occur during pregnancy? Revista Clínica Española (English Edition) 2021;221:93–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7351039</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33998494</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paramanathan S, Kyng K, Laursen A, Jensen L, Grejs A, Jain D. COVID-19 with severe acute respiratory distress in a pregnant woman leading to preterm caesarean section: A case report. Case Rep Womens Health. 2021;30:e00304. doi: 10.1016/j.crwh. 2021.e00304.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7938214</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33718007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tolu LB, Ezeh A, Feyissa GT. Vertical transmission of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2: A scoping review. PloS One. 2021;16:e0250196. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone. 0250196.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8062014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33886645</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carbayo-Jiménez T, Carrasco-Colom J, Epalza C, Folgueira D, Pérez-Rivilla A, Barbero-Casado P, et al. Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 vertical transmission from an asymptomatic mother. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2021;40:e115–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33565817</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiong X, Wei H, Zhang Z, Chang J, Ma X, Gao X, et al. Vaginal delivery report of a healthy neonate born to a convalescent mother with COVID-19. J Med Virol. 2020;92:1657–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7262245</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32275072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheikhahmadi S, Behzadi S, Zakaryaei F. Evaluating vertical transmission of COVID-19 from mothers to neonates: An iranian case series of 8 patients. Arch Iran Med. 2021;24:405–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34196206</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al Asadi J, Mousa SM. Intrauterine vertical transmission of COVID-19 during pregnancy: A systematic review. The Medical Journal of Basrah University. 2021;39:7–20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma R, Seth S, Sharma R, Yadav S, Mishra P, Mukhopadhyay S. Perinatal outcome and possible vertical transmission of coronavirus disease 2019: Experience from North India. Clin Exp Pediatr. 2021;64:239.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8103039</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33592686</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cai J, Tang M, Gao Y, Zhang H, Yang Y, Zhang D, et al. Cesarean section or vaginal delivery to prevent possible vertical transmission from a pregnant mother confirmed with COVID-19 to a neonate: A systematic review. Front Med. 2021;8:634949. doi: 10.3389/fmed. 2021.634949.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7926203</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33681259</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mendoza-Hernández M, Huerta-Niño de Rivera I, Yoldi-Negrete M, Saviñon-Tejeda P, Franco-Cendejas R, López-Jácome LE, et al. Probable case of vertical transmission of SARS-CoV-2 in a newborn in Mexico. Neonatology. 2021;118:364–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8247818</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33957638</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maeda MdFY, Brizot MdL, Gibelli MABC, Ibidi SM, Carvalho WBd, Hoshida MS, et al. Vertical transmission of SARS-CoV2 during pregnancy: A high-risk cohort. Prenatal Diagn. 2021;41:998–1008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8242902</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34101871</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaichian S, Mehdizadehkashi A, Mirgaloybayat S, Hashemi N, Farzaneh F, Derakhshan R, et al. Maternal and fetal outcomes of pregnant women infected with coronavirus based on tracking the results of 90-days data in Hazrat-E-Rasoul Akram Hospital, Iran University of Medical Sciences. Bull Emerg Trauma. 2021;9:145.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8286654</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34307705</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sinaci S, Ocal DF, Seven B, Anuk AT, Besimoglu B, Keven MC, et al. Vertical transmission of SARS-CoV-2: A prospective cross-sectional study from a tertiary center. J Med Virol. 2021;93:5864–72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8242620</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34081331</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lopian M, Kashani-Ligumsky L, Czeiger S, Cohen R, Schindler Y, Lubin D, et al. Safety of vaginal delivery in women infected with COVID-19. Pediatr Neonatol. 2021;62:90–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7605754</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33218936</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta V, Yadav Y, Sharma R, Mishra M, Ambedkar D, Gupta V, et al. Maternal and perinatal outcomes of hospitalized COVID-19 positive pregnant women. Cureus. 2022;14:e21817. doi: 10.7759/cureus. 21817.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8894144</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35261836</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akyıldız D, Çamur Z. Comparison of early postnatal clinical outcomes of newborns born to pregnant women with COVID-19: A case–control study. J Matern Fetal Neonatal Med. 2022;35:8673–80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34732087</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zamaniyan M, Rahmani Z, Ghasemian R, Karimi Z, Arab R-K, Ebadi A, et al. Maternal and neonatal outcomes in pregnant women with COVID-19 admitted to Imam Khomeini Hospital of Sari, Iran, 2019-2020. Arch Clin Infect Dis. 2023;18:e119394. doi: 10.5812/archcid-119394.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sunuwar N, Jaishi PP, Twayana AR, Neupane PK, Neupane SK. A retrospective study of COVID during pregnancy and the outcome of vaginal delivery. Ann Med Surg. 2022;84:104880. doi: 10.1016/j.amsu. 2022.104880.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9674396</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36438876</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Florea RM, Sultana CM. COVID-19 and breastfeeding: Can SARS-CoV-2 be spread through lactation? Discoveries. 2021;9:e132.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8570917</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34754901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ceulemans M, Cuppers B, de Vries L, Allegaert K, Duvekot J, van Puijenbroek EP. COVID-19 during pregnancy and lactation: What do we already know? Ned Tijdschr Geneeskd. 2021;164:D5036.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33560604</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao X, Wang S, Zeng W, Chen S, Wu J, Lin X, et al. Clinical and immunologic features among COVID-19–affected mother–infant pairs: Antibodies to SARS-CoV-2 detected in breast milk. New Microbes New Infect. 2020;37:100752. doi: 10.1016/j.nmni. 2020.100752.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7462625</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32904990</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centeno-Tablante E, Medina-Rivera M, Finkelstein JL, Rayco-Solon P, Garcia-Casal MN, Rogers L, et al. Transmission of SARS-CoV-2 through breast milk and breastfeeding: A living systematic review. Ann N Y Acad Sci. 2021;1484:32–54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7970667</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32860259</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pérez-Bermejo M, Peris-Ochando B, Murillo-Llorente MT. COVID-19: Relationship and Impact on Breastfeeding—A systematic review. Nutrients. 2021;13:2972.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8470649</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34578848</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bäuerl C, Randazzo W, Sánchez G, Selma-Royo M, Verdevio EG, Martínez L, et al. SARS-CoV-2 RNA and antibody detection in breast milk from a prospective multicentre study in Spain. Arch Dis Child Fetal Neonatal Ed. 2022;107:216–21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8384494</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34417223</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aiman U, Sholehah M, Husein MG. Risk transmission through breastfeeding and antibody in COVID-19 mother. Gaceta Sanitaria. 2021;35:S524–9. doi: 10.1016/j.gaceta. 2021.07.029.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8677354</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34929891</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vassilopoulou E, Feketea G, Koumbi L, Mesiari C, Berghea EC, Konstantinou GN. Breastfeeding and COVID-19: From nutrition to immunity. Front Immunol. 2021;12:661806. doi: 10.3389/fimmu. 2021.661806.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8058436</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33897707</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ng YPM, Low YF, Goh XL, Fok D, Amin Z. Breastfeeding in COVID-19: A pragmatic approach. Am J Perinatol. 2020;37:1377–84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7645812</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32898920</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Low JM, Low YW, Zhong Y, Lee CYC, Chan M, Ng NBH, et al. Titres and neutralising capacity of SARS-CoV-2-specific antibodies in human milk: A systematic review. Arch Dis Child Fetal Neonatal Ed. 2022;107:174–80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34257103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hethyshi R. Breast feeding in suspected or confirmed cases of COVID 19–a new perspective. J Obstet Gynecol India. 2020;70:267–71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7340186</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32760171</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pereira A, Cruz-Melguizo S, Adrien M, Fuentes L, Marin E, Forti A, et al. Breastfeeding mothers with COVID-19 infection: A case series. Int Breastfeed J. 2020;15:1–8. doi: 10.1186/s13006-020-00314-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7414278</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32770999</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lackey KA, Pace RM, Williams JE, Bode L, Donovan SM, Järvinen KM, et al. SARS-CoV-2 and human milk: What is the evidence? Matern Child Nutr. 2020;16:e13032.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7300480</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32472745</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lou F, Qin H, He S, Li M, An X, Song L, et al. The benefits of breastfeeding still outweigh the risks of COVID-19 transmission. Front Med. 2021:1451.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8455845</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34568367</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lubbe W, Botha E, Niela-Vilen H, Reimers P. Breastfeeding during the COVID-19 pandemic–a literature review for clinical practice. Int Breastfeed J. 2020;15:1–9. doi: 10.3389/fmed. 2021.703950.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7487446</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32928250</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fry HL, Levin O, Kholina K, Bianco JL, Gallant J, Chan K, et al. Infant feeding experiences and concerns among caregivers early in the COVID-19 State of Emergency in Nova Scotia, Canada. Matern Child Nutr. 2021;17:e13154. doi: 10.1111/mcn. 13154.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7995067</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33619906</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Kuraishy HM, Al-Gareeb AI, Atanu FO, El-Zamkan MA, Diab HM, Ahmed AS, et al. Maternal transmission of SARS-CoV-2: safety of breastfeeding in infants born to infected mothers. Frontiers in Pediatrics. 2021;9:738263.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8696119</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34956971</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kunjumon B, Wachtel EV, Lumba R, Quan M, Remon J, Louie M, et al. Breast milk and breastfeeding of infants born to SARS-CoV-2 positive mothers: A prospective observational cohort study. Am J Perinatol. 2021;38:1209–16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34182576</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mishra G, Dwivedi R, Jain A. Risk of transmission of COVID-19 to newborns in COVID-19 positive mothers-A case series. J Cardiovasc Dis Res. 2022;13:716–24.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kasraeian M, Zare M, Vafaei H, Asadi N, Faraji A, Bazrafshan K, et al. COVID-19 pneumonia and pregnancy; a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Matern Fetal Neonatal Med. 2022;35:1652–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32429786</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehta OP, Bhandari P, Raut A, Kacimi SEO, Huy NT. Coronavirus disease (COVID-19): Comprehensive review of clinical presentation. Front Public Health. 2021;8:582932. doi: 10.3389/fpubh. 2020.582932.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7844320</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33520910</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naz S, Rahat T, Memon FN. Vertical transmission of SARS-CoV-2 from COVID-19 infected pregnant women: A review on intrauterine transmission. Fetal Pediatr Pathol. 2021;40:80–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33356716</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tammaro A, Kulakowska KA, Cantisani C, Parisella FR, Scarabello A, Adebanjo GAR. Female genital mucosal lesions associated with COVID-19 vaccination: A brief review of the literature. J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol. 2023;37:e143–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9874779</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36310391</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Falkenhain-López D, Agud-Dios M, Ortiz-Romero P, Sánchez-Velázquez A. COVID-19-related acute genital ulcers. J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol. 2020;34:e655–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7323140</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32534473</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kotlyar AM, Grechukhina O, Chen A, Popkhadze S, Grimshaw A, Tal O, et al. Vertical transmission of coronavirus disease 2019: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2021;224:35–53. e3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7392880</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32739398</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryan GA, Purandare NC, McAuliffe FM, Hod M, Purandare CN. Clinical update on COVID-19 in pregnancy: A review article. J Obstet Gynaecol Res. 2020;46:1235–45.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7300676</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32500549</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heidary Z, Gargari OK, Fathi H, Zaki-Dizaji M, Ghaemi M, Rashidi BH. Maternal and neonatal complications, outcomes and possibility of vertical transmission in iranian women with COVID-19. Arch Iran Med. 2021;24:713–21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34816690</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lessler J. An overlooked role for fecal transmission of SARS-CoV-2? Clinical Infectious Diseases: An Official Publication of the Infectious Diseases Society of America. 2020</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7665370</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33064139</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nori W, Salman DA. Seminal fluid changes in the COVID-19 era: During infection and Post-vaccination. Gynecology and Obstetrics Clinical Medicine. 2023;3:88–93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10133885</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38620126</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation> Available from: https://dergipark.org.tr/en/pub/eurj/ issue/24881/1193573 . Des 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tristão LS, Bresler R, Modesto VA, Fernandes RdC, Bernardo WM. Urological complications of COVID-19: A systematic review. Int Braz J Urol. 2023;49:24–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9881803</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36512453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fornari F. Vertical transmission of Covid-19-A systematic review. J Pediatr Perinatol Child Health. 2020;4:7–13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuan J, Qian H, Cao S, Dong B, Yan X, Luo S, et al. Is there possibility of vertical transmission of COVID-19: A systematic review. Transl Pediatr. 2021;10:423.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7944168</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33708529</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Najafi TF, Dashti S, Bahri N. Vertical transmission of covid-19: A systematic review. Archives of Pediatric Infectious Diseases, 2021:9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manigandan S, Wu M-T, Ponnusamy VK, Raghavendra VB, Pugazhendhi A, Brindhadevi K. A systematic review on recent trends in transmission, diagnosis, prevention and imaging features of COVID-19. Process Biochem. 2020;98:233–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7439988</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32843849</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Luca D, Vauloup-Fellous C, Benachi A, Vivanti A. Transmission of SARS-CoV-2 from mother to fetus or neonate: What to know and what to do? Semin Fetal Neonatal Med. 2023;28:101429. doi: 10.1016/j.siny. 2023.101429.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10010052</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36935314</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goulioumis A, Angelopoulou M, Kourelis K, Mourtzouchos K, Tsiakou M, Asimakopoulos A. Hearing screening test in neonates born to COVID-19–positive mothers. European Journal of Pediatrics. 2023;182:1077–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9789365</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36565323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim YK, Kim EH. Pregnancy and COVID-19: Past, present and future. Obstet Gynecol Sci. 2023;66:149–60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10191757</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36938588</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muhidin S, Moghadam ZB, Vizheh M. Analysis of maternal coronavirus infections and neonates born to mothers with 2019-nCoV; a systematic review. Arch Acad Emerg Med. 2020;8:e49.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7211430</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32440660</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Y, Liu C, Dong L, Zhang C, Chen Y, Liu J, et al. Viral shedding of COVID-19 in pregnant women. SSRN. 2020 doi: 10.2139/ssrn. 3562059.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sokou R, Konstantinidi A, Boutsikou T, Iliodromiti Z, Iacovidou N. Breastfeeding in the era of COVID-19. A narrative review. J Obstet Gynaecol. 2022;42:539–45.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34396925</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jakuszko K, Kościelska-Kasprzak K, Żabińska M, Bartoszek D, Poznański P, Rukasz D, et al. Immune response to vaccination against COVID-19 in breastfeeding health workers. Vaccines. 2021;9:663.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8235492</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34204501</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krishnamurthy G, Sahni R, Leone T, Kim F, Brooks MC, Villaraza-Morales S, et al. Care of the COVID-19 exposed complex newborn infant. Semin Perinatol. 2020;44:151282. doi: 10.1016/j.semperi. 2020.151282.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7373040</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32819725</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh V, Trigunait P, Majumdar S, Ganeshan R, Sahu R. Managing pregnancy in COVID-19 pandemic: A review article. Journal of family medicine and primary care. 2020;9:5468–73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7842457</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33532380</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kimani RW, Maina R, Shumba C, Shaibu S. Maternal and newborn care during the COVID-19 pandemic in Kenya: Re-contextualising the community midwifery model. Hum Resour Health. 2020;18:1–5. doi: 10.1186/s12960-020-00518-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7539267</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33028347</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhatt H. Should COVID-19 mother breastfeed her newborn child? A literature review on the safety of breastfeeding for pregnant women with COVID-19. Curr Nutr Rep. 2021;10:71–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7780073</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33394459</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jorgensen SC, Burry L, Tabbara N. Role of maternal COVID-19 vaccination in providing immunological protection to the newborn. Pharmacotherapy. 2022;42:58–70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34816467</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koç E, Dilli D. How does COVID-19 affect maternal and neonatal outcomes? J Perinat Med. 2023;51:277–83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36580338</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>