<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39316377</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2198-3844</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Advanced science (Weinheim, Baden-Wurttemberg, Germany)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Adv Sci (Weinh)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Proximity-Unlocked Luminescence by Sequential Enzymatic Reactions from Antibody and Antibody/Aptamer (PULSERAA): A Platform for Detection and Visualization of Virus-Containing Spots.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e2403871</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e2403871</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/advs.202403871</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The SARS-CoV-2 pandemic has challenged more scientists to detect viruses and to visualize virus-containing spots for diagnosis and infection control; however, detection principles of commercially available technologies are not optimal for visualization. Here, a convenient and universal homogeneous detection platform named proximity-unlocked luminescence by sequential enzymatic reactions from antibody and antibody/aptamer (PULSERAA) is developed. This is designed so that the signal appears only when the donor and acceptor are in proximity on the viral surface. PULSERAA specifically detected in the range of 25-500 digital copies/mL of inactivated SARS-CoV-2 after simply mixing reagents; it is elucidated that the accumulation of chemical species in a limited space of the viral surface contributed to such high sensitivity. PULSERAA was quickly adapated to detect another virus variant, inactivated influenza A virus, and infectious SARS-CoV-2 in a clinical sample. Furthermore, on-site (direct, rapid, and portable) visualization of the inactivated SARS-CoV-2-containing spots by a conventional smartphone camera was achieved, demonstrating that PULSERAA can be a practical tool for preventing the next pandemic in the future.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Advanced Science published by Wiley‐VCH GmbH.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Miura</LastName><ForeName>Daimei</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0007-0005-9976</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biotechnology and Life Science, Graduate School of Engineering, Tokyo University of Agriculture and Technology, 2-24-16 Naka-cho, Koganei, Tokyo, 184-8588, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Global Innovation Research, Tokyo University of Agriculture and Technology, 3-8-1 Harumi-cho, Fuchu, Tokyo, 183-8538, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hayashi</LastName><ForeName>Wakana</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biotechnology and Life Science, Graduate School of Engineering, Tokyo University of Agriculture and Technology, 2-24-16 Naka-cho, Koganei, Tokyo, 184-8588, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hirano</LastName><ForeName>Kensuke</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Industrial Technology and Innovation, Graduate School of Engineering, Tokyo University of Agriculture and Technology, 2-24-16 Naka-cho, Koganei, Tokyo, 184-8588, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sasaki</LastName><ForeName>Ikkei</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biotechnology and Life Science, Graduate School of Engineering, Tokyo University of Agriculture and Technology, 2-24-16 Naka-cho, Koganei, Tokyo, 184-8588, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tsukakoshi</LastName><ForeName>Kaori</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biotechnology and Life Science, Graduate School of Engineering, Tokyo University of Agriculture and Technology, 2-24-16 Naka-cho, Koganei, Tokyo, 184-8588, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kakizoe</LastName><ForeName>Hidehumi</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Laboratory Medicine, Tokai University School of Medicine, 143 Shimokasuya, Isehara, Kanagawa, 259-1193, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Asai</LastName><ForeName>Satomi</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Laboratory Medicine, Tokai University School of Medicine, 143 Shimokasuya, Isehara, Kanagawa, 259-1193, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infection Control, Tokai University Hospital, 143 Shimokasuya, Isehara, Kanagawa, 259-1193, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vavricka</LastName><ForeName>Christopher J</ForeName><Initials>CJ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2101-4359</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biotechnology and Life Science, Graduate School of Engineering, Tokyo University of Agriculture and Technology, 2-24-16 Naka-cho, Koganei, Tokyo, 184-8588, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Global Innovation Research, Tokyo University of Agriculture and Technology, 3-8-1 Harumi-cho, Fuchu, Tokyo, 183-8538, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Takemae</LastName><ForeName>Hitoshi</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Infectious Disease Epidemiology and Prevention Research, Faculty of Agriculture, Tokyo University of Agriculture and Technology, 3-5-8 Saiwai-cho, Fuchu, Tokyo, 183-8509, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mizutani</LastName><ForeName>Tetsuya</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Infectious Disease Epidemiology and Prevention Research, Faculty of Agriculture, Tokyo University of Agriculture and Technology, 3-5-8 Saiwai-cho, Fuchu, Tokyo, 183-8509, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cooperative Division of Veterinary Sciences, Graduate School of Agriculture, Tokyo University of Agriculture and Technology, 3-5-8 Saiwai-cho, Fuchu, Tokyo, 183-8509, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tsugawa</LastName><ForeName>Wakako</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biotechnology and Life Science, Graduate School of Engineering, Tokyo University of Agriculture and Technology, 2-24-16 Naka-cho, Koganei, Tokyo, 184-8588, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sode</LastName><ForeName>Koji</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Joint Department of Biomedical Engineering, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and North Carolina State University, Chapel Hill, NC, 27599, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ikebukuro</LastName><ForeName>Kazunori</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2838-0562</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biotechnology and Life Science, Graduate School of Engineering, Tokyo University of Agriculture and Technology, 2-24-16 Naka-cho, Koganei, Tokyo, 184-8588, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Asano</LastName><ForeName>Ryutaro</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6795-8377</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biotechnology and Life Science, Graduate School of Engineering, Tokyo University of Agriculture and Technology, 2-24-16 Naka-cho, Koganei, Tokyo, 184-8588, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Global Innovation Research, Tokyo University of Agriculture and Technology, 3-8-1 Harumi-cho, Fuchu, Tokyo, 183-8538, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>21K18321</GrantID><Agency>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>JPNP20004</GrantID><Agency>New Energy and Industrial Technology Development Organization</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>JST-Mirai Program</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Adv Sci (Weinh)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101664569</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2198-3844</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antibody‐enzyme complex</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">bispecific aptamer</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">homogeneous immunosensor</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sequential enzymatic reactions</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">virus detection and visualization</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39316377</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/advs.202403871</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>E. Engvall, P. Perlmann, Immunochemistry 1971, 8, 871.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Peng, C. Liu, Z. Li, Z. Xue, P. Mao, J. Hu, F. Xu, C. Yao, M. You, TrAC Trends Anal. Chem. 2022, 152, 116605.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Safarikova, I. Safarik, Magn. Electr. Sep. 2001, 10, 223.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. A. Posthuma‐Trumpie, J. Korf, Van Amerongen, Anal. Bioanal. Chem. 2009, 393, 569.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Barni, S. W. Lewis, A. Berti, G. M. Miskelly, G. Lago, Talanta 2007, 72, 896.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. C. Boguslaski, T. M. LiLi, Appl. Biochem. Biotechnol. 1982, 7, 401.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. F. Ullman, H. Kirakossian, A. C. Switchenko, J. Ishkanian, M. Ericson, C. A. Wartchow, M. Pirio, J. Pease, B. R. Irvin, S. Singh, R. Singh, R. Patel, A. Dafforn, D. Davalian, C. Skold, N. Kurn, D. B. Wagner, Clin. Chem. 1996, 42, 1518.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Beaudet, R. Rodriguez‐suarez, M. Caron, J. Bédard, V. Brechler, S. Parent, M. Bielefeld‐sévigny, Nat. Methods 2008, 5, 8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. M. Eglen, T. Reisine, P. Roby, N. Rouleau, C. Illy, R. Bossé, M. Bielefeld, Curr. Chem. Genomics 2008, 1, 2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Akter, C. K. Rhee, M. A. Rahman, Biosens. Bioelectron. 2015, 66, 539.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. Li, S. Chen, Y. Yang, Y. Song, C. Ma, X. Qiao, C. Hong, Microchim. Acta 2021, 188, 61.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Shao, H. Zhou, Q. Wu, Y. Xiong, J. Wang, Y. Ding, Biotechnol. Adv. 2021, 53, 107867.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Jeong, R. Akter, O. H. Han, C. K. Rhee, M. A. Rahman, Anal. Chem. 2013, 85, 1784.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Kimura, R. Asano, N. Tsukamoto, W. Tsugawa, K. Sode, Anal. Chem. 2018, 90, 14500.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Kimura, D. Miura, W. Tsugawa, K. Ikebukuro, K. Sode, R. Asano, Biosens. Bioelectron. 2021, 175, 112885.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Miura, H. Kimura, W. Tsugawa, K. Ikebukuro, K. Sode, R. Asano, Talanta 2021, 234, 122638.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Miura, S. Motohashi, A. Goto, H. Kimura, W. Tsugawa, K. Sode, K. Ikebukuro, R. Asano, Int. J. Mol. Sci. 2024, 25, 2859.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Ferri, K. Kojima, K. Sode, J. Diabetes Sci. Technol. 2011, 5, 1068.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Shi, C. Shan, X. Duan, Z. Chen, P. Liu, J. Song, T. Song, X. Bi, C. Han, L. Wu, G. Gao, X. Hu, Y. Zhang, Z. Tong, W. Huang, W. J. Liu, G. Wu, B. Zhang, L. Wang, J. Qi, H. Feng, F. S. Wang, Q. Wang, G. F. Gao, Z. Yuan, J. Yan, Nature 2020, 584, 120.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Komiya, S. Takamatsu, D. Miura, K. Tsukakoshi, W. Tsugawa, K. Sode, K. Ikebukuro, R. Asano, J. Am. Chem. Soc. 2023, 146, 4087.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U. B. Nielsen, G. P. Adams, L. M. Weiner, J. D. Marks, Cancer Res. 2000, 60, 6434.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Tsukakoshi, Y. Yamagishi, M. Kanazashi, K. Nakama, D. Oshikawa, N. Savory, A. Matsugami, F. Hayashi, J. Lee, T. Saito, K. Sode, K. Khunathai, H. Kuno, K. Ikebukuro, Nucleic Acids Res. 2021, 49, 6069.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Song, J. Song, X. Wei, M. Huang, M. Sun, L. Zhu, B. Lin, H. Shen, Z. Zhu, C. Yang, Anal. Chem. 2020, 92, 9895.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Tsukakoshi, Y. Ikuta, K. Abe, W. Yoshida, K. Iida, Y. Ma, K. Nagasawa, K. Sode, K. Ikebukuro, Chem. Commun. 2016, 52, 12646.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. V. Potapovich, A. N. Eryomin, I. M. Artzukevich, I. P. Chernikevich, D. I. Metelitza, Biochem. 2001, 66, 646.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. K. Khan, M. S. Mondal, L. Padhy, S. Mitra, Eur. J. Biochemistry 1998, 257, 547.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. X. Guo, H. X. Shen, L. Li, Mikrochim. Acta 1999, 131, 171.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. T. Smith, N. Santama, S. Dacey, M. Edwards, R. C. Bray, R. N. F. Thorneley, J. F. Burke, J. Biol. Chem. 1990, 265, 13335.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Cassidy, M. van Genne, E. Lizarazo‐Forero, H. G. M. Niesters, L. Gard, Front. Microbiol. 2022, 13, 854209.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. W. Li, S. F. Cheng, Y. T. Tseng, Y. C. Yang, W. C. Liu, S. C. Wang, M. J. Chou, Y. J. Lin, Y. Wang, P. W. Hsiao, S. C. Wu, D. K. Chang, Arch. Virol. 2016, 161, 19.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Jones, D. Mantle, D. M. Davies, H. C. Kelly, Biochemistry 1977, 16, 3974.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Portsmouth, E. A. Beal, Eur. J. Biochem. 1971, 19, 479.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Travascio, Y. Li, D. Sen, Chem. Biol. 1998, 5, 505.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Hu, F. Wang, C. H. Lu, J. Girsh, E. Golub, I. Willner, Chem. A Eur. J. 2014, 20, 16203.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Zhang, B. Huang, J. Zhang, K. Wang, J. Jin, J. Sci. Food Agric. 2012, 92, 1944.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. T. F. Yu, H. Guan, M. K. Cheung, W. M. McHugh, T. T. Cornell, T. P. Shanley, K. Kurabayashi, J. Fu, Sci. Rep. 2015, 5, 11129.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. T. Cao, W. S. Zhang, H. Wang, S. H. Ma, Y. M. Liu, New J. Chem. 2019, 43, 1424.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. Xu, Y. Xiong, W. Lai, Y. Xu, C. Li, M. Xie, Biosens. Bioelectron. 2014, 56, 144.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. J. Hou, S. Chiba, P. Halfmann, C. Ehre, M. Kuroda, K. H. Dinnon, S. R. Leist, A. Schäfer, N. Nakajima, K. Takahashi, R. E. Lee, T. M. Mascenik, R. Graham, C. E. Edwards, L. V. Tse, K. Okuda, A. J. Markmann, L. Bartelt, A. de Silva, D. M. Margolis, R. C. Boucher, S. H. Randell, T. Suzuki, L. E. Gralinski, Y. Kawaoka, R. S. Baric, Science 2020, 370, 1464.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Liu, L. Mendonça, Y. Yang, Y. Gao, C. Shen, J. Liu, T. Ni, B. Ju, C. Liu, X. Tang, J. Wei, X. Ma, Y. Zhu, W. Liu, S. Xu, Y. Liu, J. Yuan, J. Wu, Z. Liu, Z. Zhang, L. Liu, P. Wang, P. Zhang, Structure 2020, 28, 1218.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Leng, H. P. Wei, Z. P. Zhang, Y. F. Zhou, J. Y. Deng, Z. Q. Cui, D. Men, X. Y. You, Z. N. Yu, M. Luo, X. E. Zhang, Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. 2010, 49, 7243.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. A. Grant, B. Heits, S. Kleiboeker, Sens. Lett. 2006, 4, 246.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Pinto, Y. J. Park, M. Beltramello, A. C. Walls, M. A. Tortorici, S. Bianchi, S. Jaconi, K. Culap, F. Zatta, A. de Marco, A. Peter, B. Guarino, R. Spreafico, E. Cameroni, J. B. Case, R. E. Chen, C. Havenar‐Daughton, G. Snell, A. Telenti, H. W. Virgin, A. Lanzavecchia, M. S. Diamond, K. Fink, D. Veesler, D. Corti, Nature 2020, 583, 290.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. F. M. Teunis, C. L. Moe, P. Liu, S. E. Miller, L. Lindesmith, R. S. Baric, J. Le Pendu, R. L. Calderon, J. Med. Virol. 2006, 80, 1468.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. R. O'Donnell, T. A. Tummino, C. Bardine, C. S. Craik, B. K. Shoichet, J. Med. Chem. 2021, 64, 17530.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Jensen, K. Thomas, D. G. Sharp, Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 1980, 40, 633.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>I. Samandoulgou, I. Fliss, J. Jean, Food Environ. Virol. 2015, 7, 249.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. M. Kahler, T. L. Cromeans, M. G. Metcalfe, C. D. Humphrey, V. R. Hill, Food Environ. Virol. 2016, 8, 148.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Eltzov, S. Guttel, A. L. Y. Kei, P. D. Sinawang, R. E. Ionescu, R. S. Marks, Electroanalysis 2015, 27, 2116.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Ni, B. J. H. M. Rosier, E. A. van Aalen, E. T. L. Hanckmann, L. Biewenga, A. M. M. Pistikou, B. Timmermans, C. Vu, S. Roos, R. Arts, W. Li, T. F. A. de Greef, M. M. G. J. van Borren, F. J. M. van Kuppeveld, B. J. Bosch, M. Merkx, Nat. Commun. 2021, 12, 4568.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Arena, S. Pollini, G. M. Rossolini, M. Margaglione, Int. J. Mol. Sci. 2021, 22, 1298.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Peng, X. Jiao, Z. Liang, H. Zhao, Y. Zhao, J. Xie, Y. Jiang, X. Yu, X. Fang, X. Dai, Biosensors 2022, 12, 13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Asano, T. Kumagai, K. Nagai, S. Taki, I. Shimomura, K. Arai, H. Ogata, M. Okada, F. Hayasaka, H. Sanada, T. Nakanishi, T. Karvonen, H. Hayashi, Y. Katayose, M. Unno, T. Kudo, M. Umetsu, I. Kumagai, Protein Eng. Des. Sel. 2013, 26, 359.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Asano, Y. Sone, K. Makabe, K. Tsumoto, H. Hayashi, Y. Katayose, M. Unno, T. Kudo, I. Kumagai, Clin. Cancer Res. 2006, 12, 4036.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Asano, T. Kudo, Y. Nishimura, K. Makabe, H. Hayashi, M. Suzuki, K. Tsumoto, I. Kumagai, J. Biochem. 2002, 132, 903.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Okurita, N. Suzuki, N. Loew, H. Yoshida, W. Tsugawa, K. Mori, K. Kojima, D. C. Klonoff, K. Sode, Bioelectrochemistry 2018, 123, 62.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Savory, D. Lednor, K. Tsukakoshi, K. Abe, W. Yoshida, S. Ferri, B. V. Jones, K. Ikebukuro, Biotechnol. Bioeng. 2013, 110, 2573.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>I. Shiratori, J. Akitomi, D. A. Boltz, K. Horii, M. Furuichi, I. Waga, Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 2014, 443, 37.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. M. Woo, J. M. Lee, S. Yim, Y. J. Jeong, PLoS One 2015, 10, e0125060.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>