<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39310089</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2633-4402</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>4</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>NIHR open research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>NIHR Open Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Evaluating video and hybrid group consultations in general practice: mixed-methods, participatory study protocol (TOGETHER 2).</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>30</StartPage><MedlinePgn>30</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">30</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3310/nihropenres.13584.2</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">General practice is facing an unprecedented challenge in managing the consequences of the pandemic. In the midst of a policy drive to balance remote and in-person service provision, substantial workload pressures remain, together with increasing prevalence of long-term conditions, and declining staff numbers and morale. To address these challenges, some practices in the UK have been delivering video and hybrid group consultations (VHGCs) providing clinical care to multiple patients at the same time. Despite positive initial findings and enthusiasm, there are still gaps in our understanding of the influence VHGCs have on patient experience, healthcare utilisation, quality, safety, equity and affordability.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">To generate an in-depth understanding of VHGCs for chronic conditions in general practice, surface assumptions and sociotechnical dynamics, inform practice and extend theorisation.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Mixed-methods, multi-site research study using co-design and participatory methods, from qualitative, quantitative and cost-related perspectives. WP1 includes a national, cross-sectional survey on VHGC provision across the UK. In WP2 we will engage patients and general practice staff in co-design workshops to develop VHGC models with emphasis on digital inclusion and equity. In WP3 we will carry out a mixed-methods process evaluation in up to 10 GP practices across England (5 sites already running VHGCs and 5 comparison sites). Qualitative methods will include interviews, focus groups and ethnographic observation to examine the experiences of patients, carers, clinical and non-clinical NHS staff, commissioners and policy-makers. Quantitative methods will examine the impact of VHGCs on healthcare utilisation in primary and secondary care, patient satisfaction, engagement and activation. We will also assess value for money of group and individual care models from a health economics perspective.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">We aim to develop transferable learning on sociotechnical change in healthcare delivery, using VHGCs as an exemplar of technology-supported innovation. Findings will also inform the design of a future study.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: © 2024 Papoutsi C et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Papoutsi</LastName><ForeName>Chrysanthi</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1189-7100</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nuffield Department of Primary Care Health Sciences, University of Oxford, Oxford, England, OX26GG, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abel</LastName><ForeName>Gary</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health and Community Science, Smeall Building, St Luke's Campus, University of Exeter, Exeter, England, EX1 2LU, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Iglesias</LastName><ForeName>Cynthia</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Sciences, Seebohm Rowntree Building, University of York, York, England, YO10 5SQ, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>van Dael</LastName><ForeName>Jackie</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nuffield Department of Primary Care Health Sciences, University of Oxford, Oxford, England, OX26GG, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Reidy</LastName><ForeName>Claire</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nuffield Department of Primary Care Health Sciences, University of Oxford, Oxford, England, OX26GG, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Faulkner</LastName><ForeName>Stuart D</ForeName><Initials>SD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nuffield Department of Primary Care Health Sciences, University of Oxford, Oxford, England, OX26GG, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Raynsford</LastName><ForeName>Helene</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Independent public contributor, UK, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Siciliano</LastName><ForeName>Michele</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0000-7354-5368</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Sciences, Seebohm Rowntree Building, University of York, York, England, YO10 5SQ, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Beltran Galindo</LastName><ForeName>Luis</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9199-8467</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Sciences, Seebohm Rowntree Building, University of York, York, England, YO10 5SQ, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gc</LastName><ForeName>Vijay</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0365-2605</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Human &amp; Health Sciences, University of Huddersfield, Huddersfield, England, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Campbell</LastName><ForeName>John</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health and Community Science, Smeall Building, St Luke's Campus, University of Exeter, Exeter, England, EX1 2LU, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Greenhalgh</LastName><ForeName>Trisha</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2369-8088</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nuffield Department of Primary Care Health Sciences, University of Oxford, Oxford, England, OX26GG, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shaw</LastName><ForeName>Sara E</ForeName><Initials>SE</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7014-4793</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nuffield Department of Primary Care Health Sciences, University of Oxford, Oxford, England, OX26GG, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>NIHR Open Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9918333281906676</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2633-4402</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><OtherAbstract Type="plain-language-summary" Language="eng"><AbstractText Label="AIM" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">To better understand how group consultations for chronic conditions can benefit patients and the health service when delivered via video and/or in-person in general practice.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Before the pandemic, group consultations were starting to gain ground in the UK as a new way of delivering clinical care to multiple patients at the same time, with potential benefits resulting from peer support and time efficiencies. When in-person care was restricted due to Covid-19, clinicians started delivering group consultations over video. Despite significant interest, we still know little about how group consultations delivered over video or hybrid models (combining video and in-person sessions) can be best implemented.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESEARCH METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">In up to 5 GP practices across England, where group consultations are already being delivered, we will evaluate how these new approaches to clinical care are implemented, and how they may support an inclusive service that engages patients with different needs and preferences. The evaluation will include interviews with patients, carers, NHS staff, policy-makers and commissioners, as well as group discussions and observations, including research led by patients themselves. We will also collect numerical data on the number and type of patients attending, whether they are more satisfied or confident with their self-management, or less likely to need to go to hospital. We will explore costs associated with these new ways of delivering care and will develop comparisons to face-to-face individual appointments. We will also work with comparable clinical sites only delivering one-to-one appointments, to collect numerical data on patient attendance, satisfaction and use of health services. With the involvement of our patient and public involvement (PPI) group, we will bring together our data to develop practical knowledge.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: © 2024 Papoutsi C et al.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">general practice</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">group consulting</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">invisible work</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">lived experience</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">remote care</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>No competing interests were disclosed.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>29</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>58</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39310089</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11415752</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3310/nihropenres.13584.2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Cooksley T, Clarke S, Dean J, et al. : NHS crisis: rebuilding the NHS needs urgent action. BMJ. 2023;380:1. 10.1136/bmj.p1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.p1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36596578</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
UK Government:
Health and care act 2022.
 2022.
Reference Source
</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
NHS England:
NHS long term plan.London,2019.
Reference Source
</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greenhalgh T, Rosen R: Remote by default general practice: must we, should we, dare we? Br J Gen Pract. 2021;71(705):149–50. 10.3399/bjgp21X715313</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3399/bjgp21X715313</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8007254</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33771790</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mroz G, Papoutsi C, Greenhalgh T: From ‘a rapid and necessary revolution’ to ‘telemedicine killed the PE teacher’: changing representations of remote GP consultations in UK media during the COVID-19 pandemic.In: Lewis M, Govender E, Holland K, editors. Communicating COVID-19: Media, Trust, and Public Engagement.Cham: Springer International Publishing,2024;125–44. 10.1007/978-3-031-41237-0_7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-3-031-41237-0_7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaw SE, Hughes G, Wherton J, et al. : Achieving spread, scale up and sustainability of video consulting services during the COVID-19 pandemic? findings from a comparative case study of policy implementation in England, Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland. Front Digit Health. 2021;3: 754319. 10.3389/fdgth.2021.754319</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fdgth.2021.754319</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8720935</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34988546</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greenhalgh T, Shaw SE, Alvarez Nishio A, et al. : Protocol: remote care as the ‘new normal’? Multi-site case study in UK general practice [version 1; peer review: 3 approved]. NIHR Open Res. 2022;2:46. 10.3310/nihropenres.13289.1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3310/nihropenres.13289.1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10593351</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37881300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Veinot T: Power to the patient? a critical examination of patient empowerment discourses.In: Harris R, Wathen N, Wyatt S, editors. Configuring Health Consumers: Health Work and the Imperative of Personal Responsibility.London: Palgrave Macmillan UK,2010;30–41. 10.1057/9780230292543_3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1057/9780230292543_3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mazanderani F, Locock L, Powell J: Biographical value: towards a conceptualisation of the commodification of illness narratives in contemporary healthcare. Sociol Health Illn. 2013;35(6):891–905. 10.1111/1467-9566.12001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1467-9566.12001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23551016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halloy A, Simon E, Hejoaka F: Defining patient’s experiential knowledge: who, what and how patients know. A narrative critical review. Sociol Health Illn. 2023;45(2):405–22. 10.1111/1467-9566.13588</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1467-9566.13588</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10100415</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36443986</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mazanderani F, Locock L, Powell J: Being differently the same: the mediation of identity tensions in the sharing of illness experiences. Soc Sci Med. 2012;74(4):546–53. 10.1016/j.socscimed.2011.10.036</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2011.10.036</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22227237</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mazanderani F, Noorani T, Dudhwala F, et al. : Knowledge, evidence, expertise? The epistemics of experience in contemporary healthcare. Evid Policy. 2020;16(2):267–84. 10.1332/174426420X15808912561112</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1332/174426420X15808912561112</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hayhoe B, Verma A, Kumar S: Shared medical appointments. BMJ. 2017;358: j4034. 10.1136/bmj.j4034</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.j4034</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28855156</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papoutsi C, Colligan G, Hagell A, et al. : Promises and perils of group clinics for young people living with diabetes: a realist review. Diabetes Care. 2019;42(5):705–12. 10.2337/dc18-2005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/dc18-2005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31010940</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trento M, Gamba S, Gentile L, et al. : Rethink Organization to iMprove Education and Outcomes (ROMEO): a multicenter randomized trial of lifestyle intervention by group care to manage type 2 diabetes. Diabetes Care. 2010;33(4):745–7. 10.2337/dc09-2024</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/dc09-2024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2845019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20103547</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong SH, Barrow N, Hall K, et al. : The Effective management of idiopathic intracranial hypertension delivered by in-person and virtual group consultations: results and reflections from a phase one service delivery. Neuroophthalmology. 2021;45(4):246–52. 10.1080/01658107.2021.1887287</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/01658107.2021.1887287</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8312588</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34366512</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Graham F, Tang MY, Jackson K, et al. : Barriers and facilitators to implementation of shared medical appointments in primary care for the management of long-term conditions: a systematic review and synthesis of qualitative studies. BMJ Open. 2021;11(8): e046842. 10.1136/bmjopen-2020-046842</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2020-046842</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8386233</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34429309</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Swaithes L, Paskins Z, Duffy H, et al. : Experience of implementing and delivering group consultations in UK general practice: a qualitative study. Br J Gen Pract. 2021;71(707):e413–e422. 10.3399/BJGP.2020.0856</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3399/BJGP.2020.0856</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8049217</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33685921</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Graham F, Martin H, Lecouturier J, et al. : Shared medical appointments in english primary care for long-term conditions: a qualitative study of the views and experiences of patients, primary care staff and other stakeholders. BMC Prim Care. 2022;23(1): 180. 10.1186/s12875-022-01790-z</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12875-022-01790-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9298712</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35858833</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Booth A, Cantrell A, Preston L, et al. : What is the evidence for the effectiveness, appropriateness and feasibility of group clinics for patients with chronic conditions? A systematic review. Health Serv Delivery Res. 2015;3(46). 10.3310/hsdr03460</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3310/hsdr03460</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26726695</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nederveld A, Phimphasone-Brady P, Gurfinkel D, et al. : Delivering diabetes shared medical appointments in primary care: early and mid-program adaptations and implications for successful implementation. BMC Prim Care. 2023;24(1): 52. 10.1186/s12875-023-02006-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12875-023-02006-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9936115</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36803773</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scott E, Swaithes L, Wynne-Jones G, et al. : Use of video group consultations by general practice staff during the COVID-19 pandemic. Prim Health Care. 2023;33(3). 10.7748/phc.2023.e1801</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7748/phc.2023.e1801</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blatgé H, Shanmugam S, Slattery B, et al. : Patient perception of group consultations for knee osteoarthritis and influence of area-level deprivation: a service evaluation in a physiotherapy musculoskeletal setting. Musculoskeletal Care. 2024;22(1): e1870. 10.1002/msc.1870</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/msc.1870</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38381078</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papoutsi C, Hargreaves D, Colligan G, et al. : Group clinics for young adults with diabetes in an ethnically diverse, socioeconomically deprived setting (TOGETHER study): protocol for a realist review, co-design and mixed methods, participatory evaluation of a new care model. BMJ Open. 2017;7(6): e017363. 10.1136/bmjopen-2017-017363</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2017-017363</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5726054</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28637744</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papoutsi C, Hargreaves D, Hagell A, et al. : Group clinics for young adults living with diabetes in an ethnically diverse, socioeconomically deprived population: mixed-methods evaluation. National Institute for Health and Care Research. Southampton (UK),2022. 10.3310/NKCR8246</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3310/NKCR8246</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36063481</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papoutsi C, Hargreaves D, Hagell A, et al. : Implementation and delivery of group consultations for young people with diabetes in socioeconomically deprived, ethnically diverse settings. BMC Med. 2022;20(1):459. 10.1186/s12916-022-02654-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12916-022-02654-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9701006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36434593</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papoutsi C, Shaw S, Greenhalgh T: Implementing video group consultations in general practice during COVID-19: a qualitative study. Br J Gen Pract. 2022;72(720):e483–e91. 10.3399/BJGP.2021.0673</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3399/BJGP.2021.0673</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9256071</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35636969</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Hughes G, Wood G, Shaw S:
Video consultations in the NHS: summary findings from a UK-wide survey.2020.
Reference Source
</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Donetto S, Tsianakas V, Robert G:
Using Experience-Based Co-Design (EBCD) to improve the quality of healthcare: mapping where we are now and establishing future directions. London: King’s College London,2014.
Reference Source
</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
The King’s Fund:
Experience-Based Co-Design toolkit 2013.
Reference Source
</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murphy M, Hollinghurst S, Cowlishaw S, et al. : Primary Care Outcomes Questionnaire: psychometric testing of a new instrument. Br J Gen Pract. 2018;68(671):e433–e40. 10.3399/bjgp18X695765</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3399/bjgp18X695765</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6001981</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29581130</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bardsley M, Blunt I, Davies S, et al. : Is secondary preventive care improving? Observational study of 10-year trends in emergency admissions for conditions amenable to ambulatory care. BMJ open. 2013;3(1): e002007. 10.1136/bmjopen-2012-002007</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2012-002007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3549201</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23288268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roberts M, Russell LB, Paltiel AD, et al. : Conceptualizing a model: a report of the ISPOR-SMDM modeling good research practices task force–2. Med Decis Making. 2012;32(5):678–89. 10.1177/0272989X12454941</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0272989X12454941</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22990083</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greenhalgh T, Wherton J, Papoutsi C, et al. : Beyond adoption: a new framework for theorizing and evaluating Nonadoption, Abandonment, and challenges to the Scale-Up, Spread, and Sustainability of health and care technologies (NASSS framework). J Med Internet Res. 2017;19(11): e367. 10.2196/jmir.8775</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/jmir.8775</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5688245</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29092808</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greenhalgh T, Shaw S, Byng R: Planning and Evaluating Remote Consultation Services (PERCS): a new conceptual framework incorporating complexity and practical ethics. Front Digit Health. under review.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8521880</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34713199</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herdman M, Gudex C, Lloyd A, et al. : Development and preliminary testing of the new five-level version of EQ-5D (EQ-5D-5L). Qual Life Res. 2011;20(10):1727–36. 10.1007/s11136-011-9903-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11136-011-9903-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3220807</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21479777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salisbury C, Burgess A, Lattimer V, et al. : Developing a standard short questionnaire for the assessment of patient satisfaction with out-of-hours primary care. Fam Pract. 2005;22(5):560–9. 10.1093/fampra/cmi050</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/fampra/cmi050</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15964865</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Veinot TC, Mitchell H, Ancker JS: Good intentions are not enough: how informatics interventions can worsen inequality. J Am Med Inform Assoc. 2018;25(8):1080–8. 10.1093/jamia/ocy052</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jamia/ocy052</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7646885</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29788380</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>May CR, Eton DT, Boehmer K, et al. : Rethinking the patient: using Burden of Treatment Theory to understand the changing dynamics of illness. BMC Health Serv Res. 2014;14(1): 281. 10.1186/1472-6963-14-281</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1472-6963-14-281</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4080515</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24969758</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng Y, Walsham G: Inequality of what? An intersectional approach to digital inequality under COVID-19. Information and Organization. 2021;31(1): 100341. 10.1016/j.infoandorg.2021.100341</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.infoandorg.2021.100341</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greenhalgh T, Papoutsi C: Spreading and scaling up innovation and improvement. BMJ. 2019;365: l2068. 10.1136/bmj.l2068</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.l2068</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6519511</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31076440</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greenhalgh T, Papoutsi C: Studying complexity in health services research: desperately seeking an overdue paradigm shift. BMC Med. 2018;16(1): 95. 10.1186/s12916-018-1089-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12916-018-1089-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6009054</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29921272</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>