<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39313909</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1365-2141</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>British journal of haematology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Br J Haematol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Re-vaccination against SARS-CoV-2 in allogeneic HSCT patients: Repeated primary vaccine doses increase seroconversion rates.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/bjh.19780</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Patients with haematological malignancies often exhibit reduced antibody responses to severe acute respiratory syndrome-related coronavirus vaccines, especially those who have undergone allogeneic haematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT). Limited data exist on vaccine efficacy in this group. In a retrospective analysis of 75 post-HSCT patients, we assessed serologic responses to one to four doses of Pfizer-BioNTech (PB), AstraZeneca (AZ) or Moderna (MU) vaccines within 2 years post-transplant. Seroconversion rates were 50.7%, 78%, 79% and 83% after the first to fourth doses respectively. The median time from allograft to first re-vaccination was 145 days (range 79-700). Failure to respond to the first vaccine dose was linked to acute GVHD (p = 0.042) and rituximab treatment within 12 months (p = 0.019). A trend was observed with chronic GVHD and seroconversion failure after the second (p = 0.07) and third (p = 0.09) doses. Patients vaccinated before HSCT showed better antibody responses post-transplant (p = 0.019). Coronavirus disease 2019 incidence was 16%, with 17% hospitalized and one death (8%). Despite low initial seroconversion rates post-HSCT, antibody responses improved after the second dose. Early full re-vaccination and boosters post-HSCT are recommended to reduce mortality. Rituximab use and active GVHD were identified as risk factors, warranting further investigation.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 British Society for Haematology and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tsoutsoukis</LastName><ForeName>Marios</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0003-1250-2905</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Royal Marsden NHS Hospital, Sutton, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>United Lincolnshire Hospitals NHS Trust, Lincoln, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Anthias</LastName><ForeName>Chloe</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Royal Marsden NHS Hospital, Sutton, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Easdale</LastName><ForeName>Sandra</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Royal Marsden NHS Hospital, Sutton, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nicholson</LastName><ForeName>Emma</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6439-0795</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Royal Marsden NHS Hospital, Sutton, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Br J Haematol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0372544</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0007-1048</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">HSC transplantation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS‐CoV‐2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vaccines</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>12</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39313909</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/bjh.19780</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Fox TA, Kirkwood AA, Enfield L, O'Reilly M, Arulogun S, D'Sa S, et al. Low seropositivity and suboptimal neutralisation rates in patients fully vaccinated against COVID‐19 with B‐cell malignancies. Br J Haematol. 2021;195(5):706–709.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fendler A, Shepherd STC, Au L, Wilkinson KA, Wu M, Byrne F, et al. Adaptive immunity and neutralizing antibodies against SARS‐CoV‐2 variants of concern following vaccination in patients with cancer: the CAPTURE study. Nat Cancer. 2021;2(12):1305–1320.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fendler A, Shepherd STC, Au L, Wu M, Harvey R, Schmitt AM, et al. Omicron neutralising antibodies after third COVID‐19 vaccine dose in patients with cancer. Lancet. 2022;399(10328):905–907.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fendler A, Shepherd STC, Au L, Wu M, Harvey R, Wilkinson KA, et al. Functional immune responses against SARS‐CoV‐2 variants of concern after fourth COVID‐19 vaccine dose or infection in patients with blood cancer. Cell Rep Med. 2022;3(10):100781.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shem‐Tov N, Yerushalmi R, Danylesko I, Litachevsky V, Levy I, Olmer L, et al. Immunogenicity and safety of the BNT162b2 mRNA COVID‐19 vaccine in haematopoietic stem cell transplantation recipients. Br J Haematol. 2022;196(4):884–891.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Easdale S, Shea R, Ellis L, Bazin J, Davis K, Dallas F, et al. Serologic responses following a single dose of SARS‐Cov‐2 vaccination in allogeneic stem cell transplantation recipients. Transplant Cell Ther. 2021;27(10):880.e1–880.e4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abid MB, Rubin M, Ledeboer N, Szabo A, Longo W, Mohan M, et al. Efficacy of a third SARS‐CoV‐2 mRNA vaccine dose among hematopoietic cell transplantation, CAR T cell, and BiTE recipients. Cancer Cell. 2022;40(4):340–342.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>SARS‐CoV‐2 vaccination following haematopoietic stem cell transplant (HSCT) and chimeric antigen receptor T‐cell (CAR‐T) therapy. Prepared by the British Society of Blood and Marrow Transplantation and Cellular Therapy Vaccination Sub‐Committee (BSBMT‐CT‐VSC).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Canti L, Ariën KK, Desombere I, Humblet‐Baron S, Pannus P, Heyndrickx L, et al. Antibody response against SARS‐CoV‐2 Delta and Omicron variants after third‐dose BNT162b2 vaccination in allo‐HCT recipients. Cancer Cell. 2022;40(4):335–337.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maillard A, Redjoul R, Klemencie M, Labussière Wallet H, le Bourgeois A, D'Aveni M, et al. Antibody response after 2 and 3 doses of SARS‐CoV‐2 mRNA vaccine in allogeneic hematopoietic cell transplant recipients. Blood. 2022;139(1):134–137.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vijenthira A, Gong I, Betschel SD, Cheung M, Hicks LK. Vaccine response following anti‐CD20 therapy: a systematic review and meta‐analysis of 905 patients. Blood Adv. 2021;5(12):2624–2643.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishikubo M, Shimomura Y, Maruoka H, Nasu S, Nishioka T, Sakizono K, et al. Humoral response and safety of the BNT162b2 and mRNA‐1273 COVID‐19 vaccines in patients with haematological diseases treated with anti‐CD20 antibodies: an observational study. Br J Haematol. 2022;197(6):709–713.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Canti L, Humblet‐Baron S, Desombere I, Neumann J, Pannus P, Heyndrickx L, et al. Predictors of neutralizing antibody response to BNT162b2 vaccination in allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplant recipients. J Hematol Oncol. 2021;14(1):174.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Majeed A, Harris Z, Brucks E, Hinchman A, Farooqui AA, Tariq MJ, et al. Revisiting role of vaccinations in donors, transplant recipients, immunocompromised hosts, travelers, and household contacts of stem cell transplant recipients. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant. 2020;26(2):e38–e50.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ambati A, Boas LS, Ljungman P, Testa L, de Oliveira JF, Aoun M, et al. Evaluation of pretransplant influenza vaccination in hematopoietic SCT: a randomized prospective study. Bone Marrow Transplant. 2015;50(6):858–864.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ljungman P, de la Camara R, Mikulska M, Tridello G, Aguado B, Zahrani M, et al. COVID‐19 and stem cell transplantation; results from an EBMT and GETH multicenter prospective survey. Leukemia. 2021;35(10):2885–2894.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>