<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39310546</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>8</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The Impact of COVID-19 on Patients With Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder in Gulf Countries: A Narrative Review.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e67381</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e67381</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e67381</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.67381</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Gulf countries, like other parts of the world, were affected by the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic. Along with its biological effects, the pandemic has had serious psychological and social effects. The pandemic-associated general stress and the increased efforts of handwashing and general hygiene might trigger obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD). The objective of this narrative review was to explore the influence of the COVID-19 pandemic on the prevalence, severity of symptoms, and accessibility of treatment for OCD in Gulf countries. A comprehensive literature search was conducted to review and collect research and/or reports on the prevalence, symptoms, diagnosis, and treatment adaptations and strategies of OCD during the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic in seven Arab Gulf countries. The search spanned from the onset of the crisis in 2020 to 2024. Peer-reviewed articles and reports were sourced from PubMed/Medline and Google Scholar, while abstracts presented at the American Society of Clinical Oncology (ASCO) and the European Society for Medical Oncology (ESMO) congresses were also included in the review. A total of four studies from Saudi Arabia, two from the United Arab Emirates, and two from Qatar were retrieved for analysis. These studies focused on investigating the impact of the pandemic on OCD. Studies from Kuwait, Oman, and Bahrain reported a negative impact of the pandemic on mental health, yet no specific data were provided. The studies highlighted an increased prevalence of OCD symptoms, both in terms of the incidence of new symptoms and the exacerbation of existing pre-pandemic manifestations. Furthermore, individuals with pre-existing psychological disorders or OCD were particularly susceptible to the negative impact of the pandemic. A review of local studies and reports from the Arab Gulf region reveals a striking paucity of research on the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on OCD. The pandemic has been associated with an increase in the prevalence of OCD, the onset of new symptoms, and the worsening and exacerbation of existing pre-pandemic obsessions and compulsions.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Algadeeb et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Algadeeb</LastName><ForeName>Jihad</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Preventive Medicine Department, Al-Ahsa Health Cluster, Ministry of Health, Al-Ahsa, SAU.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alramdan</LastName><ForeName>Mohammed J</ForeName><Initials>MJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Community Wellness Department, Al-Ahsa Health Cluster, Ministry of Health, Al-Ahsa, SAU.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>AlGadeeb</LastName><ForeName>Rahma B</ForeName><Initials>RB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Preventive Medicine Department, Al-Ahsa Health Cluster, Ministry of Health, Al-Ahsa, SAU.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Almusawi</LastName><ForeName>Kumail Naser</ForeName><Initials>KN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatrics Department, King Faisal General Hospital, Al-Ahsa Health Cluster, Ministry of Health, Al-Ahsa, SAU.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">covid-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">gulf region</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mental health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">obsessive-compulsive disorder</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39310546</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11413977</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.67381</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>The global assessment of OCD. Pampaloni I, Marriott S, Pessina E, et al. Compr Psychiatry. 2022;118:152342.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36007341</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clinical advances in treatment strategies for obsessive-compulsive disorder in adults. Roh D, Jang KW, Kim CH. Clin Psychopharmacol Neurosci. 2023;21:676–685.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10591165</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37859440</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Relationship of obsessive-compulsive disorders with religion and psychosocial attitude among local medical college students of Karachi: An epidemiological study. Asghar MA, Rehman AA, Shafiq Y, et al. J Pak Med Assoc. 2020;70:1563–1567.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33040109</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The prevalence of diagnosed obsessive compulsive disorder and associated comorbidities: A population-based Canadian study. Osland S, Arnold PD, Pringsheim T. Psychiatry Res. 2018;268:137–142.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30025284</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>National survey of prevalence of mental disorders in Egypt: Preliminary survey. Ghanem M, Gadallah M, Meky FA, Mourad S, El-Kholy G. East Mediterr Health J. 2009;15:65–75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19469428</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prevalence of mental disorders in the WHO Eastern Mediterranean region: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Zuberi A, Waqas A, Naveed S, Hossain MM, Rahman A, Saeed K, Fuhr DC. Front Psychiatry. 2021;12:665019.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8316754</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34335323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burden and epidemiology of mental disorders in the Middle East and North Africa from 1990 to 2019: Findings from the global burden of disease study. Effatpanah M, Nakhostin-Ansari A, Gorgani F, et al. Balkan Med J. 2024;41:121–129.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10913114</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38332586</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Women are at greater risk of OCD than men: A meta-analytic review of OCD prevalence worldwide. Fawcett EJ, Power H, Fawcett JM. J Clin Psychiatry. 2020;81:19.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32603559</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19, a pandemic that affects more than just physical health: Two case reports. Lim LJ, Fong LM, Hariram J, Lee YW, Tor PC. Asian J Psychiatr. 2020;53:102200.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7282747</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32540751</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Government responses to the COVID-19 pandemic of the Gulf Cooperation Council countries: Good practices and lessons for future preparedness. Chen S, Guo L, Xie Y, et al. Glob Health Res Policy. 2024;9:10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10941437</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38486301</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levels and predictors of anxiety, depression and health anxiety during COVID-19 pandemic in Turkish society: The importance of gender. Özdin S, Bayrak Özdin Ş. Int J Soc Psychiatry. 2020;66:504–511.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7405629</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32380879</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>How to manage obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD) under COVID-19: A clinician's guide from the International College of Obsessive Compulsive Spectrum Disorders (ICOCS) and the Obsessive-Compulsive and Related Disorders Research Network (OCRN) of the European College of Neuropsychopharmacology. Fineberg NA, Van Ameringen M, Drummond L, et al. Compr Psychiatry. 2020;100:152174.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7152877</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32388123</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>How have COVID-19 isolation policies affected young people's mental health? - Evidence from Chinese college students. Chen B, Sun J, Feng Y. Front Psychol. 2020;11:1529.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7327104</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32670172</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Impact of COVID-19 pandemic and lockdown measures on the mental health of the general population in the Gulf Cooperation Council States: A cross-sectional study. Al-Mutawa N, Al-Mutairi N. Front Psychiatry. 2021;12:801002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8721202</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34987435</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Exploring the relationship between context and obsessions in individuals with obsessive-compulsive disorder symptoms: A narrative review. Weiss F, Schwarz K, Endrass T. Front Psychiatry. 2024;15:1353962.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10899460</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38419899</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Impact of COVID-19 on obsessive-compulsive disorder patients. Littman R, Naftalovich H, Huppert JD, Kalanthroff E. Psychiatry Clin Neurosci. 2020;74:660–661.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32920936</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The epidemiology of obsessive-compulsive disorder in the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia: Data from the Saudi National Mental Health Survey. Altwaijri Y, Stein DJ, Akkad M, et al. J Anxiety Disord. 2024;103:102856.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38554604</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Depression and obsessive-compulsive disorders amid the COVID-19 pandemic in Saudi Arabia. AlHusseini N, Sajid M, Altayeb A, Alyousof S, Alsheikh H, Alqahtani A, Alsomali A. Cureus. 2021;13:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7934801</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33728107</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The impact of the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic on the development of obsessive-compulsive symptoms in Saudi Arabia. Alateeq DA, Almughera HN, Almughera TN, Alfedeah RF, Nasser TS, Alaraj KA. Saudi Med J. 2021;42:750–760.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9195531</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34187919</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The impact of COVID-19 pandemic on obsession and compulsion symptoms in Saudi Arabia. Alhujaili N, Alghamdi A, Abo Talib T, Alhaqbani M, Alfelali M, Alghamdi W. Cureus. 2021;13:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8716747</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34987909</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prevalence of post-COVID symptoms of obsessive-compulsive disorder in Saudi Arabia. Alblowi MA, Alkhammash WM, Alzahrani TM, et al. Neurosciences (Riyadh) 2023;28:27–35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9987626</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36617460</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prevalence, sociodemographic and academic correlates of obsessive-compulsive disorder in the students of college of applied medical sciences, Umm Al-Qura university. Sultan S, Fallata EO, Bashar MA, Olaqi EE, Alsharif GH, BinSaleh RA, Fakieh RA. J Obsessive Compuls Relat Disord. 2021;28:100604.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prevalence and comorbidity of depression, anxiety and obsessive compulsive disorders among Saudi secondary school girls, Taif Area, KSA. Desouky Del S, Abdellatif Ibrahem R, Salah Omar M. https://www.researchgate.net/publication/274513650_Prevalence_and_Comorbidity_of_Depression_Anxiety_and_Obsessive_Compulsive_Disorders_among_Saudi_Secondary_School_Girls_Taif_Area_KSA. Arch Iran Med. 2015;18:234–238.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25841944</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Obsessive-compulsive disorder during the COVID-19 pandemic: Preliminary findings from a study in the United Arab Emirates. Hassani GA, Mufaddel AA. Prim Care Companion CNS Disord. 2022;24:21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35254740</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prevalence of OCD symptoms in the UAE during the COVID-19 pandemic: A cross-sectional study. Al Nasere NB, Ali AM, Ali LAM, et al. Research Square. 2022:1–17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 pandemic fears and obsessive-compulsive symptoms in adolescents with pre-existing mental disorders: An exploratory cross-sectional study. Khan YS, Jouda M, Albobali Y, Osman Abouelseoud M, Souid A, AlMeraisi MJ, Alabdulla M. Clin Child Psychol Psychiatry. 2022;27:89–103.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8814615</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34049450</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The impact of COVID-19 pandemic on individuals with pre-existing obsessive-compulsive disorder in the state of Qatar: An exploratory cross-sectional study. Siddiqui M, Wadoo O, Currie J, et al. Front Psychiatry. 2022;13:833394.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9040606</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35492736</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anxiety symptoms among children visiting a pediatric emergency center in Qatar during the COVID-19 pandemic: A cross-sectional study. Khan AW, Khan YS, Khoodoruth MA, Dehwari A, Hammoudeh S, Al-Amri MH, Alabdulla M. Bull Menninger Clin. 2022;86:283–299.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36454154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The prevalence of common mental disorders among the students of Kuwait university after the Covid-19 pandemic. Haggag AA. Research Square. 2022</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Psychological impact of Covid-19 pandemic on the general population of Oman: A national community-based study. Al-Jadidi S, Al-Harrasi M, Kassim NM, Alkalbani A, Muthukrishnan A, Al-Shukaili A. Mal J Med Health Sci. 2022;18:114–121.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Depression, anxiety, and stress among medical students during COVID-19 at Sultan Qaboos University in Oman. AlHarthi AS, AlZaabi A, Al Harthi MS, Al Ghafri TS. Cureus. 2023;15:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10613834</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37908948</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Health, economic, and social implications of COVID-19 for China's rural population. Wang H, Dill SE, Zhou H, et al. Agric Econ. 2021;52:495–504.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8207079</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34149132</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Implication of coronavirus pandemic on obsessive-compulsive-disorder symptoms. Sulaimani MF, Bagadood NH. Rev Environ Health. 2021;36:1–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32866131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The relationship between trauma exposure and obsessive-compulsive disorder in youth: A systematic review. Wislocki K, Kratz HE, Martin G, Becker-Haimes EM. Child Psychiatry Hum Dev. 2023;54:1624–1652.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35488083</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Obsessive-compulsive disorder. Stein DJ, Costa DL, Lochner C, et al. Nat Rev Dis Primers. 2019;5:52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7370844</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31371720</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The other side of COVID-19: Impact on obsessive compulsive disorder (OCD) and hoarding. Banerjee DD. Psychiatry Res. 2020;288:112966.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7151248</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32334276</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Immediate psychological distress in quarantined patients with COVID-19 and its association with peripheral inflammation: A mixed-method study. Guo Q, Zheng Y, Shi J, et al. Brain Behav Immun. 2020;88:17–27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7235603</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32416290</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Impact of COVID-19 and lockdown on mental health of children and adolescents: A narrative review with recommendations. Singh S, Roy D, Sinha K, Parveen S, Sharma G, Joshi G. Psychiatry Res. 2020;293:113429.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7444649</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32882598</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Individual factors predicted to influence outcome in group CBT for psychosis (CBTp) and related therapies. Menon M, Andersen DR, Quilty LC, Woodward TS. Front Psychol. 2015;6:1563.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4623397</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26578995</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Psychobiological factors of resilience and depression in late life. Laird KT, Krause B, Funes C, Lavretsky H. Transl Psychiatry. 2019;9:88.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6375932</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30765686</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stigma on mental illness in the Arab world: Beyond the socio-cultural barriers. Merhej R. Int J Hum Rights Healthc. 2019;12:285–298.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahman MM, Al-Azm A. Singapore: Springer Nature; 2023. Social Change and Transformation in the Gulf Region. Social Change in the Gulf Region: Multidisciplinary Perspectives.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Influence of culture in obsessive-compulsive disorder and its treatment. Nicolini H, Salin-Pascual R, Cabrera B, Lanzagorta N. Curr Psychiatry Rev. 2017;13:285–292.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5872369</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29657563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Impact of COVID-19 pandemic on utilization of healthcare services and spending patterns in Dubai, United Arab Emirates: A cross-sectional study. Soni MM, Mamdouh HM, Suliman EA. Healthcare (Basel) 2024;12:473.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11290142</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38391849</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The nature and availability of mental health services in Arab Gulf countries: A scoping review. Alanazi TNM, McKenna L, Buck M. Saudi J Health Syst Res. 2023;3:10–34.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Efficacy of a six-week-long therapist-guided online therapy versus self-help internet-based therapy for COVID-19-induced anxiety and depression: Open-label, pragmatic, randomized controlled trial. Al-Alawi M, McCall RK, Sultan A, et al. JMIR Ment Health. 2021;8:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7886373</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33512323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The role of telehealth in reducing the mental health burden from COVID-19. Zhou X, Snoswell CL, Harding LE, Bambling M, Edirippulige S, Bai X, Smith AC. Telemed J E Health. 2020;26:377–379.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32202977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Effect of COVID-19 pandemic on patient utilization of the telemedicine services in Dubai. Swidan A, Alnoon NA, Makki I, et al. Dubai Med J. 2022;5:110–116.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Telehealth to the rescue during COVID-19: A convergent mixed methods study investigating patients' perception. Al-Sharif GA, Almulla AA, AlMerashi E, et al. Front Public Health. 2021;9:730647.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8669510</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34917570</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Telehealth: Seven strategies to successfully implement disruptive technology and transform health care. Schwamm LH. Health Aff (Millwood) 2014;33:200–206.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24493761</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Telepsychiatry in the Arab world: A viewpoint before and during COVID-19. El Hayek S, Nofal M, Abdelrahman D, et al. Neuropsychiatr Dis Treat. 2020;16:2805–2815.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7682595</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33239877</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 and telepsychiatry: Development of evidence-based guidance for clinicians. Smith K, Ostinelli E, Macdonald O, Cipriani A. JMIR Ment Health. 2020;7:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7485934</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32658857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Obsessive compulsive disorder during the COVID-19 pandemic: A brief review of course, psychological assessment and treatment considerations. Maye CE, Wojcik KD, Candelari AE, Goodman WK, Storch EA. J Obsessive Compuls Relat Disord. 2022;33:100722.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8855616</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35194549</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>How are OCD patients and their families coping with the COVID-19 pandemic? A qualitative study. Tandt HL, Van Parys H, Leyman L, Purdon C, Lemmens GM. Curr Psychol. 2022;41:505–515.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8040748</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33867778</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Physical exercise as therapy to fight against the mental and physical consequences of COVID-19 quarantine: Special focus in older people. Jiménez-Pavón D, Carbonell-Baeza A, Lavie CJ. Prog Cardiovasc Dis. 2020;63:386–388.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7118448</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32220590</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Exacerbation of obsessive compulsive disorder symptoms in children and adolescents during COVID-19 pandemic. Tanir Y, Karayagmurlu A, Kaya İ, et al. Psychiatry Res. 2020;293:113363.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7837048</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32798931</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Acute exacerbation of OCD symptoms precipitated by media reports of COVID-19. French I, Lyne J. Ir J Psychol Med. 2020;37:291–294.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7306547</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32434605</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on patients with OCD: Effects of contamination symptoms and remission state before the quarantine in a preliminary naturalistic study. Davide P, Andrea P, Martina O, Andrea E, Davide D, Mario A. Psychiatry Res. 2020;291:113213.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7280119</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32535508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Obsessive-compulsive disorder during the COVID-19 pandemic: A systematic review. Guzick AG, Candelari A, Wiese AD, Schneider SC, Goodman WK, Storch EA. Curr Psychiatry Rep. 2021;23:71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8493778</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34613498</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Obsessive-compulsive symptoms and the Covid-19 pandemic: A rapid scoping review. Grant JE, Drummond L, Nicholson TR, Fagan H, Baldwin DS, Fineberg NA, Chamberlain SR. Neurosci Biobehav Rev. 2022;132:1086–1098.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8570941</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34740755</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Obsessive-compulsive disorder during the COVID-19 pandemic-A systematic review. Linde ES, Varga TV, Clotworthy A. Front Psychiatry. 2022;13:806872.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8989845</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35401266</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>