<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39312696</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2220-315X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>14</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>20</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>World journal of experimental medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>World J Exp Med</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Phytochemical analysis of <i>Tinospora cordifolia</i> and <i>Withania somnifera</i> and their therapeutic activities with special reference to COVID-19.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>95512</StartPage><MedlinePgn>95512</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">95512</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.5493/wjem.v14.i3.95512</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Various important medicines make use of secondary metabolites that are produced by plants. Medicinal plants, such as <i>Withania somnifera</i> and <i>Tinospora cordifolia</i>, are rich sources of chemically active compounds and are reported to have numerous therapeutic applications. The therapeutic use of medicinal plants is widely mentioned in Ayurveda and has folkloric importance in different parts of the world. The aim of this review is to summarize the phytochemical profiles, folkloric importance, and primary pharmacological activity of <i>W. somnifera</i> and <i>T. cordifolia</i> with emphasis on their action against the novel coronavirus.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>©The Author(s) 2024. Published by Baishideng Publishing Group Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rai</LastName><ForeName>Prateek</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Chemistry, Amity Institute of Applied Sciences, Amity University, Noida 201301, Uttar Pradesh, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Garain</LastName><ForeName>Tanya</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Chemistry, Amity Institute of Applied Sciences, Amity University, Noida 201301, Uttar Pradesh, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gupta</LastName><ForeName>Deepshikha</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Chemistry, Amity Institute of Applied Sciences, Amity University, Noida 201301, Uttar Pradesh, India. deep34.gupta@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>20</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>World J Exp Med</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101618808</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2220-315X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Ashwagandha</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Giloy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Immunomodulators</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Phytochemical analysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Tinospora cordifolia</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Withania somnifera</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflict-of-interest statement: No competing interests or conflicts to declare.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>15</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39312696</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11372741</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5493/wjem.v14.i3.95512</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Suwannarach N, Kumla J, Sujarit K, Pattananandecha T, Saenjum C, Lumyong S. Natural Bioactive Compounds from Fungi as Potential Candidates for Protease Inhibitors and Immunomodulators to Apply for Coronaviruses. Molecules. 2020;25</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7221821</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32295300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali K, Shuaib M, Ilyas M, Hussain F, Hussain F. Medicinal Uses of Chemical Extracts from Withania somnifera and Its Antimicrobial Activity: A Mini-Review. PSM Microbiology. 2017;2:20–23.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mittal J, Sharma MM, Batra A. Tinospora cordifolia: a multipurpose medicinal plant- A review. J Med Plants Stud. 2014;2:32–47.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mukherjee P, Nema N, Pandit S, Mukherjee K. Indian Medicinal Plants with Hypoglycemic Potential. Bioactive Food as Dietary Interventions for Diabetes, 2013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Srivastava AK, Chaurasia JP, Dhand C, Khan R, Verma S. Role of Medicinal Plants of Traditional Use in Recuperating Devastating Role of Medicinal Plants of Traditional Use in Recuperating Devastating COVID-19 Situation. Med Aromat Plants (Los Angel) 2020;9:1–16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saiyed A, Jahan N, Majeedi SF, Roqaiya M. Medicinal properties, phytochemistry and pharmacology of Withania somnifera: an important drug of Unani Medicine. J Sci Innov Res. 2016;5:156–160.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doshi GM, Une HD, Shanbhag PP. Rasayans and non-rasayans herbs: Future immunodrug - Targets. Pharmacogn Rev. 2013;7:92–96.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3842000</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24347916</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chulet R, Pradhan P. A review on rasayana. Pharmacogn Rev. 2009;3:229–234.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balasubramani SP, Venkatasubramanian P, Kukkupuni SK, Patwardhan B. Plant-based Rasayana drugs from Ayurveda. Chin J Integr Med. 2011;17:88–94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21390573</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thakur M, Weng A, Fuchs H, Sharma V, Bhargava CS, Chauhan NS, Dixit VK, Bhargava S. Rasayana properties of Ayurvedic herbs: Are polysaccharides a major contributor. Carbohydr Polym. 2012;87:3–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34662964</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta GD, Sujatha N, Dhanik A, Rai NP. Clinical Evaluation of Shilajatu Rasayana in patients with HIV Infection. Ayu. 2010;31:28–32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3215318</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22131681</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baliga MS, Meera S, Shivashankara AR, Palatty PL, Haniadka R. The Health Benefits of Indian Traditional Ayurvedic Rasayana (Anti-aging) Drugs: A Review. In: Watson RR, Preedy VR, editors. Foods and Dietary Supplements in the Prevention and Treatment of Disease in Older Adults. San Diego: Academic Press, 2015: 151-161.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng WS, Li M, Hao ZY, Zhang JK. Analytical Methods of Isolation and Identification. In: Rao V, Mans D, Rao L, editors. Phytochemicals in Human Health. London: IntechOpen, 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Filipiak-Szok A, Kurzawa M, Szłyk E, Twarużek M, Błajet-Kosicka A, Grajewski J. Determination of mycotoxins, alkaloids, phytochemicals, antioxidants and cytotoxicity in Asiatic ginseng (Ashwagandha, Dong quai, Panax ginseng) Chem Zvesti. 2017;71:1073–1082.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5425489</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28553006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ansari J, Khan A, Ahmad M, Fatima N, Rastogi N, Khan M, Khan H, Mahdi A. Phytochemicals, Antioxidant and Antiproliferative Studies of Some Medicinal Plants from Indian Sub-continent. BJPR. 2016;11:1–11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Altemimi A, Lakhssassi N, Baharlouei A, Watson DG, Lightfoot DA. Phytochemicals: Extraction, Isolation, and Identification of Bioactive Compounds from Plant Extracts. Plants (Basel) 2017;6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5750618</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28937585</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gurib-Fakim A. Medicinal plants: traditions of yesterday and drugs of tomorrow. Mol Aspects Med. 2006;27:1–93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16105678</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sibi PI, Rahees T. Tinosporacordifolia: A potential plant with immunomodulatory activity. IJPT. 2013;12:30–38.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spandana U, Ali SL, Nirmala T, Santhi M, Sipai Babu SD. A review on tinospora cordifolia. IJPPR. 2013;4:61–68.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saha S, Ghosh S. Tinospora cordifolia: One plant, many roles. Anc Sci Life. 2012;31:151–159.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3644751</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23661861</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choudhary N, Siddiqui MB, Azmat S, Khatoon S. Tinospora Cordifolia: Ethnobotany, Phytopharmacology and Phytochemistry Aspects. IJPSR. 2013;4:891–899.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaur G, Prabhakar PK, Lal UR, Suttee A. Phytochemical and biological analysis of Tinospora cordifolia. IJTPR. 2016;8:297–305.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tiwari P, Nayak P, Prusty SK, Sahu PK. Phytochemistry and Pharmacology of Tinospora cordifolia: A Review. SRP. 2018;9:70–78.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kulkarni SK, Dhir A. Withania somnifera: an Indian ginseng. Prog Neuropsychopharmacol Biol Psychiatry. 2008;32:1093–1105.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17959291</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dar NJ, Hamid A, Ahmad M. Pharmacologic overview of Withania somnifera, the Indian Ginseng. Cell Mol Life Sci. 2015;72:4445–4460.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11113996</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26306935</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dhar RS, Verma V, Suri KA, Sangwan RS, Satti NK, Kumar A, Tuli R, Qazi GN. Phytochemical and genetic analysis in selected chemotypes of Withania somnifera. Phytochemistry. 2006;67:2269–2276.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16956635</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uddin Q, Samiulla L, Singh VK, Jamil SS. Phytochemical and pharmacological profile of Withania somnifera dunal: A review. J Appl Pharm Sci. 2012;2:170–175.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalra R, Kaushik N. Withania somnifera (Linn.) Dunal: a review of chemical and pharmacological diversity. Phytochem Rev. 2017;16:953–987.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dar PA, Singh LR, Kamal MA, Dar TA. Unique Medicinal Properties of Withania somnifera: Phytochemical Constituents and Protein Component. Curr Pharm Des. 2016;22:535–540.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26601969</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murugesan S, Kottekad S, Crasta I, Sreevathsan S, Usharani D, Perumal MK, Mudliar SN. Targeting COVID-19 (SARS-CoV-2) main protease through active phytocompounds of ayurvedic medicinal plants - Emblica officinalis (Amla), Phyllanthus niruri Linn. (Bhumi Amla) and Tinospora cordifolia (Giloy) - A molecular docking and simulation study. Comput Biol Med. 2021;136:104683.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8302490</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34329860</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Srivastava MP, Gupta S, Dixit S, Yadav N, Yadav V, Singh H, Kanaujia P, Sharma YK. Withania somnifera (Ashwagandha): A wonder herb with multiple medicinal properties. Asian J Pharm Pharmacol. 2018;4:123–130.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mikulska P, Malinowska M, Ignacyk M, Szustowski P, Nowak J, Pesta K, Szeląg M, Szklanny D, Judasz E, Kaczmarek G, Ejiohuo OP, Paczkowska-Walendowska M, Gościniak A, Cielecka-Piontek J. Ashwagandha (Withania somnifera)-Current Research on the Health-Promoting Activities: A Narrative Review. Pharmaceutics. 2023;15</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10147008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37111543</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choudhry N, Singh S, Siddiqui MB, Khatoon S. Impact of seasons and dioecy on therapeutic phytoconstituents of Tinospora cordifolia, a Rasayana drug. Biomed Res Int. 2014;2014:902138.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4142535</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25177701</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maurya R. Chemistry and pharmacology of Withania coagulans: an Ayurvedic remedy. J Pharm Pharmacol. 2010;62:153–160.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20487193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bashir A, Nabi M, Tabassum N, Afzal S, Ayoub M. An updated review on phytochemistry and molecular targets of Withania somnifera (L.) Dunal (Ashwagandha) Front Pharmacol. 2023;14:1049334.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10090468</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37063285</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saleem A, Akhtar MF, Haris M, Abdel-Daim MM. Recent updates on immunological, pharmacological, and alternative approaches to combat COVID-19. Inflammopharmacology. 2021;29:1331–1346.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8324454</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34331179</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Saber Batiha G, Magdy Beshbishy A, El-Mleeh A, Abdel-Daim MM, Prasad Devkota H. Traditional Uses, Bioactive Chemical Constituents, and Pharmacological and Toxicological Activities of Glycyrrhiza glabra L. (Fabaceae) Biomolecules. 2020;10</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7175350</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32106571</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aher V, Wahi A. Pharmacological study of Tinospora cordifolia as an immunomodulator. Int J Curr Pharm Res. 2010;2:50–52.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Srivastava N, Chauhan AS, Sharma B. Isolation and characterization of some phytochemicals from Indian traditional plants. Biotechnol Res Int. 2012;2012:549850.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3529893</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23304524</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma P, Dwivedee BP, Bisht D, Dash AK, Kumar D. The chemical constituents and diverse pharmacological importance of Tinospora cordifolia. Heliyon. 2019;5:e02437.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6827274</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31701036</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar V, Singh S, Singh A, Dixit AK, Srivastava B, Sidhu GK, Singh R, Meena AK, Singh RP, Subhose V, Prakash O. Phytochemical, Antioxidant, Antimicrobial, and Protein Binding Qualities of Hydro-ethanolic Extract of Tinospora cordifolia. JBAPN. 2018;8:192–200.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kavitha BT, Shruthi SD, Rai SP, Ramachandra YL. Phytochemical analysis and hepatoprotective properties of Tinospora cordifolia against carbon tetrachloride-induced hepatic damage in rats. J Basic Clin Pharm. 2011;2:139–142.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3979222</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24826014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xia GY, Cao SJ, Chen LX, Qiu F. Natural withanolides, an update. Nat Prod Rep. 2022;39:784–813.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34816854</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reddy NM, Reddy R. Tinospora cordifolia Chemical Constituents and Medicinal Properties: A Review. SAJP. 2015;4:364–369.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kavya B, Kavya N, Ramarao V, Venkateshwarlu G. Tinospora Cordifolia (Willd.) Miers.: Nutritional, Ethnomedical And Therapeutic Utility. Int J Res Ayurveda Pharm. 2015;6:195–198.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phan VK, Chau VM, Nguyen TD, La VK, Dan TH, Nguyen HN, Nguyen XC, Hoang TH, Trinh VL. Aporphine alkaloids, clerodane diterpenes, and other constituents from Tinospora cordifolia. Fitoterapia. 2010;81:485–489.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20080155</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaur LB, Singh SP, Gaur SC, Bornare SS, Chavan AS, Kumar S, Ram M. A Basic Information, Cultivation and Medicinal Use of Tinospora cordifolia. Popular Kheti. 2014;2:188–192.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maurya R, Wazir V, Kapil A, Kapil RS. Cordifoliosides A and B, two New Phenylpropene Disaccharides fromTinospora cordifoliapossessing Immunostimulant Activity. Natural Product Letters. 1996;8:7–10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali H, Dixit S. Extraction optimization of Tinospora cordifolia and assessment of the anticancer activity of its alkaloid palmatine. ScientificWorldJournal. 2013;2013:376216.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3863568</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24379740</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghosal S, Vishwakarma RA. Tinocordiside, a New Rearranged Cadinane Sesquiterpene Glycoside from Tinospora cordifolia. J Nat Prod. 1997;60:839–841.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Budhiraja R, Krishan P, Sudhir S. Biological Activity of Withanolides. JSIR. 2000;59:904–911.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choudhary MI, Nawaz SA, ul-Haq Z, Lodhi MA, Ghayur MN, Jalil S, Riaz N, Yousuf S, Malik A, Gilani AH, ur-Rahman A. Withanolides, a new class of natural cholinesterase inhibitors with calcium antagonistic properties. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 2005;334:276–287.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16108094</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abou-Douh AM. New withanolides and other constituents from the fruit of Withania somnifera. Arch Pharm (Weinheim) 2002;335:267–276.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12210769</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verma SK, Kumar A. Therapeutic uses of withania somnifera (Ashwagandha) with a note on withanolides and its pharmacological actions. AJPCR. 2011;4:1–4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kapil A, Sharma S. Immunopotentiating compounds from Tinospora cordifolia. J Ethnopharmacol. 1997;58:89–95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9406896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akhtar S. Use of Tinospora cordifolia in HIV infection. Indian J Pharmacol. 2010;42:57.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2885645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20606842</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sinha K, Mishra N, Singh J, Khanuja S. Tinospora cordifolia (Guduchi), a reservoir plant for therapeutic applications: A Review. IJTK. 2004;03:257–270.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sudhakaran DS, Srirekha P, Devasree LD, Premsingh S, Michael RD. Immunostimulatory effect of Tinospora cordifolia Miers leaf extract in Oreochromis mossambicus. Indian J Exp Biol. 2006;44:726–732.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16999027</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mishra P, Jamdar P, Desai S, Patel D, Meshram D. Phytochemical analysis and assessment of in vitro antibacterial activity of Tinospora cordifolia. Int J Curr Microbiol App Sci. 2014;3:224–234.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verma R, Khan AB. Antioxidant, Immunomodulatory and Anticancer Potential of Tinospora Cordifolia - a Review. Int J Pharm Biol Sci. 2018;8:54–69.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruan CT, Lam SH, Chi TC, Lee SS, Su MJ. Borapetoside C from Tinospora crispa improves insulin sensitivity in diabetic mice. Phytomedicine. 2012;19:719–724.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22579212</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>White PT, Subramanian C, Motiwala HF, Cohen MS. Natural Withanolides in the Treatment of Chronic Diseases. Adv Exp Med Biol. 2016;928:329–373.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7121644</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27671823</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ascher KRS, Eliyahu M, Glotter E, Kirson I, Abraham A. Distribution of the chemotypes ofWithania somnifera in some areas of Israel: Feeding studies withSpodoptera littoralis larvae and chemical examination of withanolide content. Phytoparasitica. 1984;12:147–155.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dhawan M, Parmar M, Sharun K, Tiwari R, Bilal M, Aq KD. Medicinal and therapeutic potential of withanolides from Withania somnifera against COVID-19. J Appl Pharm Sci. 2021;11:006–013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh A, Raza A, Amin S, Damodaran C, Sharma AK. Recent Advances in the Chemistry and Therapeutic Evaluation of Naturally Occurring and Synthetic Withanolides. Molecules. 2022;27</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8840339</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35164150</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarbishegi M, Heidari Z, Mahmoudzadeh-Sagheb H, Valizadeh M, Doostkami M. Neuroprotective effects of Withania coagulans root extract on CA1 hippocampus following cerebral ischemia in rats. Avicenna J Phytomed. 2016;6:399–409.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4967835</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27516980</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaurav H, Yadav D, Maurya A, Yadav H, Yadav R, Shukla AC, Sharma M, Gupta VK, Palazon J. Biodiversity, Biochemical Profiling, and Pharmaco-Commercial Applications of Withania somnifera: A Review. Molecules. 2023;28</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9921868</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36770874</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khanna K, Kohli SK, Kaur R, Bhardwaj A, Bhardwaj V, Ohri P, Sharma A, Ahmad A, Bhardwaj R, Ahmad P. Herbal immune-boosters: Substantial warriors of pandemic Covid-19 battle. Phytomedicine. 2021;85:153361.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7532351</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33485605</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kashyap VK, Dhasmana A, Yallapu MM, Chauhan SC, Jaggi M. Withania somnifera as a potential future drug molecule for COVID-19. Future Drug Discov. 2020;2:FDD50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7702281</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33269342</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borse S, Joshi M, Saggam A, Bhat V, Walia S, Marathe A, Sagar S, Chavan-Gautam P, Girme A, Hingorani L, Tillu G. Ayurveda botanicals in COVID-19 management: An in silico multi-target approach. PLoS One. 2021;16:e0248479.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8195371</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34115763</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rawat K, Kumari P, Saha L. COVID-19 vaccine: A recent update in pipeline vaccines, their design and development strategies. Eur J Pharmacol. 2021;892:173751.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7685956</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33245898</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang F, Zhang Y, Tariq A, Jiang X, Ahmed Z, Zhihao Z, Idrees M, Azizullah A, Adnan M, Bussmann RW. Food as medicine: A possible preventive measure against coronavirus disease (COVID-19) Phytother Res. 2020;34:3124–3136.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7283886</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32468635</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaul SC, Wadhwa R. Science of Ashwagandha: Preventive and Therapeutic Potentials. Cham: Springer Cham, 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh N, Yadav SS, Rao AS, Nandal A, Kumar S, Ganaie SA, Narasihman B. Review on anticancerous therapeutic potential of Withania somnifera (L.) Dunal. J Ethnopharmacol. 2021;270:113704.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33359918</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Straughn AR, Kakar SS. Withaferin A: a potential therapeutic agent against COVID-19 infection. J Ovarian Res. 2020;13:79.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7369003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32684166</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>John J. Therapeutic potential of Withania somnifera: A report on phyto-pharmacological properties. Int J Pharm Sci Res. 2014;5:2131–2148.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sudeep HV, Gouthamchandra K, Shyamprasad K. Molecular docking analysis of Withaferin A from Withania somnifera with the Glucose regulated protein 78 (GRP78) receptor and the SARS-CoV-2 main protease. Bioinformation. 2020;16:411–417.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7434955</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32831523</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shree P, Mishra P, Selvaraj C, Singh SK, Chaube R, Garg N, Tripathi YB. Targeting COVID-19 (SARS-CoV-2) main protease through active phytochemicals of ayurvedic medicinal plants - Withania somnifera (Ashwagandha), Tinospora cordifolia (Giloy) and Ocimum sanctum (Tulsi) - a molecular docking study. J Biomol Struct Dyn. 2022;40:190–203.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7484581</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32851919</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prajapati KS, Singh AK, Kushwaha PP, Shuaib M, Maurya SK, Gupta S, Senapati S, Singh SP, Waseem M, Kumar S. Withaniasomnifera phytochemicals possess SARS-CoV-2 RdRp and human TMPRSS2 protein binding potential. Vegetos. 2023;36:701–720.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9199469</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35729946</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abood WN, Fahmi I, Abdulla MA, Ismail S. Immunomodulatory effect of an isolated fraction from Tinospora crispa on intracellular expression of INF-γ, IL-6 and IL-8. BMC Complement Altern Med. 2014;14:205.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4227069</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24969238</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dhama K, Sachan S, Khandia R, Munjal A, Iqbal HMN, Latheef SK, Karthik K, Samad HA, Tiwari R, Dadar M. Medicinal and Beneficial Health Applications of Tinospora cordifolia (Guduchi): A Miraculous Herb Countering Various Diseases/Disorders and its Immunomodulatory Effects. Recent Pat Endocr Metab Immune Drug Discov. 2017;10:96–111.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28260522</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bala M, Pratap K, Verma PK, Singh B, Padwad Y. Validation of ethnomedicinal potential of Tinospora cordifolia for anticancer and immunomodulatory activities and quantification of bioactive molecules by HPTLC. J Ethnopharmacol. 2015;175:131–137.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26253577</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalikar MV, Thawani VR, Varadpande UK, Sontakke SD, Singh RP, Khiyani RK. Immunomodulatory effect of Tinospora cordifolia extract in human immuno-deficiency virus positive patients. Indian J Pharmacol. 2008;40:107–110.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2792597</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20040936</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamra Verma A, Anita VK. Assessment of the Multifaceted Immunomodulatory Potential of the Aqueous Extract of Tinospora Cordifolia. Res J Chem Sci. 1:71–79.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma U, Bala M, Kumar N, Singh B, Munshi RK, Bhalerao S. Immunomodulatory active compounds from Tinospora cordifolia. J Ethnopharmacol. 2012;141:918–926.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22472109</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jena S, Munusami P, Mm B, Chanda K. Computationally approached inhibition potential of Tinospora cordifolia towards COVID-19 targets. Virusdisease. 2021;32:65–77.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7980128</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33778129</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krupanidhi S, Abraham Peele K, Venkateswarulu TC, Ayyagari VS, Nazneen Bobby M, John Babu D, Venkata Narayana A, Aishwarya G. Screening of phytochemical compounds of Tinospora cordifolia for their inhibitory activity on SARS-CoV-2: an in silico study. J Biomol Struct Dyn. 2021;39:5799–5803.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7441789</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32627715</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mulpuru V, Mishra N. Computational Identification of SARS-CoV-2 Inhibitor in Tinospora cordifolia, Cinnamomum zeylanicum and Myristica fragrans. Virus disease. 2021;32:511–517.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8312711</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34337109</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaudhary A, Das R, Mehta K, Mehta DK. Indian herb Tinospora cordifolia and Tinospora species: Phytochemical and therapeutic application. Heliyon. 2024;10:e31229.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11133831</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38813196</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thakkar SS, Shelat F, Thakor P. Magical bullets from an indigenous Indian medicinal plant Tinospora cordifolia: An in silico approach for the antidote of SARS-CoV-2. Egypt J Pet. 2021;30:53–66.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kulkarni AV, Hanchanale P, Prakash V, Kalal C, Sharma M, Kumar K, Bishnu S, Kulkarni AV, Anand L, Patwa AK, Kumbar S, Kainth S, Philips CA Liver Research Club India. Tinospora Cordifolia (Giloy)-Induced Liver Injury During the COVID-19 Pandemic-Multicenter Nationwide Study From India. Hepatol Commun. 2022;6:1289–1300.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9134809</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35037744</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Panneer Selvam K, Payyappallimana U, Ravikumar K, Venkatasubramanian P. Can Guduchi (Tinospora cordifolia), a well-known ayurvedic hepato-protectant cause liver damage? J Ayurveda Integr Med. 2023;14:100658.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10105241</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36400639</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>