<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39311916</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1432-1084</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>European radiology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Eur Radiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Diagnostic performance of radiologists in distinguishing post-COVID-19 residual abnormalities from interstitial lung abnormalities.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s00330-024-11075-x</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">Distinguishing post-COVID-19 residual abnormalities from interstitial lung abnormalities (ILA) on CT can be challenging if clinical information is limited. This study aimed to evaluate the diagnostic performance of radiologists in distinguishing post-COVID-19 residual abnormalities from ILA.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">This multi-reader, multi-case study included 60 age- and sex-matched subjects with chest CT scans. There were 40 cases of ILA (20 fibrotic and 20 non-fibrotic) and 20 cases of post-COVID-19 residual abnormalities. Fifteen radiologists from multiple nations with varying levels of experience independently rated suspicion scores on a 5-point scale to distinguish post-COVID-19 residual abnormalities from fibrotic ILA or non-fibrotic ILA. Interobserver agreement was assessed using the weighted κ value, and the scores of individual readers were compared with the consensus of all readers. Receiver operating characteristic curve analysis was conducted to evaluate the diagnostic performance of suspicion scores for distinguishing post-COVID-19 residual abnormalities from ILA and for differentiating post-COVID-19 residual abnormalities from both fibrotic and non-fibrotic ILA.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Radiologists' diagnostic performance for distinguishing post-COVID-19 residual abnormalities from ILA was good (area under the receiver operating characteristic curve (AUC) range, 0.67-0.92; median AUC, 0.85) with moderate agreement (κ = 0.56). The diagnostic performance for distinguishing post-COVID-19 residual abnormalities from non-fibrotic ILA was lower than that from fibrotic ILA (median AUC = 0.89 vs. AUC = 0.80, p = 0.003).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Radiologists demonstrated good diagnostic performance and moderate agreement in distinguishing post-COVID-19 residual abnormalities from ILA, but careful attention is needed to avoid misdiagnosing them as non-fibrotic ILA.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="KEY POINTS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Question How good are radiologists at differentiating interstitial lung abnormalities (ILA) from changes related to COVID-19 infection? Findings Radiologists had a median AUC of 0.85 in distinguishing post-COVID-19 abnormalities from ILA with moderate agreement (κ = 0.56). Clinical relevance Radiologists showed good diagnostic performance and moderate agreement in distinguishing post-COVID-19 residual abnormalities from ILA; nonetheless, caution is needed in distinguishing residual abnormalities from non-fibrotic ILA.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lee</LastName><ForeName>Jong Eun</ForeName><Initials>JE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology and Research Institute of Radiology, Asan Medical Center, Seoul, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lee</LastName><ForeName>Hyo-Jae</ForeName><Initials>HJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, Chonnam National University Hospital Gwangju, Gwangju, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Park</LastName><ForeName>Gyeryeong</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, Chonnam National University Hospital Gwangju, Gwangju, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chae</LastName><ForeName>Kum Ju</ForeName><Initials>KJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, Research Institute of Clinical Medicine of Jeonbuk National University-Biomedical Research Institute of Jeonbuk National University Hospital, Jeonju, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jin</LastName><ForeName>Kwang Nam</ForeName><Initials>KN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, Seoul National University-Seoul Metropolitan Government Boramae Medical Center, Seoul, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Castañer</LastName><ForeName>Eva</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, Parc Taulí Hospital Universitari, Institut d'Investigació i Innovació Parc Taulí (I3PT-CERCA), Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona, Sabadell, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ghaye</LastName><ForeName>Benoit</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, Cliniques Universitaires Saint Luc, Catholic University of Louvain, Brussels, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ko</LastName><ForeName>Jane P</ForeName><Initials>JP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, NYU Langone Health, NYU Grossman School of Medicine, New York, NY, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Prosch</LastName><ForeName>Helmut</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Imaging and Image-Guided Therapy, Medical University of Vienna, Vienna General Hospital, Vienna, Austria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Simpson</LastName><ForeName>Scott</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, Hospital of the University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Larici</LastName><ForeName>Anna Rita</ForeName><Initials>AR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Diagnostic Imaging and Oncological Radiotherapy, Department of Radiological and Hematological Sciences, A. Gemelli University Polyclinic Foundation IRCCS, Catholic University of the Sacred Heart, Rome, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kanne</LastName><ForeName>Jeffrey P</ForeName><Initials>JP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, University of Wisconsin School of Medicine and Public Health, Madison, WI, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Frauenfelder</LastName><ForeName>Thomas</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Diagnostic and Interventional Radiology, University Hospital Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jeong</LastName><ForeName>Yeon Joo</ForeName><Initials>YJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, Research Institute for Convergence of Biomedical Science and Technology, Pusan National University Yangsan Hospital, Pusan National University School of Medicine, Yangsan, Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yoon</LastName><ForeName>Soon Ho</ForeName><Initials>SH</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3700-0165</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, Seoul National University College of Medicine, Seoul National University Hospital, Seoul, Korea. yshoka@snu.ac.kr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Eur Radiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9114774</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0938-7994</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Diagnostic imaging</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Lung diseases, Interstitial</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Tomography, X-ray computed</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39311916</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00330-024-11075-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s00330-024-11075-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (WHO) COVID-19 dashboard. https://data.who.int/dashboards/covid19/cases/ . Accessed March, 2023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fabbri L, Moss S, Khan FA et al (2023) Parenchymal lung abnormalities following hospitalisation for COVID-19 and viral pneumonitis: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Thorax 78:191–201</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2021-218275</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35338102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stewart I, Jacob J, George PM et al (2023) Residual lung abnormalities after COVID-19 hospitalization: interim analysis of the UKILD post–COVID-19 study. Am J Respir Crit Care Med 207:693–703</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1164/rccm.202203-0564OC</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36457159</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang P, Li J, Liu H et al (2020) Long-term bone and lung consequences associated with hospital-acquired severe acute respiratory syndrome: a 15-year follow-up from a prospective cohort study. Bone Res 8:8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41413-020-0084-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32128276</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7018717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burnham EL, Janssen WJ, Riches DW, Moss M, Downey GP (2014) The fibroproliferative response in acute respiratory distress syndrome: mechanisms and clinical significance. Eur Respir J 43:276–285</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1183/09031936.00196412</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23520315</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hata A, Schiebler ML, Lynch DA, Hatabu H (2021) Interstitial lung abnormalities: state of the art. Radiology 301:19–34</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1148/radiol.2021204367</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34374589</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoon SH, Ham S-Y, Da Nam B et al (2020) Establishment of a nationwide Korean imaging cohort of coronavirus disease 2019. J Korean Med Sci 35:e413</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3346/jkms.2020.35.e413</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33258333</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7707929</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehta P, Rosas IO, Singer M (2022) Understanding post-COVID-19 interstitial lung disease (ILD): a new fibroinflammatory disease entity. Intensive Care Med 48:1803–1806</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00134-022-06877-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36074167</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9453725</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hatabu H, Hunninghake GM, Richeldi L et al (2020) Interstitial lung abnormalities detected incidentally on CT: a Position Paper from the Fleischner Society. Lancet Respir Med 8:726–737</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(20)30168-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32649920</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7970441</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cha MJ, Solomon JJ, Lee JE et al (2024) Chronic lung injury after COVID-19 pneumonia: clinical, radiologic, and histopathologic perspectives. Radiology 310:e231643</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1148/radiol.231643</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38193836</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee JH, Koh J, Jeon YK, Goo JM, Yoon SH (2023) An integrated radiologic-pathologic understanding of COVID-19 pneumonia. Radiology 306:e222600</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1148/radiol.222600</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36648343</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murphy MC, Little BP (2023) Chronic pulmonary manifestations of COVID-19 infection: imaging evaluation. Radiology 307:e222379</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1148/radiol.222379</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36692398</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han X, Chen L, Fan Y et al (2023) Longitudinal assessment of chest CT findings and pulmonary function after COVID-19 infection. Radiology 307:e222888</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1148/radiol.222888</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36786698</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang H, Huang C, Gu X et al (2024) 3-year outcomes of discharged survivors of COVID-19 following the SARS-CoV-2 omicron (B.1.1.529) wave in 2022 in China: a longitudinal cohort study. Lancet Respir Med 12:55–66</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(23)00387-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38000376</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watanabe A, So M, Iwagami M et al (2022) One‐year follow‐up CT findings in COVID‐19 patients: a systematic review and meta‐analysis. Respirology 27:605–616</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/resp.14311</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35694728</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9350074</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vargas Centanaro G, Calle Rubio M, Álvarez-Sala Walther JL et al (2022) Long-term outcomes and recovery of patients who survived COVID-19: lung injury COVID-19 study. Open Forum Infect Dis 9:ofac098</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ofid/ofac098</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35360197</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8903519</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu X, Liu X, Zhou Y et al (2021) 3-month, 6-month, 9-month, and 12-month respiratory outcomes in patients following COVID-19-related hospitalisation: a prospective study. Lancet Respir Med 9:747–754</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(21)00174-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33964245</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8099316</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed H, Patel K, Greenwood DC et al (2020) Long-term clinical outcomes in survivors of severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) and Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS) outbreaks after hospitalisation or ICU admission: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Rehabil Med 52:jrm00063</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32449782</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ong KC, Ng A-K, Lee L-U et al (2004) Pulmonary function and exercise capacity in survivors of severe acute respiratory syndrome. Eur Respir J 24:436–442</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1183/09031936.04.00007104</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15358703</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martini K, Larici AR, Revel M-P et al (2021) COVID-19 pneumonia imaging follow-up: when and how? A proposition from ESTI and ESR. Eur Radiol 32:2639–2649</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00330-021-08317-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34713328</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8553396</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lazar M, Barbu EC, Chitu CE et al (2022) Interstitial lung fibrosis following COVID-19 pneumonia. Diagnostics (Basel) 12:2028</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/diagnostics12082028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36010377</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9407299</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faverio P, Luppi F, Rebora P et al (2022) One-year pulmonary impairment after severe COVID-19: a prospective, multicenter follow-up study. Respir Res 23:65</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12931-022-01994-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35313890</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8934910</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>