<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39318890</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1564-0604</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>102</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Bulletin of the World Health Organization</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Bull World Health Organ</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Using the WHO-INTEGRATE framework to develop a COVID-19 guideline for schools, Germany.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>742</StartPage><EndPage>748</EndPage><MedlinePgn>742-748</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.2471/BLT.24.291550</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="PROBLEM" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">At the beginning of the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic, reliable, globally applicable recommendations for safe and continuous school operations were lacking.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="APPROACH" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">In October 2020, the German Association of Scientific Medical Societies' task force for COVID-19 guidelines and public health researchers at Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität München initiated the rapid development of a living evidence- and consensus-based guideline to reduce severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 transmission in schools. To facilitate transparent, structured and comprehensive decision-making with a whole-of-society perspective, they applied the WHO-INTEGRATE evidence-to-decision framework. This framework supported a broad, multisectoral composition of the guideline panel. The panel used newly synthesized evidence on nine school measures. Participating medical societies or the guideline secretariat completed evidence-to-decision tables. They also drafted recommendations for the guideline panel, who discussed and revised them during moderated consensus conferences.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="LOCAL SETTING" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">In Germany, each state is responsible for organizing schooling. The German Association of Scientific Medical Societies coordinates development of evidence- and consensus-based guidelines.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RELEVANT CHANGES" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The first version of the guideline was published in February 2021, and the guideline dissemination created much media attention. Of the 16 state education ministries, almost all knew about the guideline, nine recognized it as a relevant source of information and five used it to check existing directives.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="LESSONS LEARNT" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The WHO-INTEGRATE framework facilitated a comprehensive assessment of school measures from the start of guideline development, considering the broad societal impact of the measures. Using the framework in rapid mode was feasible, but it fell short of its potential.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2024 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rehfuess</LastName><ForeName>Eva A</ForeName><Initials>EA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine, Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität München, Elisabeth-Winterhalter-Weg 6, 81377Munich, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pfadenhauer</LastName><ForeName>Lisa</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine, Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität München, Elisabeth-Winterhalter-Weg 6, 81377Munich, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nothacker</LastName><ForeName>Monika</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Association of the Scientific Medical Societies in Germany, Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Strahwald</LastName><ForeName>Brigitte</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine, Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität München, Elisabeth-Winterhalter-Weg 6, 81377Munich, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Bull World Health Organ</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7507052</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0042-9686</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005858" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Germany</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014944" MajorTopicYN="Y">World Health Organization</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012574" MajorTopicYN="Y">Schools</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000458" MajorTopicYN="N">organization &amp; administration</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="Y">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="fre"><AbstractText Label="PROBLÈME" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Au début de la pandémie de maladie à coronavirus 2019 (COVID-19), il n'existait pas de recommandations fiables et applicables à l'échelle mondiale pour assurer le fonctionnement des écoles sans interruption et en toute sécurité.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="APPROCHE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">En octobre 2020, le groupe de travail de l'Association allemande des sociétés scientifiques et médicales chargé d'émettre des lignes directrices sur la COVID-19, en collaboration avec des chercheurs en santé publique de l'Université Louis-et-Maximilien de Munich, a lancé le développement rapide d'une orientation évolutive fondée sur le consensus et sur des preuves, afin de limiter la transmission du coronavirus 2 du syndrome respiratoire aigu sévère dans les écoles. Pour favoriser un processus décisionnel transparent, structuré et exhaustif adoptant la perspective de la société dans son ensemble, il a appliqué le cadre WHO-INTEGRATE, un outil privilégiant une prise de décision fondée sur des données probantes. Ce cadre a permis de composer un vaste panel multisectoriel qui, à la lumière d'une synthèse récente d'éléments factuels, a examiné neuf mesures scolaires. De leur côté, les sociétés médicales participantes ou le Secrétariat des directives ont complété des tableaux de prises de décision fondées sur des données probantes. Ils ont également formulé des recommandations à l'attention du panel, qui en a discuté et les a révisées lors de conférences de concertation modérées.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="ENVIRONNEMENT LOCAL" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">En Allemagne, l'éducation relève de la responsabilité des États fédérés. C'est l'Association allemande des sociétés scientifiques et médicales qui coordonne l'élaboration de lignes directrices fondées sur le consensus et sur des preuves.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CHANGEMENTS SIGNIFICATIFS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">La première version de l'orientation a été publiée en février 2021 et sa diffusion a engendré une forte couverture médiatique. Parmi les 16 Ministères de l'Éducation des États fédérés, presque tous en connaissaient l'existence, neuf d'entre eux la considéraient comme une source d'information pertinente et cinq l'utilisaient pour vérifier les directives existantes.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="LEÇONS TIRÉES" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Vu l'impact majeur de ces mesures sur la société, le cadre WHO-INTEGRATE a contribué à une évaluation globale des mesures scolaires dès le début de l'élaboration de l'orientation. Ce cadre a pu être rapidement mis en œuvre, mais n'a pas atteint son plein potentiel.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2024 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="spa"><AbstractText Label="SITUACIÓN" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Al principio de la pandemia de la enfermedad por coronavirus de 2019 (COVID-19), no existían recomendaciones fiables y aplicables a escala mundial para el funcionamiento seguro y continuo de las escuelas.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="ENFOQUE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">En octubre de 2020, el grupo de trabajo encargado de las directrices sobre la COVID-19 de la Asociación alemana de sociedades científicas médicas e investigadores de salud pública de la Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität München iniciaron el desarrollo rápido de una directriz activa basada en la evidencia y el consenso para reducir la transmisión del síndrome respiratorio agudo grave por coronavirus 2 en las escuelas. Para facilitar una toma de decisiones transparente, estructurada y exhaustiva con una perspectiva de toda la sociedad, aplicaron el marco WHO-INTEGRATE, una herramienta para la toma de decisiones basada en evidencias. Este marco propició una composición amplia y multisectorial del panel de directrices. El panel utilizó pruebas recientemente sintetizadas sobre nueve medidas escolares. Las sociedades médicas participantes o la secretaría de la directriz completaron las tablas de evidencia para la toma de decisiones. También redactaron recomendaciones para el panel de directrices, que las debatió y revisó durante conferencias de consenso moderadas.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MARCO REGIONAL" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">En Alemania, cada estado es responsable de organizar la escolarización. La Asociación alemana de sociedades científicas médicas coordina la elaboración de directrices basadas en la evidencia y el consenso.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CAMBIOS IMPORTANTES" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">La primera versión de la directriz se publicó en febrero de 2021 y su difusión suscitó una gran atención mediática. De los 16 ministerios de educación estatales, casi todos conocían la directriz, nueve la reconocieron como fuente de información pertinente y cinco la utilizaron para verificar las directrices existentes.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="LECCIONES APRENDIDAS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">El marco WHO-INTEGRATE permitió una evaluación exhaustiva de las medidas escolares desde el inicio de la elaboración de las directrices, y tuvo en cuenta el amplio impacto social de las medidas. Utilizar el marco en modo rápido fue factible, pero no alcanzó su potencial.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2024 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="ara"><AbstractText Label="المشكلة" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">في بداية جائحة مرض فيروس كورونا 2019 (كوفيد 19)، كانت هناك حاجة لتوصيات موثوقة، وقابلة للتطبيق عالميًا من أجل عمليات مدرسية آمنة ومستمرة.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="الأسلوب" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">في أكتوبر/تشرين أول 2020، بدأ فريق العمل التابع الهيئة الألمانية للجمعيات الطبية العلمية، والمعنية بالمبادئ التوجيهية لكوفيد 19، والباحثين في مجال الصحة العامة في جامعة لودفيج ماكسيميليانز في ميونيخ، في التطوير السريع لمبادئ توجيهية مباشرة تعتمد على الأدلة والإجماع، وذلك بهدف الحد من انتشار فيروس كورونا 2 المسبب لمتلازمة الجهاز التنفسي الحادة الشديدة في المدارس. لتسهيل اتخاذ قرارات تتمتع بالشفافية والتنظيم والشمول، من منظور المجتمع بالكامل، فقد قاموا بتطبيق إطار عمل WHO-INTEGRATE بدءًا من الأدلة وحتى القرار. دعم إطار العمل هذا تكوينًا واسع النطاق ومتعدد القطاعات للجنة المبادئ التوجيهية. استخدمت اللجنة أدلة تم تجميعها حديثًا حول تسعة من الإجراءات المدرسية. أكملت الجمعيات الطبية المشاركة أو أمانة المبادئ التوجيهية جداول من الأدلة وحتى القرار. كما قاموا أيضًا بصياغة التوصيات للجنة المبادئ التوجيهية، والتي قامت بمناقشتها ومراجعتها أثناء مؤتمرات الإجماع المتوسطة.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="المواقع المحلية" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">في ألمانيا، تعد كل ولاية مسؤولة عن تنظيم العمل في المدارس. تقوم الهيئة الألمانية للجمعيات الطبية العلمية بتنسيق تطوير المبادئ التوجيهية القائمة على الأدلة والإجماع.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="التغيّرات ذات الصلة" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">نُشرت النسخة الأولى من المبادئ التوجيهية في فبراير/شباط 2021، وجذب نشر المبادئ التوجيهية اهتمامًا إعلاميًا كبيرًا. من بين وزارات التعليم الحكومية الست عشرة، كانت جميعها تقريبًا على علم بالمبادئ التوجيهية، وأقرت تسع وزارات بأنها مصدر مهم للمعلومات، واستخدمتها خمس وزارات للتحقق من التوجيهات الحالية.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="الدروس المستفادة" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">أدى إطار عمل WHO-INTEGRATE إلى تسهيل إجراء تقييم شامل لإجراءات المدارس منذ بداية تطوير المبادئ التوجيهية، مع مراعاة التأثير المجتمعي الواسع لهذه الإجراءات. كان استخدام إطار العمل في وضع سريع ممكنًا، لكنه عجز عن تحقيق إمكاناته.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2024 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="chi"><AbstractText Label="问题" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">在新冠病毒 (COVID-19) 疫情之初，缺乏适用于全球的可确保学校安全和持续运行的可靠建议。.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="方法" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">2020 年 10 月，德国科学医学会协会的 COVID-19 指南特别工作组和慕尼黑大学的公共卫生研究人员着手快速制定了一份基于实时证据和共识的指南，以减少严重急性呼吸系统综合症冠状病毒 2 在学校的传播。为了从全社会的角度提升决策的透明化、结构化和全面性，他们实施了 WHO-INTEGRATE 循证决策框架。该框架支持由广泛、多部门组成的指南小组。该小组利用最新的综合证据制定了九项学校措施。参与的医学会或指南小组秘书处编制了循证决策表格。他们还为指南小组起草了建议，该小组在所主持的共识会议上讨论并修改了这些建议。.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="当地状况" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">在德国，每个州都负责组织学校教育。德国科学医学会协会负责协调并制定基于证据和共识的指南。.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="相关变化" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">第一版指南于 2021 年 2 月发布，该指南的传播引起了媒体的广泛关注。在 16 个州的教育部中，几乎所有人都知道该指南，其中 9 个州认为它是相关信息的一个来源，5 个州用它来检查现有的方针。.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="经验教训" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">鉴于这些措施产生的广泛社会影响，WHO-INTEGRATE 框架从指南制定之初就促进了对学校措施的全面评估。快速利用该框架制定指南是可行的，但未能充分发挥其潜力。.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2024 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="rus"><AbstractText Label="ПРОБЛЕМА" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">В начале пандемии коронавирусной инфекции 2019 года (COVID-19) отсутствовали надежные, применимые во всем мире рекомендации по обеспечению безопасной и бесперебойной работы школ.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="ПОДХОД" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">В октябре 2020 года целевая группа Немецкой ассоциации научных медицинских обществ по разработке рекомендаций по борьбе с COVID-19 и исследователи в области общественного здравоохранения из Университета Людвига-Максимилиана в Мюнхене приступили к оперативной разработке основанного на фактических данных и консенсусе руководства по снижению передачи коронавируса тяжелого острого респираторного синдрома 2-го типа в школах. Для содействия прозрачному, структурированному и всеобъемлющему принятию решений с учетом интересов всего общества они применили разработанную ВОЗ систему учета фактических данных при принятии решений WHO-INTEGRATE. Эта структура поддерживала широкий, многосекторальный состав группы по разработке руководящих принципов. Группа использовала новые обобщенные данные по девяти школьным показателям. Участвующие медицинские общества или секретариат группы разработки руководства заполнили таблицы фактических данных, необходимые для принятия решения. Они также подготовили проект рекомендаций для группы экспертов, которые обсудили и пересмотрели их в ходе модерируемых конференций по достижению консенсуса.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="МЕСТНЫЕ УСЛОВИЯ" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">В Германии каждая земля несет ответственность за организацию школьного образования. Немецкая ассоциация научных медицинских обществ координирует разработку руководящих принципов, основанных на фактических данных и консенсусе.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="ОСУЩЕСТВЛЕННЫЕ ПЕРЕМЕНЫ" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Первая версия руководства была опубликована в феврале 2021 года, и распространение руководства привлекло большое внимание средств массовой информации. Из 16 земельных министерств образования почти все были осведомлены об этом руководстве, девять признали его важным источником информации, а пять использовали для проверки существующих директив.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="ВЫВОДЫ" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Рамочная структура WHO-INTEGRATE способствовала всесторонней оценке школьных мер с самого начала разработки руководящих принципов с учетом их широкого влияния на общество. Использование системы в ускоренном режиме было возможным, но ее потенциал оказался недостаточным.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2024 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39318890</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11418849</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2471/BLT.24.291550</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">BLT.24.291550</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Public health and social measures in response to COVID-19 [internet]. Copenhagen: World Health Organization Regional Office for Europe; 2024. Available from: https://phsm.euro.who.int/covid-19/schools [cited 2024 Aug 2]. </Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krishnaratne S, Littlecott H, Sell K, Burns J, Rabe JE, Stratil JM, et al. Measures implemented in the school setting to contain the COVID-19 pandemic. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2022. Jan 17;1(1):CD015029.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8762709</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35037252</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kratzer S, Pfadenhauer LM, Biallas RL, Featherstone R, Klinger C, Movsisyan A, et al. Unintended consequences of measures implemented in the school setting to contain the COVID-19 pandemic: a scoping review. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2022. Jun 6;6(6):CD015397.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9169532</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35661990</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 education response - country dashboard. Montreal: UNESCO Institute of Statistics; 2024. Available from: https://covid19.uis.unesco.org/global-monitoring-school-closures-covid19/country-dashboard/ [cited 2024 Aug 2].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Standing Guidelines Commission. Guidance manual and rules for guideline development. 1st ed. Frankfurt am Main: German Association of the Scientific Medical Societies; 2012. English. Available from: https://www.awmf.org/fileadmin/user_upload/dateien/downloads_regelwerk/AWMF-Guidance_2013.pdf [cited 2024 Aug 23].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kunzler AM, Iannizzi C, Burns J, Metzendorf M-I, Voigt-Radloff S, Piechotta V, et al. CEOsys Consortium. Informing pandemic management in Germany with trustworthy living evidence syntheses and guideline development: lessons learned from the COVID-19 evidence ecosystem. J Clin Epidemiol. 2024. Jul 14;173:111456; online ahead of print. 10.1016/j.jclinepi.2024.111456</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2024.111456</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39002765</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Littlecott H, Krishnaratne S, Burns J, Rehfuess E, Sell K, Klinger C, et al. Measures implemented in the school setting to contain the COVID-19 pandemic. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2024. May 2;5(5):CD015029.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11064884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38695826</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rehfuess EA, Stratil JM, Scheel IB, Portela A, Norris SL, Baltussen R. The WHO-INTEGRATE evidence-to-decision framework version 1.0: integrating WHO norms and values and a complexity perspective. BMJ Glob Health. 2019. Jan 25;4 Suppl 1:e000844. 10.1136/bmjgh-2018-000844</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjgh-2018-000844</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6350705</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30775012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moberg J, Oxman AD, Rosenbaum S, Schünemann HJ, Guyatt G, Flottorp S, et al. GRADE Working Group. The GRADE Evidence-to-Decision (EtD) framework for health system and public health decisions. Health Res Policy Syst. 2018. May 29;16(1):45. 10.1186/s12961-018-0320-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12961-018-0320-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5975536</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29843743</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Movsisyan A, Backhaus S, Butchart A, Gardner F, Strahwald B, Rehfuess E. Applying the WHO-INTEGRATE evidence-to-decision framework in the development of WHO guidelines on parenting interventions: step-by-step process and lessons learnt. Health Res Policy Syst. 2024. Jul 5;22(1):79. 10.1186/s12961-024-01165-z</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12961-024-01165-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11227174</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38970125</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rehfuess E, Strahwald B. Application_of_the_WHO-INTEGRATE_framework_supplementary_file [online repository]. Meyrin: Zenodo; 2024. 10.5281/zenodo.13368087</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5281/zenodo.13368087</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karliczek: Wichtiger Beitrag der Wissenschaft für Schule in Pandemiezeiten. Bonn: Federal Ministry of Education and Research; 2021. German. Available from: https://www.bmbf.de/bmbf/shareddocs/pressemitteilungen/de/karliczek-wichtiger-beitrag-de--fuer-schule-in-pandemiezeiten.html#searchFacets [cited 2024 Aug 23].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schweitzer J. Ansteckungen unter Schülern kann die Leitlinie nicht ganz verhindern. Zeit Online. 2021 Feb 8. German. Available from: https://www.zeit.de/wissen/gesundheit/2021-02/corona-massnahmen-eva-rehfuess-leitlinie-schule-schulaemter-bundesregierung [cited 2024 Aug 23].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Technical Advisory Group on schooling during COVID-19 [internet]. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2020. Available from: https://www.who.int/europe/groups/technical-advisory-group-on-schooling-during-covid-19#:~:text=To%20review%20the%20evidence%20and,during%20the%20COVID%2D19%20pandemic [cited 2024 Feb 26].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wabnitz K, Rueb M, Rehfuess EA, Strahwald B, Pfadenhauer LM. Assessing the impact of an evidence- and consensus-based guideline for controlling SARS-CoV-2 transmission in German schools on decision-making processes: a multi-component qualitative analysis. Health Res Policy Syst. 2023. Dec 19;21(1):138. 10.1186/s12961-023-01072-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12961-023-01072-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10729453</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38115061</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>