<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39319891</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1518-8345</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>32</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Revista latino-americana de enfermagem</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Rev Lat Am Enfermagem</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Young nurses' perceptions about their employment, working and health conditions.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e4335</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e4335</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e4335</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1590/1518-8345.7398.4335</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0104-11692024000100367</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">to interpret young nursing professionals' perceptions about the relationship between working, employment and health conditions.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHOD" NlmCategory="METHODS">a qualitative study with an interpretive approach regarding the work-related experiences of 15 young nurses, who took part in the research through voluntary snowball sampling. The data from the interviews and the focus group were analyzed to reach an approximation to the realities inherent to the nurses' work life.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">the relevant study findings pointed out that work precariousness is a characteristic feature in the population group, mainly related to hiring modalities and to wages. According to the participants, the psychosocial working conditions (which were intensified during the COVID-19 pandemic) were the ones that caused the most effects on their mental and physical health.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">from the young nurses' perspective, this study reports how the macro- and micro-structural working conditions and their relationship with health are perceived, pointing out the key elements to devise interventions focused on life paths that foster decent and healthy work postulates in their work environments, as well as actions to prevent injuries or harms to nurses' health.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Díaz</LastName><ForeName>Mabel Rocío Hernández</ForeName><Initials>MRH</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1239-7802</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pontificia Universidad Javeriana, Instituto de Salud Pública, Bogotá, DC, Colombia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Morales</LastName><ForeName>Zuly Bibiana Suárez</ForeName><Initials>ZBS</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8699-9617</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pontificia Universidad Javeriana, Instituto de Salud Pública, Bogotá, DC, Colombia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Monroy</LastName><ForeName>Angelica María Vargas</ForeName><Initials>AMV</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6087-9462</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pontificia Universidad Javeriana, Instituto de Salud Pública, Bogotá, DC, Colombia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Prieto</LastName><ForeName>Andrey Sebastián Castiblanco</ForeName><Initials>ASC</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0868-7594</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pontificia Universidad Javeriana, Instituto de Salud Pública, Bogotá, DC, Colombia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><Language>spa</Language><Language>por</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Brazil</Country><MedlineTA>Rev Lat Am Enfermagem</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9420934</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0104-1169</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004651" MajorTopicYN="Y">Employment</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D036301" MajorTopicYN="Y">Qualitative Research</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009726" MajorTopicYN="N">Nurses</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055815" MajorTopicYN="N">Young Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017132" MajorTopicYN="N">Workplace</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001291" MajorTopicYN="N">Attitude of Health Personnel</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006304" MajorTopicYN="N">Health Status</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017144" MajorTopicYN="N">Focus Groups</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016272" MajorTopicYN="N">Occupational Health</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="spa"><AbstractText Label="OBJETIVO">interpretar las percepciones que tienen los profesionales jóvenes de enfermería de la relación entre condiciones de trabajo, empleo y salud.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MÉTODO" NlmCategory="METHODS">estudio cualitativo con abordaje interpretativo de las experiencias laborales de 15 enfermeros jóvenes, quienes participaron de la investigación a través de un muestreo voluntario por bola de nieve. Se realizó análisis de datos de las entrevistas y grupo focal para lograr una aproximación a las realidades de la vida laboral.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTADOS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">los hallazgos relevantes del estudio señalaron que la precarización laboral es característica en este grupo poblacional, relacionada principalmente con tipo de contratación y retribución recibida. Las condiciones de trabajo psicosociales fueron las que más generaron efectos en la salud mental y física según los participantes, las cuales se agudizaron durante la pandemia por COVID-19.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIÓN" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">este estudio aporta, desde la perspectiva de los jóvenes enfermeros, cómo se perciben las características macro y microestructurales del trabajo y su relación con la salud, señalando los elementos clave para generar intervenciones con enfoque de curso de vida que promulguen los postulados de trabajo decente y saludable en sus entornos de trabajo, al igual que acciones para la prevención de lesiones o daños en la salud de los enfermeros.</AbstractText></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="spa"><AbstractText><b>(1)</b> Los jóvenes enfermeros perciben una precarización laboral significativa. <b>(2)</b> Los tipos de contratación y la remuneración se perciben como las condiciones más desfavorables. <b>(3)</b> Los participantes indican que las condiciones de empleo y de trabajo afectan su salud. <b>(4)</b> Las condiciones de trabajo psicosociales son las más nocivas según los participantes.</AbstractText></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="por"><AbstractText Label="OBJETIVO">interpretar as percepções que os jovens profissionais de enfermagem têm sobre a relação entre condições de trabalho, emprego e saúde.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MÉTODO">estudo qualitativo com abordagem interpretativa das experiências de trabalho de quinze jovens enfermeiros, que participaram da pesquisa por meio de amostragem voluntária em bola de neve. Realizou-se a análise dos dados das entrevistas e grupo focal para alcançar uma aproximação à realidade da vida profissional.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTADOS">os achados relevantes do estudo indicaram que a precarização no trabalho é característica desse grupo populacional, principalmente no que diz respeito ao tipo de contratação e à remuneração recebida. As condições psicossociais de trabalho foram as que mais provocaram efeitos na saúde mental e física segundo os participantes, sendo essas condições agravadas durante a pandemia da COVID-19.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSÃO">este estudo apresenta, na perspectiva de jovens enfermeiros, como são percebidas as características macro e microestruturais do trabalho e sua relação com a saúde, apontando os elementos-chave para gerar intervenções com abordagem de curso de vida que divulguem os postulados do trabalho decente e ambiente saudável em seus ambientes de trabalho, bem como ações para prevenir lesões ou danos à saúde dos enfermeiros.</AbstractText></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="por"><AbstractText><b>(1)</b> Os jovens enfermeiros percebem uma significativa precarização do trabalho. <b>(2)</b> As modalidades de contratação e remuneração são percebidas como as condições mais desfavoráveis. <b>(3)</b> Os participantes indicam que o emprego e as condições de trabalho afetam a sua saúde. <b>(4)</b> As condições psicossociais de trabalho são as mais prejudiciais segundo os participantes.</AbstractText></OtherAbstract><CoiStatement>
<b>Conflict of interest:</b> the authors have declared that there is no conflict of interest. </CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>34</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39319891</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11421518</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/1518-8345.7398.4335</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0104-11692024000100367</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Úbeda M., Cabasés M. A., Pardell A. Empleos de calidad para las personas jóvenes: una inversión de presente y de futuro.  [2024-03-08];Cuad Relac Labo [Internet] 2020 38(1):39–57.  Available from:  https://revistas.ucm.es/index.php/CRLA/article/view/68867/4564456553368
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>International Labour Organization  . Global Employment Trends for Youth 2020 [Internet] ILO; Geneva: 2020.  [2024-03-08].   Available from:  https://www.ilo.org/wcmsp5/groups/public/---dgreports/---dcomm/---publ/documents/publication/wcms_737648.pdf
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crismon D., Mansfield K., Hiatt S., Christensen S., Cloyes K. COVID-19 pandemic impact on experiences and perceptions of nurse graduates. J Prof Nurs. 2021;37(5):857–65. doi: 10.1016/j.profnurs.2021.06.008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.profnurs.2021.06.008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9767315</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34742515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benach J., Muntaner C., Solar O., Santana V., Quinlan M. Empleo, trabajo y desigualdades en salud: Una visión global. Icaria Editorial S.A; Barcelona: 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Musie A., Wolvaardt J. Risk and reward: Experiences of healthcare professionals caring for drug-resistant tuberculosis patients. SA J Hum Resour Manag. 2021;19:1–12. doi: 10.4102/sajhrm.v19i0.1191.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4102/sajhrm.v19i0.1191</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torres-Tovar M.  In: América Latina: Sociedad, política y salud en tiempos de pandemia [Internet] Henrion C. T., Henriquez D. I., Schor-Landman coord, editors. CLACSO; Buenos Aires: 2021.  [2024-03-08]. COVID-19: pandemia y precariedad laboral en el sector salud y su impacto en la salud de las y los trabajadores; pp. 382–382.  Available from:  https://biblioteca.clacso.edu.ar/clacso/gt/20210312065632/America-Latina-Sociedad-politica-y-salud.pdf
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministerio de Salud y Protección Social (CO)  Resolución 755 de 2022. Por la cual se adoptan la "Política Nacional de Talento Humano de Enfermería y el Plan Estratégico 2022-2031" para el fortalecimiento del talento humano en salud.  [2024-03-08];Diario Oficial [Internet] 2022 May 16;  Available from:  https://normograma.supersalud.gov.co/normograma/docs/resolucion_minsaludps_0755_2022.htm
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Millones Trinidad ML  Working conditions and job satisfaction of the nurses of the Hospital Complex PNP Luis N Sáenz.  [2024-03-08];Rev Científica [Internet] 2022 1(4):39–50.  Available from:  https://revistacientifica.edu.pe/index.php/revistacientifica/article/view/21/58
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coffré J. A. F., Pérez T. R., Miranda M. E. T., Pozo C. E. V. Nursing students’ perspectives on their professional future.  [2024-03-08];Dominio Ciencias [Internet] 2021 9(1):570–83.  Available from:  https://dominiodelasciencias.com/ojs/index.php/es/article/view/3151
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martínez-Rodríguez L., Muñoz-Devesa A., Tejero-Vidal L. Construction of nursing professional image during the Covid-19 pandemic through press news.  [2024-03-08];Index Enferm [Internet] 2022 31(3):151–5.  Available from:  https://scielo.isciii.es/scielo.php?pid=S1132-12962022000300003&amp;script=sci_arttext
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Domínguez W. J. G. Condiciones de trabajo de enfermería en tiempos de covid-19. Sincelejo, Sucre (Colombia) Horiz Enferm. 2022;33(2) doi: 10.7764/Horiz_Enferm.33.2.191-202.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7764/Horiz_Enferm.33.2.191-202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vasilachis I. Métodos Cualitativos I. Los problemas teórico-epistemológicos. Centro Editor de América Latina; Buenos Aires: 1992. 38</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tong A., Sainsbury P., Craig J. Consolidated criteria for reporting qualitative research (COREQ) : a 32-item checklist for interviews and focus groups. Int J Qual Health Care. 2007;19(6):349–57. doi: 10.1093/intqhc/mzm042.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/intqhc/mzm042</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17872937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kitzinger J. Qualitative Research: introducing focus group. BMJ. 1995;311:299–302. doi: 10.1136/bmj.311.7000.299.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.311.7000.299</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2550365</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7633241</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castro C., Labra O., Chamblas I. El análisis de contenido temático: una mirada a sus etapas desde Nvivo12^©^. Rev Int Cien Soc Interdiscip. 2022;10(1):143–58. doi: 10.18848/2474-6029/CGP/v10i01/143-158.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18848/2474-6029/CGP/v10i01/143-158</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strauss A., Corbin J. Técnicas y procedimientos para desarrollar la teoría fundamentada en bases de la investigación cualitativa. Editorial Universidad de Antioquia; Medellín: 2002.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castillo C. Pandemia y precarización laboral en Argentina. Social Questão. 2021;49:89–110. doi: 10.17771/PUCRio.OSQ.51112.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.17771/PUCRio.OSQ.51112</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quispe-Llanzo M., Pacovilca-Alejo O., Zea-Montesinos C., García-Delgado R., Oyola-García A. Discriminatory barriers for professional practice in Peruvian nurses. Rev Cuerpo Med HNAAA. 2020;12(4):275–82. doi: 10.35434/rcmhnaaa.2019.124.560.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.35434/rcmhnaaa.2019.124.560</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aliaga-Zamora G., Delgado-Céspedes V., Romero-Cueva Y., Cholán-Valdez O., Rondon-Jara E. Psychosocial Risk Components and Job Satisfaction in Nurses from a Hospital in Cojamarca, Peru.  [2024-03-08];Rev Cubana Enferm [Internet] 2022 38(3):e4794   Available from:  http://scielo.sld.cu/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0864-03192022000300008
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delgado-Fernández V., Rey-Merchán M., López Arquillos A. Estudio comparativo de los riesgos psicosociales laborales entre profesionales médicos.  [2024-03-08];Rev Asoc Esp Esp Med Trab [Internet] 2021 30(1):24–33.  Available from:  https://scielo.isciii.es/pdf/medtra/v30n1/1132-6255-medtra-30-01-24.pdf
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schultz C. C., Colet C. D. F., Benetti E. R. R., Tavares J. P., Stumm E. M. F., Treviso P. Resilience and the reduction of occupational stress in Nursing. Rev. Latino-Am. Enfermagem. 2022;30:e3636. doi: 10.1590/1518-8345.5866.3636.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/1518-8345.5866.3636</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9545937</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36228234</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cachi N., Valdés J. Psychosocial factors as a fundamental pillar of nursing staff management. Salud Cien Tecnol. 2021;1:36 doi: 10.56294/saludcyt202136.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.56294/saludcyt202136</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pousa P. C. P., Lucca SR. Psychosocial factors in nursing work and occupational risks: a systematic review. Rev Bras Enferm. 2021;74(3):1–7. doi: 10.1590/0034-7167-2020-0198.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/0034-7167-2020-0198</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33503207</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hernández-Silverio A., Gómez-Ortega M., González-González G., Salgado-Guadarrama J. Risk factors of nursing staff in the surgical area of a tertiary level hospital. Rev Enferm Neurol. 2021;20(3):197–206. doi: 10.51422/ren.v20i3.340.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.51422/ren.v20i3.340</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Resquin L. V. Repercussion of working conditions and environment with the health status of nursing human resources. Salud Cien Tecnol. 2021;1:31 doi: 10.56294/saludcyt202131.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.56294/saludcyt202131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rivera-Rojas F., Ceballos-Vásquez P., González-Palacios Y. Riesgos psicosociales y satisfacción laboral: una relación significativa para los trabajadores de oncología. Aquichan. 2021;21(1):1–11. doi: 10.5294/aqui.2021.21.1.4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5294/aqui.2021.21.1.4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mbue N., Wang W. Nurses’ experience with chronic foot pain and their job-the national science foundation foot health survey. Heliyon. 2023;9(3):1–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10036639</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36967960</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nahid N., Behzad I., Reza K. Operating room nurses’ lived experiences of occupational hazards: A phenomenological study. Perioper Care Oper Room Manag. 2021;25(100211):1–5. doi: 10.1016/j.pcorm.2021.100211.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pcorm.2021.100211</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pugh J., Gelder L., Cormack K., Williams A., Twigg D., Giles M. Changes in exercise and musculoskeletal symptoms of novice nurses: A one-year follow-up study. Collegian. 2021;28(2):206–13. doi: 10.1016/j.colegn.2020.07.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.colegn.2020.07.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marin-Vargas B., Gonzalez-Argote J. Ergonomic risks and their impact on the health of nursing personnel. Rev Inform Cient. 2022;101(1)  Available from:  https://revinfcientifica.sld.cu/index.php/ric/article/view/3724/5069#:\~:text=Los%20riesgos%20ergon%C3%B3micos%20que%20influyen,para%20realizar%20sus%20actividades%20diarias
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diktas H., Oncul A., Tahtasakal C., Sevgi D., Kaya O., Cimenci N. What were the changes during the COVID-19 pandemic era concerning occupational risks among health care workers? J Infect Public Health. 2021;14(10):1334–9. doi: 10.1016/j.jiph.2021.06.006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jiph.2021.06.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8490998</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34172412</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silva L., Almeida A., Pascoal L., Santos M., Neto, Lima F., Santos F. Skin injuries due to Personal Protective Equipment and preventive measures in the COVID-19 context: an integrative review. Rev. Latino-Am. Enfermagem. 2022;30:e3522. doi: 10.1590/1518-8345.5636.3522.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/1518-8345.5636.3522</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9019902</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35476010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>González-Beteta J., Sánchez-Gómez M. Factors associated with needlestick injuries in nurses: a systematic review. Rev Asoc Esp Esp Med Trab [Internet]  [2024-03-08];2021 30:353–61.  Available from:  https://scielo.isciii.es/pdf/medtra/v30n3/1132-6255-medtra-30-03-353.pdf
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silva P. L. N., Teixeira A. A. L., Neta Oliveira A. I., Oliveira Gomes, VV, Martins A., Alves E. C. S. Prevalence and intervention of occupational risks in the work process of nurses: integrative literature review. Rev Sustinere. 2021;9(2):463–77. doi: 10.12957/sustinere.2021.47779.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.12957/sustinere.2021.47779</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nankongnab N., Kongtip P., Tipayamongkholgul M., Silpasuwan P., Kaewboonchoo O., Luksamijarulkul P. Occupational hazards, health conditions and personal protective equipment used among healthcare workers in hospitals, Thailand. Hum Ecol Risk Assess. 2021;27(3):804–24. doi: 10.1080/10807039.2020.1768824.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10807039.2020.1768824</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8448198</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34539172</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Romerate M. J., Villacreses V. P., Reyes N. A., Chávez J. D., Ripalda K. B. Resiliencia en el personal de enfermería durante la pandemia covid-19. Cien Latina Rev Cient Multidisc. 2022;6(2):645–60. doi: 10.37811/cl_rcm.v6i2.1912.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.37811/cl_rcm.v6i2.1912</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu H., Stjernswärd S., Glasdam S., Caliari J., Santos M, Pereira F, Oliveira H, Ceolim M. Psychosocial experiences of frontline nurses working in hospital-based settings during the COVID-19 pandemic-A qualitative systematic review. Int J Nurs Stud Adv. 2021;3(e3795):e100037 doi: 10.1016/j.ijnsa.2021.100037.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijnsa.2021.100037</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8285218</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34308373</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kantorski L. P., Oliveira M. M., Alves P. F., Treichel C. A. S., Wünsch C. G., Santos L. H. Intention to leave Nursing during the COVID-19 pandemic. Rev. Latino-Am. Enfermagem. 2022;30:e3549. doi: 10.1590/1518-8345.5815.3549.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/1518-8345.5815.3549</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9342914</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35920540</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silva A. F., Dalri R. C. M. B., Eckeli A. L., Uva A. N. P. S., Mendes A. M. O. C., Robazzi M. L. C. C. Sleep quality, personal and work variables and life habits of hospital nurses. Rev. Latino-Am. Enfermagem. 2022;30:e3538. doi: 10.1590/1518-8345.5756.3538.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/1518-8345.5756.3538</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9109468</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35584413</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>