<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39312920</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2352-3026</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>20</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Lancet. Haematology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Lancet Haematol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Venetoclax plus decitabine as a bridge to allogeneic haematopoietic stem-cell transplantation in older patients with acute myeloid leukaemia (VEN-DEC GITMO): final report of a multicentre, single-arm, phase 2 trial.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S2352-3026(24)00241-2</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/S2352-3026(24)00241-2</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Access to allogeneic haematopoietic stem-cell transplantation (HSCT) remains challenging for older patients (aged &gt;60 years) with acute myeloid leukaemia. We aimed to evaluate the efficacy of venetoclax plus decitabine as first-line therapy and bridge to transplantation in this patient population.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">This multicentre, single-arm, phase 2 trial was conducted in 20 Gruppo Italiano Trapianto Midollo Osseo (GITMO) centres in Italy. Patients aged ≥60 and &lt;75 years, with newly diagnosed acute myeloid leukaemia categorised as intermediate or high risk according to 2016 WHO and 2017 European LeukemiaNet, an ECOG performance status of less than 2, and considered fit for allogeneic HSCT were included. Patients received oral venetoclax with a 3-day ramp-up: 100 mg on day 1, 200 mg on day 2, and 400 mg once per day from day 3 of cycle one, and then every 28 days of each cycle (two to four in total). Decitabine was administered intravenously at a dose of 20 mg/m<sup>2</sup> from days 1 to 5 every 28 days. At cycle one, patients were admitted to hospital for a minimum of 24 h, whereas subsequent cycles could be administered on an outpatient basis. Two additional cycles were allowed while waiting for allogeneic HSCT or for those with no response or partial response after cycle two. The primary endpoint was the proportion of patients who had allogeneic HSCT performed during first complete remission, assessed in all patients who received at least one dose of the study medication. This study was registered with ClinicalTrials.gov (NCT04476199, ongoing) and EudraCT (2020-002297-26).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="FINDINGS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Between June 1, 2021, and Dec 30, 2022, 93 patients were enrolled and started venetoclax plus decitabine induction (44 [47%] at intermediate risk and 49 [53%] at high risk). The median age was 68·5 (IQR 60·3-74·7). All 93 participants were White, of whom 43 (46%) were female and 50 (54%) were male. The median follow-up was 236 days (IQR 121-506). 64 (69%) of 93 patients reached complete remission and 53 (57%) underwent allogeneic HSCT in complete remission. 53 (83%) of 64 with a complete remission underwent allogeneic HSCT. Five (8%) of 64 patients in complete remission relapsed before transplantation and four died as a consequence. Adverse events (grade ≥3) occurred in 49 (53%) of 93 patients. The most common adverse events were infections (including pneumonia, bacterial sepsis, and SARS-CoV-2 causing seven deaths among 28 [57%] of 49 patients), neutropenia (17 [35%]), thrombocytopenia (two [4%], including one fatal CNS bleeding), and cardiac events (four [8%], including one fatal heart failure). No treatment-related deaths were observed.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="INTERPRETATION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Venetoclax plus decitabine induction can significantly enhance the feasibility of allogeneic HSCT in older patients with acute myeloid leukaemia who are deemed fit for transplantation.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="FUNDING" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">AbbVie and Johnson &amp; Johnson.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved, including those for text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Russo</LastName><ForeName>Domenico</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical and Experimental Science, University of Brescia, ASST Spedali Civili di Brescia, Brescia, Italy. Electronic address: domenico.russo@unibs.it.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Polverelli</LastName><ForeName>Nicola</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Molecular Medicine, Division of Hematology, Fondazione IRCCS Policlinico San Matteo, University of Pavia, Pavia, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bernardi</LastName><ForeName>Simona</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical and Experimental Science, University of Brescia, ASST Spedali Civili di Brescia, Brescia, Italy; Centro di Ricerca Emato-Oncologica AIL, ASST Spedali Civili di Brescia, Brescia, Italy; National Center for Gene Therapy and Drug based on RNA Technology, Padova, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Santarone</LastName><ForeName>Stella</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centro Trapianti Midollo Osseo, Azienda Sanitaria Locale di Pescara, Pescara, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Farina</LastName><ForeName>Mirko</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical and Experimental Science, University of Brescia, ASST Spedali Civili di Brescia, Brescia, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Borlenghi</LastName><ForeName>Erika</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Hematology, ASST Spedali Civili di Brescia, Brescia, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Onida</LastName><ForeName>Francesco</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MTN Fondazione IRCCS Ca' Granda Ospedale Maggiore Policlinico, ASST Fatebenefratelli-Sacco, University of Milan, Milan, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Castagna</LastName><ForeName>Luca</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bone Marrow Transplantation Unit, Ospedali Riuniti Villa Sofia-Cervello, Palermo, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bramanti</LastName><ForeName>Stefania</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Humanitas Clinical and Research Center, IRCCS, Rozzano, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Carella</LastName><ForeName>Angelo Michele</ForeName><Initials>AM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>IRCCS Ospedale Casa Sollievo della Sofferenza, Foggia, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sorasio</LastName><ForeName>Roberto</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Hematology, S Croce e Carle Hospital, Cuneo, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Martino</LastName><ForeName>Massimo</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centro Unico Trapianti, Division of Hematology, Grande Ospedale Metropolitano Bianchi Melacrino Morelli, Reggio Calabria, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alati</LastName><ForeName>Caterina</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centro Unico Trapianti, Division of Hematology, Grande Ospedale Metropolitano Bianchi Melacrino Morelli, Reggio Calabria, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Olivieri</LastName><ForeName>Attilio</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinica di Ematologia Azienda Ospedaliero Universitaria delle Marche, Ancona, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Beltrami</LastName><ForeName>Germana</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>UO Ematologia e Terapie Cellulari, IRCCS Azienda Ospedaliera Universitaria San Martino, Genova, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Curti</LastName><ForeName>Antonio</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>IRCCS Azienda Ospedaliero-Universitaria di Bologna, Istituto di Ematologia Seràgnoli, Bologna, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vetro</LastName><ForeName>Calogero</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Hematology, BMT Unit, AOU Policlinico G Rodolico S Marco, Catania, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Leotta</LastName><ForeName>Salvatore</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Hematology, BMT Unit, AOU Policlinico G Rodolico S Marco, Catania, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mancini</LastName><ForeName>Valentina</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Hematology, ASST Grande Ospedale Metropolitano Niguarda, Milan, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Terruzzi</LastName><ForeName>Elisabetta</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Hematology, Fondazione IRCCS San Gerardo dei Tintori, Monza, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bernardi</LastName><ForeName>Massimo</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Unit of Hematology and Bone Marrow Transplantation, IRCCS Ospedale San Raffaele, Milan, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Galieni</LastName><ForeName>Piero</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>UOC Hematology, Mazzoni Hospital Ascoli Piceno, Ascoli Piceno, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Musto</LastName><ForeName>Pellegrino</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>UOC Ematologia, Bari, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cerretti</LastName><ForeName>Raffaella</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Hematology, Stem Cell Transplant Unit, Policlinico Tor Vergata, Rome, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Giaccone</LastName><ForeName>Luisa</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Univesity of Torino, AOU Città Della Salute E Della Scienza Di Torino, Torino, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Skert</LastName><ForeName>Cristina</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Unit of Haematology and Bone Marrow Transplantation, Ospedale Dell'Angelo, Venezia Mestre, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Radici</LastName><ForeName>Vera</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical and Experimental Science, University of Brescia, ASST Spedali Civili di Brescia, Brescia, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vezzoli</LastName><ForeName>Marika</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Molecular and Translational Medicine, University of Brescia, Brescia, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Calza</LastName><ForeName>Stefano</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Molecular and Translational Medicine, University of Brescia, Brescia, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Leoni</LastName><ForeName>Alessandro</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical and Experimental Science, University of Brescia, ASST Spedali Civili di Brescia, Brescia, Italy; Centro di Ricerca Emato-Oncologica AIL, ASST Spedali Civili di Brescia, Brescia, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Garuffo</LastName><ForeName>Luca</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical and Experimental Science, University of Brescia, ASST Spedali Civili di Brescia, Brescia, Italy; Centro di Ricerca Emato-Oncologica AIL, ASST Spedali Civili di Brescia, Brescia, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bonvicini</LastName><ForeName>Cristian</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Molecular Markers Laboratory, IRCCS Istituto Centro San Giovanni Di Dio Fatebenefratelli, Brescia, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pellizzeri</LastName><ForeName>Simone</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical and Experimental Science, University of Brescia, ASST Spedali Civili di Brescia, Brescia, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Malagola</LastName><ForeName>Michele</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical and Experimental Science, University of Brescia, ASST Spedali Civili di Brescia, Brescia, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ciceri</LastName><ForeName>Fabio</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Unit of Hematology and Stem Cell Transplantation, Ospedale San Raffaele, University Vita-Salute San Raffaele, Milan, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><DataBankList CompleteYN="Y"><DataBank><DataBankName>ClinicalTrials.gov</DataBankName><AccessionNumberList><AccessionNumber>NCT04476199</AccessionNumber></AccessionNumberList></DataBank></DataBankList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>20</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Lancet Haematol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101643584</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2352-3026</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CoiStatement>Declaration of interests DR received consulting fees from Medac; honoraria and travel grants from Jazz Pharma, Novartis, MSD, Kite Gilead, and Medac; and has participated in data safety monitoring and advisory board meetings for Novartis, MSD, Kite Gilead, Medac, AbbVie, and Janssen. EB received consulting fees from AbbVie; travel grants from Amgen, Novartis, and AbbVie; and has participated in data safety monitoring and advisory board meetings for Otsuka and Amgen. FO received honoraria from Takeda, Medac, and Kyowa; and travel grants from Roche, Janssen, Kyowa, Takeda, Jazz Pharma, and Medac. RS received a travel grant from Takeda. MaM received honoraria from Novartis, MSD, Astellas Pharma, AbbVie, Takeda, Pfizer, Sanofi, Jazz Pharma, Janssen Cilag, Kite Gilead, Medac, and Bristol Myers Squibb; travel grants from Kite Gilead, Roche, and Janssen Cilag; has participated in data safety monitoring and advisory board meetings for Novartis, Takeda, Kite Gilead, Pfizer, Bristol Myers Squibb, and Janssen Cilag; and served as president of GITMO. CA received honoraria from AbbVie and Jazz Pharma; and has participated in data safety monitoring and advisory board meetings for AbbVie, Jazz Pharma, and Amgen. GB received travel grants from Janssen Cilag and Amgen. AC received honoraria from AbbVie, Menarini (Stemline), Pfizer, Jazz Pharma, and Servier; a travel grant from Jazz Pharma; and has participated in data safety monitoring and advisory board meetings for AbbVie and Menarini (Stemline). CG received consulting fees from AbbVie, Jazz Pharma, Incyte, Bristol Myers Squibb, and Astellas; and a travel grant from Jazz Pharma. PM received honoraria and travel grants from AbbVie and Johnson &amp; Johnson. LG received honoraria from Novartis, MSD, Gilead, AbbVie, Sanofi, and Bristol Myers Squibb; and travel grants from Janssen and AbbVie. CS received honoraria from Jazz Pharma and Kite Pharma; and a travel grant from Jazz Pharma. VR received travel grants from Neovii, Medac, and Jazz Pharma. All other authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39312920</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2352-3026(24)00241-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2352-3026(24)00241-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>