<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39314571</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>8</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Identifying Lower Extremity Deformities in the Coronal Plane: Lessons From Remote Learning During the COVID-19 Pandemic.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e67684</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e67684</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e67684</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.67684</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Introduction During the COVID-19 pandemic, the AO Foundation, an orthopedic education organization, had to transition its live education programs to an online format. Skills that were previously evaluated and corrected in person by educators were now assessed through online lectures and discussion groups. Our goal was to evaluate an online course designed to teach the skill of "leg length and coronal deformity measurement" and to assess participants' ability to demonstrate this skill using online software. Methods An IRB-approved study was conducted during an online osteotomy course. A total of 176 participants were instructed on how to measure length and angulation through the course lectures and planning tutorials. The Bonesetter App (Detroit Bonesetter, Detroit, Michigan, USA) was used as the digital planning tool. Participants analyzed four cases of coronal deformity using long-leg standing radiographs. They were required to identify any deformities present, specify the type of deformity, and determine whether it affected the femur, tibia, or joint. Additionally, participants needed to calculate the deformity as part of the osteotomy planning process. Their measurements and drawings were saved and subsequently evaluated by two independent observers. Results Out of 176 online participants, 76% (315 out of 417) correctly completed the four exercises. The most frequent errors occurred in measuring total deformity and joint deformity. The average standard deviation of length measurements was ±0.29 cm (based on 244 measurements), while for angular measurements, it was ±0.71 degrees (based on 688 measurements). The intraclass correlation coefficient was greater than 0.96. Conclusions The online course effectively taught coronal deformity measurement, although participants struggled most with measuring joint angles and total deformity. Future courses should provide more detailed explanations for these measurements.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Vaidya et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vaidya</LastName><ForeName>Rahul</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Orthopedic Surgery, Wayne State University Detroit Medical Center, Detroit, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rosinski</LastName><ForeName>Kadence</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Orthopedic Surgery, Wayne State University School of Medicine, Detroit, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bunge</LastName><ForeName>Tatiana</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Orthopedic Surgery, Wayne State University School of Medicine, Detroit, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cavazos</LastName><ForeName>Daniel</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Orthopedic Surgery, Wayne State University Detroit Medical Center, Detroit, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sirkin</LastName><ForeName>Michael S</ForeName><Initials>MS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Orthopedics and Trauma, Rutgers University New Jersey Medical School, Newark, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Purushotham</LastName><ForeName>Anagha</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Orthopedic Surgery, Wayne State University, Detroit, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Crist</LastName><ForeName>Brett</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Orthopedics and Trauma, University of Missouri, Columbia, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Teitge</LastName><ForeName>Robert</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Orthopedic Surgery, Wayne State University School of Medicine, Detroit, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">coronal alignment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">femoral deformity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">joint deformity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">tibial deformity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">total deformity</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Wayne State University Institutional Review Board issued approval 21-10-4123. Animal subjects: All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>40</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39314571</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11419592</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.67684</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Pauwels F. Berlin, Heidelberg, Germany: Springer; 1980. Biomechanics of the Locomotor Apparatus: Contributions on the Functional Anatomy of the Locomotor Apparatus.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mueller ME, Francillon MR. Stuttgart, Germany: Georg Thieme; 1971. Die hüftnahen Femurosteotomien unter Berücksichtigung der Form, Funktion und Benspruchung des Hüftgelenkes; p. 9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mast J, Jakob R, Ganz R. Planning and Reduction Technique in Fracture Surgery. Berlin, Heidelberg: Springer; 1989. Reduction with plates.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paley D. Principles of Deformity Correction. Berlin, Heidelberg: Springer; 2002. Normal lower limb alignment and joint orientation.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Why are legs shaped the way they are? AO Trauma North America. https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=df9S5x1hZn8 2020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Online instruction to measure axial alignment with the bonesetter app. Bernstein M, Bunge T, Rosinski K, Kfuri M, Crist B, Knapp A, Vaidya R. Medicina (Kaunas) 2022;58:1079.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9415140</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36013547</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osteotomy course. AO Trauma North America. https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLK_-TIY7xyD45C4upDXXY5xK28_3P4k6t </Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonesetter App. Bonesetter App (2020. https://detroitbonesetter.com/ 18</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>OSTEOTOMY WEEK 1: April 18 - Deformity Evaluation. https://www.youtube.com/live/REFXfzoHUY0?app=desktop&amp;t=935s </Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Analytics Calculators.  [
Sep;
2022 
]. https://www.analyticscalculators.com/category.aspx https://www.analyticscalculators.com/category.aspx</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Building a successful massive open online course about multiple sclerosis: a process description. Claflin SB, Gates R, Maher M, Taylor BV. J Med Internet Res. 2020;22:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7424472</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32723726</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Self-paced online learning to improve knowledge competencies for hypertension among medical students in Uganda: a pre-post study. Edward A, Kalyesubula R, Pariyo G, Kyazze AP, Hu X, Appel LJ, Matsushita K. PLOS Glob Public Health. 2023;3:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10351720</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37459296</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delivering an online course in emergency nursing education during the pandemic: what are the effects on students' learning? Lei T, Yu X, Zou M, Wang P, Yuan RH. Australas Emerg Care. 2021;24:314–318.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8500169</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33910775</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 pandemic and its impact on dental education: digitalization - progress or regress? Example of an online hands-on course. Oetter N, Möst T, Weber M, et al. BMC Med Educ. 2022;22:591.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9340732</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35915461</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Update of students' and lecturers' perspectives on online learning in dental education after a five-semester experience due to the SARS-CoV-2 (COVID-19) pandemic: insights for future curriculum reform. Schlenz MA, Wöstmann B, Krämer N, Schulz-Weidner N. BMC Med Educ. 2023;23:556.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10411012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37553629</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>