<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39314699</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2376-5992</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>10</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>PeerJ. Computer science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>PeerJ Comput Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Enhancing rice yield prediction: a deep fusion model integrating ResNet50-LSTM with multi source data.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e2219</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e2219</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e2219</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7717/peerj-cs.2219</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Rice production is pivotal for ensuring global food security. In Pakistan, rice is not only the dominant Kharif crop but also a significant export commodity that significantly impacts the state's economy. However, Pakistan faces challenges such as abrupt climate change and the COVID-19 pandemic, which affect rice production and underscore the need for predictive models for informed decisions aimed at improving productivity and ultimately the state's economy. This article presents an innovative deep learning-based hybrid predictive model, ResNet50-LSTM, designed to forecast rice yields in the Gujranwala district, Pakistan, utilizing multi-modal data. The model incorporates MODIS satellite imagery capturing EVI, LAI, and FPAR indices along with meteorological and soil data. Google Earth Engine is used for the collection and preprocessing of satellite imagery, where the preprocessing steps involve data filtering, applying region geometry, interpolation, and aggregation. These preprocessing steps were applied manually on meteorological and soil data. Following feature extraction from the imagery data using ResNet50, the three LSTM model configurations are presented with distinct layer architectures. The findings of this study exhibit that the model configuration featuring two LSTM layers with interconnected cells outperforms other proposed configurations in terms of prediction performance. Analysis of various feature combinations reveals that the selected feature set (EVI, FPAR, climate, and soil variables) yields highly accurate results with an R<sup>2</sup> = 0.9903, RMSE = 0.1854, MAPE = 0.62%, MAE = 0.1384, MRE = 0.0062, and Willmott's index of agreement = 0.9536. Moreover, the combination of EVI and FPAR is identified as particularly effective. Our findings revealed the potential of our framework for globally estimating crop yields through the utilization of publicly available multi-source data.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Aslam and Farhan.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Aslam</LastName><ForeName>Aqsa</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3447-8278</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Computer Science, Lahore College for Women University, Lahore, Punjab, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Farhan</LastName><ForeName>Saima</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Computer Science, Lahore College for Women University, Lahore, Punjab, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>13</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>PeerJ Comput Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101660598</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2376-5992</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Deep learning</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Google Earth Engine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">NASA POWER project</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Remote sensing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ResNet-LSTM</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Rice yield prediction</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39314699</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11419660</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7717/peerj-cs.2219</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">cs-2219</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Anguita D, Ghelardoni L, Ghio A, Oneto L, Ridella S. ESANN 2012 Proceedings, 20th European Symposium on Artificial Neural Networks, Computational Intelligence and Machine Learning. 2012. The ‘K’ in K-fold cross validation.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campbell RHW, James B. Introduction to remote sensing. Fifth Edition. New York: Guilford Press; 2011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao J, Zhang Z, Tao F, Zhang L, Luo Y, Zhang J, Han J, Xie J. Integrating multi-source data for rice yield prediction across China using machine learning and deep learning approaches. Agricultural and Forest Meteorology. 2021;297(6):108275. doi: 10.1016/j.agrformet.2020.108275.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.agrformet.2020.108275</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chu Z, Yu J. An end-to-end model for rice yield prediction using deep learning fusion. Computers and Electronics in Agriculture. 2020;174:105471. doi: 10.1016/J.COMPAG.2020.105471.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/J.COMPAG.2020.105471</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crops Statistics  Crop reporting service Government of Punjab. 2022. https://crs.agripunjab.gov.pk/reports https://crs.agripunjab.gov.pk/reports</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CRS  Crop reporting service. 2022. https://crs.agripunjab.gov.pk/  [20 November 2023]. https://crs.agripunjab.gov.pk/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dang C, Liu Y, Yue H, Qian JX, Zhu R. Autumn crop yield prediction using data-driven approaches: -support vector machines, random forest, and deep neural network methods. Canadian Journal of Remote Sensing. 2021;47(2):162–181. doi: 10.1080/07038992.2020.1833186.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/07038992.2020.1833186</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Didan K. “MODIS/Terra vegetation indices 16-Day L3 global 1km SIN Grid V061 [Data set],” NASA EOSDIS land processes distributed active archive center. 2021. https://doi.org/10.5067/MODIS/MOD13A2.061.  [20 November 2023]. https://doi.org/10.5067/MODIS/MOD13A2.061</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAOSTAT  Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations. https://www.fao.org/faostat/en/#rankings/commodities_by_country_exports.  [16 April 2023];2024 </Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fei S, Hassan MA, Xiao Y, Su X, Chen Z, Cheng Q, Duan F, Chen R, Ma Y. UAV-based multi-sensor data fusion and machine learning algorithm for yield prediction in wheat. Precision Agriculture. 2023;24(1):187–212. doi: 10.1007/s11119-022-09938-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11119-022-09938-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9362526</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35967193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernandez-Beltran R, Baidar T, Kang J, Pla F. Rice-yield prediction with multi-temporal sentinel-2 data and 3D CNN: a case study in Nepal. Remote Sensing. 2021;13(7):1391. doi: 10.3390/RS13071391.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/RS13071391</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Friedl M, Sulla-Menashe D. “MCD12Q1 MODIS/Terra+Aqua land cover type yearly L3 global 500m SIN grid V006,” NASA EOSDIS land processes distributed active archive center2. 2019. https://doi.org/10.5067/MODIS/MCD12Q1.006.  [20 November 2023]. https://doi.org/10.5067/MODIS/MCD12Q1.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu T, Tian S, Zhan Q. Phenological analysis and yield estimation of rice based on multi-spectral and SAR data in Maha Sarakham. Journal of Spatial Science. 2023;69(1):149–165. doi: 10.1080/14498596.2023.2184428.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/14498596.2023.2184428</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goeb J, Zone PP, Kham Synt NL, Zu AM, Tang Y, Minten B. Food prices, processing, and shocks: evidence from rice and COVID-19. Journal of Agricultural Economics. 2022;73(2):338–355. doi: 10.1111/1477-9552.12461.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1477-9552.12461</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8652574</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34898718</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gokila M, Santhi S. A review on deep learning technique on basis of different types of crop diseases. EAI/Springer Innovations in Communication and Computing. 2022;1:651–665. doi: 10.1007/978-3-030-86165-0_54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-86165-0_54</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo Y, Fu Y, Hao F, Zhang X, Wu W, Jin X, Robin Bryant C, Senthilnath J. Integrated phenology and climate in rice yields prediction using machine learning methods. Ecological Indicators. 2021;120(3–4):106935. doi: 10.1016/j.ecolind.2020.106935.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecolind.2020.106935</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Humanitarian Data Exchange  Pakistan-subnational administrative boundaries, humanitarian data exchange. 2022. https://data.humdata.org/dataset/cod-ab-pak.  [20 November 2023]. https://data.humdata.org/dataset/cod-ab-pak</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ketkar N. Introduction to Keras. Deep Learning with Python. 2017;1:97–111. doi: 10.1007/978-1-4842-2766-4_7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-1-4842-2766-4_7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koonce B. Convolutional Neural Networks with Swift Tensorflow. Vol. 1. New York: Springer; 2021. ResNet 50; pp. 63–72.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lecun Y, Bengio Y, Hinton G. Deep learning. Nature. 2015;521(7553):436–444. doi: 10.1038/nature14539.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nature14539</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26017442</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y, Wang S, Chen J, Chen B, Wang X, Hao D, Sun L. Rice yield prediction and model interpretation based on satellite and climatic indicators using a transformer method. Remote Sensing. 2022;14(19):5045. doi: 10.3390/rs14195045.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/rs14195045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McKinney W. Python for data analysis. Second Edition. Sebastopol: O’Reilly Media Inc; 2013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mukherjee S. “The Annotated ResNet-50,” Towards Data Science. 2022. https://towardsdatascience.com/the-annotated-resnet-50-a6c536034758.  [25 November 2023]. https://towardsdatascience.com/the-annotated-resnet-50-a6c536034758</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muruganantham P, Wibowo S, Grandhi S, Samrat NH, Islam N. A systematic literature review on crop yield prediction with deep learning and remote sensing. Remote Sensing. 1990;14(9):1990. doi: 10.3390/RS14091990.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/RS14091990</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Myneni R, Knyazikhin Y, Park T. “MODIS/Terra leaf area index/FPAR 8-Day L4 global 500m SIN grid V061 [Data set],” NASA EOSDIS land processes distributed active archive center. 2021. https://doi.org/10.5067/MODIS/MOD15A2H.061.  [20 November 2023]. https://doi.org/10.5067/MODIS/MOD15A2H.061</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oikonomidis A, Catal C, Kassahun A. Deep learning for crop yield prediction: a systematic literature review. New Zealand Journal of Crop and Horticultural Science. 2023;51(1):1–26. doi: 10.1080/01140671.2022.2032213.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/01140671.2022.2032213</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>POWER  National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) 2020. https://power.larc.nasa.gov/data-access-viewer/  [20 November 2023]. https://power.larc.nasa.gov/data-access-viewer/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saifi S, Horowitz J. Blackouts and soaring prices: Pakistan’s economy is on the brink. CNN business. 2023. https://edition.cnn.com/2023/02/02/economy/pakistan-economy-crisis/index.html .  [6 May 2023]. https://edition.cnn.com/2023/02/02/economy/pakistan-economy-crisis/index.html </Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shakoor U, Saboor A, Baig I, Afzal A, Rahman A. Climate variability impacts on rice crop production in Pakistan. Pakistan Journal of Agricultural Research. 2015;28(1):19–27.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh P, Manure A. Learn TensorFlow 2.0. Berkeley, CA: Apress; 2020. Introduction to TensorFlow 2.0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-1-4842-5558-2_1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sivakumar MVK, Roy PS, Harmsen K, Saha SK. Proceedings of the Training Workshop 7-11 July, 2003, Dehra Dun, India. Geneva: World Meteorological Organisation; 2003. Satellite remote sensing and GIS applications in agricultural meteorology.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siyal AA, Dempewolf J, Becker-Reshef I. Rice yield estimation using landsat ETM+ data. Journal of Applied Remote Sensing. 2015;9(1):095986. doi: 10.1117/1.JRS.9.095986.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1117/1.JRS.9.095986</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Son NT, Chen CF, Chen CR, Guo HY, Cheng YS, Chen SL, Lin HS, Chen SH. Machine learning approaches for rice crop yield predictions using time-series satellite data in Taiwan. International Journal of Remote Sensing. 2020;41(20):7868–7888. doi: 10.1080/01431161.2020.1766148.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/01431161.2020.1766148</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Statista  Total global rice consumption. 2024. https://www.statista.com/statistics/255977/total-global-rice-consumption/  [3 December 2023]. https://www.statista.com/statistics/255977/total-global-rice-consumption/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Swapna B, Manivannan S, Kamalahasan M. Prognostic of soil nutrients and soil fertility index using machine learning classifier techniques. International Journal of e-Collaboration. 2022;18(2):1–14. doi: 10.4018/IJEC.304034.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4018/IJEC.304034</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tahseen Haider S, Ge W, Muhammad Haider S, Iqbal SZABIST F, Zulkar Ali Bhutto S. Cotton prediction from weather parameters of different city of Pakistan using machine learning technique. 2022;23(20):20688. doi: 10.21203/rs.3.rs-2018015/v1. Research Square.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21203/rs.3.rs-2018015/v1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tian H, Wang P, Tansey K, Zhang J, Zhang S, Li H. An LSTM neural network for improving wheat yield estimates by integrating remote sensing data and meteorological data in the Guanzhong plain, PR China. Agricultural and Forest Meteorology. 2021;310(6):108629. doi: 10.1016/J.AGRFORMET.2021.108629.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/J.AGRFORMET.2021.108629</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Usman M, Ijaz M, Aziz M, Hassan M, Ahmed AM, Soomro DM, Ali S. Locust attack: managing and control strategies by the Government of Pakistan. Proceedings of the Pakistan Academy of Sciences: B. Life and Environmental Sciences. 2022;59(2):25–33. doi: 10.53560/PPASB(59-2)718.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.53560/PPASB(59-2)718</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Wild O, Ashworth K, Chen X, Wu Q, Qi Y, Wang Z. Reductions in crop yields across China from elevated ozone. Environmental Pollution. 2022;292(7):118218. doi: 10.1016/j.envpol.2021.118218.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2021.118218</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34571069</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xing D, Wang Y, Sun P, Huang H, Lin E. A CNN-LSTM-att hybrid model for classification and evaluation of growth status under drought and heat stress in Chinese fir (Cunninghamia lanceolata) Plant Methods. 2023;19(1):660. doi: 10.1186/s13007-023-01044-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13007-023-01044-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10316624</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37400865</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu Y, Si X, Hu C, Zhang J. A review of recurrent neural networks: LSTM cells and network architectures. Neural Computation. 2019;31(7):1235–1270. doi: 10.1162/NECO_A_01199.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1162/NECO_A_01199</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31113301</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang L, Zhang Z, Luo Y, Cao J, Tao F. Combining optical, fluorescence, thermal satellite, and environmental data to predict county-level maize yield in China using machine learning approaches. Remote Sensing. 2019;12(1):21. doi: 10.3390/RS12010021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/RS12010021</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou S, Xu L, Chen N. Rice yield prediction in Hubei province based on deep learning and the effect of spatial heterogeneity. Remote Sensing. 2023;15(5):1361. doi: 10.3390/RS15051361.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/RS15051361</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>