<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39316285</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1867-108X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Japanese journal of radiology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Jpn J Radiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Recent developments in the field of radiotherapy for the management of lung cancer.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s11604-024-01663-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Lung cancer has a poor prognosis, and further improvements in outcomes are needed. Radiotherapy plays an important role in the treatment of unresectable lung cancer, and there have been recent developments in the field of radiotherapy for the management of lung cancer. However, to date, there have been few reviews on the improvement in treatment outcomes associated with high precision radiotherapy for lung cancer. Thus, this review aimed to summarize the recent developments in radiotherapy techniques and indicate the future directions in the use of radiotherapy for lung cancer. Stereotactic body radiotherapy (SBRT) for unresectable stage I lung cancer has been reported to improve local control rates without severe adverse events, such as radiation pneumonitis. For locally advanced lung cancer, a combination of chemoradiotherapy and adjuvant immune checkpoint inhibitors dramatically improves treatment outcomes, and intensity-modulated radiotherapy (IMRT) enables safer radiation therapy with less frequent pneumonitis. Particle beam therapy, such as carbon-ion radiotherapy and proton beam therapy, has been administered as advanced medical care for patients with lung cancer. Since 2024, it has been covered under insurance for early stage lung cancer with tumors ≤ 5 cm in size in Japan. In addition to chemotherapy, local ablative radiotherapy improves treatment outcomes in patients with oligometastatic stage IV lung cancer. A particular problem with radiotherapy for lung cancer is that the target location changes with respiratory motion, and various physical methods have been used to control respiratory motion. Recently, coronavirus disease has had a major impact on lung cancer treatment, and cancer treatment during situations, such as the coronavirus pandemic, must be performed carefully. To improve treatment outcomes for lung cancer, it is necessary to fully utilize evolving radiotherapy modalities, and the role of radiotherapy in lung cancer treatment is expected to increase.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shirai</LastName><ForeName>Katsuyuki</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2096-8847</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, Jichi Medical University Hospital, 3311-1, Yakushiji, Shimotsuke-shi, Tochigi, 329-0498, Japan. kshirai@jichi.ac.jp.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, Jichi Medical University Saitama Medical Center, Saitama, Saitama, Japan. kshirai@jichi.ac.jp.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Aoki</LastName><ForeName>Shuri</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>QST Hospital, National Institutes for Quantum Science and Technology, Anagawa, Chiba, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Endo</LastName><ForeName>Masashi</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, Jichi Medical University Hospital, 3311-1, Yakushiji, Shimotsuke-shi, Tochigi, 329-0498, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Takahashi</LastName><ForeName>Yuta</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, Jichi Medical University Saitama Medical Center, Saitama, Saitama, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fukuda</LastName><ForeName>Yukiko</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, Jichi Medical University Hospital, 3311-1, Yakushiji, Shimotsuke-shi, Tochigi, 329-0498, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, Jichi Medical University Saitama Medical Center, Saitama, Saitama, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Akahane</LastName><ForeName>Keiko</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, Jichi Medical University Saitama Medical Center, Saitama, Saitama, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Musha</LastName><ForeName>Atsushi</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Gunma University Heavy Ion Medical Center, Maebashi, Gunma, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sato</LastName><ForeName>Harutoshi</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, Jichi Medical University Hospital, 3311-1, Yakushiji, Shimotsuke-shi, Tochigi, 329-0498, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wakatsuki</LastName><ForeName>Masaru</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>QST Hospital, National Institutes for Quantum Science and Technology, Anagawa, Chiba, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ishikawa</LastName><ForeName>Hitoshi</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>QST Hospital, National Institutes for Quantum Science and Technology, Anagawa, Chiba, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sasaki</LastName><ForeName>Ryohei</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Radiation Oncology, Kobe University Graduate School of Medicine, Kobe, Hyogo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Japan</Country><MedlineTA>Jpn J Radiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101490689</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1867-1071</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">IMRT</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Lung cancer</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Particle therapy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Radiotherapy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SBRT</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39316285</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11604-024-01663-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s11604-024-01663-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Torre LA, Bray F, Siegel RL, Ferlay J, Lortet-Tieulent J, Jemal AJ. Global cancer statistics, 2012. CA Cancer J Clin. 2015;65:87–108. https://doi.org/10.3322/caac.21262 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3322/caac.21262</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25651787</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saji H, Okada M, Tsuboi M, Nakajima R, Suzuki K, Aokage K, et al. Segmentectomy versus lobectomy in small-sized peripheral non-small-cell lung cancer (JCOG0802/WJOG4607L): a multicentre, open-label, phase 3, randomised, controlled, non-inferiority trial. Lancet. 2022;399:1607–17. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(21)02333-3 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(21)02333-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35461558</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang JY, Senan S, Paul MA, Mehran RJ, Louie AV, Balter P, et al. Stereotactic ablative radiotherapy versus lobectomy for operable stage I non-small-cell lung cancer: a pooled analysis of two randomised trials. Lancet Oncol. 2015;16:630–7. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1470-2045(15)70168-3 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(15)70168-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25981812</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4489408</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nyman J, Hallqvist A, Lund JÅ, Brustugun OT, Bergman B, Bergström P, et al. SPACE—a randomized study of SBRT vs conventional fractionated radiotherapy in medically inoperable stage I NSCLC. Radiother Oncol. 2016;121:1–8. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.radonc.2016.08.015 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.radonc.2016.08.015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27600155</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ball D, Mai GT, Vinod S, Babington S, Ruben J, Kron T, et al. Stereotactic ablative radiotherapy versus standard radiotherapy in stage 1 non-small-cell lung cancer (TROG 09.02 CHISEL): a phase 3, open-label, randomised controlled trial. Lancet Oncol. 2019;20:494–503. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1470-2045(18)30896-9 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(18)30896-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30770291</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bucknell NW, Kron T, Herschtal A, Hardcastle N, Irving L, MacManus M, et al. Comparison of changes in pulmonary function after stereotactic body radiation therapy versus conventional 3-dimensional conformal radiation therapy for stage I and IIA non-small cell lung cancer: an analysis of the TROG 09.02 (CHISEL) phase 3 trial. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2023;117:378–86. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijrobp.2023.04.009 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijrobp.2023.04.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37087060</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Timmerman R, Paulus R, Galvin J, Michalski J, Straube W, Bradley J, et al. Stereotactic body radiation therapy for inoperable early stage lung cancer. JAMA. 2010;303:1070–6. https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2010.261 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2010.261</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20233825</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2907644</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nagata Y, Hiraoka M, Shibata T, Onishi H, Kokubo M, Karasawa K, et al. Prospective trial of stereotactic body radiation therapy for both operable and inoperable T1N0M0 non-small cell lung cancer: Japan Clinical Oncology Group Study JCOG0403. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2015;93:989–96. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijrobp.2015.07.2278 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijrobp.2015.07.2278</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26581137</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kishi N, Matsuo Y, Menju T, Hamaji M, Nakakura A, Hanazawa H, et al. Propensity score-based analysis of stereotactic body radiotherapy, lobectomy and sublobar resection for stage I non-small cell lung cancer. J Radiat Res. 2022;63:758–71. https://doi.org/10.1093/jrr/rrac041 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jrr/rrac041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35818291</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9494527</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Timmerman RD, Paulus R, Pass HI, Gore EM, Edelman MJ, Galvin J, et al. Stereotactic body radiation therapy for operable early-stage lung cancer: findings from the NRG Oncology RTOG 0618 trial. JAMA Oncol. 2018;4:1263–6. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoncol.2018.1251 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamaoncol.2018.1251</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29852037</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6117102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Onishi H, Shirato H, Nagata Y, Hiraoka M, Fujino M, Gomi K, et al. Hypofractionated stereotactic radiotherapy (HypoFXSRT) for stage I non-small cell lung cancer: updated results of 257 patients in a Japanese multi-institutional study. J Thorac Oncol. 2007;2(Suppl 3):S94–100. https://doi.org/10.1097/JTO.0b013e318074de34 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/JTO.0b013e318074de34</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17603311</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moreno AC, Fellman B, Hobbs BP, Liao Z, Gomez DR, Chen A, et al. Biologically effective dose in stereotactic body radiotherapy and survival for patients with early-stage NSCLC. J Thorac Oncol. 2020;15:101–9. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtho.2019.08.2505 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jtho.2019.08.2505</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31479748</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kimura T, Nagata Y, Eba J, Ozawa S, Ishikura S, Shibata T, et al. A randomized Phase III trial of comparing two dose-fractionations stereotactic body radiotherapy (SBRT) for medically inoperable Stage IA non-small cell lung cancer or small lung lesions clinically diagnosed as primary lung cancer: Japan Clinical Oncology Group Study JCOG1408 (J-SBRT trial). Jpn J Clin Oncol. 2017;47:277–81. https://doi.org/10.1093/jjco/hyw198 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jjco/hyw198</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28073946</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ganesh A, Korpics M, Pasquinelli M, Feldman L, Spiotto M, Koshy M. Increased utilization of stereotactic body radiotherapy is associated with decreased disparities and improved survival for early-stage NSCLC. Clin Lung Cancer. 2023;24:60–71. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cllc.2022.09.006 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cllc.2022.09.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36289032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashworth A, Kong W, Owen T, Hanna TP, Brundage M. The management of stage I non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) in Ontario: a population-based study of patterns of care and stereotactic ablative body radiotherapy (SABR) utilization from 2010 to 2019. Radiother Oncol. 2024;194: 110153. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.radonc.2024.110153 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.radonc.2024.110153</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38364940</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Non-small Cell Lung Cancer Collaborative Group. Chemotherapy in non-small cell lung cancer: a meta-analysis using updated data on individual patients from 52 randomised clinical trials. Non-small Cell Lung Cancer Collaborative Group. BMJ. 1995;311:899–909. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.311.7010.899</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bradley JD, Paulus R, Komaki R, Masters G, Blumenschein G, Schild S, et al. Standard-dose versus high-dose conformal radiotherapy with concurrent and consolidation carboplatin plus paclitaxel with or without cetuximab for patients with stage IIIA or IIIB non-small-cell lung cancer (RTOG 0617): a randomised, two-by-two factorial phase 3 study. Lancet Oncol. 2015;16:187–99. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1470-2045(14)71207-0 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(14)71207-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25601342</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4419359</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kong F, Hu C, Machtay M, Matuszak M, Xiao Y, Ten Haken R, et al. OA02.04 randomized phase II trial (RTOG1106) on midtreatment PET/CT guided adaptive radiotherapy in locally advanced non-small cell lung cancer. J Thorac Oncol. 2021;16:S104–5. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtho.2021.01.277 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jtho.2021.01.277</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antonia SJ, Villegas A, Daniel D, Vicente D, Murakami S, Hui R, et al. Durvalumab after chemoradiotherapy in stage III non-small-cell lung cancer. N Engl J Med. 2017;377:1919–29. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMoa1709937 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1709937</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28885881</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antonia SJ, Villegas A, Daniel D, Vicente D, Murakami S, Hui R, et al. Overall survival with durvalumab after chemoradiotherapy in stage III NSCLC. N Engl J Med. 2018;379:2342–50. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMoa1809697 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1809697</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30280658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kubo N, Kobayashi D, Iwanaga M, Matsuura M, Higuchi K, Eishima J, et al. Radiotherapy patterns of care for locally-advanced non-small cell lung cancer in the pre- and post-durvalumab era: a region-wide survey in a Japanese prefecture. J Radiat Res. 2022;63:264–71. https://doi.org/10.1093/jrr/rrab116 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jrr/rrab116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34970980</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chun SG, Hu C, Choy H, Komaki RU, Timmerman RD, Schild SE, et al. Impact of intensity-modulated radiation therapy technique for locally advanced non-small-cell lung cancer: a secondary analysis of the NRG Oncology RTOG 0617 randomized clinical trial. J Clin Oncol. 2017;35:56–62. https://doi.org/10.1200/JCO.2016.69.1378 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1200/JCO.2016.69.1378</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28034064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsujino K, Hirota S, Endo M, Obayashi K, Kotani Y, Satouchi M, et al. Predictive value of dose-volume histogram parameters for predicting radiation pneumonitis after concurrent chemoradiation for lung cancer. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2003;55:110–5. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0360-3016(02)03807-5 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s0360-3016(02)03807-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12504042</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan C, Lang S, Rowbottom C, Guckenberger M, Faivre-Finn C. IASLC Advanced Radiation Technology Committee. Intensity-modulated radiotherapy for lung cancer: current status and future developments. J Thorac Oncol. 2014;9:1598–608. https://doi.org/10.1097/JTO.0000000000000346 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/JTO.0000000000000346</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25436795</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsukita Y, Yamamoto T, Mayahara H, Hata A, Takeda Y, Nakayama H, et al. Intensity-modulated radiation therapy with concurrent chemotherapy followed by durvalumab for stage III non-small cell lung cancer: a multi-center retrospective study. Radiother Oncol. 2021;160:266–72. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.radonc.2021.05.016 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.radonc.2021.05.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34023330</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schild SE, Fan W, Stinchcombe TE, Vokes EE, Ramalingam SS, Bradley JD, et al. Toxicity related to radiotherapy dose and targeting strategy: a pooled analysis of cooperative group trials of combined modality therapy for locally advanced non-small cell lung cancer. J Thorac Oncol. 2019;14:298–303. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtho.2018.09.021 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jtho.2018.09.021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30292852</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nestle U, Schimek-Jasch T, Kremp S, Schaefer-Schuler A, Mix M, Küsters A, et al. Imaging-based target volume reduction in chemoradiotherapy for locally advanced non-small-cell lung cancer (PET-Plan): a multicentre, open-label, randomised, controlled trial. Lancet Oncol. 2020;21:581–92. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1470-2045(20)30013-9 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(20)30013-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32171429</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turrisi AT III, Kim K, Blum R, Sause WT, Livingston RB, Komaki R, et al. Twice-daily compared with once-daily thoracic radiotherapy in limited small-cell lung cancer treated concurrently with cisplatin and etoposide. N Engl J Med. 1999;340:265–71. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJM199901283400403-71 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJM199901283400403-71</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9920950</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faivre-Finn C, Snee M, Ashcroft L, Appel W, Barlesi F, Bhatnagar A, et al. Concurrent once-daily versus twice-daily chemoradiotherapy in patients with limited-stage small-cell lung cancer (CONVERT): an open-label, phase 3, randomised, superiority trial. Lancet Oncol. 2017;18:1116–25. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1470-2045(17)30318-2 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(17)30318-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28642008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5555437</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spigel DR, Cheng Y, Cho BC, Laktionov KK, Fang J, Chen Y, et al. Adriatic: durvalumab (D) as consolidation treatment (tx) for patients (pts) with limited-stage small-cell lung cancer (LS-SCLC). J Clin Oncol. 2024;42:sLBA5. https://doi.org/10.1200/JCO.2024.42.17_suppl.LBA5 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1200/JCO.2024.42.17_suppl.LBA5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banfill K, Giuliani M, Aznar M, Franks K, McWilliam A, Schmitt M, et al. Cardiac toxicity of thoracic radiotherapy: existing evidence and future directions. J Thorac Oncol. 2021;16:216–27. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtho.2020.11.002 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jtho.2020.11.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33278607</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7870458</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Speirs CK, DeWees TA, Rehman S, Molotievschi A, Velez MA, Mullen D, et al. Heart dose is an independent dosimetric predictor of overall survival in locally advanced non-small cell lung cancer. J Thorac Oncol. 2017;12:293–301. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtho.2016.09.134 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jtho.2016.09.134</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27743888</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruan H, Xiong J. Value of carbon-ion radiotherapy for early stage non-small cell lung cancer. Clin Transl Radiat Oncol. 2022;36:16–23. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ctro.2022.06.005 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ctro.2022.06.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35756194</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9213230</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamada T, Tsujii H, Blakely EA, Debus J, De Neve W, Durante M, et al. Carbon ion radiotherapy in Japan: an assessment of 20 years of clinical experience. Lancet Oncol. 2015;16:e93–100. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1470-2045(14)70412-7 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(14)70412-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25638685</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sakurai H, Ishikawa H, Okumura T. Proton beam therapy in Japan: current and future status. Jpn J Clin Oncol. 2016;46:885–92. https://doi.org/10.1093/jjco/hyw102 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jjco/hyw102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27534798</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang JY, Mehran RJ, Feng L, Verma V, Liao Z, Welsh JW, et al. Stereotactic ablative radiotherapy for operable stage I non-small-cell lung cancer (revised STARS): long-term results of a single-arm, prospective trial with prespecified comparison to surgery. Lancet Oncol. 2021;22:1448–57. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1470-2045(21)00401-0 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(21)00401-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34529930</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8521627</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ohnishi K, Nakamura N, Harada H, Tokumaru S, Wada H, Arimura T, et al. Proton beam therapy for histologically or clinically diagnosed stage I non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC): the first nationwide retrospective study in Japan. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2020;106:82–9. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijrobp.2019.09.013 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijrobp.2019.09.013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31580927</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kubo N, Suefuji H, Nakajima M, Tokumaru S, Okano N, Yoshida D, et al. Five-year survival outcomes after carbon-ion radiotherapy for operable stage I NSCLC: a Japanese national registry study (J-CROS-LUNG). J Thorac Oncol. 2024;19:491–9. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtho.2023.10.016 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jtho.2023.10.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37924974</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kubo N, Suefuji H, Nakajima M, Tokumaru S, Okano N, Yoshida D, et al. Clinical results of carbon ion radiotherapy for inoperable stage I non-small cell lung cancer: a Japanese national registry study (J-CROS-LUNG). Radiother Oncol. 2023;183: 109640. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.radonc.2023.109640 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.radonc.2023.109640</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36990390</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okano N, Suefuji H, Nakajima M, Tokumaru S, Kubo N, Yoshida D, et al. Clinical results of carbon-ion radiotherapy for stage I non-small cell lung cancer with concomitant interstitial lung disease: a Japanese national registry study (J-CROS-LUNG). J Radiat Res. 2023;64(Suppl 1):i2-7. https://doi.org/10.1093/jrr/rrad008 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jrr/rrad008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37036751</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10278880</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aoki S, Ishikawa H, Nakajima M, Yamamoto N, Mori S, Wakatsuki M, et al. Long-term outcomes of ablative carbon-ion radiotherapy for central non-small cell lung cancer: a single-center, retrospective study. Cancers. 2024;16:933. https://doi.org/10.3390/cancers16050933 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/cancers16050933</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38473295</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10931128</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kadoya N, Obata Y, Kato T, Kagiya M, Nakamura T, Tomoda T, et al. Dose-volume comparison of proton radiotherapy and stereotactic body radiotherapy for non-small-cell lung cancer. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2011;79:1225–31. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijrobp.2010.05.016 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijrobp.2010.05.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20732759</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Upadhyay R, Venkatesulu BP, Giridhar P, Kim BK, Sharma A, Elghazawy H, et al. Risk and impact of radiation related lymphopenia in lung cancer: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Radiother Oncol. 2021;157:225–33. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.radonc.2021.01.034 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.radonc.2021.01.034</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33577865</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iwata H, Akita K, Yamaba Y, Kunii E, Takakuwa O, Yoshihara M, et al. Concurrent chemo-proton therapy using adaptive planning for unresectable stage 3 non-small cell lung cancer: a phase 2 study. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2021;109:1359–67. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijrobp.2020.11.035 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijrobp.2020.11.035</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33227444</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tatebe H, Harada H, Mori K, Iwata H, Akimoto T, Murakami M, et al. Clinical results of proton beam radiotherapy for inoperable stage III non-small cell lung cancer: a Japanese national registry study. J Radiat Res. 2023;64(Suppl 1):i8–15. https://doi.org/10.1093/jrr/rrad017 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jrr/rrad017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37137157</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10278876</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gjyshi O, Xu T, Elhammali A, Boyce-Fappiano D, Chun SG, Gandhi S, et al. Toxicity and survival after intensity-modulated proton therapy versus passive scattering proton therapy for NSCLC. J Thorac Oncol. 2021;16:269–77. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtho.2020.10.013 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jtho.2020.10.013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33198942</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hayashi K, Yamamoto N, Nakajima M, Nomoto A, Tsuji H, Ogawa K, et al. Clinical outcomes of carbon-ion radiotherapy for locally advanced non-small-cell lung cancer. Cancer Sci. 2019;110:734–41. https://doi.org/10.1111/cas.13890 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/cas.13890</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30467928</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6361552</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saitoh JI, Shirai K, Abe T, Kubo N, Ebara T, Ohno T, et al. A phase I study of hypofractionated carbon-ion radiotherapy for stage III non-small cell lung cancer. Anticancer Res. 2018;38:885–91. https://doi.org/10.21873/anticanres.12298 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21873/anticanres.12298</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29374716</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hellman S, Weichselbaum RR. Oligometastases. J Clin Oncol. 1995;13:8–10. https://doi.org/10.1200/JCO.1995.13.1.8 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1200/JCO.1995.13.1.8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7799047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dingemans AC, Hendriks LE, Berghmans T, Levy A, Hasan B, Faivre-Finn C, et al. Definition of synchronous oligometastatic non-small cell lung cancer-a consensus report. J Thorac Oncol. 2019;14:2109–19. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtho.2019.07.025 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jtho.2019.07.025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31398540</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iyengar P, All S, Berry MF, Boike TP, Bradfield L, Dingemans AC, et al. Treatment of oligometastatic non-small cell lung cancer: an ASTRO/ESTRO clinical practice guideline. Pract Radiat Oncol. 2023;13:393–412. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.prro.2023.04.004 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.prro.2023.04.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37294262</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guckenberger M, Lievens Y, Bouma AB, Collette L, Dekker A, deSouza NM, et al. Characterisation and classification of oligometastatic disease: a European Society for Radiotherapy and Oncology and European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer consensus recommendation. Lancet Oncol. 2020;21:e18-28. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1470-2045(19)30718-1 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(19)30718-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31908301</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashworth AB, Senan S, Palma DA, Riquet M, Ahn YC, Ricardi U, et al. An individual patient data metaanalysis of outcomes and prognostic factors after treatment of oligometastatic non-small-cell lung cancer. Clin Lung Cancer. 2014;15:346–55. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cllc.2014.04.003 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cllc.2014.04.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24894943</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gomez DR, Blumenschein GR Jr, Lee JJ, Hernandez M, Ye R, Camidge DR, et al. Local consolidative therapy versus maintenance therapy or observation for patients with oligometastatic non-small-cell lung cancer without progression after first-line systemic therapy: a multicentre, randomised, controlled, phase 2 study. Lancet Oncol. 2016;17:1672–82. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1470-2045(16)30532-0 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(16)30532-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27789196</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5143183</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gomez DR, Tang C, Zhang J, Blumenschein GR Jr, Hernandez M, Lee JJ, et al. Local consolidative therapy vs. maintenance therapy or observation for patients with oligometastatic non-small-cell lung cancer: long-term results of a multi-institutional, phase II, randomized study. J Clin Oncol. 2019;37:1558–65. https://doi.org/10.1200/JCO.19.00201 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1200/JCO.19.00201</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31067138</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6599408</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iyengar P, Wardak Z, Gerber DE, Tumati V, Ahn C, Hughes RS, et al. Consolidative radiotherapy for limited metastatic non-small-cell lung cancer: a phase 2 randomized clinical trial. JAMA Oncol. 2018;4: e173501. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamaoncol.2017.3501 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamaoncol.2017.3501</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28973074</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palma DA, Olson R, Harrow S, Gaede S, Louie AV, Haasbeek C, et al. Stereotactic ablative radiotherapy versus standard of care palliative treatment in patients with oligometastatic cancers (SABR-comet): a randomised, phase 2, open-label trial. Lancet. 2019;393:2051–8. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(18)32487-5 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(18)32487-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30982687</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Colosimo C, Pasqualetti F, Aristei C, Borghesi S, Forte L, Mignogna M, et al. Stereotactic radiotherapy for bone oligometastases. Rep Pract Oncol Radiother. 2022;27:40–5. https://doi.org/10.5603/RPOR.a2022.0009 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5603/RPOR.a2022.0009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35402030</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8989454</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Falcinelli L, Menichelli C, Casamassima F, Aristei C, Borghesi S, Ingrosso G, et al. Stereotactic radiotherapy for lung oligometastases. Rep Pract Oncol Radiother. 2022;27:23–31. https://doi.org/10.5603/RPOR.a2022.0002 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5603/RPOR.a2022.0002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35402023</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8989443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borghesi S, Casamassima F, Aristei C, Grandinetti A, Di Franco R. Stereotactic radiotherapy for adrenal oligometastases. Rep Pract Oncol Radiother. 2022;27:52–6. https://doi.org/10.5603/RPOR.a2021.0104 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5603/RPOR.a2021.0104</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35402020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8989453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pasqualetti F, Trippa F, Aristei C, Borghesi S, Colosimo C, Cantarella M, et al. Stereotactic radiotherapy for oligometastases in the lymph nodes. Rep Pract Oncol Radiother. 2022;27:46–51. https://doi.org/10.5603/RPOR.a2022.0007 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5603/RPOR.a2022.0007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35402021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8989441</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flannery TW, Suntharalingam M, Regine WF, Chin LS, Krasna MJ, Shehata MK, et al. Long-term survival in patients with synchronous, solitary brain metastasis from non-small-cell lung cancer treated with radiosurgery. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2008;72:19–23. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijrobp.2007.12.031 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijrobp.2007.12.031</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18280058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin Q, Zhou N, Zhu X, Lin J, Fang J, Gu F, et al. Outcomes of SBRT for lung oligo-recurrence of non-small cell lung cancer: a retrospective analysis. J Radiat Res. 2022;63:272–80. https://doi.org/10.1093/jrr/rrab118 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jrr/rrab118</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34958672</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang XS, Bai YF, Verma V, Yu RL, Tian W, Ao R, et al. Randomized trial of first-line tyrosine kinase inhibitor with or without radiotherapy for synchronous oligometastatic EGFR-mutated non-small cell lung cancer. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2023;115:742–8. https://doi.org/10.1093/jnci/djac015 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jnci/djac015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35094066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iyengar P, Hu C, Gomez DR, Timmerman RD, Simone CB II, Robinson CG, et al. NRG-LU002: randomized phase II/III trial of maintenance systemic therapy versus local consolidative therapy (LCT) plus maintenance systemic therapy for limited metastatic non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC). J Clin Oncol. 2024;42: s8506. https://doi.org/10.1200/JCO.2024.42.16_suppl.8506 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1200/JCO.2024.42.16_suppl.8506</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keall PJ, Mageras GS, Balter JM, Emery RS, Forster KM, Jiang SB, et al. The management of respiratory motion in radiation oncology report of AAPM Task Group 76. Med Phys. 2006;33:3874–900. https://doi.org/10.1118/1.2349696 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1118/1.2349696</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17089851</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mayo JR, Müller NL, Henkelman RM. The double-fissure sign: a motion artifact on thin-section CT scans. Radiology. 1987;165:580–1. https://doi.org/10.1148/radiology.165.2.3659392 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1148/radiology.165.2.3659392</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3659392</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korreman SS. Image-guided radiotherapy and motion management in lung cancer. Br J Radiol. 2015;88:20150100. https://doi.org/10.1259/bjr.20150100 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1259/bjr.20150100</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25955231</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4628536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>International Commission on Radiation Units and Measurements (ICRU). Report 62. Prescribing, recording and reporting photon beam therapy (supplement to ICRU Report 50). Bethesda: ICRU; 1999.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edvardsson A, Nordström F, Ceberg C, Ceberg S. Motion induced interplay effects for VMAT radiotherapy. Phys Med Biol. 2018;63: 085012. https://doi.org/10.1088/1361-6560/aab957 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1088/1361-6560/aab957</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29671410</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarkar V, Huang L, Huang YJ, Szegedi MW, Rassiah-Szegedi P, Zhao H, et al. Dosimetric evaluation of abdominal compression as a method to reduce the incidence of radiation-induced pneumonitis in lung SBRT treatment. J Radiosurg SBRT. 2016;4:125–32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29296437</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5658874</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ball HJ, Santanam L, Senan S, Tanyi JA, van Herk M, Keall PJ. Results from the AAPM Task Group 324 respiratory motion management in radiation oncology survey. J Appl Clin Med Phys. 2022;23: e13810. https://doi.org/10.1002/acm2.13810 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/acm2.13810</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36316761</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9680579</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korreman S, Persson G, Nygaard D, Brink C, Juhler-Nøttrup T. Respiration-correlated image guidance is the most important radiotherapy motion management strategy for most lung cancer patients. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2012;83:1338–43. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijrobp.2011.09.010 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijrobp.2011.09.010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22245194</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yasue K, Fuse H, Oyama S, Hanada K, Shinoda K, Ikoma H, et al. Quantitative analysis of the intra-beam respiratory motion with baseline drift for respiratory-gating lung stereotactic body radiation therapy. J Radiat Res. 2022;63:137–47. https://doi.org/10.1093/jrr/rrab098 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jrr/rrab098</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34718704</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li W, Konishi K, Ohira K, Hirata M, Wakabayashi K, Aramaki S, et al. Development of a novel airbag system of abdominal compression for reducing respiratory motion: preliminary results in healthy volunteers. J Radiat Res. 2022;63:699–705. https://doi.org/10.1093/jrr/rrac019 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jrr/rrac019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35575580</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9303601</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Negoro Y, Nagata Y, Aoki T, Mizowaki T, Araki N, Takayama K, et al. The effectiveness of an immobilization device in conformal radiotherapy for lung tumor: reduction of respiratory tumor movement and evaluation of the daily setup accuracy. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2001;50:889–98. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0360-3016(01)01516-4 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s0360-3016(01)01516-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11429216</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bouilhol G, Ayadi M, Rit S, Thengumpallil S, Schaerer J, Vandemeulebroucke J, et al. Is abdominal compression useful in lung stereotactic body radiation therapy? A 4DCT and dosimetric lobe-dependent study. Phys Med. 2013;29:333–40. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejmp.2012.04.006 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ejmp.2012.04.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22617761</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (WHO). Coronavirus disease (COVID-19): how is it transmitted?; 2024. Available from http://who.int/news-room/q-a-detail/coronavirus-disease-covid-19-how-is-it-transmitted . Accessed 9 Apr 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Voidarou C, Rozos G, Stavropoulou E, Giorgi E, Stefanis C, Vakadaris G, et al. COVID-19 on the spectrum: a scoping review of hygienic standards. Front Public Health. 2023;11:1202216. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpubh.2023.1202216 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2023.1202216</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38026326</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10646607</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stadnytskyi V, Bax CE, Bax A, Anfinrud P. The airborne lifetime of small speech droplets and their potential importance in SARS-CoV-2 transmission. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2020;117:11875–7. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2006874117 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.2006874117</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32404416</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7275719</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dbouk T, Drikakis D. On coughing and airborne droplet transmission to humans. Phys Fluids. 1994;2020(32): 053310. https://doi.org/10.1063/5.0011960 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1063/5.0011960</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Doremalen N, Bushmaker T, Morris DH, Holbrook MG, Gamble A, Williamson BN, et al. Aerosol and surface stability of SARS-CoV-2 as compared with SARS-CoV-1. N Engl J Med. 2020;382:1564–7. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMc2004973 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMc2004973</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32182409</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Musha A, Kubo N, Kawamura H, Okano N, Yanagisawa K, Sugawara K, et al. Pilot study of aerosols visualized and evaluated in a radiotherapy room. J Radiat Res. 2023;64:420–7. https://doi.org/10.1093/jrr/rrac109 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jrr/rrac109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36715177</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10036095</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tamari K, Nagata Y, Mizowaki T, Kodaira T, Onishi H, Ogawa K, et al. The impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on radiotherapy in Japan: nationwide surveys from May 2020 through June 2021. J Radiat Res. 2023;64:126–32. https://doi.org/10.1093/jrr/rrac055 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jrr/rrac055</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36109327</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carrouel F, Conte MP, Fisher J, Gonçalves LS, Dussart C, Llodra JC, et al. COVID-19: a recommendation to examine the effect of mouthrinses with β-Cyclodextrin combined with Citrox in preventing infection and progression. J Clin Med. 2020;9:1126. https://doi.org/10.3390/jcm9041126 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/jcm9041126</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32326426</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7230644</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herrera D, Serrano J, Roldán S, Sanz M. Is the oral cavity relevant in SARS-CoV-2 pandemic? Clin Oral Investig. 2020;24:2925–30. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00784-020-03413-2 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00784-020-03413-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32577830</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7309196</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>