<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39310544</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>8</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Spontaneous Air Embolism Following Contrast Injection: A Diagnostic Challenge in a Post-COVID-19 Patient.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e67375</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e67375</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e67375</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.67375</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>A 72-year-old male with a complex medical history, including chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), hypertension, atrial fibrillation, and a recent COVID-19 infection, presented to the emergency department with shortness of breath and chest pain. Physical examination revealed stable vital signs but notable bilateral decreased air entry and diffuse wheezing. A computed tomography angiogram (CTA) of the chest confirmed a small to moderate volume of air embolism within the main pulmonary artery and right ventricle, with no evidence of pulmonary embolism. The air embolism was suspected to have been introduced during a contrast injection for the CT scan, as no other iatrogenic factors, recent invasive procedures, or history of lung trauma were present. Initial management included repositioning the patient to a supine position and administering 100% oxygen, which was critical in stabilizing his condition. Despite the ongoing symptoms of shortness of breath, the patient's condition improved with supportive care focused on managing COPD exacerbation. Spontaneous air embolism without decompression sickness or prior instrumentation is exceptionally rare, particularly in a post-COVID-19 patient, making this case notable. It highlights the critical need for prompt recognition, thorough evaluation, and appropriate management of air embolism in complex medical scenarios to prevent life-threatening complications. This case also underscores the importance of considering iatrogenic causes, such as contrast injection, in the differential diagnosis, especially following recent imaging studies.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Al Yacoub et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Al Yacoub</LastName><ForeName>Raed</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ladna</LastName><ForeName>Michael</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Al-Radideh</LastName><ForeName>Zaid</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, Al-Balqa' Applied University, As-Salt, JOR.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jaber</LastName><ForeName>Johnny F</ForeName><Initials>JF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pulmonary, Critical Care, and Sleep Medicine, University of Florida College of Medicine, Gainesville, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D002363">Case Reports</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">air embolism</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">clinical case report</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">covid – 19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">spontaneous air ambolism</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vascular air embolism</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>17</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>17</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39310544</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11413837</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.67375</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Venous air embolism: a systematic review. Alzghoul H, Obeidat O, Abughazaleh S, et al.  https://www.chestcc.org/article/S2949-7884(24)00003-0/fulltext CHEST Crit Care. 2024;2:100049.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fatal venous air embolism in the setting of hemodialysis and pulmonary hypertension: a point of care ultrasound diagnosis. Alzghoul H, Jin P, Vahdatpour C, Alzghoul BN. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36860648/ Respir Med Case Rep. 2023;42:101819.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9969267</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36860648</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hyperbaric oxygen therapy for massive arterial air embolism during cardiac operations. Ziser A, Adir Y, Lavon H, Shupak A. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/10096979/ J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 1999;117:818–821.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10096979</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pulmonary (venous) air embolism. Durant TM, Long J, Oppenheimer MJ. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/20286347/ Am Heart J. 1947;33:269–281.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20286347</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pulmonary air embolism. Souders JE. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/12580220/ J Clin Monit Comput. 2000;16:375–383.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12580220</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bennett PB, Neuman TS. Philadelphia: Saunders; [ Jan; 2024 ]. 2024. Bennett and Elliott’s Physiology and Medicine of Diving.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Repeated massive pulmonary air embolism during pacemaker implantation. Wu BT, Chen YT. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/23024126/ Interact Cardiovasc Thorac Surg. 2012;15:1085–1087.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3501317</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23024126</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pulmonary air embolism in a patient with COVID-19 with extracorporeal membrane oxygenation support. Tejero-Aranguren J, Riera J, Martínez-Martínez M, et al. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2022;205:1239.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9872794</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35353653</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pulmonary air embolism: an infrequent complication in the radiology suite. Lanfranco J, Romero Legro I, Freire AX, Nearing K, Ratnakant S. Am J Case Rep. 2017;18:80–84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5282968</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28115731</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Intraoperative air embolism originating from a pulmonary vein. Siddiqui M, Sami S, Atiq M, Amanullah MM. World J Pediatr Congenit Heart Surg. 2015;6:304–306.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25870354</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pulmonary air embolism in severe head injury. Kerner T, Fritz G, Unterberg A, Falke KJ. Resuscitation. 2003;56:111–115.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12505747</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Air embolism in CT-guided transthoracic needle biopsy: emphasis on pulmonary vein injury. Ahn Y, Lee SM, Kim HJ, Choe J, Oh SY, Do KH, Seo JB. Eur Radiol. 2022;32:6800–6811.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36006429</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venous air embolism activates complement C3 without corresponding C5 activation and trigger thromboinflammation in pigs. Storm BS, Ludviksen JK, Christiansen D, et al. Front Immunol. 2022;13:839632.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8964959</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35371063</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flow field around bubbles on formation of air embolism in small vessels. Li Z, Li G, Li Y, Chen Y, Li J, Chen H. https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8255810/ Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2021;118:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8255810</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34155104</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diagnosis and treatment of vascular air embolism. Mirski MA, Lele AV, Fitzsimmons L, Toung TJ. Anesthesiology. 2007;106:164–177.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17197859</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iatrogenic air embolism: pathoanatomy, thromboinflammation, endotheliopathy, and therapies. Marsh PL, Moore EE, Moore HB, et al. Front Immunol. 2023;14:1230049.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10546929</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37795086</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gas embolism. Muth CM, Shank ES. N Engl J Med. 2000;342:476–482.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10675429</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Postoperative management of cerebral air embolism: gas physiology for surgeons. Tovar EA, Del Campo C, Borsari A, Webb RP, Dell JR, Weinstein PB. Ann Thorac Surg. 1995;60:1138–1142.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7574975</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Effects of hyperbaric oxygen on intracranial pressure and cerebral blood flow in experimental cerebral oedema. Miller JD, Ledingham IM, Jennett WB. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry. 1970;33:745–755.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC493587</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">5497875</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cerebral arterial gas embolism following diagnostic bronchoscopy: delayed treatment with hyperbaric oxygen. Wherrett CG, Mehran RJ, Beaulieu MA. Can J Anaesth. 2002;49:96–99.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11782337</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haemoconcentration in neurological decompression illness. Boussuges A, Blanc P, Molenat F, Bergmann E, Sainty JM. Int J Sports Med. 1996;17:351–355.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8858406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Increased damage after ischemic stroke in patients with hyperglycemia with or without established diabetes mellitus. Pulsinelli WA, Levy DE, Sigsbee B, Scherer P, Plum F. Am J Med. 1983;74:540–544.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6837584</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spontaneous cerebral air embolism-an unusual scenario. Bansal R, Bhuyan S, Gupta R, Garg A, Bansal AR. Neurol India. 2023;71:772–774.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37635514</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>