<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39311626</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-9071</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>96</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Analyzing infections caused by 11 respiratory pathogens in children: Pre- and post-COVID-19 pandemic trends in China.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e29929</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e29929</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jmv.29929</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>With the lifting of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) restrictions in December 2022 in China, the population was widely infected with COVID-19. We aim to analyzed changes in the epidemiological characteristics of other respiratory pathogens in children before and after the COVID-19 pandemic. We conducted a retrospective analysis of 44 704 children with acute respiratory infections who underwent 11 respiratory pathogen tests based on multiplex polymerase chain reaction between February and December in both 2022 and 2023. The total pathogen detection rate (24861, 74.80% vs. 6423, 56.01%; p = 0.000) and detection rates of coinfection (4059, 12.21% vs. 676, 5.89%; p = 0.000) in 2023 was significantly higher than that in 2022. The detection rates of influenza A (2567, 7.72% vs. 222, 1.94%; p = 0.000), influenza B (383, 1.15% vs. 37, 0.32%; p = 0.000), human parainfluenza virus (2175, 6.54% vs. 602, 5.25%; p = 0.000), human metapneumovirus (1354, 4.07% vs. 346, 3.01%; p = 0.000), respiratory syncytial virus (3148, 9.47% vs. 870, 7.59%; p = 0.000), and Mycoplasma pneumonia (MP; 9494, 28.56% vs. 1790, 15.61%; p = 0.000) in 2023 were significantly higher than those in 2022, whereas the detection rates of human adenovirus (1124, 3.38% vs. 489, 4.26%; p = 0.000) and human bocavirus (629, 1.89% vs. 375, 3.27%; p = 0.000) were significantly lower than those in 2022. Chlamydia, human rhinovirus, and human coronavirus showed similar detection rates between 2023 and 2022. In 2023, the influenza virus and human parainfluenza virus regained seasonal characteristic, an outbreak of MP infection occurred, the epidemic season of respiratory syncytial virus changed, and the proportion of children with acute respiratory infection aged 0-28 days and over 3 years old increased. Influenza B, metapneumovirus, and human bocavirus were detected in children aged 0-28 days in 2023, but not in 2022. After the COVID-19 pandemic, we should be alert to the increase of respiratory diseases and the change of epidemic season and susceptible age.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Huamei</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Laboratory, Children's Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine, National Clinical Research Center For Child Health, Hangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Ying</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2294-7249</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Diseases, Children's Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine, National Clinical Research Center For Child Health, Hangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tao</LastName><ForeName>Ran</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Laboratory, Children's Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine, National Clinical Research Center For Child Health, Hangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shang</LastName><ForeName>Shiqiang</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5389-6750</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Laboratory, Children's Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine, National Clinical Research Center For Child Health, Hangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>LY21H040002</GrantID><Agency>Zhejiang Provincial Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7705876</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0146-6615</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002681" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">China</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012189" MajorTopicYN="N">Retrospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002675" MajorTopicYN="N">Child, Preschool</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012141" MajorTopicYN="Y">Respiratory Tract Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D060085" MajorTopicYN="Y">Coinfection</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007223" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="N">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000293" MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescent</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007231" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant, Newborn</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007251" MajorTopicYN="N">Influenza, Human</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D060885" MajorTopicYN="N">Multiplex Polymerase Chain Reaction</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">acute respiratory tract infections</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">children</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">respiratory pathogens</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>49</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39311626</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.29929</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Vos T, Lim SS, Abbafati C, et al., GBD 2019 Diseases and Injuries Collaborators. Global burden of 369 diseases and injuries in 204 countries and territories, 1990–2019: a systematic analysis for the global burden of disease study 2019. Lancet. 2020;396(10258):1204‐1222.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu L, Oza S, Hogan D, et al. Global, regional, and national causes of under‐5 mortality in 2000‐15: an updated systematic analysis with implications for the sustainable development goals. Lancet. 2016;388(10063):3027‐3035.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silver SA, Beaubien‐Souligny W, Shah PS, et al. The prevalence of acute kidney injury in patients hospitalized with COVID‐19 infection: a systematic review and meta‐analysis. Kidney Med. 2021;3(1):83‐98.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mutiawati E, Syahrul S, Fahriani M, et al. Global prevalence and pathogenesis of headache in COVID‐19: a systematic review and meta‐analysis. F1000Research. 2020;9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roh EJ, Lee MH, Lee JY, et al. Analysis of national surveillance of respiratory pathogens for community‐acquired pneumonia in children and adolescents. BMC Infect Dis. 2022;22(1):330.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li X, Li T, Chen N, Kang P, Yang J. Changes of Mycoplasma pneumoniae prevalence in children before and after COVID‐19 pandemic in Jenan, China. J Infect. 2023;86(3):256‐308.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu D, Chen Z, Zhu G. Change of epidemiological characteristics of four respiratory viral infections in children before and during COVID‐19 pandemic. Infectious Dis Now. 2024;54(3):104858.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan CM, Wahab AA, Ali A. Assessing the impact of COVID‐19 on epidemiological changes of severe pediatric respiratory syncytial virus infections in Malaysia. Front Public Health. 2024;12:1246921.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang L, Davis PB, Berger NA, Kaelber DC, Volkow ND, Xu R. Disrupted seasonality and association of COVID‐19 with medically attended respiratory syncytial virus infections among young children in the US: January 2010‐January 2023. medRxiv [Preprint]. 2023:2023.05.12.23289898.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei M, Li S, Lu X, Hu K, Li Z, Li M. Changing respiratory pathogens infection patterns after COVID‐19 pandemic in Shanghai, China. J Med Virol. 2024;96(4):e29616.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lei C, Yang L, Lou CT, et al. Viral etiology and epidemiology of pediatric patients hospitalized for acute respiratory tract infections in Macao: a retrospective study from 2014 to 2017. BMC Infect Dis. 2021;21(1):306.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li ZJ, Zhang HY, Ren LL, et al. Etiological and epidemiological features of acute respiratory infections in China. Nat Commun. 2021;12(1):5026.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grunberg M, Sno R, Adhin MR. Epidemiology of respiratory viruses in patients with severe acute respiratory infections and influenza‐like illness in Suriname. Influenza Other Respir Viruses. 2021;15(1):72‐80.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stein RT, Zar HJ. RSV through the COVID‐19 pandemic: burden, shifting epidemiology, and implications for the future. Pediatr Pulmonol. 2023;58:1631‐1639.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daniels D, Wang D, Suryadevara M, et al. Epidemiology of RSV bronchiolitis among young children in central New York before and after the onset of the COVID‐19 pandemic. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2023;42:1056‐1062.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rao S, Armistead I, Messacar K, et al. Shifting epidemiology and severity of respiratory syncytial virus in children during the COVID‐19 pandemic. JAMA Pediatr. 2023;177:730‐732.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Methi F, Størdal K, Telle K, Larsen VB, Magnusson K. Hospital admissions for respiratory tract infections in children aged 0‐5 years for 2017/2023. Front Pediatr. 2022;9:822985.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hatter L, Eathorne A, Hills T, Bruce P, Beasley R. Respiratory syncytial virus: paying the immunity debt with interest. Lancet Child Adolesc Health. 2021;5(12):e44‐e45.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glynne P, Tahmasebi N, Gant V, Gupta R. Long COVID following mild SARS‐CoV‐2 infection: characteristic T cell alterations and response to antihistamines. J Investig Med. 2022;70(1):61‐67.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubin R. From “immunity debt” to “immunity Theft”‐How COVID‐19 might be tied to recent respiratory disease surges. JAMA. 2024;331(5):378‐381.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Opsteen S, Files JK, Fram T, Erdmann N. The role of immune activation and antigen persistence in acute and long COVID. J Investig Med. 2023;71(5):545‐562.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phetsouphanh C, Darley DR, Wilson DB, et al. Immunological dysfunction persists for 8 months following initial mild‐to‐moderate SARS‐CoV‐2 infection. Nature Immunol. 2022;23(2):210‐216.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheong JG, Ravishankar A, Sharma S, et al. Epigenetic memory of coronavirus infection in innate immune cells and their progenitors. Cell. 2023;186(18):3882‐3902.e24.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nenna R, Pierangeli A, Matera L, et al. Respiratory syncytial virus bronchiolitis before and after COVID‐19 pandemic: has the immunity debt been paid off? Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2024;43(7):635‐639.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pierangeli A, Nenna R, Fracella M, et al. Genetic diversity and its impact on disease severity in respiratory syncytial virus subtype‐A and ‐B bronchiolitis before and after pandemic restrictions in Rome. J Infect. 2023;87:305‐314.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Midulla F, Nenna R, Scagnolari C, et al. How respiratory syncytial virus genotypes influence the clinical course in infants hospitalized for bronchiolitis. J Infect Dis. 2019;219:526‐534.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Firquet S, Beaujard S, Lobert PE, et al. Survival of enveloped and non‐enveloped viruses on inanimate surfaces. Microbes Environ. 2015;30(2):140‐144.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Principi N, Autore G, Ramundo G, Esposito S. Epidemiology of respiratory infections during the COVID‐19 pandemic. Viruses. 2023;15(5):1160.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen AP, Chu IY, Yeh ML, et al. Differentiating impacts of nonpharmaceutical interventions on non‐coronavirus disease‐2019 respiratory viral infections: hospital‐based retrospective observational study in Taiwan. Influ Other Respir Viruses. 2021;15:478‐487.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fahim M., Abu ElSood H., AbdElGawad B., et al. Adapting an integrated acute respiratory infections sentinel surveillance to the COVID‐19 pandemic requirements, Egypt, 2020–2022. Public Health Pract. 2023;5:100358.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan CM, Wahab AA, Ali A. Determining the relationship of meteorological factors and severe pediatric respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) infection in central peninsular Malaysia. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2023;20(3):1848.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ujiie M, Tsuzuki S, Nakamoto T, Iwamoto N. Resurgence of respiratory syncytial virus infections during COVID‐19 pandemic, Tokyo, Japan. Emerging Infect Dis. 2021;27(11):2969‐2970.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee CY, Wu TH, Fang YP, et al. Delayed respiratory syncytial virus outbreak in 2020 in Taiwan was correlated with two novel RSV‐A genotype ON1 variants. Influenza Other Respir Viruse. 2022;16(3):511‐520.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishimura N, Nishio H., Lee M.J., Uemura K. The clinical features of respiratory syncytial virus: lower respiratory tract infection after upper respiratory tract infection due to influenza virus. Pediatr Int. 2005;47(4):412‐416.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kurkela S, Puolakkainen M, Hokynar K, et al. Mycoplasma pneumoniae outbreak, Southeastern Finland, 2017‐2018: molecular epidemiology and laboratory diagnostic lessons. Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis. 2019; 38(10):1867‐1871.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee KL, Lee CM, Yang TL, et al. Severe Mycoplasma pneumoniae pneumonia requiring intensive care in children, 2010‐2019. J Formos Med Assoc. 2021;120(1 Pt 1):281‐291.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cai F, Shou X, Ye Q. Epidemiological study on Mycoplasma pneumoniae and Chlamydia pneumoniae infection of hospitalized children in a single center during the COVID‐19 pandemic. Front Cell Infect Microbiol. 2022;12:843463.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>