<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39310442</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>8</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Sending a Signal: Evaluating the Impact of Program and Geographic Preference Signaling on the Internal Medicine Residency Match.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e67379</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e67379</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e67379</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.67379</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Background For over a decade, the number of residency applications has surged, a trend known as "application inflation." COVID-19 further intensified this trend, leading the Association of American Medical Colleges (AAMC) to address the issue by introducing a supplemental application in the 2021-2022 cycle, allowing programs to identify applicants with a connection to their program or geographic region. For the 2022-2023 cycle, the number of program signals increased from five to seven. The impact of the supplemental application and the increase in signals on the likelihood of an applicant matching with a program has yet to be evaluated. Methods This retrospective cohort study evaluated the impact of program signaling and geographic preference on the matching likelihood in our internal medicine residency program. Data from MyERAS® and the Supplemental Application for 640 applicants who applied to our large, urban, university-based program in the Southeastern United States during the 2020-2021 and 2022-2023 application cycles were included. Using univariate and multivariate analysis, we examined the correlation between program signal, geographic preference, and final match location. Results Applicants who sent a program signal had nearly three-fold higher odds of matching with our program. Geographic preference was numerically but not statistically associated with higher odds of matching. Both signaling a preference for matching with a program in an urban environment and couples matching correlated with decreased odds of matching with our program. Geography was an important predictor of match location as residing in our AAMC geographic region, our four-state area, and our specific state had increased odds of matching with our program. Conclusions Signaling our program was associated with increased odds of matching with our program. Geographic preferences were less predictive of a match with our program; however, they did predict the likelihood of a match at a program within that region. Future studies are needed to ensure external validity.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Norton et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Norton</LastName><ForeName>Dustin L</ForeName><Initials>DL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, Wake Forest University School of Medicine, Winston-Salem, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Richardson</LastName><ForeName>Karl M</ForeName><Initials>KM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cardiology, Wake Forest University School of Medicine, Winston-Salem, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lippert</LastName><ForeName>William C</ForeName><Initials>WC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, Wake Forest University School of Medicine, Winston-Salem, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Valente</LastName><ForeName>Jessica</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, Wake Forest University School of Medicine, Winston-Salem, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Williams</LastName><ForeName>Donna M</ForeName><Initials>DM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, Wake Forest University School of Medicine, Winston-Salem, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">application inflation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">electronic residency application services (eras)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">geographic preference</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">holistic review residency application</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">internal medicine residency</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">national residency match program (nrmp) match</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">residency match</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">supplemental application</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Wake Forest University Health Sciences Institutional Review Board issued approval IRB00096304. Animal subjects: All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>49</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>48</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39310442</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11415154</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.67379</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Application inflation for internal medicine applicants in the match: drivers, consequences, and potential solutions. Pereira AG, Chelminski PR, Chheda SG, et al. Am J Med. 2016;129:885–891.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27154785</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Average length of rank order list by match status: 2003-2022 Main Residency Match.  [
Aug;
2022 
];https://www.nrmp.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/Average-Length-of-ROL-by-Match-Status.pdf 2022 24:2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 increased residency applications and how virtual interviews impacted applicants. Meyer AM, Hart AA, Keith JN. Cureus. 2022;14:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9298600</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35875277</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trends in US internal medicine residency and fellowship applications during the COVID-19 pandemic vs previous years. Huppert LA, Santhosh L, Babik JM. JAMA Netw Open. 2021;4:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8082322</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33909057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drivers of application inflation: a national survey of internal medicine residents. Angus SV, Williams CM, Kwan B, Vu TR, Harris L, Muntz M, Pereira A. Am J Med. 2018;131:447–452.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29355512</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Application fever: Reviewing the causes, costs, and cures for residency application inflation. Carmody JB, Rosman IS, Carlson JC. Cureus. 2021;13:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8034763</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33850672</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A computer simulation model to analyze the application process for competitive residency programs. Whipple ME, Law AB, Bly RA. J Grad Med Educ. 2019;11:30–35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6375320</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30805093</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evaluating the impact of the novel geographic preferences section on interview rate and residency match outcomes. Benjamin WJ, Lenze NR, Bohm LA, et al. J Gen Intern Med. 2024;39:359–365.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10897073</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37528251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Association of American Medical Colleges. Supplemental application data and reports.  [
Aug;
2022 
]. 2022. https://www.aamc.org/data-reports/students-residents/report/supplemental-eras-application-data-and-reports https://www.aamc.org/data-reports/students-residents/report/supplemental-eras-application-data-and-reports</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Impact of applicants’ characteristics and geographic connections to residency programs on preference signaling outcomes in the match. Benjamin WJ, Lenze NR, Bohm LA, et al. Acad Med. 2024;99:437–444.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37976398</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Outcomes of the internal medicine supplemental application: preliminary data on the 2022-2023 match. Szumel ES, Dockery HO, Alexander SM, et al. Cureus. 2024;16:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10866185</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38357052</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>