<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39318885</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1564-0604</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>102</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Bulletin of the World Health Organization</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Bull World Health Organ</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Adaptation of WHO COVID-19 guidelines by Caribbean countries and territories.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>699</StartPage><EndPage>706</EndPage><MedlinePgn>699-706</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.2471/BLT.23.290796</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The normative role of the World Health Organization (WHO) involves creating evidence-based, principled guidelines to guide its Member States in making well-informed public health decisions. While these guidelines often need to be adapted to ensure contextual relevance, foster better implementation and adherence, adapting existing guidelines is more efficient than creating new ones. Here we describe the adaptation of the WHO coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) living guideline on pharmacological interventions for the Caribbean using the grading of recommendations, assessment, development and evaluation (GRADE)-ADOLOPMENT method. The Caribbean Public Health Agency and the Pan American Health Organization led the effort, assembling a diverse panel of 16 experts from seven Caribbean countries and territories. The adaptation process, involving 15 steps, was guided by an experienced methodologist and included selecting relevant clinical questions and prioritizing them based on regional needs. The panel evaluated the latest WHO guidelines and integrated additional local data. They adjusted the direction and strength of several recommendations to better fit the Caribbean context, considering local values and preferences, resources, accessibility, feasibility and impact on health equity. Ultimately, we changed the direction of two recommendations and the strength of five, tailoring them to regional realities. This effort highlights the importance of adapting global guidelines to local settings, improving their applicability and effectiveness. The adaptation process also serves as a valuable opportunity for skill transfer and capacity-building in guideline development. Continued research is needed to assess the impact of these adaptations on health-care outcomes in the Caribbean.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2024 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Evans-Gilbert</LastName><ForeName>Tracy</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of the West Indies, Mona, Kingston, Jamaica.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Blades</LastName><ForeName>Edmund</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Queen Elizabeth Hospital, Bridgetown, Barbados.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Boodoosingh</LastName><ForeName>Ronela</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>South-West Regional Health Authority, San Fernando, Trinidad and Tobago.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Campbell</LastName><ForeName>Michael H</ForeName><Initials>MH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Queen Elizabeth Hospital, Bridgetown, Barbados.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Christie</LastName><ForeName>Celia Dc</ForeName><Initials>CD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of the West Indies, Mona, Kingston, Jamaica.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Manzanero</LastName><ForeName>Marvin</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Belmopan, Belize.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mullings-George</LastName><ForeName>Janice</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Ministry of Health, Hamilton, Bermuda.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ottley</LastName><ForeName>Earl</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>North-Central Regional Health Authority, Chaguanas, Trinidad and Tobago.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Outerbridge</LastName><ForeName>Cil-Maria</ForeName><Initials>CM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bermuda Hospitals Board, King Edward VII Memorial Hospital, Hamilton, Bermuda.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sobers</LastName><ForeName>Natasha P</ForeName><Initials>NP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of the West Indies, Cave Hill, Barbados.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Davidson</LastName><ForeName>Tamu</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Caribbean Public Health Agency, Port of Spain, Trinidad and Tobago.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Extavour</LastName><ForeName>Rian M</ForeName><Initials>RM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Caribbean Public Health Agency, Port of Spain, Trinidad and Tobago.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>St John</LastName><ForeName>Joy</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Caribbean Public Health Agency, Port of Spain, Trinidad and Tobago.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Reveiz</LastName><ForeName>Ludovic</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pan American Health Organization, WashingtonDC, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sagastuy</LastName><ForeName>Begona</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pan American Health Organization, WashingtonDC, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Neumann</LastName><ForeName>Ignacio</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Medicine, Universidad San Sebastian, Lota 2465, Providencia, Santiago7510157, Chile.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Bull World Health Organ</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7507052</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0042-9686</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014944" MajorTopicYN="Y">World Health Organization</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017691" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Caribbean Region</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="Y">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017410" MajorTopicYN="Y">Practice Guidelines as Topic</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000093485" MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19 Drug Treatment</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="fre"><AbstractText>Le rôle normatif de l’Organisation mondiale de la santé (OMS) consiste à élaborer des lignes directrices fondées sur des données scientifiques et sur des principes afin d’aider ses États membres à prendre des décisions éclairées en matière de santé publique. Bien qu’elles nécessitent souvent des adaptations pour garantir leur pertinence par rapport à des contextes précis et pour favoriser une meilleure mise en œuvre et adhésion, il est plus efficace d’adapter les lignes directrices existantes que d’en créer de nouvelles. La présente publication décrit l’adaptation de la ligne directrice évolutive de l’OMS sur les interventions pharmacologiques dans le cadre de la maladie à coronavirus (COVID-19) pour les Caraïbes en appliquant la méthodologie GRADE (classement des recommandations, de l’appréciation, du développement et de l’évaluation)-ADOLOPMENT. L’Agence de santé publique des Caraïbes et l’Organisation panaméricaine de la Santé ont dirigé les travaux en réunissant un groupe diversifié de 16 experts issus de sept pays et territoires des Caraïbes. Le processus d’adaptation, comptant 15 étapes et encadré par un méthodologiste expérimenté, a consisté à sélectionner des questions cliniques pertinentes et à les classer par ordre de priorité selon les besoins régionaux. Ce groupe a évalué les dernières lignes directrices de l’OMS et a intégré des données locales supplémentaires. Il a ensuite ajusté l’orientation et le poids de plusieurs recommandations afin de mieux les adapter au contexte des Caraïbes, en tenant compte des valeurs et des préférences locales, des ressources, de l’accessibilité, de la faisabilité et de l’impact sur l’équité en matière de santé. En fin de compte, l’orientation de deux recommandations et le poids de cinq autres ont été modifiés, en les adaptant aux réalités régionales. Cet effort souligne l’importance d’adapter des lignes directrices mondiales aux contextes locaux, afin d’en améliorer l’applicabilité et l’efficacité. Le processus d’adaptation représente également une occasion précieuse de transfert de compétences et de renforcement des capacités en matière d’élaboration de lignes directrices. Des recherches continues s’imposent pour évaluer l’impact de ces adaptations sur les résultats des soins de santé dans les Caraïbes.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2024 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="spa"><AbstractText>La función normativa de la Organización Mundial de la Salud (OMS) consiste en elaborar directrices basadas en pruebas y principios para orientar a sus Estados Miembros en la toma de decisiones de salud pública bien fundamentadas. Aunque con frecuencia es necesario adaptar estas directrices para garantizar su pertinencia contextual y fomentar una mejor implementación y observancia, la adaptación de directrices existentes es más eficiente que la creación de otras nuevas. Aquí describimos la adaptación de la directriz vigente de la OMS sobre la enfermedad por coronavirus (COVID-19) relativa a las intervenciones farmacológicas para el Caribe utilizando el método de clasificación de valoración, elaboración y evaluación de las recomendaciones (GRADE)-ADOLOPMENT. La Agencia de Salud Pública del Caribe y la Organización Panamericana de la Salud lideraron la iniciativa, que reunió a un variado grupo de 16 expertos de siete países y territorios caribeños. El proceso de adaptación, que comprendió 15 pasos y fue guiado por un metodólogo experimentado, incluyó la selección de preguntas clínicas pertinentes y su priorización en función de las necesidades regionales. El grupo evaluó las últimas directrices de la OMS e integró datos locales adicionales. Ajustaron la orientación y la fuerza de varias recomendaciones para adaptarlas mejor al contexto caribeño, teniendo en cuenta los valores y preferencias locales, los recursos, la accesibilidad, la viabilidad y el impacto en la equidad sanitaria. Finalmente, cambiamos la orientación de dos recomendaciones y la fuerza de cinco para adaptarlas a las realidades regionales. Esta iniciativa destaca la importancia de adaptar las directrices mundiales a los contextos locales, lo que mejora su aplicabilidad y eficacia. El proceso de adaptación también constituye una valiosa oportunidad para la transferencia de conocimientos y el desarrollo de capacidades en la elaboración de directrices. Es necesario seguir investigando para evaluar el impacto de estas adaptaciones en los resultados de la atención sanitaria en el Caribe.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2024 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="ara"><AbstractText>يتضمن الدور المعياري لمنظمة الصحة العالمية (WHO) وضع مبادئ توجيهية أساسية قائمة على الأدلة لتوجيه الدول الأعضاء لديها في ما يتعلق باتخاذ قرارات مستنيرة في مجال الصحة العامة. في حين أن هذه المبادئ التوجيهية تحتاج في كثير من الأحيان إلى التكييف لضمان ملاءمتها للسياق، وتعزيز التنفيذ والالتزام بشكل أفضل، إلا إن تكييف المبادئ التوجيهية القائمة يُعد أكثر فعالية من وضع مبادئ توجيهية جديدة. نحن هنا نصف تكييف المبدأ التوجيهي الحالي لدى منظمة الصحة العالمية لمرض فيروس كورونا (كوفيد 19)، والخاص بالتدخلات الدوائية لمنطقة الكاريبي باستخدام طريقة تصنيف التوصيات، والتقويم، والتطوير، والتقييم (GRADE)-ADOLOPMENT. وقامت كل من هيئة الصحة العامة في منطقة الكاريبي، ومنظمة الصحة للدول الأمريكية، بقيادة هذا الجهد، حيث قامتا بتكوين لجنة متنوعة من 16 خبيرا من سبعة من دول وأقاليم منطقة الكاريبي. وتضمنت عملية التكيف 15 خطوة، وتم توجيهها بواسطة منهجية ذات خبرة، وشملت اختيار الأسئلة الإكلينيكية ذات الصلة وتحديد أولوياتها بناءً على الاحتياجات الإقليمية. وقام الفريق بتقييم أحدث المبادئ التوجيهية لمنظمة الصحة العالمية، ودمج البيانات المحلية الإضافية. وقاموا بتعديل اتجاه وقوة العديد من التوصيات لتتناسب بشكل أفضل مع سياق منطقة الكاريبي، مع الأخذ في الاعتبار القيم والتفضيلات المحلية، والموارد، وإمكانية الوصول، والجدوى، والتأثير على المساواة الصحية. وفي النهاية، قمنا بتغيير اتجاه توصيتين وقوة خمس توصيات، حيث قمنا بتخصيصها وفقًا لحالات الواقع الإقليمي. يسلط هذا الجهد الضوء على أهمية تكييف المبادئ التوجيهية العالمية مع الأوضاع المحلية، وتحسين قابلية تطبيقها وفعاليتها. تعد عملية التكيف أيضًا بمثابة فرصة ذات قيمة لنقل المهارات وبناء القدرات في وضع المبادئ التوجيهية. هناك حاجة إلى مواصلة الأبحاث لتقييم تأثير هذه التعديلات على نتائج الرعاية الصحية في منطقة الكاريبي.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2024 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="chi"><AbstractText>世界卫生组织 (WHO) 的规范性作用包括创建有据可依的原则性指南,以指导其成员国在充分了解相关信息的基础上制定公共卫生决策。虽然通常需要调整这些指南来确保符合当地情况,从而有利于更顺利地实施方针和提高遵从性,但是调整现有指南比创建新指南的效率还是更高。在本文中,我们描述了如何使用推荐分级的评估、制定与评价 (GRADE) 工作组开发的 ADOLOPMENT 方法根据加勒比地区的情况对世界卫生组织的冠状病毒病(新冠肺炎)药物干预相关生活指南进行调整。加勒比公共卫生署和泛美卫生组织领导实施该项工作,并从七个加勒比国家和地区邀请了 16 名专家以组建多元化小组。调整过程共分为 15 个步骤,由一位经验丰富的方法学家指导实施,包括选择相关临床问题,并根据区域需求对其进行优先排序。该小组评估了世界卫生组织的最新指南,并综合考虑了其他地方数据。考虑到当地的价值观和偏好、资源、可及性、可行性以及对卫生公平性的影响,该小组调整了几项建议的实施方向和力度,以确保更加符合加勒比地区的情况。最终,我们修改了两项建议的实施方向和五项建议的实施力度,以确保其符合区域实际情况。该项工作突出了根据当地情况调整全球指南、提高其适用性和有效性的重要性。调整过程也是在指南制定过程中实现技能转让和能力建设的宝贵机会。需要继续进行研究,以评估这些调整对加勒比地区医疗保健结果的影响。.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2024 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="rus"><AbstractText>Нормативная функция Всемирной организации здравоохранения (ВОЗ) заключается в разработке основанных на фактических данных принципов, которыми должны руководствоваться государства-члены ВОЗ при принятии обоснованных решений в области общественного здравоохранения. Несмотря на то что эти руководящие принципы часто требуют адаптации для обеспечения их соответствия контексту, более эффективного внедрения и соблюдения, адаптация существующих руководящих принципов является более эффективной по сравнению с созданием новых. В данной статье приведено описание адаптации руководящего принципа ВОЗ по фармакологическим вмешательствам при коронавирусной болезни (COVID-19) для стран Карибского бассейна с использованием метода градации рекомендаций, анализа, развития и оценки (GRADE)-ADOLOPMENT. Карибское агентство общественного здравоохранения и Панамериканская организация здравоохранения возглавили эту работу, собрав разнообразную группу из 16 экспертов из семи стран и территорий Карибского бассейна. Процесс адаптации, состоящий из 15 этапов и проводимый под руководством опытного методиста, включал отбор актуальных клинических вопросов и определение их приоритетности с учетом региональных потребностей. Группа экспертов оценила последние рекомендации ВОЗ и включила дополнительные местные данные. Специалисты скорректировали направление и силу некоторых рекомендаций для более полного соответствия условиям Карибского бассейна, учитывая местные ценности и предпочтения, ресурсы, доступность, осуществимость и влияние на справедливость в сфере здравоохранения. В итоге с учетом региональных реалий были изменены направления двух и степень важности пяти рекомендаций. Эти усилия подчеркивают важность адаптации глобальных руководящих принципов к местным условиям, что повышает их применимость и эффективность. Процесс адаптации также представляет собой ценную возможность для передачи навыков и наращивания потенциала в области разработки рекомендаций. Для оценки влияния таких адаптаций на результаты медицинского обслуживания в странах Карибского бассейна необходимо проведение дальнейших исследований.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2024 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39318885</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11418840</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2471/BLT.23.290796</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">BLT.23.290796</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Schwalb A, Armyra E, Méndez-Aranda M, Ugarte-Gil C. COVID-19 in Latin America and the Caribbean: Two years of the pandemic. J Intern Med. 2022. Sep;292(3):409–27. 10.1111/joim.13499</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/joim.13499</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9115176</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35411985</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agarwal A, Hunt B, Stegemann M, Rochwerg B, Lamontagne F, Siemieniuk RA, et al. A living WHO guideline on drugs for COVID-19. BMJ. 2020. Sep 4;370:m3379. 10.1136/bmj.m3379</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.m3379</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32887691</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neumann I, Izcovich A, Alexander KE, Castano J, Plovnick R, Kunkle R, et al. Methodology for adaptation of the ASH Guidelines for management of venous thromboembolism for the Latin American context. Blood Adv. 2021. Aug 10;5(15):3047–52. 10.1182/bloodadvances.2021004268</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1182/bloodadvances.2021004268</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8361463</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34374749</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harrison MB, Légaré F, Graham ID, Fervers B. Adapting clinical practice guidelines to local context and assessing barriers to their use. CMAJ. 2010. Feb 9;182(2):E78–84. 10.1503/cmaj.081232</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1503/cmaj.081232</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2817341</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19969563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor L. Covid-19: lagging vaccination leaves the Caribbean vulnerable, says PAHO. BMJ. 2022. Feb 28;376:o519. 10.1136/bmj.o519</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.o519</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35228259</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schünemann HJ, Wiercioch W, Brozek J, Etxeandia-Ikobaltzeta I, Mustafa RA, Manja V, et al. GRADE evidence to decision (EtD) frameworks for adoption, adaptation, and de novo development of trustworthy recommendations: GRADE-ADOLOPMENT. J Clin Epidemiol. 2017. Jan;81:101–10. 10.1016/j.jclinepi.2016.09.009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2016.09.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27713072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Graham R, Mancher M, Miller Wolman D, Greenfield S, Steinberg E, editors. Clinical practice guidelines we can trust. Washington, DC: National Academies Press; 2011. 10.17226/13058</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.17226/13058</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24983061</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qaseem A, Forland F, Macbeth F, Ollenschläger G, Phillips S, van der Wees P; Board of Trustees of the Guidelines International Network. Guidelines International Network: toward international standards for clinical practice guidelines. Ann Intern Med. 2012. Apr 3;156(7):525–31. 10.7326/0003-4819-156-7-201204030-00009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-156-7-201204030-00009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22473437</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strengthening countries’ capacities to adopt and adapt evidence-based guidelines: a handbook for guideline contextualization. Copenhagen: World Health Organization Regional Office for Europe; 2023. Available from: https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/372275 [cited 2024 Apr 23].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alonso-Coello P, Schünemann HJ, Moberg J, Brignardello-Petersen R, Akl EA, Davoli M, et al. GRADE Working Group. GRADE evidence-to-decision (EtD) frameworks: a systematic and transparent approach to making well informed healthcare choices. 1: introduction. BMJ. 2016. Jun 28;353:i2016. 10.1136/bmj.i2016</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.i2016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27353417</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>CARPHA Member States [internet] Port of Spain, Caribbean Public Health Agency, 2024. Available from: https://carpha.org/Who-We-Are/Member-States [cited 2024 Sep 19].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neumann I, Izcovich A, Aguilar R, Basantes GL, Casais P, Colorio CC, et al. ASH, ABHH, ACHO, Grupo CAHT, Grupo CLAHT, SAH, SBHH, SHU, SOCHIHEM, SOMETH, Sociedad Panameña de Hematología, SPH, and SVH 2021 guidelines for management of venous thromboembolism in Latin America. Blood Adv. 2021. Aug 10;5(15):3032–46. 10.1182/bloodadvances.2021004267</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1182/bloodadvances.2021004267</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8361455</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34374748</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neumann I, Izcovich A, Aguilar R, Basantes GL, Casais P, Colorio CC, et al. American Society of Hematology, ABHH, ACHO, Grupo CAHT, Grupo CLAHT, SAH, SBHH, SHU, SOCHIHEM, SOMETH, Sociedad Panameña de Hematología, Sociedad Peruana de Hematología, and SVH 2022 guidelines for prevention of venous thromboembolism in surgical and medical patients and long-distance travelers in Latin America. Blood Adv. 2022. Jun 28;6(12):3636–49. 10.1182/bloodadvances.2021006482</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1182/bloodadvances.2021006482</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9631558</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35195676</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neumann I, Izcovich A, Aguilar R, Basantes GL, Casais P, Colorio CC, et al. American Society of Hematology, ABHH, ACHO, Grupo CAHT, Grupo CLAHT, SAH, SBHH, SHU, SOCHIHEM, SOMETH, Sociedad Panameña de Hematología, Sociedad Peruana de Hematología, and SVH 2023 guidelines for diagnosis of venous thromboembolism and for its management in special populations in Latin America. Blood Adv. 2023. Jul 11;7(13):3005–21. 10.1182/bloodadvances.2021006534</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1182/bloodadvances.2021006534</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10320207</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36929813</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morgano GP, Mbuagbaw L, Santesso N, Xie F, Brozek JL, Siebert U, et al. Defining decision thresholds for judgments on health benefits and harms using the grading of recommendations assessment, development and evaluation (GRADE) evidence-to-decision (EtD) frameworks: a protocol for a randomised methodological study (GRADE-THRESHOLD). BMJ Open. 2022. Mar 10;12(3):e053246. 10.1136/bmjopen-2021-053246</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2021-053246</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8915269</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35273045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neumann I, Quiñelen E, Nahuelhual P, Burdiles P, Celedón N, Cerda K, et al. Using explicit thresholds were valuable for judging benefits and harms in partially contextualized GRADE guidelines. J Clin Epidemiol. 2022. Jul;147:69–75. 10.1016/j.jclinepi.2022.03.017</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2022.03.017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8963975</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35364230</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schünemann HJ, Neumann I, Hultcrantz M, Brignardello-Petersen R, Zeng L, Murad MH, et al. GRADE Working Group. GRADE guidance 35: update on rating imprecision for assessing contextualized certainty of evidence and making decisions. J Clin Epidemiol. 2022. Oct;150:225–42. 10.1016/j.jclinepi.2022.07.015</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2022.07.015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35934266</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lotfi T, Stevens A, Akl EA, Falavigna M, Kredo T, Mathew JL, et al. eCOVID Collaborators. Getting trustworthy guidelines into the hands of decision-makers and supporting their consideration of contextual factors for implementation globally: recommendation mapping of COVID-19 guidelines. J Clin Epidemiol. 2021. Jul;135:182–6. 10.1016/j.jclinepi.2021.03.034</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2021.03.034</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8022513</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33836255</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID19 recommendations [database]. Available from: https://covid19.recmap.org/guideline/p_l_dinasami5071_hotmail_com_0_79b7c2ac-e3f5-451d-b4e6-171d1d24bd26-$-e5af70ed4d3a536f5bbde1e3152b323c2338ee02 [cited 2024 Apr 23]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evans-Gilbert T, Ackie A, Blades E, Boodoosingh R, Campbell MH, Christie CDC, et al. Adaptation of WHO COVID-19 guidelines to the Caribbean context using the GRADE-ADOLOPMENT method. Complete list of recommendations for the Caribbean and a summary infographic. Supplementary file [online repository]. Meyrin: Zenodo; 2024. 10.5281/zenodo.11066343</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5281/zenodo.11066343</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strengthening national evidence-informed guideline programs. A tool for adapting and implementing guidelines in the Americas. Washington, DC: World Health Organization Regional Office for the Americas; 2018. Available from: https://iris.paho.org/handle/10665.2/49145 [cited 2024 Apr 18].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Handbook for adapting and implementing evidence-informed guidelines. Second Edition 2023. Washington, DC: World Health Organization Regional Office for the Americas; 2023. Available from: https://iris.paho.org/handle/10665.2/58021 [cited 2024 Apr 23].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torres M, Ragusa M, Abdala V, Brocard E, Schunemann H, Garcia-Saiso S, et al. BIGG, the international database of GRADE guidelines. Lancet Reg Health Am. 2022. Feb;6:100099. 10.1016/j.lana.2021.100099</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lana.2021.100099</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8863112</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35233554</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO handbook for guideline development. 2nd ed. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2014. Available from: https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/145714 [cited 2024 Apr 23].</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>