<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39318929</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>8</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Real-World Experience With Janus Kinase Inhibitors in Immune-Mediated Diseases: Clinical Experience of a University Hospital.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e67729</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e67729</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e67729</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.67729</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Several Janus kinase (JAK) inhibitors have been developed in recent years. These agents are widely applicable in clinical practice as an alternative treatment for immune-mediated diseases. While the safety and efficacy profile of these drugs has been evaluated in several randomized clinical trials and studies, very few authors have assessed safety and effectiveness under the real-world conditions of daily clinical practice.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">This study aims to describe the effectiveness and safety of JAK inhibitors in daily clinical practice for the treatment of immune-mediated rheumatic diseases in a university hospital.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">We performed a single-center observational, descriptive, retrospective study of all patients with rheumatoid arthritis (RA), spondyloarthritis (SpA), and psoriatic arthritis (PsA) receiving active treatment with JAK inhibitors between March 2022 and February 2023. We recorded study variables from the clinical history for subsequent analysis using STATA 12.0 (StataCorp LLC, College Station, TX). A 95% confidence interval was applied.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The final analysis was performed on 64 patients (upadacitinib: 27, baricitinib: 16, tofacitinib: 13, filgotinib: eight), with a mean age of 55.69±10.78 years (60.94% females). The distribution by disease was as follows: RA, 44 (70.31%); SpA, 11 (17.18%); and PsA, eight (12.5%). A significant improvement was observed in all groups at six to 12 months, as follows: RA, remission in 48.89% and low activity in 26.67%; SpA, remission in 9.09% and low activity in 54.54%; and PsA, low activity in 87.5%. The factors most associated with poor response to treatment were activity before initiation of treatment and previous failure of biological disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs (bDMARDs). Adverse effects and complications were detected in 26.56% (SARS-CoV-2, one case; basal cell carcinoma, one case; and herpes zoster, two cases). There were no reports of cardiovascular or thromboembolic events, opportunistic infection, or tuberculosis.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Our real-world data show that treatment with JAK inhibitors leads to a high rate of remission/low activity that remains unchanged at six to 12 months in RA, SpA, and PsA. The predictors of a poor response to JAK inhibitors in our study population were the level of activity before initiation of treatment and previous failure of bDMARDs. No cardiovascular or thromboembolic events were reported. Of note, we did record one case of severe infection, one case of basal cell carcinoma, and two cases of herpes zoster.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Ramirez Huaranga et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ramirez Huaranga</LastName><ForeName>Marco Aurelio</ForeName><Initials>MA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Rheumatology, Hospital General Universitario de Ciudad Real, Ciudad Real, ESP.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Calvo Pascual</LastName><ForeName>Luis Angel</ForeName><Initials>LA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Quantitative Methods, Instituto Católico de Administración y Dirección de Empresas (ICADE), Comillas Pontifical University, Madrid, ESP.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Velasco Sanchez</LastName><ForeName>David</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Rheumatology, Hospital General Universitario de Ciudad Real, Ciudad Real, ESP.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Martin de la Sierra Lopez</LastName><ForeName>Lourdes</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Rheumatology, Hospital General Universitario de Ciudad Real, Ciudad Real, ESP.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jimenez Rodriguez</LastName><ForeName>Laura</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Rheumatology, Hospital General Universitario de Ciudad Real, Ciudad Real, ESP.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lopez Menchero Mora</LastName><ForeName>Alberto</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Rheumatology, Hospital General Universitario de Ciudad Real, Ciudad Real, ESP.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Castro Corredor</LastName><ForeName>David</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Rheumatology, Hospital General Universitario de Ciudad Real, Ciudad Real, ESP.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gonzalez Peñas</LastName><ForeName>Marina</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Rheumatology, Hospital General Universitario de Ciudad Real, Ciudad Real, ESP.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">disease activity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">jak inhibitors</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">psoriatic arthritis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">real-world</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">rheumatoid arthritis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">spondyloarthritis</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Local ethics committee of General University Hospital of Ciudad Real issued approval (Registry 01/2023). All patients gave their informed consent to participate in the study. Animal subjects: All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39318929</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11421408</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.67729</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>The Janus kinases (Jaks) Yamaoka K, Saharinen P, Pesu M, Holt VE 3rd, Silvennoinen O, O'Shea JJ. Genome Biol. 2004;5:253.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC545791</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15575979</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Discovery and development of Janus kinase (JAK) inhibitors for inflammatory diseases. Clark JD, Flanagan ME, Telliez JB. J Med Chem. 2014;57:5023–5038.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24417533</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>JAK-STAT inhibitors for the treatment of immunomediated diseases. Serra López-Matencio JM, Morell Baladrón A, Castañeda S. Med Clin (Barc) 2019;152:353–360.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30527218</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The emerging safety profile of JAK inhibitors in rheumatic disease. Winthrop KL. Nat Rev Rheumatol. 2017;13:234–243.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28250461</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Switching from adalimumab to tofacitinib in the treatment of patients with rheumatoid arthritis. Genovese MC, van Vollenhoven RF, Wilkinson B, et al. Arthritis Res Ther. 2016;18:145.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4918072</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27334658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tofacitinib, an oral Janus kinase inhibitor, for the treatment of chronic plaque psoriasis: long-term efficacy and safety results from 2 randomized phase-III studies and 1 open-label long-term extension study. Papp KA, Krueger JG, Feldman SR, et al. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2016;74:841–850.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26899199</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patient-reported outcomes from a phase 3 study of baricitinib versus placebo or adalimumab in rheumatoid arthritis: secondary analyses from the RA-BEAM study. Keystone EC, Taylor PC, Tanaka Y, et al. Ann Rheum Dis. 2017;76:1853–1861.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5705852</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28798049</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baricitinib in patients with inadequate response or intolerance to conventional synthetic DMARDs: results from the RA-BUILD study. Dougados M, van der Heijde D, Chen YC, et al. Ann Rheum Dis. 2017;76:88–95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5264214</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27689735</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Efficacy and safety of ABT-494, a selective JAK-1 inhibitor, in a phase IIb study in patients with rheumatoid arthritis and an inadequate response to methotrexate. Genovese MC, Smolen JS, Weinblatt ME, et al. Arthritis Rheumatol. 2016;68:2857–2866.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5132065</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27390150</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A phase IIb study of ABT-494, a selective JAK-1 inhibitor, in patients with rheumatoid arthritis and an inadequate response to anti-tumor necrosis factor therapy. Kremer JM, Emery P, Camp HS, et al. Arthritis Rheumatol. 2016;68:2867–2877.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5132116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27389975</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clinical confirmation that the selective JAK1 inhibitor filgotinib (GLPG0634) has a low liability for drug-drug interactions. Namour F, Desrivot J, Van der Aa A, Harrison P, Tasset C, van't Klooster G. Drug Metab Lett. 2016;10:38–48.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26693854</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Filgotinib (GLPG0634/GS-6034), an oral selective JAK1 inhibitor, is effective as monotherapy in patients with active rheumatoid arthritis: results from a randomised, dose-finding study (DARWIN 2) Kavanaugh A, Kremer J, Ponce L, et al. Ann Rheum Dis. 2017;76:1009–1019.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27993828</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Real-world effectiveness and safety of Jak inhibitors in rheumatoid arthritis: a single-centre study. González Mazarío R, Fragío Gil JJ, Ivorra Cortés J, et al. Reumatol Clin (Engl Ed) 2022;18:523–530.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36309409</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>2010 rheumatoid arthritis Classification Criteria: an American College of Rheumatology/European League Against Rheumatism collaborative initiative. Aletaha D, Neogi T, Silman AJ, et al. Arthritis Rheum. 2010;62:2569–2581.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20872595</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The development of Assessment of SpondyloArthritis international Society classification criteria for axial spondyloarthritis (part II): validation and final selection. Rudwaleit M, van der Heijde D, Landewé R, et al. Ann Rheum Dis. 2009;68:777–783.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19297344</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Classification criteria for psoriatic arthritis: development of new criteria from a large international study. Taylor W, Gladman D, Helliwell P, Marchesoni A, Mease P, Mielants H. Arthritis Rheum. 2006;54:2665–2673.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16871531</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tofacitinib: real-world data and treatment persistence in rheumatoid arthritis. Bertoldi I, Caporali R. Open Access Rheumatol. 2021;13:221–237.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8326925</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34349573</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ToRaRI (Tofacitinib in Rheumatoid Arthritis a Real-Life experience in Italy): effectiveness, safety profile of tofacitinib and concordance between patient-reported outcomes and physician's global assessment of disease activity in a retrospective study in central Italy. D'Alessandro F, Cazzato M, Laurino E, et al. Clin Rheumatol. 2024;43:657–665.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10834550</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38135860</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Real-world treatment patterns and clinical outcomes of baricitinib in rheumatoid arthritis patients in Spain: results of a multicenter, observational study in routine clinical practice (the ORBIT-RA study) Hernández-Cruz B, Rosas J, Díaz-Torné C, et al. Rheumatol Ther. 2022;9:589–608.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8964893</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35041155</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Systematic literature review of real-world evidence on baricitinib for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis. Hernández-Cruz B, Kiltz U, Avouac J, et al. Rheumatol Ther. 2023;10:1417–1457.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10654279</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37715917</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Real-world effectiveness of upadacitinib for treatment of rheumatoid arthritis in Canadian patients: interim results from the prospective observational close-up study. Bessette L, Chan J, Chow A, et al. Rheumatol Ther. 2024;11:563–582.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11111641</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38467912</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Effectiveness and safety of filgotinib in rheumatoid arthritis: a real-life multicentre experience. La Barbera L, Rizzo C, Camarda F, et al. Clin Exp Rheumatol. 2024;42:991–998.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38197190</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Real-life comparison of four JAK inhibitors in rheumatoid arthritis (ELECTRA-I study) . Benucci M, Li Gobbi F, Damiani A, et al. J Clin Med. 2024;13:1821.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10971497</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38542045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Safety of Janus kinase inhibitors: a real-world multicenter retrospective cohort study. Lanzillotta M, Boffini N, Barone E, et al. J Rheumatol. 2023</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37527867</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Effectiveness and safety of generic tofacitinib in spondyloarthritis: a real-world retrospective analysis from India. Phatak S, Khenat A, Malandkar M, Amin S. Int J Rheum Dis. 2023;26:487–492.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36670550</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Comparative effectiveness of tofacitinib and adalimumab in axial spondyloarthritis: a real-world clinical context multicenter study. Goswami RP, Sinha D, Chatterjee M, Bhadu D, Das S. J Clin Rheumatol. 2024;30:0–14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38509045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Early real-world experience of tofacitinib for psoriatic arthritis: data from a United States healthcare claims database. Mease PJ, Young P, Gruben D, Fallon L, Germino R, Kavanaugh A. Adv Ther. 2022;39:2932–2945.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9123050</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35482248</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Real-world evaluation of persistence, effectiveness and usage patterns of tofacitinib in treatment of psoriatic arthritis in Australia. Littlejohn G, Leadbetter J, Butcher BE, et al. Clin Rheumatol. 2024;43:1579–1589.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11018696</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38459357</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>