<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39311822</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1942-969X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Psychological trauma : theory, research, practice and policy</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Psychol Trauma</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Risk factors of PTSD and substance use disorders in clinical and counseling psychology doctoral students.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1037/tra0001803</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">This study investigated the prevalence of probable alcohol use disorder (AUD), drug use disorders (DUDs), and posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD) among psychology doctoral students. Additionally, it explored the unique relationships between risk factors (lifetime trauma, recent stressful experiences, COVID-19-related stress, general stress, financial stress) and AUD, DUD, and PTSD while accounting for demographic factors.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHOD" NlmCategory="METHODS">The sample included 889 clinical and counseling psychology doctoral students, and the Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test, Screen of Drug Use, and Primary Care PTSD Screen for <i>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders</i> (5th ed.) were used to measure current probable AUD, DUD, and PTSD, respectively.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Approximately 43.8% had probable AUD, 23.2% had probable DUD, and 14.7% had probable PTSD. The univariate analysis results indicated a pattern of elevated risk among Black, Indigenous, and people of color, lesbian, gay, bisexual, queer, and other (LGBQ+) individuals, and women students. The results of the multivariate logistic regression analyses revealed that increased lifetime trauma and COVID-19-related stress were associated with higher adjusted odds of probable PTSD. Higher adjusted odds of probable AUD were observed among individuals experiencing elevated levels of COVID-19-related stress and among younger, women, and non-Hispanic White individuals. LGBQ+ individuals and those with no religious affiliation were found to have higher adjusted odds of probable DUD.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">These findings underscore the alarming prevalence of AUD, DUD, and PTSD in this population, raising concerns that warrant attention. Women; Black, Indigenous, and people of color; and LGBQ+ individuals face heightened risks of PTSD, AUD, and DUD, emphasizing the urgent need for mental health care for psychology doctoral students and marginalized groups. (PsycInfo Database Record (c) 2024 APA, all rights reserved).</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tiet</LastName><ForeName>Quyen Q</ForeName><Initials>QQ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0723-1077</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinical Psychology PhD Program, California School of Professional Psychology, Alliant International University.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Brooks</LastName><ForeName>Jordan</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, Sutter Health, California Pacific Medical Center.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Patton</LastName><ForeName>Cyrano</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinical Psychology PhD Program, California School of Professional Psychology, Alliant International University.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Alliant University Foundation</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Psychol Trauma</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101495376</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1942-969X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39311822</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/tra0001803</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">2025-28368-001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>