<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39314963</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>13</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>medRxiv : the preprint server for health sciences</Title><ISOAbbreviation>medRxiv</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Timely vaccine strain selection and genomic surveillance improves evolutionary forecast accuracy of seasonal influenza A/H3N2.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">2024.09.11.24313489</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1101/2024.09.11.24313489</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>For the last decade, evolutionary forecasting models have influenced seasonal influenza vaccine design. These models attempt to predict which genetic variants circulating at the time of vaccine strain selection will be dominant 12 months later in the influenza season targeted by vaccination campaign. Forecasting models depend on hemagglutinin (HA) sequences from the WHO's Global Influenza Surveillance and Response System to identify currently circulating groups of related strains (clades) and estimate clade fitness for forecasts. However, the average lag between collection of a clinical sample and the submission of its sequence to the Global Initiative on Sharing All Influenza Data (GISAID) EpiFlu database is ~3 months. Submission lags complicate the already difficult 12-month forecasting problem by reducing understanding of current clade frequencies at the time of forecasting. These constraints of a 12-month forecast horizon and 3-month average submission lags create an upper bound on the accuracy of any long-term forecasting model. The global response to the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic revealed that modern vaccine technology like mRNA vaccines can reduce how far we need to forecast into the future to 6 months or less and that expanded support for sequencing can reduce submission lags to GISAID to 1 month on average. To determine whether these recent advances could also improve long-term forecasts for seasonal influenza, we quantified the effects of reducing forecast horizons and submission lags on the accuracy of forecasts for A/H3N2 populations. We found that reducing forecast horizons from 12 months to 6 or 3 months reduced average absolute forecasting errors to 25% and 50% of the 12-month average, respectively. Reducing submission lags provided little improvement to forecasting accuracy but decreased the uncertainty in current clade frequencies by 50%. These results show the potential to substantially improve the accuracy of existing influenza forecasting models by modernizing influenza vaccine development and increasing global sequencing capacity.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huddleston</LastName><ForeName>John</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4250-2063</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Vaccine and Infectious Disease Division, Fred Hutchinson Cancer Center, Seattle, WA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bedford</LastName><ForeName>Trevor</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4039-5794</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Vaccine and Infectious Disease Division, Fred Hutchinson Cancer Center, Seattle, WA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Seattle, WA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>R01 AI165821</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D000076942">Preprint</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>13</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>medRxiv</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101767986</NlmUniqueID></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement>Competing interests The authors declare that no competing interests exist.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39314963</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11419249</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/2024.09.11.24313489</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">2024.09.11.24313489</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Abousamra E, Figgins M, Bedford T. Fitness models provide accurate short-term forecasts of SARS-CoV-2 variant frequency. PLOS Computational Biology. 2024. 09; 20(9):1–20. 10.1371/journal.pcbi.1012443, doi: 10.1371/journal.pcbi.1012443.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1012443</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1012443</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11410224</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39241101</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baden LR, El Sahly HM, Essink B, Kotloff K, Frey S, Novak R, Diemert D, Spector SA, Rouphael N, Creech CB, McGettigan J, Khetan S, Segall N, Solis J, Brosz A, Fierro C, Schwartz H, Neuzil K, Corey L, Gilbert P, et al. Efficacy and Safety of the mRNA-1273 SARS-CoV-2 Vaccine. N Engl J Med. 2021. Feb; 384(5):403–416.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7787219</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33378609</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Black A, MacCannell DR, Sibley TR, Bedford T. Ten recommendations for supporting open pathogen genomic analysis in public health. Nat Med. 2020. Jun; 26(6):832–841.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7363500</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32528156</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brazzoli M, Magini D, Bonci A, Buccato S, Giovani C, Kratzer R, Zurli V, Mangiavacchi S, Casini D, Brito LM, De Gregorio E, Mason PW, Ulmer JB, Geall AJ, Bertholet S. Induction of Broad-Based Immunity and Protective Efficacy by Self-amplifying mRNA Vaccines Encoding Influenza Virus Hemagglutinin. J Virol. 2016. Jan; 90(1):332–344.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4702536</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26468547</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brito AF, Semenova E, Dudas G, Hassler GW, Kalinich CC, Kraemer MUG, Ho J, Tegally H, Githinji G, Agoti CN, Matkin LE, Whittaker C, Howden BP, Sintchenko V, Zuckerman NS, Mor O, Blankenship HM, de Oliveira T, Lin RTP, Siqueira MM, et al. Global disparities in SARS-CoV-2 genomic surveillance. Nat Commun. 2022. Nov; 13(1):7003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9667854</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36385137</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Z, Azman AS, Chen X, Zou J, Tian Y, Sun R, Xu X, Wu Y, Lu W, Ge S, Zhao Z, Yang J, Leung DT, Domman DB, Yu H. Global landscape of SARS-CoV-2 genomic surveillance and data sharing. Nat Genet. 2022. Apr; 54(4):499–507.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9005350</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35347305</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feldman RA, Fuhr R, Smolenov I, Mick Ribeiro A, Panther L, Watson M, Senn JJ, Smith M, Almarsson Ö, Pujar HS, Laska ME, Thompson J, Zaks T, Ciaramella G. mRNA vaccines against H10N8 and H7N9 influenza viruses of pandemic potential are immunogenic and well tolerated in healthy adults in phase 1 randomized clinical trials. Vaccine. 2019. May; 37(25):3326–3334.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31079849</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grant R, Sacks JA, Abraham P, Chunsuttiwat S, Cohen C, Figueroa JP, Fleming T, Fine P, Goldblatt D, Hasegawa H, MacIntrye CR, Memish ZA, Miller E, Nishioka S, Sall AA, Sow S, Tomori O, Wang Y, Van Kerkhove MD, Wambo MA, et al. When to update COVID-19 vaccine composition. Nat Med. 2023. Apr; 29(4):776–780.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36807683</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greaney AJ, Starr TN, Bloom JD. An antibody-escape estimator for mutations to the SARS-CoV-2 receptor-binding domain. Virus Evol. 2022; 8(1):veac021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9092643</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35573973</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hay AJ, McCauley JW. The WHO global influenza surveillance and response system (GISRS)-A future perspective. Influenza Other Respir Viruses. 2018. Sep; 12(5):551–557.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6086842</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29722140</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huddleston J, Barnes JR, Rowe T, Xu X, Kondor R, Wentworth DE, Whittaker L, Ermetal B, Daniels RS, McCauley JW, Fujisaki S, Nakamura K, Kishida N, Watanabe S, Hasegawa H, Barr I, Subbarao K, Barrat-Charlaix P, Neher RA, Bedford T. Integrating genotypes and phenotypes improves long-term forecasts of seasonal influenza A/H3N2 evolution. eLife. 2020. Sep; 9:e60067. 10.7554/eLife.60067, doi: 10.7554/eLife.60067.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7554/eLife.60067</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7554/eLife.60067</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7553778</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32876050</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huddleston J, Bedford T, Chang J, Lee J, Neher RA. Seasonal influenza circulation patterns and projections for February 2024 to February 2025. Zenodo. 2024. Mar; 10.5281/zenodo.10846007, doi: 10.5281/zenodo.10846007.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5281/zenodo.10846007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5281/zenodo.10846007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huddleston J, Hadfield J, Sibley TR, Lee J, Fay K, Ilcisin M, Harkins E, Bedford T, Neher RA, Hodcroft EB. Augur: a bioinformatics toolkit for phylogenetic analyses of human pathogens. J Open Source Softw. 2021; 6(57).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8237802</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34189396</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jariani A, Warth C, Deforche K, Libin P, Drummond AJ, Rambaut A, Matsen IV FA, Theys K. SANTA-SIM: simulating viral sequence evolution dynamics under selection and recombination. Virus Evolution. 2019. Mar; 5(1).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6407609</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30863552</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalia K, Saberwal G, Sharma G. The lag in SARS-CoV-2 genome submissions to GISAID. Nat Biotechnol. 2021. Sep; 39(9):1058–1060.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34376850</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katoh K, Standley DM. MAFFT multiple sequence alignment software version 7: improvements in performance and usability. Mol Biol Evol. 2013. Apr; 30(4):772–780.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3603318</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23329690</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katoh K, Misawa K, Kuma K, Miyata T. MAFFT: a novel method for rapid multiple sequence alignment based on fast Fourier transform. Nucleic Acids Research. 2002. July; 30(14):3059–3066. 10.1093/nar/gkf436, doi: 10.1093/nar/gkf436.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/nar/gkf436</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/nar/gkf436</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC135756</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12136088</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kistler KE, Bedford T. An atlas of continuous adaptive evolution in endemic human viruses. Cell Host Microbe. 2023; 31(11):1898–1909.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37883977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lässig M, Mustonen V, Walczak AM. Predicting evolution. Nat Ecol Evol. 2017. Feb; 1(3):77.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28812721</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee JM, Eguia R, Zost SJ, Choudhary S, Wilson PC, Bedford T, Stevens-Ayers T, Boeckh M, Hurt AC, Lakdawala SS, Hensley SE, Bloom JD. Mapping person-to-person variation in viral mutations that escape polyclonal serum targeting influenza hemagglutinin. Elife. 2019. Aug; 8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6711711</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31452511</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loes AN, Tarabi RAL, Huddleston J, Touyon L, Wong SS, Cheng SMS, Leung NHL, Hannon WW, Bedford T, Cobey S, Cowling BJ, Bloom JD. High-throughput sequencing-based neutralization assay reveals how repeated vaccinations impact titers to recent human H1N1 influenza strains. bioRxiv. 2024. Mar;.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11494878</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39315814</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Łuksza M, Lässig M. A predictive fitness model for influenza. Nature. 2014. Mar; 507(7490):57–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24572367</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meijers M, Ruchnewitz D, Eberhardt J, Łuksza M, Lässig M. Population immunity predicts evolutionary trajectories of SARS-CoV-2. Cell. 2023. Nov; 186(23):5151–5164.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10964984</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37875109</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meijers M, Ruchnewitz D, Eberhardt J, Karmakar M, Łuksza M, Lässig M. Concepts and methods for predicting viral evolution. bioRxiv. 2024; https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2024/05/02/2024.03.19.585703, doi: 10.1101/2024.03.19.585703.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/2024.03.19.585703</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morris DH, Gostic KM, Pompei S, Bedford T, Łuksza M, Neher RA, Grenfell BT, Lässig M, McCauley JW. Predictive modeling of influenza shows the promise of applied evolutionary biology. Trends Microbiol. 2018. Oct;.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5830126</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29097090</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mulligan MJ, Lyke KE, Kitchin N, Absalon J, Gurtman A, Lockhart S, Neuzil K, Raabe V, Bailey R, Swanson KA, Li P, Koury K, Kalina W, Cooper D, Fontes-Garfias C, Shi PY, reci Ö, Tompkins KR, Walsh EE, Frenck R, et al. I/II study of COVID-19 RNA vaccine BNT162b1 in adults. Nature. 2020. Oct; 586(7830):589–593.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32785213</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neher RA, Russell CA, Shraiman BI. Predicting evolution from the shape of genealogical trees. Elife. 2014. Nov; 3:e03568.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4227306</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25385532</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen LT, Schmidt HA, von Haeseler A, Minh BQ. IQ-TREE: A fast and effective stochastic algorithm for estimating maximum-likelihood phylogenies. Molecular Biology and Evolution. 2014. November; 32(1):268–274. 10.1093/molbev/msu300, doi: 10.1093/molbev/msu300.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/molbev/msu300</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/molbev/msu300</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4271533</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25371430</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Toole A, Scher E, Underwood A, Jackson B, Hill V, McCrone JT, Colquhoun R, Ruis C, Abu-Dahab K, Taylor B, Yeats C, du Plessis L, Maloney D, Medd N, Attwood SW, Aanensen DM, Holmes EC, Pybus OG, Rambaut A. Assignment of epidemiological lineages in an emerging pandemic using the pangolin tool. Virus Evol. 2021; 7(2):veab064.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8344591</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34527285</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pardi N, Parkhouse K, Kirkpatrick E, McMahon M, Zost SJ, Mui BL, Tam YK, ó K, Barbosa CJ, Madden TD, Hope MJ, Krammer F, Hensley SE, Weissman D. Nucleoside-modified mRNA immunization elicits influenza virus hemagglutinin stalk-specific antibodies. Nat Commun. 2018. Aug; 9(1):3361.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6105651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30135514</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petrova VN, Russell CA. The evolution of seasonal influenza viruses. Nature Reviews Microbiology. 2018. Jan; 16(1):47–60. 10.1038/nrmicro.2017.118, doi: 10.1038/nrmicro.2017.118.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nrmicro.2017.118</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nrmicro.2017.118</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29081496</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petsch B, Schnee M, Vogel AB, Lange E, Hoffmann B, Voss D, Schlake T, Thess A, Kallen KJ, Stitz L, Kramps T. Protective efficacy of in vitro synthesized, specific mRNA vaccines against influenza A virus infection. Nat Biotechnol. 2012. Dec; 30(12):1210–1216.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23159882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubner Y, Tomasi C, Guibas LJ. A metric for distributions with applications to image databases. In: Sixth International Conference on Computer Vision (IEEE Cat. No.98CH36271); 1998. p. 59–66. doi: 10.1109/ICCV.1998.710701.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/ICCV.1998.710701</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sagulenko P, Puller V, Neher RA. TreeTime: Maximum-likelihood phylodynamic analysis. Virus Evolution. 2018. January; 4(1). 10.1093/ve/vex042, doi: 10.1093/ve/vex042.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ve/vex042</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ve/vex042</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5758920</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29340210</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shu Y, McCauley J. GISAID: Global initiative on sharing all influenza data – from vision to reality. Eurosurveillance. 2017; 22(13).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5388101</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28382917</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith DJ, Lapedes AS, de Jong JC, Bestebroer TM, Rimmelzwaan GF, Osterhaus ADME, Fouchier RAM. Mapping the antigenic and genetic evolution of influenza virus. Science. 2004. Jul; 305(5682):371–376.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15218094</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steinbrück L, Klingen TR, McHardy AC. Computational prediction of vaccine strains for human influenza A (H3N2) viruses. J Virol. 2014. Oct; 88(20):12123–12132.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4178748</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25122778</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Virtanen P, Gommers R, Oliphant TE, Haberland M, Reddy T, Cournapeau D, Burovski E, Peterson P, Weckesser W, Bright J, van der Walt SJ, Brett M, Wilson J, Millman KJ, Mayorov N, Nelson ARJ, Jones E, Kern R, Larson E, Carey CJ, et al.
SciPy 1.0: fundamental algorithms for scientific computing in Python. Nature Methods. 2020. 
Mar; 17(3):261–272. https://www.nature.com/articles/s41592-019-0686-2, doi: 10.1038/s41592-019-0686-2, number: 3 Publisher: Nature Publishing Group.
</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41592-019-0686-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7056644</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32015543</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Welsh FC, Eguia RT, Lee JM, Haddox HK, Galloway J, Chau NVV, Loes AN, Huddleston J, Yu TC, Le MQ, Nhat NTD, Thanh NTL, Greninger AL, Chu HY, Englund JA, Bedford T, Matsen FA, Boni MF, Bloom JD. Age-dependent heterogeneity in the antigenic effects of mutations to influenza hemagglutinin. bioRxiv. 2023. Dec;.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11329357</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39032493</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong SS, Webby RJ. Traditional and new influenza vaccines. Clin Microbiol Rev. 2013. Jul; 26(3):476–492.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3719499</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23824369</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Seasonal influenza fact sheet. Available at http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs211/en/; 2014.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>