<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39310702</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">0971-5894</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>30</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Physiology and molecular biology of plants : an international journal of functional plant biology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Physiol Mol Biol Plants</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle><i>Bryophyllum pinnatum</i> (Lam.) Oken: unravelling therapeutic potential and navigating toxicity.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1413</StartPage><EndPage>1427</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1413-1427</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s12298-024-01509-7</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText><i>Bryophyllum pinnatum</i> (Lam.) Oken, a multipurpose medicinal herb, has drawn much interest for its therapeutic qualities from both traditional and modern medicine systems. Many active secondary metabolites, such as bufadienolides, triterpenes, phenols, alkaloids, glycosides, lipids, flavonoids, and organic acids, are responsible for the plant's curative properties. <i>B. pinnatum</i> exhibits a noteworthy significance in oncological research by exhibiting its ability to modify numerous pathways, which may suggest a potential anticancer impact. The herb is recommended for treating lithiasis, a common cause of renal failure, due to its effectiveness in dissolving stones and avoiding crystal formation. The plant has a major impact on diabetes, especially type II diabetes. Moreover, the versatility of <i>B. pinnatum</i> extends to its examination in connection to COVID-19. However, caution is warranted, as <i>B. pinnatum</i> has been reported to possess toxicity attributed to the presence of bufadienolides in its metabolic profile. A comprehensive investigation is essential to thoroughly understand and confirm the synthesis of potentially hazardous compounds. This is crucial for minimizing their presence and ensuring the safe consumption of <i>B. pinnatum</i> among diverse populations of organisms. This review highlights the various medical uses of <i>B. pinnatum</i>, including its ability to effectively treat kidney and liver diseases, as well as its anti-leishmanial, neuropharmacological, antibacterial, immunosuppressive, anti-tumour, and cytotoxic effects. While extensively employed in both traditional and scientific domains, the plant's complete medicinal potential, molecular mechanisms, safety profile, and pharmacodynamics remain ambiguous, rendering it an ideal candidate for pioneering research endeavours.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© Prof. H.S. Srivastava Foundation for Science and Society 2024. Springer Nature or its licensor (e.g. a society or other partner) holds exclusive rights to this article under a publishing agreement with the author(s) or other rightsholder(s); author self-archiving of the accepted manuscript version of this article is solely governed by the terms of such publishing agreement and applicable law.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sharma</LastName><ForeName>Garima</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biotechnology, Guru Jambheshwar University of Science and Technology, Hisar, Haryana India.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.411892.7</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0004 0500 4297</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jangra</LastName><ForeName>Alka</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Agriculture Biotechnology, College of Biotechnology, Chaudhary Charan Singh Haryana Agriculture University, Hisar, Haryana India.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/0261g6j35</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.7151.2</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 0170 2635</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sihag</LastName><ForeName>Sonia</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biotechnology, Guru Jambheshwar University of Science and Technology, Hisar, Haryana India.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.411892.7</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0004 0500 4297</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chaturvedi</LastName><ForeName>Siddhant</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Botany, Goswami Tulsidas Government Post Graduate College (Bundelkhand University, Jhansi), Karwi, Chitrakoot, Uttar Pradesh India.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/0003ewr82</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.411823.d</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0004 0506 5583</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yadav</LastName><ForeName>Shalu</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biotechnology, Guru Jambheshwar University of Science and Technology, Hisar, Haryana India.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.411892.7</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0004 0500 4297</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chhokar</LastName><ForeName>Vinod</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1638-7767</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biotechnology, Guru Jambheshwar University of Science and Technology, Hisar, Haryana India.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.411892.7</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0004 0500 4297</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>India</Country><MedlineTA>Physiol Mol Biol Plants</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101304333</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0974-0430</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bryophyllum pinnatum</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bufadienolides</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Medicinal properties</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Metabolic profiling</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Signalling pathways</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Toxicity</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflict of interestThe authors have no relevant financial or non-financial interests to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>17</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>17</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39310702</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11413295</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12298-024-01509-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">1509</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Adejoro IA, Babatunde DD, Tolufashe GF (2020) Molecular docking and dynamic simulations of some medicinal plants compounds against SARS-CoV-2: an in silico study. J Taibah Univ Sci 14:1563–1570</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adesanwo JK, Raji Y, Olaleye SB et al (2007) Antiulcer activity of methanolic extract of Bryophyllum pinnatum in rats. J Biol Sci 7:409–412</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Afzal M, Gupta G, Kazmi I et al (2012) Anti-inflammatory and analgesic potential of a novel steroidal derivative from Bryophyllum pinnatum. Fitoterapia 83:853–858. 10.1016/j.fitote.2012.03.013</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22465504</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akinpelu DA (2000) Antimicrobial activity of Bryophyllum pinnatum leaves. Fitoterapia 71:193–194</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10727819</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alabi DA, Onibudo MZ, Amusa NA (2005) Chemicals and nutritional composition of four botanicals with fungitoxic properties. World J Agric Sci 1:84–88</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alkhalidy H, Moore W, Zhang Y et al (2015) (2015) Small molecule kaempferol promotes insulin sensitivity and preserved pancreatic β-cell mass in middle-aged obese diabetic mice. J Diabetes Res 1:532984</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4439495</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26064984</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almeida AP, Da Silva SAG, Souza MLM et al (2000) Isolation and chemical analysis of a fatty acid fraction of Kalanchoe pinnata with a potent lymphocyte suppressive activity. Planta Med 66:134–137</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10763586</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alpert M (2005) The diverse benefits of glutathione: a key antioxidant for reversing chronic illness. Alternat Complement Therap 11:241–245</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anjoo K, Kumar SA (2010) Microscopical and preliminary phytochemical studies on aerial part (leaves and stem) of Bryophyllum pinnotum Kurz. Pharmacogn J 2:254–259</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asafo-Agyei T, Appau Y, Barimah KB, Asase A (2023) Medicinal plants used for management of diabetes and hypertension in Ghana. Heliyon 9:e22977</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10703729</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38076168</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aurora Y, Tarigan IPN, Suryanto NMM et al (2022) Identification of flavonoids of Kalanchoe Pinnata as candidate drugs for COVID-19 gamma-variant treatment. Malays J Fundam Appl Sci 18:630–643</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bernatova I, Liskova S (2021) Mechanisms modified by (−)-epicatechin and taxifolin relevant for the treatment of hypertension and viral infection: Knowledge from preclinical studies. Antioxidants 10:467</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8002320</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33809620</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cai F, Zhang Y, Li J et al (2020) Isorhamnetin inhibited the proliferation and metastasis of androgen-independent prostate cancer cells by targeting the mitochondrion-dependent intrinsic apoptotic and PI3K/Akt/mTOR pathway. Biosci Rep 40:BSR20192826</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7080645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32039440</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carvalho M, Vieira MA (2004) Changes in calcium oxalate crystal morphology as a function of supersaturation. Int Braz J Urol 30:205–209</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15689248</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y-J, Lin K-N, Jhang L-M et al (2016) Gallic acid abolishes the EGFR/Src/Akt/Erk-mediated expression of matrix metalloproteinase-9 in MCF-7 breast cancer cells. Chem Biol Interact 252:131–140</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27087131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Z, Lin T, Liao X et al (2021) Network pharmacology based research into the effect and mechanism of Yinchenhao Decoction against Cholangiocarcinoma. Chin Med 16:1–20</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7818939</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33478536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choudhary S, Bhoir V, Bhoir R, Bhoir C (2024) Bryophyllum pinnatum leaf extract in treatment of kidney stones. Int J Pharm Sci 2:1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cucinotta D, Vanelli M (2020) WHO declares COVID-19 a pandemic. Acta Bio Medica: Atenei Parmensis 91:157</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7569573</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32191675</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Devbhuti D, Gupta JK, Devbhuti P, Bose A (2008) Phytochemical and acute toxicity study on Bryophyllum calycinum Salisb. Acta Poloniae Pharm-Drug Res 65:501–504</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19051594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dinnimath BM, Jalalpure SS, Patil UK (2017) Antiurolithiatic activity of natural constituents isolated from Aerva lanata. J Ayurveda Integr Med 8:226–232</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5747499</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29169771</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du J, Li Y, Lu X et al (2023) Metabolomics-based study on the changes of endogenous metabolites during adventitious bud formation from leaf margin of Bryophyllum pinnatum (Lam.) Oken. Plant Physiol Biochem 201:107845</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37364508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duranti G, Maldini M, Crognale D et al (2021) Moringa oleifera leaf extract upregulates Nrf2/HO-1 expression and ameliorates redox status in C2C12 skeletal muscle cells. Molecules 26:5041</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8400669</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34443628</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Akad RH, Abou Zeid AH, El-Rafie HM et al (2021) Comparative metabolites profiling of Caryota mitis &amp; Caryota urens via UPLC/MS and isolation of two novel in silico chemopreventive flavonoids. J Food Biochem 45:e13648</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33559930</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elufioye TO, Oyedeji AO, Habtemariam S (2022) A review of the traditional uses, phytochemistry and pharmacology of Bryophyllum pinnatum (Lam.)(Crassulaceae). J Biol Active Prod Nature 12:1–34</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ersahin T, Tuncbag N, Cetin-Atalay R (2015) The PI3K/AKT/mTOR interactive pathway. Mol Biosyst 11:1946–1954</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25924008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan Z, Wirth AK, Chen D et al (2017) Nrf2-Keap1 pathway promotes cell proliferation and diminishes ferroptosis. Oncogenesis 6:e371–e371</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5608917</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28805788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fürer K, Raith M, Brenneisen R et al (2013) Two new flavonol glycosides and a metabolite profile of Bryophyllum pinnatum, a phytotherapeutic used in obstetrics and gynaecology. Planta Med 79:1565–1571</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24072500</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fürer K, Simões-Wüst AP, Von Mandach U et al (2016) Bryophyllum pinnatum and related species used in anthroposophic medicine: constituents, pharmacological activities, and clinical efficacy. Planta Med 82:930–941. 10.1055/s-0042-106727</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27220081</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>García-Pérez P, Lozano-Milo E, Landin M, Gallego PP (2020) From ethnomedicine to plant biotechnology and machine learning: the valorization of the medicinal plant Bryophyllum sp. Pharmaceuticals 13:444</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7762000</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33291844</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gehrig H, Gaußmann O, Marx H et al (2001) Molecular phylogeny of the genus Kalanchoe (Crassulaceae) inferred from nucleotide sequences of the ITS-1 and ITS-2 regions. Plant Sci 160:827–835</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11297779</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goraya GS, Ved DK (2017) Medicinal plants in India: an assessment of their demand and supply. In National Medicinal Plants Board, Ministry of AYUSH, Government of India, New Delhi and Indian Council of Forestry Research &amp; Education, Dehradun, 1–430</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamburger M, Potterat O, Fürer K et al (2017) Bryophyllum pinnatum–reverse engineering of an anthroposophic herbal medicine. Nat Prod Commun 12:1934578X1701200847</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han L, Guo X, Bian H et al (2016) Guizhi fuling wan, a traditional chinese herbal formula, sensitizes cisplatin-resistant human ovarian cancer cells through inactivation of the PI3K/AKT/mTOR pathway. Evid-Based Complement Altern Med 2016:4651949</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4887624</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27293459</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hernández-Caballero ME, Sierra-Ramírez JA, Villalobos-Valencia R, Seseña-Méndez E (2022) Potential of Kalanchoe pinnata as a cancer treatment adjuvant and an epigenetic regulator. Molecules 27:6425</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9573125</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36234962</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Igwe SA, Akunyili DN (2005) Analgesic effects of aqueous extracts of the leaves of Bryophyllum pinnatum. Pharm Biol 43:658–661</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jamshidi-Kia F, Lorigooini Z, Amini-Khoei H (2017) Medicinal plants: past history and future perspective. J Herbmed Pharmacol 7:1–7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jangra A, Chaturvedi S, Sihag S et al (2023) Identification and functional characterization of a novel aldo–keto reductase from Aloe vera. Planta 258:107</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37897513</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jangra A, Sharma G, Sihag S, Chhokar V (2022) The dark side of miracle plant-Aloe vera: a review. Mol Biol Rep 14:1–12</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35092563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamboj A, Saluja AK (2009) Bryophyllum pinnatum (Lam.) Kurz.: phytochemical and pharmacological profile: a review. Pharmacogn Rev 3:364–374</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kanjwani DG, Marathe TP, Chiplunkar SV, Sathaye SS (2008) Evaluation of immunomodulatory activity of methanolic extract of Piper betel. Scand J Immunol 67:589–593</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18476879</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ko E-B, Jang Y-G, Kim C-W et al (2022) Gallic acid hindered lung cancer progression by inducing cell cycle arrest and apoptosis in a549 lung cancer cells via PI3K/Akt pathway. Biomol Ther (Seoul) 30:151</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8902450</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34261818</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Komiya Y, Habas R (2008) Wnt signal transduction pathways. Organogenesis 4:68–75</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2634250</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19279717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koni M, Pinnarò V, Brizzi MF (2020) The Wnt signalling pathway: a tailored target in cancer. Int J Mol Sci 21:7697</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7589708</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33080952</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krishnan A, Hamilton JP, Alqahtani SA, Woreta TA (2021) COVID-19: an overview and a clinical update. World J Clin Cases 9:8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7809683</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33511168</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krishnaraju AV, Rao TVN, Sundararaju D et al (2005) Assessment of bioactivity of Indian medicinal plants using brine shrimp (Artemia salina) lethality assay. Int J Appl Sci Eng 3:125–134</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lans CA (2006) Ethnomedicines used in Trinidad and Tobago for urinary problems and diabetes mellitus. J Ethnobiol Ethnomed 2:1–11</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1624823</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17040567</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee Y, Bernstock JD, Nagaraja N et al (2016) Global SUMO ylation facilitates the multimodal neuroprotection afforded by quercetin against the deleterious effects of oxygen/glucose deprivation and the restoration of oxygen/glucose. J Neurochem 138:101–116</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4916017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27087120</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Kong D, Fu Y et al (2020) The effect of developmental and environmental factors on secondary metabolites in medicinal plants. Plant Physiol Biochem 148:80–89</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31951944</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li W, Cheng M, Zhang W et al (2021) New insights into the mechanisms of polyphenol from plum fruit inducing apoptosis in human lung cancer A549 cells via PI3k/AKT/FOXO1 pathway. Plant Foods Hum Nutr 76:125–132</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33641052</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu T, Li Z, Tian F (2021) Quercetin inhibited the proliferation and invasion of hepatoblastoma cells through facilitating SIRT6-medicated FZD4 silence. Hum Exp Toxicol 40:S96–S107</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34219513</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lozano-Milo E, García-Pérez P, Gallego PP (2020) Narrative review of production of antioxidants and anticancer compounds from Bryophyllum spp. (Kalanchoe) using plant cell tissue culture. Longhua Chin Med. 10.21037/lcm-20-46</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu Y, Jiang F, Jiang H et al (2010) Gallic acid suppresses cell viability, proliferation, invasion and angiogenesis in human glioma cells. Eur J Pharmacol 641:102–107</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3003697</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20553913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McKenzie RA, Franke FP, Dunster PJ (1987) The toxicity to cattle and bufadienolide content of six Bryophyllum species. Aust Vet J 64:298–301</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3439945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen TTT, Tran E, Nguyen TH et al (2004) The role of activated MEK-ERK pathway in quercetin-induced growth inhibition and apoptosis in A549 lung cancer cells. Carcinogenesis 25:647–659</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14688022</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ogidi OI, Esie NG, Dike OG (2019) Phytochemical, proximate and mineral compositions of Bryophyllum pinnatum (Never die) medicinal plant. J Pharm Phytochem 8:629–635</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ojewole JAO (2002) P-2: antihypertensive properties of Bryophyllum pinnatum (Lam) Oken leaf extracts. Am J Hypertens 15:34A</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ojewole JAO (2005) Antinociceptive, anti-inflammatory and antidiabetic effects of Bryophyllum pinnatum (Crassulaceae) leaf aqueous extract. J Ethnopharmacol 99:13–19</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15848014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okwu DE, Josiah C (2006) Evaluation of the chemical composition of two Nigerian medicinal plants. Afr J Biotechnol 5:357–361</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okwu DE, Nnamdi FU (2011) A novel antimicrobial phenanthrene alkaloid from Bryopyllum pinnatum. J Chem 8:1456–1461</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oufir M, Seiler C, Gerodetti M et al (2015) Quantification of bufadienolides in Bryophyllum pinnatum leaves and manufactured products by UHPLC-ESIMS/MS. Planta Med 81:1190–1197</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26132852</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pal S, Sen T, Chaudhuri AK (1999) Neuropsychopharmacological profile of the methanolic fraction of Bryophyllum pinnatum leaf extract. J Pharm Pharmacol 51:313–318</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10344633</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palacz-Wrobel M, Borkowska P, Paul-Samojedny M et al (2017) Effect of apigenin, kaempferol and resveratrol on the gene expression and protein secretion of tumor necrosis factor alpha (TNF-α) and interleukin-10 (IL-10) in RAW-264.7 macrophages. Biomed Pharmacother 93:1205–1212</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28738536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan B, Fang S, Zhang J et al (2020) Chinese herbal compounds against SARS-CoV-2: puerarin and quercetin impair the binding of viral S-protein to ACE2 receptor. Comput Struct Biotechnol J 18:3518–3527</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7657012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33200026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paranjpe P (2001) Indian medicinal plants: forgotten healers: a guide to ayurvedic herbal medicine with identity, habitat, botany, photochemistry, ayurvedic properties, formulations &amp; clinical usage. Chaukhamba Sanskrit Pratishthan</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park S-R, Kim S-R, Hong I-S, Lee H-Y (2020) A novel therapeutic approach for colorectal cancer stem cells: blocking the PI3K/Akt signaling axis with caffeic acid. Front Cell Dev Biol 8:585987</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7785810</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33425893</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pattewar SV (2012) Kalanchoe pinnata: phytochemical and pharmacological profile. Int J Pharm Sci Res 3:993</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pfeiffer AFH, Klein HH (2014) The treatment of type 2 diabetes. Dtsch Arztebl Int 111:69</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3952010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24612534</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quazi Majaz A, Tatiya AU, Khurshid M et al (2011) The miracle plant (Kalanchoe pinnata): a phytochemical and pharmacological review. Int J Res Ayurveda Pharm 2:1478–1482</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahman R, Al-Sabahi JN, Ghaffar A et al (2019) Phytochemical, morphological, botanical, and pharmacological aspects of a medicinal plant: Kalanchoe pinnata–A review article. Int J Chem Biochem Sci 16:5–10</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramon P, Sparks J, Omoruyi F (2021) Effect of combined K. Pinnata and metformin preparation on inflammatory cytokines in normal and diabetic skeletal muscle cells. J Med Food 24:732–740</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33179996</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ranaweera S, Weerasinghe S, Tarannum F, Walters KB (2023) Inhibition and dissolution of calcium oxalate crystals and kidney stones by the extract of Kalanchoe pinnata</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Safi A, Heidarian E, Ahmadi R (2021) Quercetin synergistically enhances the anticancer efficacy of docetaxel through induction of apoptosis and modulation of PI3K/AKT, MAPK/ERK, and JAK/STAT3 signaling pathways in MDA-MB-231 breast cancer cell line. Int J Mol Cell Med 10:11</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8256834</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34268250</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shadrack DM, Deogratias G, Kiruri LW et al (2021) Luteolin: a blocker of SARS-CoV-2 cell entry based on relaxed complex scheme, molecular dynamics simulation, and metadynamics. J Mol Model 27:1–15</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8264176</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34236507</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shawan MMAK, Halder SK, Hasan MA (2021) Luteolin and abyssinone II as potential inhibitors of SARS-CoV-2: An in silico molecular modeling approach in battling the COVID-19 outbreak. Bull Natl Res Cent 45:1–21</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7816153</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33495684</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh AP (2005) Promising phytochemicals from Indian medicinal plants. Ethnobot Leafl 2005:18</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sirota R, Gibson D, Kohen R (2015) The role of the catecholic and the electrophilic moieties of caffeic acid in Nrf2/Keap1 pathway activation in ovarian carcinoma cell lines. Redox Biol 4:48–59</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4309848</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25498967</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sirota R, Gibson D, Kohen R (2017) The timing of caffeic acid treatment with cisplatin determines sensitization or resistance of ovarian carcinoma cell lines. Redox Biol 11:170–175</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5153445</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27951496</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Srivastava NS, Srivastava RAK (2019) Curcumin and quercetin synergistically inhibit cancer cell proliferation in multiple cancer cells and modulate Wnt/β-catenin signaling and apoptotic pathways in A375 cells. Phytomedicine 52:117–128</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30599890</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tallei TE, Tumilaar SG, Niode NJ et al (2020) Potential of plant bioactive compounds as SARS-CoV-2 main protease (M pro) and spike (S) glycoprotein inhibitors: a molecular docking study. Scientifica (Cairo) 2020:6307457</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7773461</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33425427</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tanigawa S, Fujii M, Hou D-X (2007) Action of Nrf2 and Keap1 in ARE-mediated NQO1 expression by quercetin. Free Radic Biol Med 42:1690–1703</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17462537</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tatsimo SJN, de Tamokou JD, Havyarimana L et al (2012) Antimicrobial and antioxidant activity of kaempferol rhamnoside derivatives from Bryophyllum pinnatum. BMC Res Notes 5:1–6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3353177</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22433844</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trinh N-T, Nguyen TMN, Yook J-I et al (2022) Quercetin and quercitrin from Agrimonia pilosa Ledeb inhibit the migration and invasion of colon cancer cells through the JNK signaling pathway. Pharmaceuticals 15:364</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8951172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35337161</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vadvalkar SM, Dhadwe AK, Choudhary RV (2014) A review on pharmacognostical, phytochemical and pharmacological potentials of Kalanchoe pinnata (Crassulaceae). Am J PharmTech Res 4:1–15</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vivanco I, Sawyers CL (2002) The phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase–AKT pathway in human cancer. Nat Rev Cancer 2:489–501</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12094235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wagner H, Lotter H, Fischer M (1986) The toxic and sedative bufadienolides of Kalanchoe daigremontiana Hamet et Perr Die toxischen und sedierend wirkenden Bufadienolide von Kalanchoe daigremontiana Hamet et Perr. Helv Chim Acta 69:359–367</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Liu M, Chen S, Wu Q (2020) Avicularin inhibits cell proliferation and induces cell apoptosis in cutaneous squamous cell carcinoma. Exp Ther Med 19:1065–1071</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6966122</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32010270</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wortzel I, Seger R (2011) The ERK cascade: distinct functions within various subcellular organelles. Genes Cancer 2:195–209</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3128630</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21779493</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Y-C, Chen C-S, Chan Y-J (2020) The outbreak of COVID-19: an overview. J Chin Med Assoc 83:217</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7153464</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32134861</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang S, Si L, Jia Y et al (2019a) Kaempferol exerts anti-proliferative effects on human ovarian cancer cells by inducing apoptosis, G0/G1 cell cycle arrest and modulation of MEK/ERK and STAT3 pathways. J Buon 24:975–981</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31424650</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang S-Y, Pyo MC, Nam M-H, Lee K-W (2019b) ERK/Nrf2 pathway activation by caffeic acid in HepG2 cells alleviates its hepatocellular damage caused by t-butylhydroperoxide-induced oxidative stress. BMC Complement Altern Med 19:1–13</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6585055</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31221142</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao B, Hu M (2013) Gallic acid reduces cell viability, proliferation, invasion and angiogenesis in human cervical cancer cells. Oncol Lett 6:1749–1755</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4023842</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24843386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>