<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39310672</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2397-9070</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>8</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>JGH open : an open access journal of gastroenterology and hepatology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>JGH Open</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Comparison of <i>Helicobacter pylori</i> in hospitalized COVID-19 patients with and without gastrointestinal symptoms.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70020</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70020</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e70020</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jgh3.70020</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND AND AIM" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED"><i>Helicobacter pylori</i> plays an important role in causing digestive diseases. The purpose of this study is to investigate <i>Helicobacter pylori</i> in COVID-19 patients with and without gastrointestinal symptoms.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">In this case-control study, all patients with COVID-19 admitted to Imam Khomeini Hospital in Jiroft city in 2021 were convenience sampled and divided into two homogeneous groups. Ninety-five patients with COVID-19, who presented with gastrointestinal symptoms, were included in the case group, while 95 patients with COVID-19 without gastrointestinal symptoms were included in the control group. Noninvasive diagnostic methods, including serology and stool antigen tests, were used to identify <i>Helicobacter pylori</i> in the studied patients.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Fifty-three people (55.8%) from the case group had <i>Helicobacter pylori</i>, and 48 (50.5%) from the control group had <i>Helicobacter pylori</i>. Among the 53 people from the case group, 27 (50.9%) were men and 26 (49.1%) were women. Nineteen people (35.8%) were taking pantoprazole, 10 people (18.8%) were taking nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, 20 people (37.7%) were taking narcotics, and 7 people (13.2%) had peptic ulcer. Seven people (13.2%) had an H2 blocker, and 21 people had an underlying disease. A significant relationship between infection with <i>Helicobacter pylori</i> and the use of pantoprazole, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, narcotics, peptic ulcer, underlying disease, and H2 blocker in COVID-19 patients with gastrointestinal symptoms and without gastrointestinal symptoms was present (<i>P</i>-value &lt; 0.05).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The prevalence of <i>Helicobacter pylori</i> infection in patients with COVID-19, who have gastrointestinal symptoms, is high and should be considered as a treatment criterion for people infected with COVID-19.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). JGH Open: An open access journal of gastroenterology and hepatology published by Journal of Gastroenterology and Hepatology Foundation and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Saeedi</LastName><ForeName>Amin</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5853-9063</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, School of Medicine, Imam Khomeini Hospital Jiroft University of Medical Sciences Jiroft Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bagheri</LastName><ForeName>Afshin Mohammad</ForeName><Initials>AM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, School of Medicine, Imam Khomeini Hospital Jiroft University of Medical Sciences Jiroft Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Raesi</LastName><ForeName>Rasoul</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5998-5209</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nursing Torbat Jam Faculty of Medical Sciences Torbat Jam Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Services Management School of Health, Mashhad University of Medical Sciences Mashhad Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hushmandi</LastName><ForeName>Kiavash</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nephrology and Urology Research Center, Clinical Sciences Institute Baqiyatallah University of Medical Sciences Tehran Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Daneshi</LastName><ForeName>Salman</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9199-0382</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health, School of Health Jiroft University of Medical Sciences Jiroft Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Domari</LastName><ForeName>Asma Amiri</ForeName><Initials>AA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1587-7588</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Surgery, School of Medicine Imam Khomeini Hospital Jiroft University of Medical Sciences Jiroft Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gholamzadeh</LastName><ForeName>Mohammadhossein</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Medicine Imam Khomeini Hospital Jiroft University of Medical Sciences Jiroft Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kargar</LastName><ForeName>Shiva</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology School of Health, Zahedan University of Medical Sciences Zahedan Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Australia</Country><MedlineTA>JGH Open</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101730833</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2397-9070</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Helicobacter pylori (H. pylori)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">gastrointestinal</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">hospital</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">patient</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">symptom</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>17</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>17</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39310672</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11416053</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jgh3.70020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">JGH370020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Wang L, Wang Y, Ye D, Liu Q. Review of the 2019 novel coronavirus (SARS‐CoV‐2) based on current evidence. Int. J. Antimicrob. Agents. 2020; 55: 105948.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7156162</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32201353</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aumpan N, Mahachai V, Rk V. Management of Helicobacter pylori infection. JGH Open. 2023; 7: 3–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9840198</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36660052</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raygan F, Khorasanifar H, Arj A, Akbari H. The association between acute myocardial infarction and anti‐Helicobacter pylori antibody. Zahedan. J. Res. Med. Sci. 2009; 11: e94400.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang B, Chen Y, Xie Q et al. CagA‐positive Helicobacter pylori strains enhanced coronary atherosclerosis by increasing serum OxLDL and HsCRP in patients with coronary heart disease. Dig. Dis. Sci. 2011; 56: 109–114.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20503072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chobanian AV, Bakris GL, Black HR et al. Seventh report of the joint national committee on prevention, detection, evaluation, and treatment of high blood pressure. Hypertension. 2003; 42: 1206–1252.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14656957</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed AAQ, Besio R, Xiao L, Forlino A. Outer Membrane Vesicles (OMVs) as biomedical tools and their relevance as immune‐modulating agents against H. pylori Infections: current status and future prospects. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 2023; 24: 8542.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10218342</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37239888</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reszka E, Jegier B, Wasowicz W, Lelonek M, Banach M, Jaszewski R. Detection of infectious agents by polymerase chain reaction in human aortic wall. Cardiovasc. Pathol. 2008; 17: 297–302.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18402822</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith S, Oyedeji K, Arigbabu A et al. Comparison of three PCR methods for detection of Helicobacter pylori DNA and detection of cagA gene in gastric biopsy specimens. World J. Gastroenterol. 2004; 10: 1958–1960.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4572239</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15222045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Z, McGoogan JM. Characteristics of and important lessons from the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID‐19) outbreak in China: summary of a report of 72 314 cases from the Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention. JAMA. 2020; 323: 1239–1242.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32091533</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li L, Wan C, Ding R et al. Mental distress among Liberian medical staff working at the China Ebola Treatment Unit: a cross sectional study. Health Qual. Life Outcomes. 2015; 13: 1–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4583730</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26409446</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen H, Guo J, Wang C et al. Clinical characteristics and intrauterine vertical transmission potential of COVID‐19 infection in nine pregnant women: a retrospective review of medical records. Lancet. 2020; 395: 809–815.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7159281</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32151335</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu N, Zhang D, Wang W et al. A novel coronavirus from patients with pneumonia in China, 2019. New Engl. J. Med. 2020; 382: 727–733.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7092803</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31978945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Q, Guan X, Wu P et al. Early transmission dynamics in Wuhan, China, of novel coronavirus–infected pneumonia. New Engl. J. Med. 2020; 382: 1199–1207.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7121484</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31995857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salehi Z, Jelodar MH, Rassa M, Ahaki M, Mollasalehi H, Mashayekhi F. Helicobacter pylori cagA status and peptic ulcer disease in Iran. Dig. Dis. Sci. 2009; 54: 608–613.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18612816</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balamtekin N, Artuk C, Arslan M, Gülşen M. The effect of Helicobacter pylori on the presentation and clinical course of coronavirus disease 2019 infection. J. Pediatr. Gastroenterol. Nutr. 2021; 72: 511–513.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7984630</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33306581</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Falahi J, Bahador A, Motamed N, Tabib SM, Gharibi S, Homayoon K. Prevalence of Helicobacter pylori infection among patients with upper gastrointestinal symptoms in Bushehr, Iran. ISMJ. 2015; 18: 556–566.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rostami‐Nejad M, Villanacci V, Mashayakhi R et al. Celiac disease and Hp infection association in Iran. Rev. Espan. Enfermed. Digest. 2009; 101: 850–854.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20082545</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Den Hoed C, Van Eijck B, Capelle L et al. The prevalence of premalignant gastric lesions in asymptomatic patients: predicting the future incidence of gastric cancer. Eur. J. Cancer. 2011; 47: 1211–1218.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21239166</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tanih N, Okeleye B, Ndip I et al. Helicobacter pylori prevalence in dyspeptic patients in the Eastern Cape Province–race and disease status. S. Afr. Med. J. 2010; 100: 734–737.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21081026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen TL, Uchida T, Tsukamoto Y et al. Helicobacter pylori infection and gastroduodenal diseases in Vietnam: a cross‐sectional, hospital‐based study. BMC Gastroenterol. 2010; 10: 1–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2959090</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20920280</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shiota S, Murakami K, Takayama A et al. Evaluation of Helicobacter pylori status and endoscopic findings among new outpatients with dyspepsia in Japan. J. Gastroenterol. 2009; 44: 930–934.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19568686</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>González N, Fernández L, Saona G et al. Helicobacter pylori infection in Uruguayan patients of African origin: clinical, endoscopic and genetic characteristics. Acta Gastroenterol. Latinoam. 2010; 40: 206–210.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21053478</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alazmi WM, Siddique I, Alateeqi N, Al‐Nakib B. Prevalence of Helicobacter pylori infection among new outpatients with dyspepsia in Kuwait. BMC Gastroenterol. 2010; 10: 1–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2835643</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20128917</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katsanos KH, Tatsioni A, Tsakiris V, Christodoulou D, Tsianos EV. Helicobacter pylori is a major public health priority in western Balkans: an endoscopy referral center experience. Eur. J. Intern. Med. 2010; 21: 306–309.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20603041</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caramelo F, Ferreira N, Oliveiros B. Estimation of risk factors for COVID‐19 mortality‐preliminary results. MedRxiv. 2020. 2020.02. 24.20027268.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grasselli G, Greco M, Zanella A et al. Risk factors associated with mortality among patients with COVID‐19 in intensive care units in Lombardy, Italy. JAMA Inter. Med. 2020; 180: 1345–1355.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7364371</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32667669</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>England N, Improvement N. COVID‐19 Daily Deaths. London: National Health Service England, 2020; 12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alizadeh A, Ansari S, Ranjbar M et al. Seroprevalence of Helicobacter pylori in Nahavand: a population‐based study. EMHJ‐Eastern Mediterranean Health Journal. 2009; 15: 129–135.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19469435</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan A, Farooqui A, Kazmi SU. Presence of Helicobacter pylori in drinking water of Karachi, Pakistan. J. Infect. Dev. Countr. 2012; 6: 251–255.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22421606</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sotoudehmanesh R, Asgari AA, Fakheri HT, Nouraie M, Khatibian M, Shirazian N. Peptic ulcer bleeding: is Helicobacter pylori a risk factor in an endemic area. Indian J. Gastroenterol. 2005; 24: 59–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15879651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malekzadeh R, Sotoudeh M, Derakhshan M et al. Prevalence of gastric precancerous lesions in Ardabil, a high incidence province for gastric adenocarcinoma in the northwest of Iran. J. Clin. Pathol. 2004; 57: 37–42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1770167</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14693833</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holman N, Knighton P, Kar P et al. Risk factors for COVID‐19‐related mortality in people with type 1 and type 2 diabetes in England: a population‐based cohort study. Lancet Diabet. Endocrinol. 2020; 8: 823–833.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7426091</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32798471</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bastos J, Peleteiro B, Pinto H et al. Prevalence, incidence and risk factors for Helicobacter pylori infection in a cohort of Portuguese adolescents (EpiTeen). Dig. Liver Dis. 2013; 45: 290–295.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23266208</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi R, Xu S, Zhang H et al. Prevalence and risk factors for Helicobacter pylori infection in Chinese populations. Helicobacter. 2008; 13: 157–165.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18321305</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yücel T, Aygin D, Şen S, Yücel O. The prevalence of Helicobacter pylori and related factors among university students in Turkey. Jpn. J. Infect. Dis. 2008; 61: 179–183.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18503165</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muhammad JS, Sugiyama T, Zaidi SF. Gastric pathophysiological ins and outs of Helicobacter pylori: a review. J. Pak. Med. Assoc. 2013; 63: 1528–1533.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24397100</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klausz G, Buzás E, Scharek P et al. Effects of Helicobacter pylori infection on gastric inflammation and local cytokine production in histamine‐deficient (histidine decarboxylase knock‐out) mice. Immunol. Lett. 2004; 94: 223–228.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15275970</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan J, Kok K, Zhu Z et al. Genomic characterization of the 2019 novel human‐pathogenic coronavirus isolated from a patient with atypical pneumonia after visiting Wuhan. Emerg. Microb. Infect. 2020; 9: 221–236.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7067204</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31987001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoffmann M, Kleine‐Weber H, Schroeder S et al. SARS‐CoV‐2 cell entry depends on ACE2 and TMPRSS2 and is blocked by a clinically proven protease inhibitor. Cell. 2020; 181: 271–280 e8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7102627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32142651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>