<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39316362</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1559-0305</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Molecular biotechnology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Mol Biotechnol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Development and Validation of a Highly Sensitive RT-qLAMP Assay for Rapid Detection of SARS-CoV-2: Methodological Aspects.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s12033-024-01275-7</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Specific and reliable diagnostic methods are becoming increasingly essential to identify patients in light of the high transmission rate and the recent appearance of the new variants of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2). For the specific detection of SARS-CoV-2, our quantitative reverse transcription loop-mediated isothermal amplification (RT-qLAMP) assay implementation demonstrates how flexible it can be with two readouts: visualized colorimetric and real-time fluorescence. Different factors were optimized to improve the reaction conditions, including temperature (60 °C), assay runtime (60 min), primers, MgSO<sub>4</sub> (6 mM), dNTPs (1 mM), LAMP Buffer (1.2 mM Tris-HCl), KCl (50 mM), pH (8), and phenol red (10 mM) concentrations. Regarding analytical sensitivity, the colorimetric RT-LAMP method detected samples with C<sub>t</sub> values up to 29, while the RT-qLAMP assay identified up to C<sub>t</sub> = 31. RT-qLAMP was evaluated on 40 clinical samples (25 positives and 15 negatives) for viral RNA detection. All negative samples were found negative through fluorescent reading in RT-qLAMP and quantitative reverse transcription PCR (RT-qPCR) assays. Twenty-three clinically positive samples demonstrated a positive RT-qLAMP reaction (up to C<sub>t</sub> ≤ 31) with 92% clinical sensitivity, 100% clinical specificity, 100% positive predictive value (PPV), 88.24% negative predictive values (NPV), and 95% accuracy.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer Science+Business Media, LLC, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mahmoudi</LastName><ForeName>Faezeh</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2360-4240</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Biotechnology, Faculty of Allied Medical Sciences, Iran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, 14496114535, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jafari</LastName><ForeName>Davod</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2796-9597</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Biotechnology, Faculty of Allied Medical Sciences, Iran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, 14496114535, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Esfahani</LastName><ForeName>Seyedeh Mona Mousavi</ForeName><Initials>SMM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3888-5671</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Biotechnology, Faculty of Allied Medical Sciences, Iran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, 14496114535, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hoseini</LastName><ForeName>Arshad</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2077-0817</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Biotechnology, Faculty of Allied Medical Sciences, Iran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, 14496114535, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Barati</LastName><ForeName>Mahmood</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9663-9313</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Biotechnology, Faculty of Allied Medical Sciences, Iran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, 14496114535, Iran. mahmood.barati@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Saraygord-Afshari</LastName><ForeName>Neda</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0732-2750</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Biotechnology, Faculty of Allied Medical Sciences, Iran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, 14496114535, Iran. neda.s.afshari@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>IR.IUMS.REC.1400.5242</GrantID><Agency>Iran University of Medical Sciences</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>ID: 1400-1-5-21079</GrantID><Agency>Iran University of Medical Sciences</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Mol Biotechnol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9423533</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1073-6085</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Diagnostic virology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">RT-qLAMP</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">RT-qPCR</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39316362</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12033-024-01275-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s12033-024-01275-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Safiabadi Tali, S. H., LeBlanc, J. J., Sadiq, Z., Oyewunmi, O. D., Camargo, C., Nikpour, B., Armanfard, N., Sagan, S. M., &amp; Jahanshahi-Anbuhi, S. (2021). Tools and techniques for severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2)/COVID-19 detection. Clinical Microbiology Reviews. https://doi.org/10.1128/cmr.00228-20</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/cmr.00228-20</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33980687</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8142517</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Behera, B. C., Mishra, R. R., &amp; Thatoi, H. (2021). Recent biotechnological tools for diagnosis of corona virus disease: A review. Biotechnology Progress, 37(1), e3078.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/btpr.3078</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32902193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vernet, R., Charrier, E., Grogg, J., &amp; Mach, N. (2021). A quantitative ELISA protocol for detection of specific human IgG against the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein. Vaccines, 9(7), 770.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/vaccines9070770</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34358186</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8309958</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iruretagoyena, M., Vial, M. R., Spencer-Sandino, M., Gaete, P., Peters, A., Delgado, I., Perez, I., Calderon, C., Porte, L., &amp; Legarraga, P. (2021). Longitudinal assessment of SARS-CoV-2 IgG seroconversionamong front-line healthcare workers during the first wave of the Covid-19 pandemic at a tertiary-care hospital in Chile. BMC Infectious Diseases, 21(1), 1–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12879-021-06208-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aileni, M., Rohela, G. K., Jogam, P., Soujanya, S., &amp; Zhang, B. (2022). Biotechnological perspectives to combat the COVID-19 pandemic: Precise diagnostics and inevitable vaccine paradigms. Cells, 11(7), 1182.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/cells11071182</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35406746</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8997755</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alhamid, G., Tombuloglu, H., Motabagani, D., Motabagani, D., Rabaan, A. A., Unver, K., Dorado, G., Al-Suhaimi, E., &amp; Unver, T. (2022). Colorimetric and fluorometric reverse transcription loop-mediated isothermal amplification (RT-LAMP) assay for diagnosis of SARS-CoV-2. Functional &amp; Integrative Genomics, 22(6), 1391–1401.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10142-022-00900-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Y., Odiwuor, N., Xiong, J., Sun, L., Nyaruaba, R. O., Wei, H., &amp; Tanner, N. A. (2020). Rapid molecular detection of SARS-CoV-2 (COVID-19) virus RNA using colorimetric LAMP. MedRxiv 2020.02. 26.20028373</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaibun, T., Puenpa, J., Ngamdee, T., Boonapatcharoen, N., Athamanolap, P., O’Mullane, A. P., Vongpunsawad, S., Poovorawan, Y., Lee, S. Y., &amp; Lertanantawong, B. (2021). Rapid electrochemical detection of coronavirus SARS-CoV-2. Nature Communications, 12(1), 802.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-21121-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33547323</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7864991</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seo, G., Lee, G., Kim, M. J., Baek, S.-H., Choi, M., Ku, K. B., Lee, C.-S., Jun, S., Park, D., &amp; Kim, H. G. (2020). Rapid detection of COVID-19 causative virus (SARS-CoV-2) in human nasopharyngeal swab specimens using field-effect transistor-based biosensor. ACS Nano, 14(4), 5135–5142.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsnano.0c02823</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32293168</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar, R., Yeni, C. M., Utami, N. A., Masand, R., Asrani, R. K., Patel, S. K., Kumar, A., Yatoo, M. I., Tiwari, R., Natesan, S., Vora, K. S., Nainu, F., Bilal, M., Dhawan, M., Emran, T. B., Ahmad, T., Harapan, H., &amp; Dhama, K. (2021). SARS-CoV-2 infection during pregnancy and pregnancy-related conditions: Concerns, challenges, management and mitigation strategies—A narrative review. Journal of Infection and Public Health, 14(7), 863–875.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jiph.2021.04.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34118736</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8062420</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tallei, T. E., Fatimawali, N., &amp; Idroes, R., Zidan, B., Mitra, S., Celik, I., Nainu, F., Ağagündüz, D., Emran, T. B., &amp; Capasso, R. (2021). A comprehensive review of the potential use of green tea polyphenols in the management of COVID-19. Evidence-Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine, 2021, 7170736.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2021/7170736</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34899956</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8664505</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheridan, C. (2020). Fast, portable tests come online to curb coronavirus pandemic. Nature Biotechnology, 38(5), 515–518.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/d41587-020-00010-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32203294</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ravi, N., Cortade, D. L., Ng, E., &amp; Wang, S. X. (2020). Diagnostics for SARS-CoV-2 detection: A comprehensive review of the FDA-EUA COVID-19 testing landscape. Biosensors and Bioelectronics, 165, 112454.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bios.2020.112454</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32729549</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abid, S. A., Muneer, A. A., Al-Kadmy, I. M., Sattar, A. A., Beshbishy, A. M., Batiha, G.E.-S., &amp; Hetta, H. F. (2021). Biosensors as a future diagnostic approach for COVID-19. Life Sciences, 273, 119117.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lfs.2021.119117</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33508293</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7834970</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hossain, M. J., Ahmmed, F., Rahman, S. M. A., Sanam, S., Emran, T. B., &amp; Mitra, S. (2021). Impact of online education on fear of academic delay and psychological distress among university students following one year of COVID-19 outbreak in Bangladesh. Heliyon, 7(6), e07388.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2021.e07388</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34258456</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8255227</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nainu, F., Abidin, R. S., Bahar, M. A., Frediansyah, A., Emran, T. B., Rabaan, A. A., Dhama, K., &amp; Harapan, H. (2020). SARS-CoV-2 reinfection and implications for vaccine development. Human Vaccines &amp; Immunotherapeutics, 16(12), 3061–3073.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/21645515.2020.1830683</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong, Y. P., Othman, S., Lau, Y. L., Radu, S., &amp; Chee, H. Y. (2018). Loop-mediated isothermal amplification (LAMP): A versatile technique for detection of micro-organisms. Journal of Applied Microbiology, 124(3), 626–643.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jam.13647</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29165905</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ben-Assa, N., Naddaf, R., Gefen, T., Capucha, T., Hajjo, H., Mandelbaum, N., Elbaum, L., Rogov, P., King, D. A., Kaplan, S., Rotem, A., Chowers, M., Szwarcwort-Cohen, M., Paul, M., &amp; Geva-Zatorsky, N. (2020). Direct on-the-spot detection of SARS-CoV-2 in patients. Experimental Biology and Medicine (Maywood, N.J.), 245(14), 1187–1193.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1535370220941819</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32668983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chow, F.W.-N., Chan, T.T.-Y., Tam, A. R., Zhao, S., Yao, W., Fung, J., Cheng, F.K.-K., Lo, G.C.-S., Chu, S., Aw-Yong, K. L., Tang, J.Y.-M., Tsang, C.-C., Luk, H.K.-H., Wong, A.C.-P., Li, K.S.-M., Zhu, L., He, Z., Tam, E. W. T., Chung, T.W.-H., &amp; Lau, S.K.-P. (2020). A rapid, simple, inexpensive, and mobile colorimetric assay COVID-19-LAMP for mass on-site screening of COVID-19. International Journal of Molecular Sciences, 21(15), 5380.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms21155380</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32751106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7432162</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thompson, D., &amp; Lei, Y. (2020). Mini review: Recent progress in RT-LAMP enabled COVID-19 detection. Sensors and Actuators Reports, 2(1), 100017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.snr.2020.100017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35047828</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7428436</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chowdhury, K. H., Chowdhury, M. R., Mahmud, S., Tareq, A. M., Hanif, N. B., Banu, N., Reza, A., Emran, T. B., &amp; Simal-Gandara, J. (2020). Drug repurposing approach against novel coronavirus disease (COVID-19) through virtual screening targeting SARS-CoV-2 main protease. Biology (Basel), 10(1), 2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33374717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahmud, S., Paul, G. K., Afroze, M., Islam, S., Gupt, S. B. R., Razu, M. H., Biswas, S., Zaman, S., Uddin, M. S., Khan, M., Cacciola, N. A., Emran, T. B., Saleh, M. A., Capasso, R., &amp; Simal-Gandara, J. (2021). Efficacy of phytochemicals derived from avicennia officinalis for the management of COVID-19: A combined in silico and biochemical study. Molecules, 26(8), 2210.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules26082210</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33921289</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8070553</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rabaan, A. A., Al-Ahmed, S. H., Garout, M. A., Al-Qaaneh, A. M., Sule, A. A., Tirupathi, R., Mutair, A. A., Alhumaid, S., Hasan, A., Dhawan, M., Tiwari, R., Sharun, K., Mohapatra, R. K., Mitra, S., Emran, T. B., Bilal, M., Singh, R., Alyami, S. A., Moni, M. A., &amp; Dhama, K. (2021). Diverse immunological factors influencing pathogenesis in patients with COVID-19: A review on viral dissemination, immunotherapeutic options to counter cytokine storm and inflammatory responses. Pathogens, 10(5), 565.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/pathogens10050565</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34066983</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8150955</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keizerweerd, A. T., Chandra, A., &amp; Grisham, M. P. (2015). Development of a reverse transcription loop-mediated isothermal amplification (RT-LAMP) assay for the detection of Sugarcane mosaic virus and Sorghum mosaic virus in sugarcane. Journal of Virological Methods, 212, 23–29.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jviromet.2014.10.013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25445794</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salm, E., Zhong, Y., Reddy, B., Jr., Duarte-Guevara, C., Swaminathan, V., Liu, Y. S., &amp; Bashir, R. (2014). Electrical detection of nucleic acid amplification using an on-chip quasi-reference electrode and a PVC REFET. Analytical Chemistry, 86(14), 6968–6975.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/ac500897t</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24940939</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4215847</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pian, H., Yang, M., Sun, X., &amp; Zheng, Z. (2022). Sandwich hybridization-based loop-mediated isothermal amplification (SHB-LAMP) for high-throughput detection of malaria RNA from asymptomatic infections. Sensors and Actuators B: Chemical, 365, 131973.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.snb.2022.131973</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alves, P. A., de Oliveira, E. G., Franco-Luiz, A. P. M., Almeida, L. T., Gonçalves, A. B., Borges, I. A., Rocha, F., &amp; d. S., Rocha, R. P., Bezerra, M. F., Miranda, P., Capanema, F. D., Martins, H. R., Weber, G., Teixeira, S. M. R., Wallau, G. L., &amp; do Monte-Neto, R. L. (2021). Optimization and clinical validation of colorimetric reverse transcription loop-mediated isothermal amplification, a fast, highly sensitive and specific COVID-19 molecular diagnostic tool that is robust to detect SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern. Frontiers in Microbiology, 12, 713713.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2021.713713</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34867841</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8637279</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, J., Park, B. G., Lim, D. H., Jang, W. S., Nam, J., Mihn, D.-C., &amp; Lim, C. S. (2021). Development and evaluation of a multiplex loop-mediated isothermal amplification (LAMP) assay for differentiation of Mycobacterium tuberculosis and non-tuberculosis mycobacterium in clinical samples. PLoS ONE, 16(1), e0244753.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0244753</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33406154</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7787462</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, X., Wang, G., Wang, Y., Quan, S., Qi, H., Sun, L., Shen, C., Huang, H., Jiao, W., &amp; Shen, A. (2021). Development and preliminary application of multiplex loop-mediated isothermal amplification coupled with lateral flow biosensor for detection of mycobacterium tuberculosis complex. Frontiers in Cellular and Infection Microbiology, 11, 666492.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2021.666492</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33987108</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8110928</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morris, U., &amp; Aydin-Schmidt, B. (2021). Performance and application of commercially available loop-mediated isothermal amplification (LAMP) kits in malaria endemic and non-endemic settings. Diagnostics (Basel), 11(2), 336.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/diagnostics11020336</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33670618</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hong, Y., Xing, C., Yong, J., Bo, L., &amp; Rongmeng, J. (2021). On chip detection of Zika virus based on loop mediated isothermal amplification. American Journal of Biomedical and Life Sciences, 9(6), 302–306.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.11648/j.ajbls.20210906.16</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tareq, A. M., Emran, T. B., Dhama, K., Dhawan, M., &amp; Tallei, T. E. (2021). Impact of SARS-CoV-2 delta variant (B.1.617.2) in surging second wave of COVID-19 and efficacy of vaccines in tackling the ongoing pandemic. Human Vaccines &amp; Immunotherapeutics, 17(11), 4126–4127</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang, W. E., Lim, B., Hsu, C. C., Xiong, D., Wu, W., Yu, Y., Jia, H., Wang, Y., Zeng, Y., Ji, M., Chang, H., Zhang, X., Wang, H., &amp; Cui, Z. (2020). RT-LAMP for rapid diagnosis of coronavirus SARS-CoV-2. Microbial Biotechnology, 13(4), 950–961.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1751-7915.13586</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32333644</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7264870</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baek, Y. H., Um, J., Antigua, K. J. C., Park, J. H., Kim, Y., Oh, S., Kim, Y. I., Choi, W. S., Kim, S. G., Jeong, J. H., Chin, B. S., Nicolas, H. D. G., Ahn, J. Y., Shin, K. S., Choi, Y. K., Park, J. S., &amp; Song, M. S. (2020). Development of a reverse transcription-loop-mediated isothermal amplification as a rapid early-detection method for novel SARS-CoV-2. Emerging Microbes &amp; Infections, 9(1), 998–1007.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/22221751.2020.1756698</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan, C., Cui, J., Huang, L., Du, B., Chen, L., Xue, G., Li, S., Zhang, W., Zhao, L., Sun, Y., Yao, H., Li, N., Zhao, H., Feng, Y., Liu, S., Zhang, Q., Liu, D., &amp; Yuan, J. (2020). Rapid and visual detection of 2019 novel coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) by a reverse transcription loop-mediated isothermal amplification assay. Clinical Microbiology &amp; Infection, 26(6), 773–779.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmi.2020.04.001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lamb, L. E., Bartolone, S. N., Ward, E., &amp; Chancellor, M. B. (2020). Rapid detection of novel coronavirus (COVID-19) by reverse transcription-loop-mediated isothermal amplification (preprint).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu, L., Wu, S., Hao, X., Dong, X., Mao, L., Pelechano, V., Chen, W.-H., &amp; Yin, X. (2020). Rapid detection of COVID-19 coronavirus using a reverse transcriptional loop-mediated isothermal amplification (RT-LAMP) diagnostic platform. Clinical Chemistry, 66(7), 975–977.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/clinchem/hvaa102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32315390</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Tholoth, M., Bau, H. H., &amp; Song, J. (2020). A single and two-stage, closed-tube, molecular test for the 2019 novel coronavirus (COVID-19) at home, clinic, and points of entry. ChemRxiv</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Momenifar, N., Pirouzfar, M., Hashemian, Z., &amp; Daneshvar Amoli, A. (2023). Development of an optimized RT-LAMP test for the detection of SARS-CoV-2. Biologicals, 84, 101716.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.biologicals.2023.101716</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37801803</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dao Thi, V. L., Herbst, K., Boerner, K., Meurer, M., Kremer, L. P., Kirrmaier, D., Freistaedter, A., Papagiannidis, D., Galmozzi, C., Stanifer, M. L., Boulant, S., Klein, S., Chlanda, P., Khalid, D., Barreto Miranda, I., Schnitzler, P., Kräusslich, H. G., Knop, M., &amp; Anders, S. (2020). A colorimetric RT-LAMP assay and LAMP-sequencing for detecting SARS-CoV-2 RNA in clinical samples. Science Translational Medicine, 12(556), 7075.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/scitranslmed.abc7075</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmidt, J., Berghaus, S., Blessing, F., Wenzel, F., Herbeck, H., Blessing, J., Schierack, P., Rödiger, S., &amp; Roggenbuck, D. (2021). A semi-automated, isolation-free, high-throughput SARS-CoV-2 reverse transcriptase (RT) loop-mediated isothermal amplification (LAMP) test. Science and Reports, 11(1), 21385.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-00827-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, Q., Meyerson, N. R., Clark, S. K., Paige, C. L., Fattor, W. T., Gilchrist, A. R., Barbachano-Guerrero, A., Healy, B. G., Worden-Sapper, E. R., Wu, S. S., Muhlrad, D., Decker, C. J., Saldi, T. K., Lasda, E., Gonzales, P., Fink, M. R., Tat, K. L., Hager, C. R., Davis, J. C., &amp; Sawyer, S. L. (2021). Saliva TwoStep for rapid detection of asymptomatic SARS-CoV-2 carriers. eLife, 10, e65113.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7554/eLife.65113</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33779548</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8057811</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larremore, D. B., Wilder, B., Lester, E., Shehata, S., Burke, J. M., Hay, J. A., Tambe, M., Mina, M. J., &amp; Parker, R. (2021). Test sensitivity is secondary to frequency and turnaround time for COVID-19 screening. Science Advances 7(1), 5393</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>