<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39314195</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1473-2165</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of cosmetic dermatology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Cosmet Dermatol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Impact of Public Health and Social Measures on Cosmetic Treatments in the COVID-19 Pandemic: A Retrospective Multi-Center Study Combined With a Questionnaire-Based Cross-Sectional Study.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/jocd.16563</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Public health and social measures (PHSMs) are considered the most effective approaches for controlling epidemic diseases. This study aimed to explore variations in the time-dependent characteristics of and public preferences for cosmetic treatments during and after the implementation of PHSMs during the COVID-19 pandemic.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHOD" NlmCategory="METHODS">Medical records from six medical institutions were extracted retrospectively. Time-series analyses were conducted to reveal the variations in characteristics in volume and proportion of cosmetic treatments according to PHSMs. A cross-sectional study was conducted with online questionnaire designed for the general population during and after the implementation of PHSMs.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULT" NlmCategory="RESULTS">A total of 141 033 records were included in this retrospective study. The implementation of PHSMs led to extremely low treatment volumes; compared with the increases in private hospitals, the treatment volumes in public hospitals exhibited earlier and more significant increases, even higher than pre-PHSM levels (p &lt; 0.05), which mainly contributed to the increase in plastic surgery volumes during and after the implementation of PHSMs. The differences in the anxiety state, self-perceived appearance, and cosmetic treatment intentions of the participants were illustrated during and after PHSMs. We further demonstrated the participants' decisions on cosmetic treatments after the implementation of PHSMs during the COVID-19 pandemic.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The immediate effects and aftereffects of PHSMs on cosmetic treatments were different in public and private hospitals. Furthermore, as PHSMs guided the adjustment of cosmetic treatments in the post-COVID-19 era, the intention to undergo cosmetic treatment during PHSMs was associated with the anxiety states and preferences of the population.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Journal of Cosmetic Dermatology published by Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Zichao</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Plastic Surgery, Xijing Hospital, Fourth Military Medical University, Xi'an, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Tian</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8281-4459</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Basic Medicine, Fourth Military Medical University, Xi'an, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Leyang</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Plastic Surgery, Xijing Hospital, Fourth Military Medical University, Xi'an, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhu</LastName><ForeName>Yifu</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Plastic Surgery, Xijing Hospital, Fourth Military Medical University, Xi'an, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yu</LastName><ForeName>Zhou</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Plastic Surgery, Xijing Hospital, Fourth Military Medical University, Xi'an, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Song</LastName><ForeName>Baoqiang</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4771-5201</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Plastic Surgery, Xijing Hospital, Fourth Military Medical University, Xi'an, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>82072182</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2020SF-179</GrantID><Agency>Shanxi Science and Technology Coordination and Innovation Project Grants</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Cosmet Dermatol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101130964</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1473-2130</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19 pandemic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">anxiety states</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cosmetic treatment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">public health and social measures</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">questionnaire‐based study</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">time–series analysis</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39314195</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jocd.16563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>D. Shome, S. Vadera, S. R. Male, and R. Kapoor, “Does Taking Selfies Lead to Increased Desire to Undergo Cosmetic Surgery,” Journal of Cosmetic Dermatology 19, no. 8 (2020): 2025–2032.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Zhou, X. L. Yang, X. G. Wang, et al., “Addendum: A Pneumonia Outbreak Associated With a New Coronavirus of Probable Bat Origin,” Nature 588, no. 7836 (2020): E6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Chen, N. Li, J. Lourenço, et al., “Measuring the Effects of COVID‐19‐Related Disruption on Dengue Transmission in Southeast Asia and Latin America: A Statistical Modelling Study,” Lancet Infectious Diseases 22, no. 5 (2022): 657–667.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Søreide, J. Hallet, J. B. Matthews, et al., “Immediate and Long‐Term Impact of the COVID‐19 Pandemic on Delivery of Surgical Services,” British Journal of Surgery 107, no. 10 (2020): 1250–1261.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Joji, N. Patel, N. Nugent, et al., “Aesthetic Surgery Practice Resumption in the United Kingdom During the COVID‐19 Pandemic,” Aesthetic Surgery Journal 42, no. 4 (2021): 435–443.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Kaye, F. Paprottka, R. Escudero, et al., “Elective, Non‐urgent Procedures and Aesthetic Surgery in the Wake of SARS‐COVID‐19: Considerations Regarding Safety,” Feasibility and Impact on Clinical Management, Aesthetic Plastic Surgery 44, no. 3 (2020): 1014–1042.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. C. D. Silva, K. M. Zamprogna, S. S. Souza, D. H. Silva, and D. Sell, “Social Isolation and the Speed of Covid‐19 Cases: Measures to Prevent Transmission,” Revista Gaúcha de Enfermagem 42 (2021): e20200238.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. D. Haug, G. Lekakis, M. Bussi, et al., “Rhinosurgery During and After the COVID‐19 Pandemic: International Consensus Conference Statement on Preliminary Perioperative Safety Measures,” Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery 147, no. 5 (2021): 1087–1095.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Chellamuthu, J. S. Kumar, and B. A. Ramesh, “Impact of COVID ‐19 Pandemic on Plastic Surgery Practices in a Tertiary Care Set Up in Southern India,” Nigerian Journal of Clinical Practice 24, no. 10 (2021): 1558–1564.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Hernández‐Vásquez, F. Chavez‐Ecos, A. Barrenechea‐Pulache, D. Comandé, and G. Bendezu‐Quispe, “Seroprevalence and Lethality by SARS‐CoV‐2 in Indigenous Populations of Latin America and the Caribbean: A Systematic Review,” PeerJ 9 (2021): e12552.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. K. Boparai, S. Singh, and P. Kathuria, “How to Design and Validate A Questionnaire: A Guide,” Current Clinical Pharmacology 13, no. 4 (2018): 210–215.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. L. Crichton, E. K. Dudgeon, A. Shoemark, and J. D. Chalmers, “Validation of the Bronchiectasis Impact Measure (BIM): A Novel Patient‐Reported Outcome Measure,” European Respiratory Journal 57, no. 5 (2021): 2003156.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Cui, A. He, X. Wang, Y. Wang, X. Huang, and Z. Ni, “Development and Validation of a Competency Evaluation Model for Hospital Infection Prevention and Control Practitioners in the Post‐Pandemic Era: A Mixed Methods Study,” Journal of Hospital Infection 119 (2022): 132–140.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. I. Park, “Development and Validation of a Knowledge, Attitudes and Practices Questionnaire on COVID‐19 (KAP COVID‐19),” International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 18, no. 14 (2021): 7493.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Dong, Z. Yu, W. Liu, et al., “Impact of COVID‐19 Social Distancing on Medical Research From the Perspective of Postgraduate Students: A Cross‐Sectional Online Survey,” PeerJ 10 (2022): e13384.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. Mai, Y. Ren, X. Tian, et al., “Comparison of Common Human Respiratory Pathogens Among Hospitalized Children Aged ≤6 Years in Hainan Island, China, During Spring and Early Summer in 2019–2021,” Journal of Medical Virology 95 (2023): e28692.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Oral and A. Gunlu, “Adaptation of the Social Distancing Scale in the Covid‐19 Era: Its Association With Depression, Anxiety, Stress, and Resilience in Turkey,” International Journal of Mental Health and Addiction 20, no. 3 (2022): 1336–1353.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. B. Verhagen, G. SenthilKumar, T. Jaraczewski, et al., “Severity of Prior COVID‐19 Infection Is Associated With Postoperative Outcomes Following Major Inpatient Surgery,” medRxiv 2023, https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.04.12.23288412.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Machida, Y. Nishioka, T. Noda, and T. Imamura, “Research Note Changes in the Number of Outpatient Visits in Japan During the COVID‐19 Pandemic,” BMC Research Notes 16, no. 1 (2023): 70.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Gunlu, “Development of Social Distancing Phobia Scale and Its Association With Anxiety and Perceived Stress,” International Journal of Mental Health and Addiction 21, no. 1 (2023): 617–637.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. E. Riggs, P. M. Grant, D. Perivoliotis, and A. T. Beck, “Assessment of Cognitive Insight: A Qualitative Review,” Schizophrenia Bulletin 38, no. 2 (2012): 338–350.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Babadi, M. Fereidooni‐Moghadam, B. Dashtbozorgi, and B. Cheraghian, “Investigating Psychosocial Causes of the Tendency for Facial Cosmetic Surgery,” Aesthetic Plastic Surgery 42, no. 4 (2018): 1157–1163.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. M. Wimalawansa, J. P. Fox, and R. M. Johnson, “The Measurable Cost of Complications for Outpatient Cosmetic Surgery in Patients With Mental Health Diagnoses,” Aesthetic Surgery Journal 34, no. 2 (2014): 306–316.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Salehahmadi and S. R. Rafie, “Factors Affecting Patients Undergoing Cosmetic Surgery in Bushehr, Southern Iran,” World Journal of Plastic Surgery 1, no. 2 (2012): 99–106.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. J. Nold, R. L. Beamer, S. D. Helmer, and M. F. McBoyle, “Factors Influencing a woman's Choice to Undergo Breast‐Conserving Surgery Versus Modified Radical Mastectomy,” American Journal of Surgery 180, no. 6 (2000): 413–418.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. J. Paprottka, S. B. Rolfes, D. F. Richter, and K. O. Kaye, “COVID‐19 Pandemic: Evaluation of Socio‐Economic Impact on Aesthetic Plastic Surgery Providers,” Aesthetic Plastic Surgery 45, no. 4 (2021): 1877–1887.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>