<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39319948</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1678-4464</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>40</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cadernos de saude publica</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cad Saude Publica</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Biotechnological sovereignty is not a mere nationalist concept, it is a necessity for Colombia and Latin America.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e00202323</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e00202323</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e00202323</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1590/0102-311XEN202323</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0102-311X2024000901200</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>During the pandemic, Latin American countries suffered the collapse of their health systems. This was caused by the high demand for care of patients infected with SARS-CoV-2, which was added to the care of patients with other diseases. The significant increase in demand for health services caused medical and laboratory supplies to decline rapidly. The COVID-19 pandemic exacerbated a health crisis in several developing countries, mainly caused by insufficient systematic policies for integrating scientific knowledge. The current Colombian government must formulate a Biotechnological or Biosecurity Sovereignty Law that guarantees scientific autonomy, ensuring that Colombia is self-sufficient in Science, Technology, and Innovation. Colombian government should also focus on establishing and developing pharmaceutical chemical production by acquiring active chemical ingredients from other countries. This strategy could reduce the production costs and final prices of medicines, as well as generate high-level employment and wealth for the country. In this way, the Colombian government could prevent shortage of essential medicines and excessive price increases by commercial intermediation. In conclusion, the manuscript focuses on the lack of biotechnological sovereignty in Colombia. We propose a model of a Latin American Science and Technology ecosystem to achieve biotechnological sovereignty via state funding of research, strengthening universities, and fostering participation among private companies and Ministries of Science, Education, Trade, and Health. Scientific autonomy based on innovative processes that strengthen biotechnological independence can contribute to the economy by generating gross added value, creating high-quality employment, and facilitating the appropriation and social dissemination of knowledge, and cost reduction.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Guzman</LastName><ForeName>Camilo</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5616-1071</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Instituto de Investigaciones Biológicas del Trópico, Universidad de Córdoba, Montería, Colombia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mattar</LastName><ForeName>Salim</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0526-4630</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Instituto de Investigaciones Biológicas del Trópico, Universidad de Córdoba, Montería, Colombia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alvis-Guzman</LastName><ForeName>Nelson</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9458-864X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Alzak Foundation, Cartagena de Indias, Colombia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Universidad de Cartagena, Cartagena de Indias, Colombia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hoz</LastName><ForeName>Fernando De la</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9436-7935</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Departamento de Salud Pública, Universidad Nacional de Colombia, Bogotá, Colombia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Arias</LastName><ForeName>Edgar</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8371-4102</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Instituto Nacional de Salud, Bogotá, Colombia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>20</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Brazil</Country><MedlineTA>Cad Saude Publica</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8901573</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0102-311X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003105" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Colombia</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007843" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Latin America</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001709" MajorTopicYN="Y">Biotechnology</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000331" MajorTopicYN="N">legislation &amp; jurisprudence</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="spa"><AbstractText>Durante la pandemia, los países latinoamericanos vieron colapsar sus sistemas de salud. Esto se debió a la alta demanda de atención para las personas contagiadas con SARS-CoV-2 y a la atención de pacientes con otros tipos de enfermedades. El aumento significativo de la demanda de los servicios de salud llevó a la rápida disminución de los suministros médicos y de laboratorio. La pandemia de la COVID-19 intensificó la crisis sanitaria en los países en desarrollo, principalmente por una política sistemática e insuficiente de apropiación del conocimiento científico. Si el actual gobierno colombiano formulara una Ley de Soberanía Biotecnológica o de Bioseguridad por la cual se garantizaría la autonomía científica, esto conduciría a una autonomía de Colombia en Ciencia, Tecnología e Innovación. El Gobierno de Colombia también debería centrarse en fomentar y desarrollar la producción de productos químicos farmacéuticos mediante el abastecimiento de ingredientes químicos activos de otros países. Esta estrategia favorece la reducción de costos de producción y del precio final de los medicamentos, además de generar empleos de alto nivel y riqueza para el país. De esta manera, no habría escasez de medicamentos esenciales, ni alzas excesivas de precios en la intermediación comercial. Pero, la realidad es que hay una débil soberanía biotecnológica en Colombia. En este texto se propone un modelo de ecosistema basado en Ciencia y Tecnología para que Latinoamérica logre la soberanía biotecnológica mediante el financiamiento estatal a la investigación en universidades, con la participación de entidades privadas y Ministerios de Ciencia, Educación, Comercio y Salud. La autonomía científica se basa en procesos de innovación que implican el fortalecimiento de la autonomía biotecnológica.</AbstractText></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="por"><AbstractText>Durante a pandemia, os países latino-americanos sofreram o colapso de seus sistemas de saúde. Isso foi causado pela alta demanda de atendimento aos infectados pelo SARS-CoV-2, que somou-se, em paralelo, ao atendimento de pacientes com outros tipos de doenças. O aumento significativo na demanda por serviços de saúde levou à rápida diminuição dos suprimentos médicos e laboratoriais. A pandemia de COVID-19 acelerou, nos países em desenvolvimento, uma crise sanitária causada principalmente por uma política sistemática e insuficiente de apropriação do conhecimento científico. O atual governo colombiano deve formular uma Lei de Soberania Biotecnológica ou de Biossegurança que garanta a autonomia científica, o que leva à autonomia que garante que a Colômbia seja autossuficiente em Ciência, Tecnologia e Inovação. O governo da Colômbia também deve se concentrar em estabelecer e desenvolver a produção de produtos químicos farmacêuticos, adquirindo ingredientes químicos ativos de outros países. Essa estratégia reduz os custos de produção e o preço final dos medicamentos, além de gerar empregos de alto nível e riqueza para o país. Desta forma, não haveria escassez de medicamentos essenciais, nem estaríamos sujeitos a aumentos excessivos de preços por intermediação comercial. Em conclusão, o manuscrito foca na fracassada soberania biotecnológica na Colômbia. Propomos um modelo de ecossistema latino-americano de Ciência e Tecnologia para alcançar a soberania biotecnológica por meio do financiamento estatal do fortalecimento da pesquisa das universidades, com a participação de empresas privadas e Ministérios da Ciência, Educação, Comércio e Saúde. A autonomia científica é baseada em processos de inovação que fortalecem a autonomia biotecnológica.</AbstractText></OtherAbstract></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>35</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39319948</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11415050</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/0102-311XEN202323</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0102-311X2024000901200</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Mejia D, Diaz M, Charry A, Enciso K, Ramírez O, Burkart S. "Stay at home": the effects of the COVID-19 lockdown on household food waste in Colombia. Front Psychol. 2021;12:764715–764715.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8581448</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34777172</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Organización Mundial de la Salud  Fondo estratégico. Acceso a medicamentos e insumos de salud de calidad
en las Américas. Informe Anual 2016.  [30/Sep/2023].  
 https://iris.paho.org/handle/10665.2/54849
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guzman C, Mattar S, Alvis-Guzmán N. De la Hoz F The high price that Colombia has paid for its lack of biotechnological sovereignty. Lancet Reg Health Am. 2023;24:100560–100560.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10372890</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37521437</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shang W, Wang Y, Yuan J, Guo Z, Liu J, Liu M. Global excess mortality during COVID-19 pandemic a systematic review and meta-analysis. Vaccines (Basel) 2022;10:1702–1702.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9607451</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36298567</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Msemburi W, Karlinsky A, Knutson V, Aleshin-Guendel S, Chatterji S, Wakefield J. The WHO estimates of excess mortality associated with the COVID-19 pandemic. Nature. 2023;613:130–137.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9812776</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36517599</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cifuentes-Faura J. COVID-19 mortality rate and its incidence in Latin America dependence on demographic and economic variables. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18:6900–6900.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8297293</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34199070</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Worldometer  Reported cases and deaths by country or territory.  [Sep/2023].  
 https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus/#countries
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hill V, Githinji G, Vogels CBF, Bento AI, Chaguza C, Carrington CVF. Toward a global virus genomic surveillance network. Cell Host Microbe. 2023;31:861–873.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9986120</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36921604</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization  WHO guiding principles for pathogen genome data sharing.  [13/Oct/2023].  
 https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240061743
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaddar M, Milstien J, Schmitt S. Impact of BRICS' investment in vaccine development on the global vaccine market. Bull World Health Organ. 2014;92:436–446.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4047809</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24940018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xue Y, Shang L. Towards better governance on biosafety and biosecurity China's advances and perspectives in medical biotechnology legislation. Front Bioeng Biotechnol. 2022;10:939295–939295.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9289183</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35860327</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ávila Jiménez CC. Esto es lo que pagó Colombia por las vacunas contra el
COVID-19. El Tiempo. 2002 Nov 29; https://www.eltiempo.com/salud/covid-19-cuanto-valieron-las-vacunas-en-colombia-721919</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>González CAG, Fonte DM, Rodríguez LL, González AG, Gomes JO. Government strategies in confronting COVID-19 in the republic of Cuba. Work. 2022;73(1):S95–108.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36214020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mercadante E, Paranhos J. Pharmaceutical patent term extension and patent prosecution in Brazil (1997-2018) Cad Saúde Pública. 2022;38:e00043021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35107507</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization  WHO and MPP announce the first transparent, global, non-exclusive
licence for a COVID-19 technology.  [13/Oct/2023].  
 https://www.who.int/news/item/23-11-2021-who-and-mpp-announce-the-first-transparent-global-non-exclusive-licence-for-a-covid-19-technology
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hunter DJ, Abdool Karim SS, Baden LR, Farrar JJ, Hamel MB, Longo DL. Addressing vaccine inequity - COVID-19 vaccines as a global public good. N Engl J Med. 2022;386:1176–1179.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35196425</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gomez-Marin JE. Autonomía farmacéutica y biotecnológica frente a emergencias sanitarias. Infectio. 2020;24:199–200.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Departamento Nacional de Estadística  Pobreza monetaria.  [01/Jun/2023].  
 https://www.dane.gov.co/index.php/estadisticas-por-tema/pobreza-y-condiciones-de-vida/pobreza-monetaria
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharp PA, Patris J. Para una innovación biotecnológica exitosa. El Economista. 2022 Jun 08; https://www.eleconomista.com.mx/opinion/Para-una-innovacion-biotecnologica-exitosa-20220607-0127.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development  Science, Technology, and Innovation Scoreboard.  [30/Sep/2023].  
 https://www.oecd.org/en/data/datasets/science-technology-and-innovation-scoreboard.html
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>United Nations Development Programme  Sustainable Development Goals.  [30/Sep/2023].  
 https://www.undp.org/sustainable-development-goals
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>United Nations Secretary General's High-level Panel on Access to
Medicines  Promoting innovation and access to health technologies.  [30/Sep/2023].  
 http://www.unsgaccessmeds.org/final-report
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan American Health Organization  Special Program, Innovation and Regional Production Platform
(RP).  [30/Sep/2023].  
 https://www.paho.org/en/special-program-innovation-and-regional-production-platform-rp-department-innovation-access
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Bank Group  World Bank Open Data.  [30/Sep/2023].  
 https://data.worldbank.org
.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>