<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39310655</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>8</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Development and Validation of a Malay Version Questionnaire to Evaluate Remote Health Monitoring of COVID-19 via Telehealth Applications: Navigating Telehealth Evolution.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e67579</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e67579</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e67579</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.67579</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Introduction The rapid adoption of telehealth services due to the COVID-19 pandemic has highlighted the necessity for effective tools to evaluate patient experiences. This study developed and validated the Telehealth Usability, Acceptability, and Satisfaction Questionnaire (TUASQ) for virtual COVID-19 Assessment Centres (CACs) in Malaysia, aiming to comprehensively measure usability, acceptability, and satisfaction. Methodology The TUASQ was developed in two phases. Initially, the questionnaire development phase included item generation guided by the Technology Acceptance Model (TAM) and the Health Belief Model (HBM), with feedback from a panel of six experts. Items were refined through Content Validity Index (CVI) - Item-Level Content Validity Index (I-CVI) ≥ 0.82, Scale-Level Content Validity Index (S-CVI) ≥ 0.82, and Content Validity Ratio (CVR ≥ 0.78); and Face Validity Index (FVI) by 10 respondents - Item-Level Face Validity Index (I-FVI) ≥ 0.82 and Scale-Level Face Validity Index (S-FVI ≥ 0.82). The psychometric validation phase involved a cross-sectional study of 705 respondents, recruited through convenience sampling from March to July 2024, to perform Exploratory Factor Analysis (EFA) and Confirmatory Factor Analysis (CFA), followed by reliability testing using Cronbach's alpha, Composite Reliability (CR), and Average Variance Extracted (AVE). Results Content validation showed that most items' I-CVI exceeded 0.82, indicating significant expert consensus on relevance and clarity. The CVR also surpassed the 0.78 threshold, affirming their essential role. Face validation indices generally exceeded 0.80, confirming the questionnaire's clarity and comprehensiveness from the users' perspective. EFA with 250 participants indicated a high Kaiser-Meyer-Olkin Measure of Sampling Adequacy (KMO) of 0.933 and significant Bartlett's test (χ² (136) = 3752.698, p &lt; 0.001), supporting the factorability of the data and extracting three distinct factors. CFA with 455 participants initially showed a poor fit, prompting model adjustments that subsequently improved the fit indices (Root Mean Square Error of Approximation (RMSEA) = 0.076, Standardized Root Mean Square Residual (SRMR) = 0.045, Goodness of Fit Index (GFI) = 0.94, Tucker-Lewis Index (TLI) = 0.96, Comparative Fit Index (CFI) = 0.97). Reliability testing revealed a high internal consistency with Cronbach's alpha of 0.975. CR for each factor exceeded the 0.70 threshold, and the AVE for each factor was above 0.50, indicating good convergent validity. Conclusion The validated TUASQ is a reliable and effective instrument for assessing the experiences of Malaysian patients using virtual CAC. Demonstrating robust psychometric properties through comprehensive validation processes, the TUASQ accurately measures usability, acceptability, and satisfaction, identifying strengths and areas for improvement in telehealth services. This contributes to enhanced care quality and patient satisfaction in the evolving healthcare landscape.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Kannadasan et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kannadasan</LastName><ForeName>Kalaivane</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Social and Preventive Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, Universiti Malaya, Kuala Lumpur, MYS.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dahlui</LastName><ForeName>Maznah</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Research Development and Innovation, Universiti Malaya Medical Centre, Kuala Lumpur, MYS.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mohd Hairi</LastName><ForeName>Farizah</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Social and Preventive Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, Universiti Malaya, Kuala Lumpur, MYS.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Azzeri</LastName><ForeName>Amirah</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Primary Care, Public Health Unit, Universiti Sains Islam Malaysia, Nilai, MYS.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">digital health tools</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">patient satisfaction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">psychometric validation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">questionnaire development and validation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">remote healthcare services</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">telehealth evaluation</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Ethical Committee of Malaysian Research Ethical Committee (MREC) of the Ministry of Health issued approval NMRR ID-22-01180-LQL. Animal subjects: All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>17</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>17</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39310655</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11416739</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.67579</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 outbreak in Malaysia. Elengoe A. Osong Public Health Res Perspect. 2020;11:93–100.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7258884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32494567</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19: prevention and control measures in community. Güner R, Hasanoğlu I, Aktaş F. Turk J Med Sci. 2020;50:571–577.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7195988</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32293835</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Covid impact to public healthcare utilization among urban low-income subsidized community in Klang Valley Malaysia. Yunus SZ, Puteh SE, Ali AM, Daud F. Health Serv Res Manag Epidemiol. 2021;8:23333928211002407.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7975447</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33796627</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Design and validation of a questionnaire to measure patient experience in relation to hospital nursing care. López-Ibort N, Boned-Galán A, Cañete-Lairla M, Gómez-Baca CA, Angusto-Satué M, Casanovas-Marsal JO, Gascón-Catalán A. Nurs Rep. 2024;14:400–412.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10885121</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38391076</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patient-reported experiences and outcomes of virtual care during COVID-19: a systematic review. Bajgain B, Rabi S, Ahmed S, Kiryanova V, Fairie P, Santana MJ. J Patient Rep Outcomes. 2023;7:126.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10692047</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38038800</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patient satisfaction and trust in telemedicine during the COVID-19 pandemic: retrospective observational study. Orrange S, Patel A, Mack WJ, Cassetta J. JMIR Hum Factors. 2021;8:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8103305</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33822736</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The implementation of remote home monitoring models during the COVID-19 pandemic in England. Vindrola-Padros C, Sidhu MS, Georghiou T, et al. EClinicalMedicine. 2021;34:100799.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8008987</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33817610</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Improving patient outcomes through effective hospital administration: a comprehensive review. Bhati D, Deogade MS, Kanyal D. Cureus. 2023;15:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10676194</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38021686</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Development of the telehealth usability questionnaire (TUQ) Parmanto B, Lewis AN Jr, Graham KM, Bertolet MH. Int J Telerehabil. 2016;8:3–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4985278</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27563386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Usage of health belief model (HBM) in health behavior: a systematic review. Anuar H, Shah SA, Abdul Gafor AH, Mahmood MI, Ghazi HF. https://www.researchgate.net/publication/347558135_Usage_of_Health_Belief_Model_HBM_in_Health_Behavior_A_Systematic_Review Malaysian J Med Health Sci. 2020;16:201–209.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Technology acceptance model 3 and a research agenda on interventions. Venkatesh V, Bala H. Decis Sci. 2008;39:273–315.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malay version of the mHealth app usability questionnaire (M-MAUQ): translation, adaptation, and validation study. Mustafa N, Safii NS, Jaffar A, Sani NS, Mohamad MI, Abd Rahman AH, Mohd Sidik S. JMIR Mhealth Uhealth. 2021;9:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7894394</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33538704</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The most used questionnaires for evaluating satisfaction, usability, acceptance, and quality outcomes of mobile health. Hajesmaeel-Gohari S, Khordastan F, Fatehi F, Samzadeh H, Bahaadinbeigy K. BMC Med Inform Decis Mak. 2022;22:22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8793175</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35081953</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A framework for design and usability testing of telerehabilitation system for adults with chronic diseases: a panoramic scoping review. Ghaben SJ, Mat Ludin AF, Mohamad Ali N, Beng Gan K, Singh DK. Digit Health. 2023;9:20552076231191014.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10437210</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37599901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Development and validation of the Digital Health Acceptability Questionnaire. Haydon HM, Major T, Kelly JT, et al. J Telemed Telecare. 2023;29:8–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38007698</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The development of evaluation scale of the patient satisfaction with telemedicine: a systematic review. Du Y, Gu Y. BMC Med Inform Decis Mak. 2024;24:31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10832124</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38303031</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Analyzing and interpreting data from likert-type scales. Sullivan GM, Artino AR Jr. J Grad Med Educ. 2013;5:541–542.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3886444</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24454995</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ABC of content validation and content validity index calculation. Yusoff MSB. Educ Med J. 2019;11:49–54.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ABC of response process validation and face validity index calculation. Yusoff MSB. Educ Med J. 2019;11</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sample size in factor analysis. MacCallum RC, Widaman K, Zhang S, Hong S. Psychol Methods. 1999;4:84–99.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sample size guideline for exploratory factor analysis when using small sample: taking into considerations of different measurement scales. Bujang MA, Ghani PA, Soelar SA, Zulkifli NA. IEEE. 2012;1:5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quality assurance in higher education institutions: exist survey among Universiti Putra Malaysia graduating students. Konting MM, Kamaruddin N, Man NA. https://files.eric.ed.gov/fulltext/EJ1065550.pdf Int Educ Stud. 2009;2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A quantitative approach to content validity. Lawshe CH. https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1744-6570.1975.tb01393.x Pers Psychol. 1975;28:563–575.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Comparison of the performance of varimax and Promax rotations: factor structure recovery for dichotomous items. Finch H. J Educ Meas. 2006;43:39–52.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The state of telehealth before and after the COVID-19 pandemic. Shaver J. Prim Care. 2022;49:517–530.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9035352</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36357058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evaluation of psychometric properties of Thai version telehealth usability questionnaire (T-TUQ) Hirunwiwatkul P, Pongpanich P, Tulvatana W, et al. Int J Telerehabil. 2023;15:6577.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10754239</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38162944</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The telehealth satisfaction scale: reliability, validity, and satisfaction with telehealth in a rural memory clinic population. Morgan DG, Kosteniuk J, Stewart N, O'Connell ME, Karunanayake C, Beever R. Telemed J E Health. 2014;20:997–1003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4457516</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25272141</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Understanding and using patient experience feedback to improve health care quality: systematic review and framework development. Kumah E, Osei-Kesse F, Anaba C. J Patient Cent Res Rev. 2017;4:24–31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6664367</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31413967</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Translation, cross-cultural adaptation, and validation of the Hospital Consumer Assessment of Healthcare Providers and Systems (HCAHPS) into the Malay language. Zun AB, Ibrahim MI, Mokhtar AM, Halim AS, Wan Mansor WN. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2019;16:2054.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6604016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31185665</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adoption of telehealth technologies: an approach to improving healthcare system. Sharma A, Pruthi M, Sageena G. Transl Med Commun. 2022;7:20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9361246</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35967767</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>