<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39310647</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>8</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Challenges, Barriers, and Facilitators in Telemedicine Implementation in India: A Scoping Review.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e67388</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e67388</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e67388</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.67388</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Telemedicine has revolutionized healthcare access by breaking geographical barriers and facilitating remote consultations. The eSanjeevani platform has been pivotal in India, especially during the COVID-19 pandemic. Despite its benefits, implementing telemedicine faces various challenges and barriers. This scoping review aims to identify these challenges, barriers, and facilitators in the Indian context. This review follows the preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses extension for scoping reviews (PRISMA-ScR) guidelines. A comprehensive literature search was conducted using PubMed and Google Scholar to identify studies published between January 2019 and January 2024. Studies on telemedicine adoption, barriers, and facilitators in India were included. Data were extracted and synthesized from 26 quantitative, qualitative, and mixed-methods research studies. Individual-level challenges include limited digital literacy, particularly among older adults and those in rural areas, and health literacy issues. Barriers such as limited smartphone access, unreliable internet connectivity, and socio-cultural preferences for in-person consultations were identified. Facilitators at this level include family involvement, training programs, and community outreach. Provider-level challenges involve a lack of training and concerns about care quality, while barriers include insufficient infrastructure and medico-legal concerns. Facilitators include ongoing training, clear guidelines, and user-friendly telehealth systems. System-level challenges include integrating telemedicine into existing infrastructure and ensuring data security. Barriers include inadequate funding and resistance to change, while facilitators include policy support, investment in infrastructure, and collaborative efforts. Telemedicine holds great potential to enhance remote healthcare access in India, but its successful implementation requires addressing significant challenges and barriers. Strengthening digital infrastructure, enhancing digital literacy, standardizing protocols, and developing clear regulatory frameworks are essential. Collaborative efforts and tailored approaches that respect local cultures can further facilitate telemedicine adoption. Continuous research and public awareness campaigns are necessary to ensure telemedicine's sustainable and effective use in India.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Arora et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Arora</LastName><ForeName>Simran</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Public Health, Indian Institute of Public Health Gandhinagar, Gandhinagar, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huda</LastName><ForeName>Ramesh K</ForeName><Initials>RK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Information Technology, National Institute for Implementation Research on Non-Communicable Diseases, Indian Council of Medical Research, Jodhpur, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Verma</LastName><ForeName>Sakshi</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Public Health, Indian Institute of Public Health Gandhinagar, Gandhinagar, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khetan</LastName><ForeName>Mukti</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biostatistics, National Institute for Implementation Research on Non-Communicable Diseases, Indian Council of Medical Research, Jodhpur, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sangwan</LastName><ForeName>Ramesh K</ForeName><Initials>RK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Epidemiology and Public Health, National Institute for Implementation Research on Non-Communicable Diseases, Indian Council of Medical Research, Jodhpur, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">challenges &amp; barriers</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">esanjeevani</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">facilitators</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">implementation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">telemedicine</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>17</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>17</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39310647</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11414145</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.67388</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>National telemedicine initiatives: essential to healthcare reform. Bashshur RL, Shannon GW, Krupinski EA, et al. Telemed J E Health. 2009;15:600–610.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19534591</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Telemedicine for healthcare: Capabilities, features, barriers, and applications. Haleem A, Javaid M, Singh RP, Suman R. Sens Int. 2021;2:100117.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8590973</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34806053</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Telemedicine in India: Where do we stand? Chellaiyan VG, Nirupama AY, Taneja N. J Family Med Prim Care. 2019;8:1872–1876.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6618173</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31334148</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Telemedicine - meaning, challenges and opportunities. Ittipong K, Watsawee S, Manachai T. Sir Med Jr. 2019;71:246–252.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>JanMitr: Telemedicine History in India.  [
Jun;
2024 
]. 2024. https://www.janmitr.com/history.html. https://www.janmitr.com/history.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Health Mission: Evolution of telemedicine in India: Brief summary.  [
Jun;
2024 
]. 2024. https://www.nhm.gov.in/images/pdf/Telemedicine/Telemedicine.pdf https://www.nhm.gov.in/images/pdf/Telemedicine/Telemedicine.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>eSanjeevani: Telemedicine practice guidelines.  [
Jun;
2024 
]. 2020. https://esanjeevani.mohfw.gov.in/assets/guidelines/Telemedicine_Practice_Guidelines.pdf https://esanjeevani.mohfw.gov.in/assets/guidelines/Telemedicine_Practice_Guidelines.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>eSanjeevani: National telemedicine service.  [
Jun;
2024 
]. 2024. https://esanjeevani.mohfw.gov.in/ https://esanjeevani.mohfw.gov.in/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Telemedicine: an innovative healthcare delivery for tribal in the state of Rajasthan.  [
Jun;
2024 
]. 2024. https://tribal.nic.in/Telemedicine.aspx https://tribal.nic.in/Telemedicine.aspx</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>TIFAC: Current trends in telemedicine in India.  [
Jun;
2024 
]. 2024. https://www.tifac.org.in/images/latestreports/Telemedicine_Study_Report(Final%20version).pdf https://www.tifac.org.in/images/latestreports/Telemedicine_Study_Report(Final%20version).pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19: Challenges and its consequences for rural health care in India. Kumar A, Rajasekharan Nayar K, Koya SF. Public Health Pract (Oxf) 2020;1:100009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7199699</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34171041</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>PRISMA extension for scoping reviews (PRISMA-ScR): checklist and explanation. Tricco AC, Lillie E, Zarin W, et al. Ann Intern Med. 2018;169:467–473.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30178033</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Overview of e-Health initiatives in Rajasthan: An exploratory study. Joshi NK, Bhardwaj P, Suthar P, Jain YK, Joshi V, Singh K. J Family Med Prim Care. 2021;10:1369–1376.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8140245</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34041181</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stakeholders' initial experience with telemedicine services introduced at 13 government medical colleges in Uttar Pradesh, India during the COVID-19 lockdown: a qualitative study. Singh M, Chauhan AS, Mukherjee R, et al. Cureus. 2023;15:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10391304</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37533613</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Exploring doctors' views and challenges in adopting telemedicine in India: A qualitative study. Raheja R, Pani PK. https://yugato.org/index.php/yug/article/pdf/635.pdf YUGATO. 2023;75</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Attitudes and acceptability of children, caregivers, and healthcare providers about using telemedicine for pediatric HIV care in a resource-limited setting. Manglani M, Lala MM, Gabhale Y, Balakrishnan S, Bhuyan K, Rewari BB, Setia MS. PLoS One. 2022;17:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9132320</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35613106</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Telemedicine-a boon to parents of children with health care needs during COVID-19 pandemic: a qualitative study from India. Joseph HB, Kuppusamy S, Mahalik SK, Shetty AP, Das K. Turk Arch Pediatr. 2022;57:526–531.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9524430</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36062440</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teleconsultation for children with developmental disabilities during the coronavirus pandemic: caregivers' experience. Dahake U, Tripathy JP, Choudhary A, Jain S, Bang A, Girish M. Cureus. 2023;15:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10721741</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38106783</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Service users' perception and attitude toward telemedicine-based treatment for substance use disorders: A qualitative study from India. Ghosh A, Mahintamani T, Aswathy PV, et al. Indian J Psychiatry. 2023;65:774–784.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10461579</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37645352</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feasibility, outcomes, and safety of telehepatology services during the COVID-19 pandemic. Verma N, Mishra S, Singh S, et al. Hepatol Commun. 2022;6:65–76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8251420</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34230904</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Is telemedicine a holy grail in healthcare policy: clinicians' and patients' perspectives from an Apex Institution in Western India. Gupta N, Gupta MK, Joshi NK, et al. BMC Health Serv Res. 2023;23:161.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9930698</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36793030</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Telemedicine-assisted stepwise approach of service delivery for substance use disorders in India. Ghosh A, Mahintamani T, B N S, Pillai RR, Mattoo SK, Basu D. Asian J Psychiatr. 2021;58:102582.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9760420</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33607350</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Acceptance of e-consult for Substance Use Disorders during the COVID 19 pandemic: A study from India. Sahu P, Mathur A, Ganesh A, Nair S, Chand P, Murthy P. Asian J Psychiatr. 2020;54:102451.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7557176</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33271730</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Telegenetics: The experience of an Indian center (Centre for Human Genetics) during the COVID-19 pandemic. Rao N, Kanago D, Morris M, Narayan V, Varshney K, Gn S, Bhat M. J Genet Couns. 2021;30:1224–1232.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8657350</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34596296</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Telemedicine as an acceptable model of care in advanced stage cancer patients in the era of coronavirus disease 2019 - an observational study in a tertiary care centre. Adhikari SD, Biswas S, Mishra S, et al. Indian J Palliat Care. 2021;27:306–312.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8428884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34511801</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feasibility and acceptability of teleconsultation during covid-19: a cross-sectional study. Raj M, Rai P, G V L N, Onkar A, Angral S, Varshney S. http://10.25259/IJPC_45_21 Cureus. 2022;14:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9711946</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36465724</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The outlook of doctors toward telemedicine: A cross-sectional study of knowledge, awareness, and attitude in central India. Singh A, Sahoo AK, Dhaneria S, Gupta D. J Family Med Prim Care. 2021;10:3617–3624.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8653445</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34934656</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rural community health workers' readiness for mobile-phone based telemedicine uptake in India. Gandhi P A, Kathirvel S, Chakraborty S. J Rural Med. 2022;17:166–170.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9263958</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35847763</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strength, weakness, opportunities, and threats (swot) analysis of virtual outpatient department under telemedicine department during the COVID-19 pandemic. Saxena V, Bahurupi Y, Mishra A, Singh A, Parate S, Sandhu H. Cureus. 2022;14:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8943442</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35371781</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crossing barriers: Role of a tele-outreach program addressing psychosocial needs in the midst of COVID-19 pandemic. Ravindran S, P LN, Channaveerachari NK, et al. Asian J Psychiatr. 2020;53:102351.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7428763</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32871399</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Video teleconsultation services for persons with epilepsy during COVID-19 pandemic: An exploratory study from public tertiary care hospital in Southern India on feasibility, satisfaction, and effectiveness. Nair PP, Aghoram R, Thomas B, Bharadwaj B, Chinnakali P. Epilepsy Behav. 2021;117:107863.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9760560</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33677363</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A model for sustainable, partnership-based telehealth services in rural India: An early process evaluation from Tuver village, Gujarat. Ramanadhan S, Ganapathy K, Nukala L, Rajagopalan S, Camillus JC. PLoS One. 2022;17:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8757919</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35025902</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Exploring telehealth readiness in a resource limited setting: digital and health literacy among older people in rural India (DAHLIA) Rasekaba TM, Pereira P, Rani G V, Johnson R, McKechnie R, Blackberry I. https://doi.org/10.3390/geriatrics7020028 Geriatrics (Basel) 2022;7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8938771</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35314600</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Utilization and challenges of ‘Swasthya Ingit’ services faced in a district of West Bengal, India: a mixed methods approach. Mondal Mondal, Aparajita &amp; Ray, Kuntala &amp; Basu, Mausumi &amp; Rashid, Mamunur. (2023. MGM Jr Med Sci. 10:675–680.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Physicians experiences with telemedicine during the COVID-19 pandemic in India. Nagaraja V, Ghosh Dastidar B, Suri S, et al. medRxiv. 202402</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doctor consultation through mobile applications in India: An overview, challenges and the way forward. Agarwal N, Biswas B. Healthc Inform Res. 2020;26:153–158.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7278514</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32547812</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Telemedicine-based tobacco treatment model in primary care from a low-resource setting. Santhosh KT, Pant MB, Uzzafar F, Manjunatha N, Kumar CN, Math SB. J Neurosci Rural Pract. 2019;10:690–692.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6984966</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31992906</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Assisted telemedicine model for rural healthcare ecosystem. Raj D, Srikanth T. ACM Web Science Conference. 2021:86–91.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>