<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39329353</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1520-6033</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>27</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Biotechnology progress</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Biotechnol Prog</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>CHO stable pool fed-batch process development of SARS-CoV-2 spike protein production: Impact of aeration conditions and feeding strategies.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e3507</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e3507</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/btpr.3507</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Technology scale-up and transfer are a fundamental and critical part of process development in biomanufacturing. Important bioreactor hydrodynamic characteristics such as working volume, overhead gas flow rate, volumetric power input (P/V), impeller type, agitation regimen, sparging aeration strategy, sparger type, and k<sub>L</sub>a must be selected based on key performance indicators (KPI) to ensure a smooth and seamless process scale-up and transfer. Finding suitable operational setpoints and developing an efficient feeding regimen to ensure process efficacy and consistency are instrumental. In this investigation, process development of a cumate inducible Chinese hamster ovary (CHO) stable pool expressing trimeric SARS-CoV-2 spike protein in 1.8 L benchtop stirred-tank bioreactors is detailed. Various dissolved oxygen levels and aeration air caps were studied to determine their impact on cell growth and metabolism, culture longevity, and endpoint product titers. Once hydrodynamic conditions were tuned to an optimal zone, various feeding strategies were explored to increase culture performance. Dynamic feedings such as feeding based on current culture volume, viable cell density (VCD), oxygen uptake rate (OUR), and bio-capacitance signals were tested and compared to standard bolus addition. Increases in integral of viable cell concentration (IVCC) (1.25-fold) and protein yield (2.52-fold), as well as greater culture longevity (extension of 5 days) were observed in dynamic feeding strategies when compared to periodic bolus feeding. Our study emphasizes the benefits of designing feeding strategies around metabolically relevant signals such as OUR and bio-capacitance signals.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 His Majesty the King in Right of Canada and The Author(s). Biotechnology Progress published by Wiley Periodicals LLC on behalf of American Institute of Chemical Engineers. Reproduced with the permission of the Minister of Innovation, Science, and Economic Development.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Reyes</LastName><ForeName>Sebastian-Juan</ForeName><Initials>SJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Chemical Engineering, Polytechnique Montreal, Quebec, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Human Health Therapeutics Research Centre, National Research Council Canada, Montréal, Quebec, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pham</LastName><ForeName>Phuong Lan</ForeName><Initials>PL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Human Health Therapeutics Research Centre, National Research Council Canada, Montréal, Quebec, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Durocher</LastName><ForeName>Yves</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Human Health Therapeutics Research Centre, National Research Council Canada, Montréal, Quebec, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Henry</LastName><ForeName>Olivier</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2106-1331</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Chemical Engineering, Polytechnique Montreal, Quebec, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>PR-023-1</GrantID><Agency>National Research Council Canada</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>RGPIN-40482021</GrantID><Agency>Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Biotechnol Prog</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8506292</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1520-6033</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">CHO stable pool</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS‐CoV‐2 vaccine antigen</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">bio‐capacitance</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">fed‐batch process development</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">feeding strategy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">oxygen uptake rate</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39329353</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/btpr.3507</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Hacker DL, Balasubramanian S. Recombinant protein production from stable mammalian cell lines and pools. Curr Opin Struct Biol. 2016;38:129‐136. doi:10.1016/j.sbi.2016.06.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stuible M, Gervais C, Lord‐Dufour S, et al. Rapid, high‐yield production of full‐length SARS‐CoV‐2 spike ectodomain by transient gene expression in CHO cells. J Biotechnol. 2021;326:21‐27. doi:10.1016/j.jbiotec.2020.12.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joubert S, Stuible M, Lord‐Dufour S, et al. A CHO stable pool production platform for rapid clinical development of trimeric SARS‐CoV‐2 spike subunit vaccine antigens. Biotechnol Bioeng. 2023;120(7):1746‐1761.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ye J, Alvin K, Latif H, et al. Rapid protein production using CHO stable transfection pools. Biotechnol Prog. 2010;26(5):1431‐1437. doi:10.1002/btpr.469</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anane E, Knudsen IM, Wilson GC. Scale‐down cultivation in mammalian cell bioreactors—the effect of bioreactor mixing time on the response of CHO cells to dissolved oxygen gradients. Biochem Eng J. 2021;166:107870. doi:10.1016/j.bej.2020.107870</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reyes SJ, Durocher Y, Pham PL, Henry O. Modern sensor tools and techniques for monitoring, controlling, and improving cell culture processes. Processes. 2022;10(2):189‐225. doi:10.3390/pr10020189</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang A, Tsang VL, Moore B, et al. Advanced process monitoring and feedback control to enhance cell culture process production and robustness. Biotechnol Bioeng. 2015;112(12):2495‐2504. doi:10.1002/bit.25684</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Opel CF, Li J, Amanullah A. Quantitative modeling of viable cell density, cell size, intracellular conductivity, and membrane capacitance in batch and fed‐batch CHO processes using dielectric spectroscopy. Biotechnol Prog. 2010;26(4):1187‐1199. doi:10.1002/btpr.425</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Downey BJ, Graham LJ, Breit JF, Glutting NK. A novel approach for using dielectric spectroscopy to predict viable cell volume (VCV) in early process development. Biotechnol Prog. 2014;30(2):479‐487. doi:10.1002/btpr.1845</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee HW, Carvell J, Brorson K, Yoon S. Dielectric spectroscopy‐based estimation of VCD in CHO cell culture. J Chem Technol Biotechnol. 2015;90(2):273‐282. doi:10.1002/jctb.4522</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moore B, Sanford R, Zhang A. Case study: the characterization and implementation of dielectric spectroscopy (biocapacitance) for process control in a commercial GMP CHO manufacturing process. Biotechnol Prog. 2019;35(3):e2782. doi:10.1002/btpr.2782</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Justice C, Brix A, Freimark D, et al. Process control in cell culture technology using dielectric spectroscopy. Biotechnol Adv. 2011;29(4):391‐401. doi:10.1016/j.biotechadv.2011.03.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martínez‐Monge I, Comas P, Triquell J, Lecina M, Casablancas A, Cairó JJ. A new strategy for fed‐batch process control of HEK293 cell cultures based on alkali buffer addition monitoring: comparison with O.U.R. Dynamic method. Appl Microbiol Biotechnol. 2018;102(24):10469‐10483. doi:10.1007/s00253‐018‐9388‐4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goldrick S, Lee K, Spencer C, et al. On‐line control of glucose concentration in high‐yielding mammalian cell cultures enabled through oxygen transfer rate measurements. Biotechnol J. 2018;13(4):e1700607. doi:10.1002/biot.201700607</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martínez‐Monge I, Martínez C, Decker M, et al. Soft‐sensors application for automated feeding control in high‐throughput mammalian cell cultures. Biotechnol Bioeng. 2022;119(4):1077‐1090. doi:10.1002/bit.28032</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zalai D, Hevér H, Lovász K, et al. A control strategy to investigate the relationship between specific productivity and high‐mannose glycoforms in CHO cells. Appl Microbiol Biotechnol. 2016;100(16):7011‐7024. doi:10.1007/s00253‐016‐7380‐4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coulet M, Kepp O, Kroemer G, Basmaciogullari S. Metabolic profiling of CHO cells during the production of biotherapeutics. Cells. 2022;11(12):1929‐1950. doi:10.3390/cells11121929</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Templeton N, Dean J, Reddy P, Young JD. Peak antibody production is associated with increased oxidative metabolism in an industrially relevant fed‐batch CHO cell culture. Biotechnol Bioeng. 2013;110(7):2013‐2024. doi:10.1002/bit.24858</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang YM, Hu W, Rustandi E, Chang K, Yusuf‐Makagiansar H, Ryll T. Maximizing productivity of CHO cell‐based fed‐batch culture using chemically defined media conditions and typical manufacturing equipment. Biotechnol Prog. 2010;26(5):1400‐1410.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin J, Takagi M, Qu Y, Yoshida T. Possible strategy for on‐line monitoring and control of hybridoma cell culture. Biochem Eng J. 2002;11(2):205‐209. doi:10.1016/S1369‐703X(02)00028‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dorresteijn RC, Numan KH, de Gooijer CD, Tramper J, Beuvery EC. On‐line estimation of the biomass activity during animal‐cell cultivations. Biotechnol Bioeng. 1996;51(2):206‐214. doi:10.1002/(sici)1097‐0290(19960720)51:2&lt;206::Aid‐bit10&gt;3.0.Co;2‐k</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin J, Takagi M, Qu Y, Gao P, Yoshida T. Metabolic flux change in hybridoma cells under high osmotic pressure. J Biosci Bioeng. 1999;87(2):255‐257. doi:10.1016/S1389‐1723(99)89025‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martínez‐Monge I, Roman R, Comas P, et al. New developments in online OUR monitoring and its application to animal cell cultures. Appl Microbiol Biotechnol. 2019;103(17):6903‐6917.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pappenreiter M, Sissolak B, Sommeregger W, Striedner G. Oxygen uptake rate soft‐sensing via dynamic kLa computation: cell volume and metabolic transition prediction in mammalian bioprocesses. Front Bioeng Biotechnol Adv. 2019;7:195.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wallocha T, Popp O. Off‐gas‐based soft sensor for real‐time monitoring of biomass and metabolism in Chinese hamster ovary cell continuous processes in single‐use bioreactors. Processes. 2021;9(11):2073.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wagner BA, Venkataraman S, Buettner GR. Medicine. The rate of oxygen utilization by cells. Free Radical Biol. 2011;51(3):700‐712.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poulain A, Perret S, Malenfant F, Mullick A, Massie B, Durocher Y. Rapid protein production from stable CHO cell pools using plasmid vector and the cumate gene‐switch. J Biotechnol. 2017;255:16‐27. doi:10.1016/j.jbiotec.2017.06.009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mullick A, Xu Y, Warren R, et al. The cumate gene‐switch: a system for regulated expression in mammalian cells. BMC Biotechnol. 2006;6:43. doi:10.1186/1472‐6750‐6‐43</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lemire L, Pham PL, Durocher Y, Henry O. Practical considerations for the scale‐up of Chinese hamster ovary (CHO) cell cultures. Cell Culture Engineering and Technology. Springer; 2021:367‐400.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garcia‐Ochoa F, Gomez E. Bioreactor scale‐up and oxygen transfer rate in microbial processes: an overview. Biotechnol Adv. 2009;27(2):153‐176.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoshan L, Jiang R, Moroney J, et al. Effective bioreactor pH control using only sparging gases. Biotechnol Prog. 2019;35(1):e2743.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nie L, Gao D, Jiang H, et al. Development and qualification of a scale‐down mammalian cell culture model and application in design space development by definitive screening design. AAPS PharmSciTech. 2019;20(6):1‐10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Möller J, Rodríguez TH, Müller J, et al. Model uncertainty‐based evaluation of process strategies during scale‐up of biopharmaceutical processes. Comput Chem Eng. 2020;134:106693.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tescione L, Lambropoulos J, Paranandi MR, Makagiansar H, Ryll T. Application of bioreactor design principles and multivariate analysis for development of cell culture scale down models. Biotechnol Bioeng. 2015;112(1):84‐97.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mostafa SS, Gu X. Strategies for improved dCO2Removal in large‐scale fed‐batch cultures. Biotechnol Prog. 2003;19(1):45‐51.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitchell‐Logean C, Murhammer DW. Bioreactor headspace purging reduces dissolved carbon dioxide accumulation in insect cell cultures and enhances cell growth. Biotechnol Prog. 1997;13(6):875‐877.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sieblist C, Hägeholz O, Aehle M, Jenzsch M, Pohlscheidt M, Lübbert A. Insights into large‐scale cell‐culture reactors: II. Gas‐phase mixing and CO2 stripping. Biotechnol J. 2011;6(12):1547‐1556.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naciri M, Kuystermans D, Al‐Rubeai M. Monitoring pH and dissolved oxygen in mammalian cell culture using optical sensors. Cytotechnology. 2008;57:245‐250.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heidemann R, Lütkemeyer D, Büntemeyer H, Lehmann J. Effects of dissolved oxygen levels and the role of extra‐and intracellular amino acid concentrations upon the metabolism of mammalian cell lines during batch and continuous cultures. Cytotechnology. 1998;26(3):185‐197.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Restelli V, Wang MD, Huzel N, Ethier M, Perreault H, Butler M. The effect of dissolved oxygen on the production and the glycosylation profile of recombinant human erythropoietin produced from CHO cells. Biotechnol Bioeng. 2006;94(3):481‐494.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Möller J, Bhat K, Riecken K, Pörtner R, Zeng AP, Jandt U. Process‐induced cell cycle oscillations in CHO cultures: online monitoring and model‐based investigation. Biotechnol Bioeng. 2019;116(11):2931‐2943.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu WJ, Lin Y, Mi CL, Pang JY, Wang TY. Progress in fed‐batch culture for recombinant protein production in CHO cells. Appl Microbiol Biotechnol. 2023;107(4):1063‐1075. doi:10.1007/s00253‐022‐12342‐x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Signal: Signal processing. 2014. http://r‐forge.r‐project.org/projects/signal/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu S, Hoshan L, Jiang R, et al. A practical approach in bioreactor scale‐up and process transfer using a combination of constant P/V and vvm as the criterion. Biotechnol Prog. 2017;33(4):1146‐1159. doi:10.1002/btpr.2489</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu J, Tang P, Yongky A, et al. Systematic development of temperature shift strategies for Chinese hamster ovary cells based on short duration cultures and kinetic modeling. Vol 11. Taylor &amp; Francis; 2019:191‐204.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsu WT, Aulakh RP, Traul DL, Yuk IH. Advanced microscale bioreactor system: a representative scale‐down model for bench‐top bioreactors. Cytotechnology. 2012;64(6):667‐678. doi:10.1007/s10616‐012‐9446‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Handlogten MW, Zhu M, Ahuja S. Intracellular response of CHO cells to oxidative stress and its influence on metabolism and antibody production. Biochem Eng J. 2018;133:12‐20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baez A, Shiloach J. Effect of elevated oxygen concentration on bacteria, yeasts, and cells propagated for production of biological compounds. Microb Cell Factories. 2014;13:1‐7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goudar CT, Piret JM, Konstantinov KB. Estimating cell specific oxygen uptake and carbon dioxide production rates for mammalian cells in perfusion culture. Biotechnol Prog. 2011;27(5):1347‐1357.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wiese AG, Pacifici RE, Davies KJ. Transient adaptation of oxidative stress in mammalian cells. Arch Biochem Biophys. 1995;318(1):231‐240. doi:10.1006/abbi.1995.1225</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santa‐Gonzalez GA, Gomez‐Molina A, Arcos‐Burgos M, Meyer JN, Camargo M. Distinctive adaptive response to repeated exposure to hydrogen peroxide associated with upregulation of DNA repair genes and cell cycle arrest. Redox Biol. 2016;9:124‐133. doi:10.1016/j.redox.2016.07.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rish AJ, Drennen JK, Anderson CA. Metabolic trends of Chinese hamster ovary cells in biopharmaceutical production under batch and fed‐batch conditions. Biotechnol Prog. 2022;38(1):e3220. doi:10.1002/btpr.3220</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Velez‐Suberbie ML, Tarrant RD, Tait AS, Spencer DI, Bracewell DG. Impact of aeration strategy on CHO cell performance during antibody production. Biotechnol Prog. 2013;29(1):116‐126.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grein TA, Loewe D, Dieken H, Weidner T, Salzig D, Czermak P. Aeration and shear stress are critical process parameters for the production of oncolytic measles virus. Front Bioeng Biotechnol. 2019;7:78.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xing Z, Lewis AM, Borys MC, Li ZJ. A carbon dioxide stripping model for mammalian cell culture in manufacturing scale bioreactors. Biotechnol Bioeng. 2017;114(6):1184‐1194.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Becker M, Junghans L, Teleki A, Bechmann J, Takors R. The less the better: how suppressed base addition boosts production of monoclonal antibodies with Chinese hamster ovary cells. Front Bioeng Biotechnol. 2019;7:76.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao W, Wang R‐S, Handy DE, Loscalzo J. NAD (H) and NADP (H) redox couples and cellular energy metabolism. Antioxid Redox Signal. 2018;28(3):251‐272.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hosios AM, Vander Heiden MG. The redox requirements of proliferating mammalian cells. J Biol Chem. 2018;293(20):7490‐7498.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Betts J, Warr S, Finka G, et al. Impact of aeration strategies on fed‐batch cell culture kinetics in a single‐use 24‐well miniature bioreactor. Biochem Eng J. 2014;82:105‐116.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pereira S, Kildegaard HF, Andersen MR. Impact of CHO metabolism on cell growth and protein production: an overview of toxic and inhibiting metabolites and nutrients. Biotechnol J. 2018;13(3):1700499. doi:10.1002/biot.201700499</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Synoground BF, McGraw CE, Elliott KS, et al. Transient ammonia stress on Chinese hamster ovary (CHO) cells yield alterations to alanine metabolism and IgG glycosylation profiles. Biotechnol J. 2021;16(7):2100098. doi:10.1002/biot.202100098</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen P, Harcum SW. Effects of elevated ammonium on glycosylation gene expression in CHO cells. Metab Eng. 2006;8(2):123‐132. doi:10.1016/j.ymben.2005.10.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoo DW, Lee SM, Moon SY, Kim IS, Chang CL. Evaluation of conductivity‐based osmolality measurement in urine using the Sysmex UF5000. J Clin Lab Anal. 2021;35(1):e23586.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitsubayashi K, Toma K, Arakawa T. 12‐Cavitas bio/chemical sensors for internet of things in healthcare. In: Mitsubayashi K, Niwa O, Ueno Y, eds. Chemical, Gas, and Biosensors for Internet of Things and Related Applications. Elsevier; 2019:177‐191.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim NS, Lee GM. Response of recombinant Chinese hamster ovary cells to hyperosmotic pressure: effect of Bcl‐2 overexpression. J Biotechnol. 2002;95(3):237‐248.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han YK, Kim YG, Kim JY, Lee GM. Hyperosmotic stress induces autophagy and apoptosis in recombinant Chinese hamster ovary cell culture. Biotechnol Bioeng. 2010;105(6):1187‐1192.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamachi Y, Omasa T. Development of hyper osmotic resistant CHO host cells for enhanced antibody production. J Biosci Bioeng. 2018;125(4):470‐478. doi:10.1016/j.jbiosc.2017.11.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Le H, Kabbur S, Pollastrini L, et al. Multivariate analysis of cell culture bioprocess data—lactate consumption as process indicator. J Biotechnol. 2012;162(2–3):210‐223.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao S, Ahmed W, Mohsin A, Guo M. Continuous feeding reduces the generation of metabolic byproducts and increases antibodies expression in Chinese hamster ovary‐K1 cells. Life. 2021;11(9):945.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weegman BP, Nash P, Carlson AL, et al. Nutrient regulation by continuous feeding removes limitations on cell yield in the large‐scale expansion of mammalian cell spheroids. PLoS One. 2013;8(10):e76611.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horvat J, Narat M, Spadiut O. The effect of amino acid supplementation in an industrial Chinese hamster ovary process. Biotechnol Prog. 2020;36(5):e3001. doi:10.1002/btpr.3001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen D, Kiehl TR, Khattak SF, et al. Transcriptomic responses to sodium chloride‐induced osmotic stress: a study of industrial fed‐batch CHO cell cultures. Biotechnol Prog. 2010;26(4):1104‐1115. doi:10.1002/btpr.398</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu MH, Dimopoulos G, Mantalaris A, Varley J. The effect of hyperosmotic pressure on antibody production and gene expression in the GS‐NS0 cell line. Biotechnol Appl Biochem. 2004;40(Pt 1):41‐46. doi:10.1042/ba20030170</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Omasa T, Higashiyama K, Shioya S, Suga K. Effects of lactate concentration on hybridoma culture in lactate‐controlled fed‐batch operation. Biotechnol Bioeng. 1992;39(5):556‐564. doi:10.1002/bit.260390511</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheikholeslami Z, Jolicoeur M, Henry O. Probing the metabolism of an inducible mammalian expression system using extracellular isotopomer analysis. J Biotechnol. 2013;164(4):469‐478.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan L, Frye CC, Racher AJ. The use of glutamine synthetase as a selection marker: recent advances in Chinese hamster ovary cell line generation processes. Pharm Bioprocess. 2013;1(5):487‐502.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Budge JD, Roobol J, Singh G, et al. A proline metabolism selection system and its application to the engineering of lipid biosynthesis in Chinese hamster ovary cells. Metab Eng Commun. 2021;13:e00179.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carinhas N, Duarte TM, Barreiro LC, Carrondo MJT, Alves PM, Teixeira AP. Metabolic signatures of GS‐CHO cell clones associated with butyrate treatment and culture phase transition. Biotechnol Bioeng. 2013;110(12):3244‐3257. doi:10.1002/bit.24983</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chevallier V, Andersen MR, Malphettes L. Oxidative stress‐alleviating strategies to improve recombinant protein production in CHO cells. Biotechnol Bioeng. 2020;117(4):1172‐1186.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chevallier V, Schoof EM, Malphettes L, Andersen MR, Workman CT. Characterization of glutathione proteome in CHO cells and its relationship with productivity and cholesterol synthesis. Biotechnol Bioeng. 2020;117(11):3448‐3458.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orellana CA, Marcellin E, Schulz BL, Nouwens AS, Gray PP, Nielsen LK. High‐antibody‐producing Chinese hamster ovary cells up‐regulate intracellular protein transport and glutathione synthesis. J Proteome Res. 2015;14(2):609‐618.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dean J, Reddy P. Metabolic analysis of antibody producing CHO cells in fed‐batch production. Biotechnol Bioeng. 2013;110(6):1735‐1747. doi:10.1002/bit.24826</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sellick CA, Croxford AS, Maqsood AR, et al. Metabolite profiling of CHO cells: molecular reflections of bioprocessing effectiveness. Biotechnol J. 2015;10(9):1434‐1445. doi:10.1002/biot.201400664</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sellick CA, Croxford AS, Maqsood AR, et al. Metabolite profiling of recombinant CHO cells: designing tailored feeding regimes that enhance recombinant antibody production. Biotechnol Bioeng. 2011;108(12):3025‐3031. doi:10.1002/bit.23269</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rico J, Nantel A, Pham PL, et al. Kinetic model of metabolism of monoclonal antibody producing CHO cells. Curr Metabolomics. 2018;6(3):207‐217.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Savizi ISP, Maghsoudi N, Motamedian E, Lewis NE, Shojaosadati SA. Valine feeding reduces ammonia production through rearrangement of metabolic fluxes in central carbon metabolism of CHO cells. Appl Microbiol Biotechnol. 2022;106(3):1113‐1126.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chitwood DG, Uy L, Fu W, Klaubert SR, Harcum SW, Saski CA. Dynamics of amino acid metabolism, gene expression, and Circulomics in a recombinant Chinese hamster ovary cell line adapted to moderate and high levels of extracellular lactate. Genes. 2023;14(8):1576.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kirsch BJ, Bennun SV, Mendez A, et al. Metabolic analysis of the asparagine and glutamine dynamics in an industrial Chinese hamster ovary fed‐batch process. Biotechnol Bioeng. 2022;119(3):807‐819. doi:10.1002/bit.27993</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carrillo‐Cocom LM, Genel‐Rey T, Araíz‐Hernández D, et al. Amino acid consumption in naïve and recombinant CHO cell cultures: producers of a monoclonal antibody. Cytotechnology. 2015;67(5):809‐820. doi:10.1007/s10616‐014‐9720‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xing Z, Kenty B, Koyrakh I, Borys M, Pan S‐H, Li ZJ. Optimizing amino acid composition of CHO cell culture media for a fusion protein production. Process Biochem. 2011;46(7):1423‐1429. doi:10.1016/j.procbio.2011.03.014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coronel J, Klausing S, Heinrich C, Noll T, Figueredo‐Cardero A, Castilho LR. Valeric acid supplementation combined to mild hypothermia increases productivity in CHO cell cultivations. Biochem Eng J. 2016;114:101‐109. doi:10.1016/j.bej.2016.06.031</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan X, Dalm C, Wijffels RH, Martens DE. Metabolic characterization of a CHO cell size increase phase in fed‐batch cultures. Appl Microbiol Biotechnol. 2017;101(22):8101‐8113. doi:10.1007/s00253‐017‐8531‐y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bergin A, Carvell J, Butler M. Applications of bio‐capacitance to cell culture manufacturing. Biotechnol Adv. 2022;61:108048. doi:10.1016/j.biotechadv.2022.108048</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Metze S, Blioch S, Matuszczyk J, et al. Multivariate data analysis of capacitance frequency scanning for online monitoring of viable cell concentrations in small‐scale bioreactors. Anal Bioanal Chem. 2020;412:2089‐2102.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reyes SJ, Keebler M, Schulte A, et al. Impact of protein production on metabolic activity of CHO stable cell line producing palivizumab. Kuhner. Accessed 2024‐04‐12, 2024. https://kuhner.com/wAssets/docs/download/Poster/Poster-NRC/TOM_Antibody_Poster-4_NRC-Kuhner.pdf</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>