<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39327677</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1939-1676</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>26</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of veterinary internal medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Vet Intern Med</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Open label clinical trial of orally administered molnupiravir as a first-line treatment for naturally occurring effusive feline infectious peritonitis.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/jvim.17187</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Before the discovery of effective antiviral drugs, feline infectious peritonitis (FIP) was a uniformly fatal disease of cats. Multiple antiviral treatments have been recognized, but optimization of treatment protocols is needed.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To evaluate the efficacy of PO molnupiravir (MPV; EIDD-2801) to treat effusive FIP.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="ANIMALS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Ten cats with naturally occurring effusive FIP and 10 historical control cats with effusive FIP treated with PO GS-441524.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A single-center, prospective, open-label longitudinal, non-inferiority trial with historical controls. Ten cats with FIP were enrolled and treated with PO MPV (10-15 mg/kg PO q12h) for 84 days. Cats were evaluated at 0, 6, and 16 weeks, and the proportion of cats in clinical remission at 16 weeks was determined. Survival and clinicopathologic features were compared with historical control cats with effusive FIP treated with PO GS-441524.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Eight of the 10 cats treated with MPV survived and were in remission at 16 weeks. The 2 non-survivors died in the first 24 hours of treatment. No adverse events that necessitated discontinuation of treatment were observed. Survival of cats treated with PO MPV was non-inferior to historic control cats treated with PO GS-441524 (5/9 [55%] survived), with a difference in survival of 25% (90% confidence interval, -9.3% to 59.3%). Clinicopathologic features associated with FIP normalized during the study period, and no differences in clinicopathologic data at each study time point were observed when comparing cats treated with MPV and GS-441524.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS AND CLINICAL IMPORTANCE" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Molnupiravir is an effective antiviral treatment for effusive FIP.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Journal of Veterinary Internal Medicine published by Wiley Periodicals LLC on behalf of American College of Veterinary Internal Medicine.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Reagan</LastName><ForeName>Krystle L</ForeName><Initials>KL</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3426-6352</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Medicine and Epidemiology, University of California, Davis, School of Veterinary Medicine, Davis, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Brostoff</LastName><ForeName>Terza</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathology, Microbiology, and Immunology, University of California, Davis, School of Veterinary Medicine, Davis, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pires</LastName><ForeName>Jully</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Veterinary Center for Clinical Trials, University of California, Davis, School of Veterinary Medicine, Davis, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rose</LastName><ForeName>Amy</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Veterinary Center for Clinical Trials, University of California, Davis, School of Veterinary Medicine, Davis, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Castillo</LastName><ForeName>Diego</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathology, Microbiology, and Immunology, University of California, Davis, School of Veterinary Medicine, Davis, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Murphy</LastName><ForeName>Brian G</ForeName><Initials>BG</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathology, Microbiology, and Immunology, University of California, Davis, School of Veterinary Medicine, Davis, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>SOCK FIP and Center for Companion Animal Health</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>EC22-007</GrantID><Agency>EveryCat Health Foundation</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Vet Intern Med</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8708660</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0891-6640</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">FIP</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antiviral</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">feline coronavirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">infection</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39327677</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jvim.17187</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Pedersen NC. A review of feline infectious peritonitis virus infection: 1963–2008. J Feline Med Surg. 2009;11:225‐258.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pedersen NC, Sato R, Foley JE, Poland AM. Common virus infections in cats, before and after being placed in shelters, with emphasis on feline enteric coronavirus. J Feline Med Surg. 2004;6:83‐88.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vennema H, Poland A, Foley J, Pedersen NC. Feline infectious peritonitis viruses arise by mutation from endemic feline enteric coronaviruses. Virology. 1998;243:150‐157.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coggins SJ, Norris JM, Malik R, et al. Outcomes of treatment of cats with feline infectious peritonitis using parenterally administered remdesivir, with or without transition to orally administered GS‐441524. J Vet Intern Med. 2023;37:1772‐1783.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cosaro E, Pires J, Castillo D, Murphy BG, Reagan KL. Efficacy of oral remdesivir compared to GS‐441524 for treatment of cats with naturally occurring effusive feline infectious peritonitis: a blinded, non‐inferiority study. Viruses. 2023;15:1680.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murphy BG, Perron M, Murakami E, et al. The nucleoside analog GS‐441524 strongly inhibits feline infectious peritonitis (FIP) virus in tissue culture and experimental cat infection studies. Vet Microbiol. 2018;219:226‐233.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dickinson PJ, Bannasch M, Thomasy SM, et al. Antiviral treatment using the adenosine nucleoside analogue GS‐441524 in cats with clinically diagnosed neurological feline infectious peritonitis. J Vet Intern Med. 2020;34:1587‐1593.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krentz D, Zenger K, Alberer M, et al. Curing cats with feline infectious peritonitis with an oral multi‐component drug containing GS‐441524. Viruses. 2021;13:2228.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Green J, Syme H, Tayler S. Thirty‐two cats with effusive or non‐effusive feline infectious peritonitis treated with a combination of remdesivir and GS‐441524. J Vet Intern Med. 2023;37:1784‐1793.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katayama M, Uemura Y. Prognostic prediction for therapeutic effects of Mutian on 324 client‐owned cats with feline infectious peritonitis based on clinical laboratory indicators and physical signs. Vet Sci. 2023;10:136.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jones S, Novicoff W, Nadeau J, Evans S. Unlicensed GS‐441524‐like antiviral therapy can be effective for at‐home treatment of feline infectious peritonitis. Animals. 2021;11:2257.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pedersen NC, Perron M, Bannasch M, et al. Efficacy and safety of the nucleoside analog GS‐441524 for treatment of cats with naturally occurring feline infectious peritonitis. J Feline Med Surg. 2019;21:271‐281.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roy M, Jacque N, Novicoff W, Li E, Negash R, Evans SJM. Unlicensed molnupiravir is an effective rescue treatment following failure of unlicensed GS‐441524‐like therapy for cats with suspected feline infectious peritonitis. Pathogens. 2022;11:1209.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pedersen NC, Kim Y, Liu H, et al. Efficacy of a 3C‐like protease inhibitor in treating various forms of acquired feline infectious peritonitis. J Feline Med Surg. 2018;20:378‐392.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lv J, Bai Y, Wang Y, Yang L, Jin Y, Dong J. Effect of GS‐441524 in combination with the 3C‐like protease inhibitor GC376 on the treatment of naturally transmitted feline infectious peritonitis. Front Vet Sci. 2022;9:1002488.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cook S, Wittenburg L, Yan VC, et al. An optimized bioassay for screening combined anticoronaviral compounds for efficacy against feline infectious peritonitis virus with pharmacokinetic analyses of GS‐441524, remdesivir, and molnupiravir in cats. Viruses. 2022;14:2429.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sase O. Molnupiravir treatment of 18 cats with feline infectious peritonitis: a case series. J Vet Intern Med. 2023;37:1876‐1880.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lisciandro GR, Lagutchik MS, Mann KA, et al. Evaluation of an abdominal fluid scoring system determined using abdominal focused assessment with sonography for trauma in 101 dogs with motor vehicle trauma. J Vet Emerg Crit Care. 2009;19:426‐437.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lisciandro GR, Lagutchik MS, Mann KA, et al. Evaluation of a thoracic focused assessment with sonography for trauma (TFAST) protocol to detect pneumothorax and concurrent thoracic injury in 145 traumatized dogs. J Vet Emerg Crit Care. 2008;18:258‐269.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pedersen NC, Eckstrand C, Liu H, Leutenegger C, Murphy B. Levels of feline infectious peritonitis virus in blood, effusions, and various tissues and the role of lymphopenia in disease outcome following experimental infection. Vet Microbiol. 2015;175:157‐166.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sealed Envelope Ltd. Power calculator for binary outcome non‐inferiority trial [Online]. Accessed May 17, 2024. https://www.sealedenvelope.com/power/binary-noninferior/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zwicklbauer K, Krentz D, Bergmann M, et al. Long‐term follow‐up of cats in complete remission after treatment of feline infectious peritonitis with oral GS‐441524. J Feline Med Surg. 2023;25. doi:10.1177/1098612X231183250</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanderson T, Hisner R, Donovan‐Banfield I, et al. A molnupiravir‐associated mutational signature in global SARS‐CoV‐2 genomes. Nature. 2023;623:594‐600.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waters MD, Warren S, Hughes C, Lewis P, Zhang F. Human genetic risk of treatment with antiviral nucleoside analog drugs that induce lethal mutagenesis: the special case of molnupiravir. Environ Mol Mutagen. 2022;63:37‐63.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>