<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39329049</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>30</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">0017-8969</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>82</Volume><Issue>7</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Nov</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Health education journal</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Health Educ J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Early and slow weight loss responders' perceptions of an adaptive diabetes prevention trial: A qualitative perspective.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>807</StartPage><EndPage>819</EndPage><MedlinePgn>807-819</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1177/00178969231198956</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Behavioural weight loss interventions demonstrate success on average, yet participants who respond more slowly may benefit from an augmented, tailored approach. Thus, an augmented intervention for early, slow weight loss responders was implemented. This qualitative analysis explored participants' perceptions of and experiences of the 12-month weight loss programme to inform future intervention development and implementation.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DESIGN" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Individual interviews were conducted post-treatment. In-person, in-depth interviews were offered prior to the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) pandemic; videoconferencing interviews were offered following the pandemic onset.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="SETTING" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A Midwestern US university workplace.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHOD" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Adults ⩾21 years old with overweight or obesity and prediabetes (<i>n</i> = 39) were recruited and volunteered to participate in a semi-structured interview.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Content analysis identified recurring themes among early and early slow weight loss responders. Social support received during weekly group sessions was a critical intervention component. Some early slow responders expressed difficulty with self-regulatory strategies such as setting specific yet attainable goals, and requested additional contact prior to the maintenance study phase - treatment randomisation at month 5 disrupted group dynamics. Early slow responders who received the intervention via videoconferencing believed the format interfered with their ability to establish friendships with other participants and gain insight and support from others' lived experiences.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Weight loss interventions may be more efficacious when considering participant heterogeneity during implementation of behavioural strategies. Findings suggest early slow weight loss responders may benefit from greater emphasis on goal setting and striving, agentic thinking, and social support. Future research is needed to examine the implications of these insights on intervention outcomes.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>King</LastName><ForeName>Danielle</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nutrition and Dietetics, SUNY Buffalo State University, Buffalo, NY, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Miller</LastName><ForeName>Carla K</ForeName><Initials>CK</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1002-7288</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Public Health, Indiana University, Bloomington, IN, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cheavens</LastName><ForeName>Jennifer S</ForeName><Initials>JS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychology, Ohio State University, Columbus, OH, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fujita</LastName><ForeName>Kentaro</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychology, Ohio State University, Columbus, OH, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>R01 DK112930</GrantID><Acronym>DK</Acronym><Agency>NIDDK NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>UL1 TR002733</GrantID><Acronym>TR</Acronym><Agency>NCATS NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>13</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Health Educ J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0374646</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0017-8969</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Lifestyle risk reduction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">qualitative research</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">social support</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">type 2 diabetes mellitus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">weight loss</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>7</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>6</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>36</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39329049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="mid">NIHMS2019745</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11423868</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/00178969231198956</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>American Diabetes Association Professional Practice Committee (2022) Classification and diagnosis of diabetes: Standards of medical care in diabetes—2022. Diabetes Care 45(Suppl. 1): S17–S38.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34964875</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonezzi A, Brendl CM and DeAngelis M (2011) Stuck in the middle: The psychophysics of goal pursuit. Psychological Science 22(5): 607–612.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21474842</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borrerro M, Martens P and Gubelman-Borrero G (1979) Toward a theory of accountability. Journal of Sociology &amp; Social Welfare 6: 876–894.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bovend’Eerdt TJ, Botell RE and Wade DT (2009) Writing SMART rehabilitation goals and achieving goal attainment scaling: A practical guide. Clinical Rehabilitation 23(4): 352–361.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19237435</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bradshaw C, Atkinson S and Doody O (2017) Employing a qualitative description approach in health care research. Global Qualitative Nursing Research 4: 2333393617742282–2333393617742288.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5703087</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29204457</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheavens JS, Feldman DB, Gum A, et al. (2006) Hope therapy in a community sample: A pilot investigation. Social Indicators Research 77(1): 61–78.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Creswell J (2014) Research Design: Qualitative, Quantitative, and Mixed Methods Approaches. 4th ed. California: Sage.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Downe-Wamboldt B (1992) Content analysis: Method, applications, and issues. Health Care for Women International 13(3): 313–321.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1399871</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Etikan I (2016) Comparison of convenience sampling and purposive sampling. American Journal of Theoretical and Applied Statistics 5(1): 1–4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galletta A (2013) Mastering the Semi-Structured Interview and beyond. New York: New York University Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gorin AA, Powers TA, Gettens K, et al. (2020) A randomized controlled trial of a theory-based weight-loss program for couples. Health Psychology 39(2): 137–146.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6957719</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31789558</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>James BL, Roe LS, Loken E, et al. (2018) Early predictors of weight loss in a 1-year behavioural weight-loss programme. Obesity Science &amp; Practice 4(1): 20–28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5818734</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29479461</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jensen MD and Ryan DH (2014) New obesity guidelines: Promise and potential. JAMA 311(1): 23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24381963</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jessen-Winge C, Ilvig PM, Fritz H, et al. (2021) What a weight loss programme should contain if people with obesity were asked – a qualitative analysis within the DO:IT study. BMC Public Health 21(1): 28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7789717</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33407271</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knowler W, Barrett-Connor E, Fowler S, et al. (2002) Reduction in the incidence of type 2 diabetes with lifestyle intervention or metformin. New England Journal of Medicine 346(6): 393–403.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1370926</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11832527</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kramer MK, Kriska AM, Venditti EM, et al. (2009) Translating the diabetes prevention program: A comprehensive model for prevention training and program delivery. American Journal of Preventive Medicine 37(6): 505–511.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19944916</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Langford CPH, Bowsher J, Maloney JP, et al. (1997) Social support: A conceptual analysis. Journal of Advanced Nursing 25(1): 95–100.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9004016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Latham GP and Locke EA (1991) Self-regulation through goal setting. Organizational Behavior and Human Decision Processes 50(2): 212–247.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mann T, deRidder D and Fujita K (2013) Self-regulation of health behavior: Social psychological approaches to goal setting and goal striving. Health Psychology: Official Journal of the Division of Health Psychology, American Psychological Association 32(5): 487–498.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23646832</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McGill B, O’Hara BJ, Phongsavan P, et al. (2020) ‘I’m still on track’: A qualitative exploration of participant experiences of a weight loss maintenance program. Healthcare 8(1): 1–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7151193</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31963312</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miller CK, Nagaraja HN and Weinhold KR (2015) Early weight-loss success identifies nonresponders after a lifestyle intervention in a worksite diabetes prevention trial. Journal of the Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics 115(9): 1464–1471.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4554978</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26095435</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miller CK, Pawelczyk K, Cheavens JS, et al. (2017) Development and pilot testing of a novel behavioral intervention for adults with type 2 diabetes using intervention mapping. Health Psychology and Behavioral Medicine 5(1): 317–336.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miller CK, Nagaraja HN, Cheavens JS, et al. (2022) Impact of a novel diabetes prevention intervention for early weight loss responders among adults with prediabetes: An adaptive trial. Diabetes Care 45(10): 2452–2455.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9643139</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36041053</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miller CK, King D, Nagaraja HN, et al. (2023) Impact of an augmented intervention on self-regulatory, dietary and physical activity outcomes in a diabetes prevention trial among adults with prediabetes. Journal of Behavioral Medicine. Epub ahead of print 18 March. DOI: 10.1007/s10865-023-00406-w.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10865-023-00406-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10024518</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36933057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Connor C and Joffe H (2020) Intercoder reliability in qualitative research: Debates and practical guidelines. International Journal of Qualitative Methods 19: 1–13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reyes NR, Oliver TL, Klotz AA, et al. (2012) Similarities and differences between weight loss maintainers and regainers: A qualitative analysis. Journal of the Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics 112(4): 499–505.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22709701</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shumaker SA and Brownell A (1984) Toward a theory of social support: Closing conceptual gaps. Journal of Social Issues 40(4): 11–36.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Snyder CR, Harris C, Anderson JR, et al. (1991) The will and the ways: Development and validation of an individual-differences measure of hope. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology 60(4): 570–585.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2037968</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Snyder R (2011) Handbook of Hope: Theory, Measures, &amp; Applications. San Diego, CA: Academic Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spring B, Pfammatter AF, Marchese SH, et al. (2020) A factorial experiment to optimize remotely delivered behavioral treatment for obesity: Results of the Opt-IN study. Obesity (Silver Spring, Md.) 28(9): 1652–1662.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8045468</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32656994</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tong A, Sainsbury P and Craig J (2007) Consolidated criteria for reporting qualitative research (COREQ): A 32-item checklist for interviews and focus groups. International Journal for Quality in Health Care: Journal of the International Society for Quality in Health Care 19(6): 349–357.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17872937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Unick JL, Hogan PE, Neiberg RH, et al. (2014) Evaluation of early weight loss thresholds for identifying nonresponders to an intensive lifestyle intervention: Initial weight loss and 1-year outcomes. Obesity 22(7): 1608–1616.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4077939</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24771618</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walton GM, Cohen GL, Cwir D, et al. (2012) Mere belonging: The power of social connections. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology 102(3): 513–532.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22023711</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wing RR and Jeffery RW (1999) Benefits of recruiting participants with friends and increasing social support for weight loss and maintenance. Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology 67(1): 132–138.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10028217</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>