<PubmedArticle xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39333667</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>30</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2045-2322</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>14</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>27</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Scientific reports</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Sci Rep</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A simulation-based analysis of optical read-out for electrochemical reactions using composite vortex beams.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>22218</StartPage><MedlinePgn>22218</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">22218</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1038/s41598-024-72701-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>We propose an optical read-out method for extracting faradaic current in electrochemical (EC) reactions and analyze its performance using opto-EC simulations. Our approach utilizes structured electrodes to generate composite optical vortex (COV) beams upon optical illumination. Through opto-EC simulations, we demonstrate that the EC reaction of 10 mM potassium ferricyanide induces a refractive index (RI) change, <ns0:math><ns0:mi>Δ</ns0:mi></ns0:math> RI, of approximately <ns0:math><ns0:msup><ns0:mn>10</ns0:mn> <ns0:mrow><ns0:mo>-</ns0:mo> <ns0:mn>4</ns0:mn></ns0:mrow> </ns0:msup> </ns0:math> RI units, leading to the rotation of the COV beam's intensity profile with a peak rotation of <ns0:math><ns0:msup><ns0:mn>40</ns0:mn> <ns0:mo>∘</ns0:mo></ns0:msup> </ns0:math> . This rotation's magnitude is proportional to <ns0:math><ns0:mi>Δ</ns0:mi></ns0:math> RI, while the rate correlates with the faradaic current ( <ns0:math><ns0:msub><ns0:mi>I</ns0:mi> <ns0:mi>f</ns0:mi></ns0:msub> </ns0:math> ) density responsible for <ns0:math><ns0:mi>Δ</ns0:mi></ns0:math> RI. As the opto-EC information is from bulk <ns0:math><ns0:mi>Δ</ns0:mi></ns0:math> RI, it remains unaffected by interfering non-faradaic components at the interface and is advantageous for studying intermediate species and bulk homogeneous reactions. Furthermore, as rotation depends on <ns0:math><ns0:msub><ns0:mi>I</ns0:mi> <ns0:mi>f</ns0:mi></ns0:msub> </ns0:math> density rather than <ns0:math><ns0:msub><ns0:mi>I</ns0:mi> <ns0:mi>f</ns0:mi></ns0:msub> </ns0:math> itself, this method proves beneficial in low <ns0:math><ns0:msub><ns0:mi>I</ns0:mi> <ns0:mi>f</ns0:mi></ns0:msub> </ns0:math> scenarios, such as when employing micro-electrodes to decrease solution resistance or obtain localized EC data. Even in low <ns0:math><ns0:msub><ns0:mi>I</ns0:mi> <ns0:mi>f</ns0:mi></ns0:msub> </ns0:math> density scenarios, like monitoring slow EC reactions, our method enables signal amplification by accumulating rotation over time. This interdisciplinary approach holds promise for advancing EC research and addressing critical challenges across various fields, including energy storage, corrosion protection, environmental remediation, and biomedical sciences.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kumar</LastName><ForeName>Nirjhar</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for NEMS &amp; Nanophotonics CNNP and Department of Electrical Engineering, Indian Institute of Technology Madras, Chennai, 600036, India. kr.nirjhar@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Arora</LastName><ForeName>Ankit</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for NEMS &amp; Nanophotonics CNNP and Department of Electrical Engineering, Indian Institute of Technology Madras, Chennai, 600036, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Krishnan</LastName><ForeName>Ananth</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for NEMS &amp; Nanophotonics CNNP and Department of Electrical Engineering, Indian Institute of Technology Madras, Chennai, 600036, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Sci Rep</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101563288</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2045-2322</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>56</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39333667</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11437161</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-72701-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1038/s41598-024-72701-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Bard, A. J., Faulkner, L. R., Leddy, J. &amp; Zoski, C. G. Electrochemical Methods: Fundamentals and Applications, 2 edn (Wiley, 1980).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Mari, O. &amp; Vullev, V. I. Electrochemical analysis in charge-transfer science: The devil in the details. Curr. Opin. Electrochem.31, 100862 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8765593</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35059527</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bockris, J. O., Reddy, A. K. N. &amp; Gamboa-Aldeco, M. Modern Electrochemistry 2A Fundamentals of Electrodics, 2 edn (Springer, 2007).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Compton, R. G., Laborda, E. &amp; Ward, K. R. Understanding Voltammetry: Simulation of Electrode Processes, 1 edn (Imperial College Press, 2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, X. et al. Electrode material-ionic liquid coupling for electrochemical energy storage. Nat. Rev. Mater.5, 787–808 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simon, P. &amp; Gogotsi, Y. Perspectives for electrochemical capacitors and related devices. Nat. Mater.19, 1151–1163 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32747700</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venkatesan, S. V., Nandy, A., Karan, K., Larter, S. R. &amp; Thangadurai, V. Recent advances in the unconventional design of electrochemical energy storage and conversion devices. Electrochem. Energy Rev.5, 16 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tasić, ŽZ., Petrović Mihajlović, M. B., Radovanović, M. B. &amp; Antonijević, M. M. New trends in corrosion protection of copper. Chem. Pap.73, 2103–2132 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goyal, A., Pouya, H. S., Ganjian, E. &amp; Claisse, P. A review of corrosion and protection of steel in concrete. Arab. J. Sci. Eng.43, 5035–5055 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xia, D.-H. et al. Electrochemical measurements used for assessment of corrosion and protection of metallic materials in the field: A critical review. J. Mater. Sci. Technol.112, 151–183 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodrigo, M., Oturan, N. &amp; Oturan, M. A. Electrochemically assisted remediation of pesticides in soils and water: A review. Chem. Rev.114, 8720–8745 (2014).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24983494</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lacasa, E. et al. Environmental applications of electrochemical technology. What is needed to enable full-scale applications?. Curr. Opin. Electrochem.16, 149–156 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murtaza, G. et al. Recent trends and economic significance of modified/functionalized biochars for remediation of environmental pollutants. Sci. Rep.14, 217 (2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10762257</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38167973</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, J., Liu, H., Chen, W., Ma, B. &amp; Ju, H. Device integration of electrochemical biosensors. Nat. Rev. Bioeng.1, 346–360 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9951169</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37168735</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh, A. et al. Recent advances in electrochemical biosensors: Applications, challenges, and future scope. Biosensors11, 336 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8472208</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34562926</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nemčeková, K. &amp; Labuda, J. Advanced materials-integrated electrochemical sensors as promising medical diagnostics tools: A review. Mater. Sci. Eng. C120, 111751 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33545892</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baranwal, J., Barse, B., Gatto, G., Broncova, G. &amp; Kumar, A. Electrochemical sensors and their applications: A review. Chemosensors10, 363 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh, R., Gupta, R., Bansal, D., Bhateria, R. &amp; Sharma, M. A review on recent trends and future developments in electrochemical sensing. ACS Omega (2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10882602</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38405479</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kissinger, P. T. &amp; Heineman, W. R. Cyclic voltammetry. J. Chem. Educ.60, 702 (1983).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leech, M. C. &amp; Lam, K. A practical guide to electrosynthesis. Nat. Rev. Chem.6, 275–286 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37117870</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elgrishi, N. et al. A practical beginner’s guide to cyclic voltammetry. J. Chem. Educ.95, 197–206 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levey, K. J., Edwards, M. A., White, H. S. &amp; Macpherson, J. V. Simulation of the cyclic voltammetric response of an outer-sphere redox species with inclusion of electrical double layer structure and ohmic potential drop. Phys. Chem. Chem. Phys.25, 7832–7846 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36857676</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aoki, K. J., Chen, J., Liu, Y. &amp; Jia, B. Peak potential shift of fast cyclic voltammograms owing to capacitance of redox reactions. J. Electroanal. Chem.856, 113609 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Puthongkham, P. &amp; Venton, B. J. Recent advances in fast-scan cyclic voltammetry. Analyst145, 1087–1102 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7028521</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31922162</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kokoskarova, P. et al. Square-wave voltammetry of human blood serum. Sci. Rep.13, 8485 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10212954</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37231085</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar, N., Arora, A. &amp; Krishnan, A. Complementary ac voltammetry-a method for simultaneous measurement of faradaic and nonfaradaic currents in an electrochemically reversible system. IEEE Sens. J.20, 13196–13203 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, J., Guo, S.-X., Bond, A. M. &amp; Marken, F. Large-amplitude fourier transformed high-harmonic alternating current cyclic voltammetry: Kinetic discrimination of interfering faradaic processes at glassy carbon and at boron-doped diamond electrodes. Anal. Chem.76, 3619–3629 (2004).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15228333</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Mullane, A. P., Zhang, J., Brajter-Toth, A. &amp; Bond, A. M. Higher harmonic large-amplitude Fourier transformed alternating current voltammetry: Analytical attributes derived from studies of the oxidation of ferrocenemethanol and uric acid at a glassy carbon electrode. Anal. Chem.80, 4614–4626 (2008).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18484742</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sher, A. A. et al. Fourier transformed large amplitude square-wave voltammetry as an alternative to impedance spectroscopy: Evaluation of resistance, capacitance and electrode kinetic effects via an heuristic approach. Electroanalysis17, 1450–1462 (2005).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ciepiela, F. &amp; Jakubowska, M. Faradaic and capacitive current estimation by means of independent components analysis and 1 khz sampling. Talanta170, 158–164 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28501153</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uchida, Y., Kätelhön, E. &amp; Compton, R. G. Linear sweep voltammetry with non-triangular waveforms: New opportunities in electroanalysis. J. Electroanal. Chem.818, 140–148 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nardiello, D., Palermo, C., Natale, A., Quinto, M. &amp; Centonze, D. Pulsed amperometric detection at glassy carbon electrodes: A new waveform for sensitive and reproducible determination of electroactive compounds. Anal. Chim. Acta894, 1–6 (2015).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26423623</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Forster, R. J. Microelectrodes: New dimensions in electrochemistry. Chem. Soc. Rev.23, 289–297 (1994).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wipf, D. O. Ohmic drop compensation in voltammetry: Iterative correction of the applied potential. Anal. Chem.68, 1871–1876 (1996).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21619098</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, H., Qi, H., Chang, J., Gai, P. &amp; Li, F. Recent progress in homogeneous electrochemical sensors and their designs and applications. TrAC Trends Anal. Chem.156, 116712 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dalton, F. Ecs classics: Historical origins of the rotating ring-disk electrode. Electrochem. Soc. Interface25, 50 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin, Q. A primer to in-situ opto-and spectro-electrochemistry. Curr. Opin. Electrochem.37, 101201 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, C.-Y. &amp; Tian, Z.-Q. Sixty years of electrochemical optical spectroscopy: A retrospective. Chem. Soc. Rev. (2024).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38421335</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishi, N., Ikeda, Y. &amp; Sakka, T. Electrochemical surface plasmon resonance as a probe of redox reactions at the ionic liquid| gold interface. J. Electroanal. Chem.817, 210–216 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sohrabi, F., Saeidifard, S. &amp; Hamidi, S. M. Plasmonic structures for phase-sensitive ellipsometry biosensing: A review. Opt. Quant. Electron.53, 1–30 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gottesfeld, S. Ellipsometry: Principles and recent applications in electrochemistry. Electroanal. Chem. 143–266 (1989).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brosseau, C. L. et al. Electrochemical surface-enhanced Raman spectroscopy. Nat. Rev. Methods Primers3, 79 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Markin, A. V., Arzhanukhina, A. I., Markina, N. E. &amp; Goryacheva, I. Y. Analytical performance of electrochemical surface-enhanced raman spectroscopy: A critical review. TrAC, Trends Anal. Chem.157, 116776 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8724143</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34635933</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuan, B., Tong, S., Zhang, X., Li, L. &amp; Wang, C. Automatic monitoring refractive index variations of transient solution during electrochemical reactions. Measurement98, 10–16 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kosowska, M., Jakóbczyk, P., Rycewicz, M., Vitkin, A. &amp; Szczerska, M. Low-coherence photonic method of electrochemical processes monitoring. Sci. Rep.11, 12600 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8206142</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34131215</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>An, N., Zhuang, B., Li, M., Lu, Y. &amp; Wang, Z.-G. Combined theoretical and experimental study of refractive indices of water-acetonitrile-salt systems. J. Phys. Chem. B119, 10701–10709 (2015).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26203663</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kragt, H. J., Smith, C. P. &amp; White, H. S. Refractive index mapping of concentration profiles. J. Electroanal. Chem. Interfac. Electrochem.278, 403–407. 10.1016/0022-0728(90)85152-U (1990).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar, N., Arora, A. &amp; Krishnan, A. Plasmonically enhanced composite vortex beam generation using ultra-thin dielectric fork gratings. JOSA B39, 2084–2090 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richmonds, C. et al. Electron-transfer reactions at the plasma-liquid interface. J. Am. Chem. Soc.133, 17582–17585 (2011).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21985430</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar, N., Arora, A. &amp; Krishnan, A. Single-shot generation of composite optical vortex beams using hybrid binary fork gratings. Opt. Express29, 33703–33715 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34809177</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, B. Rigorous coupled-wave analysis (RCWA) matlab code tutorial (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar, N. Optoelectrochemistry (2024). https://colab.research.google.com/drive/1S_McFzHTnE329trEFCnu2SbH77yPXYVh?usp=sharing.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>