<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39330955</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1664-2848</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>166</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Schweizer Archiv fur Tierheilkunde</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Schweiz Arch Tierheilkd</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>[Psychological stress and the need for stress management in veterinary studies].</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>500</StartPage><EndPage>510</EndPage><MedlinePgn>500-510</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.17236/sat00432</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Veterinary students suffer from increased psychological stress compared to the general public and are increasingly affected by manifest mental illnesses such as depression and anxiety disorders, as well as an increased prevalence of suicidal thoughts. Additionally, veterinary students tend to ignore signs of mental distress and do not seek support for their mental health issues. This impaired mental health is also evident in fully trained veterinarians, who, among other things, have the highest suicide rates of all medical professions. In our survey, we examined a total of 428 veterinary students at the two veterinary faculties of the Universities of Zurich and Bern. The survey was carried out across all six years of the curriculum as a cross-sectional survey using standardized questionnaires on resilience, sense of coherence and depression. In all years, the students showed increased levels of depression compared to the general public, and the salutogenic parameters of resilience and sense of coherence were also reduced. The constellation with increased depression, reduced resilience and reduced sense of coherence was particularly accentuated in the second and third year. The increased affective stress on students presents itself as a consistent condition, which - if you look at studies on fully trained veterinarians - continues into their working life together with a reduced ability to cope. The low number of participants in the higher years of study and the high number of female study participants could limit the generalizability of the results. In addition, the data was collected in spring 2021 during the COVID-19 pandemic, which may have influenced the results. Active counteracting, for example by integrating the teaching of protective behavior such as mindful self-compassion and resource-oriented behavior such as mind-body techniques, therefore appears to be recommended in the veterinary training curriculum from the first semester onwards. Various measures to support students have been introduced since 2021, such as events on learning strategies, a mentoring system and seminars on mental health.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Müller</LastName><ForeName>R</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Triaplus AG Klinik Zugersee, Zentrum für Psychiatrie und Psychotherapie, Oberwil-Zug.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Scholz</LastName><ForeName>M</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Triaplus AG Klinik Zugersee, Zentrum für Psychiatrie und Psychotherapie, Oberwil-Zug.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Müller</LastName><ForeName>P</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Triaplus AG Klinik Zugersee, Zentrum für Psychiatrie und Psychotherapie, Oberwil-Zug.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Burger</LastName><ForeName>P</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Triaplus AG Klinik Zugersee, Zentrum für Psychiatrie und Psychotherapie, Oberwil-Zug.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>ger</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D004740">English Abstract</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><VernacularTitle>Psychische Belastung und die Notwendigkeit von Stressmanagement im Veterinärmedizinstudium.</VernacularTitle></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Schweiz Arch Tierheilkd</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0424247</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0036-7281</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013315" MajorTopicYN="Y">Stress, Psychological</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004520" MajorTopicYN="Y">Education, Veterinary</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003430" MajorTopicYN="N">Cross-Sectional Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011795" MajorTopicYN="N">Surveys and Questionnaires</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003863" MajorTopicYN="N">Depression</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013557" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Switzerland</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013334" MajorTopicYN="N">Students</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018634" MajorTopicYN="N">Veterinarians</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="ger"><AbstractText>Veterinärmedizinstudierende leiden, verglichen mit der Normalbevölkerung, unter erhöhter psychischer Belastung und sind vermehrt von manifesten psychischen Erkrankungen wie Depression und Angststörungen sowie einer erhöhten Prävalenz von Suizidgedanken betroffen. Darüber hinaus neigen Veterinärmedizinstudierende dazu, die Anzeichen mentaler Belastung zu übergehen und keine Unterstützung für ihre psychischen Probleme zu suchen. Diese beeinträchtigte mentale Gesundheit zeigt sich in der Folge auch bei fertig ausgebildeten Tierärztinnen und Tierärzten, welche unter anderem die höchsten Suizidraten aller Medizinberufe aufweisen. Wir untersuchten in unserer Erhebung insgesamt 428 Studierende der Veterinärmedizin an den beiden tiermedizinischen Fakultäten der Universitäten Zürich und Bern. Die Befragung erfolgte über alle sechs Studienjahre des Ausbildungscurriculums als Querschnittserhebung mithilfe standardisierter Fragebögen zu Resilienz, Kohärenzgefühl und Depressivität. In allen Jahrgängen zeigen die Studierenden im Vergleich mit der Normalbevölkerung erhöhte Depressivität, begleitend dazu waren die Salutogeneseparameter Resilienz und Kohärenzgefühl erniedrigt. Besonders akzentuiert zeigte sich die Konstellation mit erhöhter Depressivität, verringerter Resilienz und reduziertem Kohärenzgefühl im zweiten und dritten Studienjahr. Die erhöhte affektive Belastung der Studierenden präsentiert sich als durchgehend vertretenes Zustandsbild, das sich – betrachtet man die Studien zu fertig ausgebildeten Veterinärmedizinerinnen und Veterinärmedizinern – zusammen mit einer reduzierter Coping-Fähigkeit bis in das Arbeitsleben fortsetzt. Die geringe Teilnehmerzahl in den höheren Studienjahren und die hohe Anzahl weiblicher Studienteilnehmenden könnten die Generalisierbarkeit der Ergebnisse einschränken. Zudem wurden die Daten im Frühjahr 2021 während der COVID-19-Pandemie erhoben, was die Resultate beeinflusst haben könnte. Aktives Entgegenwirken, etwa durch die Integration des Lehrens protektiven Verhaltens wie achtsames Selbstmitgefühl und ressourcenorientierter Handlungsweisen wie z.B. Mind-Body-Techniken, erscheint daher bereits im Ausbildungscurriculum der Veterinärmedizin ab dem ersten Semester empfehlenswert. Seit 2021 wurden bereits verschiedene Massnahmen zur Unterstützung der Studierenden eingeführt, etwa Veranstaltungen zu Lernstrategien, ein Mentoringsystem sowie Seminare zu mentaler Gesundheit.</AbstractText></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="fre"><AbstractText>Les étudiants en médecine vétérinaire souffrent d’un stress psychologique plus important que le grand public et sont de plus en plus touchés par des maladies paychiques manifestes telles que la dépression et les troubles anxieux, ainsi que par une prévalence accrue de pensées suicidaires. En outre, les étudiants en médecine vétérinaire ont tendance à ignorer les signes de détresse mentale et ne cherchent pas de soutien pour leurs problèmes de santé mentale. Cette détérioration de la santé mentale est également évidente chez les vétérinaires formés, qui, entre autres, présentent les taux de suicide les plus élevés de toutes les professions médicales. Dans notre enquête, nous avons examiné un total de 428 étudiants vétérinaires des deux facultés vétérinaires des universités de Zurich et de Berne. L’enquête a été menée sur les six années du cursus sous forme d’enquête transversale à l’aide de questionnaires standardisés sur la résilience, le sentiment de cohérence et la dépression. Pour toutes les années, les étudiants ont montré des niveaux de dépression plus élevés que le grand public, et les paramètres salutogènes de la résilience et du sentiment de cohérence ont également été réduits. La constellation avec une dépression accrue, une résilience réduite et un sentiment de cohérence réduit était particulièrement accentuée en deuxième et troisième année. Le stress affectif accru des étudiants se présente comme un état constant qui, si on examine les études sur les vétérinaires ayant reçu une formation complète, se poursuit dans leur vie professionnelle, accompagné d’une capacité réduite à faire face. Le faible nombre de participants dans les années d’études supérieures et le nombre élevé de participantes à l’étude pourraient limiter la généralisation des résultats. En outre, les données ont été collectées au printemps 2021, pendant la pandémie de COVID-19, ce qui a pu influencer les résultats. La lutte active, par exemple en intégrant l’enseignement d’un comportement protecteur tel que l’autocompassion consciente et d’un comportement orienté vers les ressources tel que les techniques corps-esprit, semble donc être recommandée dans le programme de formation vétérinaire dès le premier semestre. Diverses mesures de soutien aux étudiants ont été introduites depuis 2021, telles que des événements sur les stratégies d’apprentissage, un système de mentorat et des séminaires sur la santé mentale.</AbstractText></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="ita"><AbstractText>Gli studenti di veterinaria soffrono di un aumento dello stress psicologico rispetto alla popolazione generale e sono sempre più colpiti da malattie mentali manifeste come depressione e disturbi d’ansia, nonché da una prevalenza accresciuta di pensieri suicidari. Inoltre, gli studenti di veterinaria tendono a ignorare i segni di disagio mentale e non cercano supporto per i loro problemi di salute mentale. Questa salute mentale compromessa si ritrova anche nei veterinari completamente formati, che, tra l’altro, comportano un tasso di suicidio più alto tra tutte le professioni mediche. Nel nostro sondaggio, abbiamo esaminato un totale di 428 studenti di veterinaria delle due facoltà veterinarie delle Università di Zurigo e Berna. Il sondaggio è stato condotto su tutti i sei anni del curriculum come un’indagine trasversale utilizzando questionari standardizzati su resilienza, senso di coerenza e depressione. Per tutti gli anni, gli studenti hanno mostrato livelli elevati di depressione rispetto alla popolazione generale, e anche i parametri salutogenici di resilienza e senso di coerenza erano inferiori. La combinazione fra aumento della depressione, riduzione della resilienza e riduzione del senso di coerenza era particolarmente accentuata nel secondo e terzo anno. L’aumento dello stress affettivo sugli studenti si presenta come una condizione costante, constatata anche negli studi eseguiti sui veterinari completamente formati, che continua nella vita lavorativa insieme a una ridotta capacità di affrontare le difficoltà. Il basso numero di partecipanti negli anni di studio superiori e l’alto numero di partecipanti femminili potrebbe limitare la generalizzazione dei risultati. Inoltre, i dati sono stati raccolti nella primavera del 2021 durante la pandemia di COVID-19, che potrebbe aver influenzato i risultati. Contrastare attivamente, ad esempio integrando l’insegnamento di comportamenti protettivi come l’autocompassione consapevole e comportamenti orientati alle risorse come le tecniche mente-corpo, sembra quindi essere consigliato nel curriculum di formazione veterinaria fin dal primo semestre. Diverse misure per supportare gli studenti sono state introdotte dal 2021, come eventi sulle strategie di apprendimento, un sistema di tutoraggio e seminari sulla salute mentale.</AbstractText></OtherAbstract><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Ausbildungsforschung</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Depression</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Kohärenzgefühl</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Recherche en formation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Resilienz</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Ricerca formativa</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Salutogenese</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Training research</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">depression</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">depressione</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">dépression</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mental health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mentale Gesundheit</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">resilience</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">resilienza</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">résilience</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">salute mentale</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">salutogenesi</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">salutogenesis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">salutogenèse</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">santé mentale</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sense of coherence</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">senso di coerenza</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sentiment de cohérence</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39330955</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.17236/sat00432</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>