<PubmedArticle xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39345408</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2692-8205</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>19</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>bioRxiv</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Real-space heterogeneous reconstruction, refinement, and disentanglement of CryoEM conformational states with HetSIREN.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">2024.09.16.613176</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1101/2024.09.16.613176</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Single-particle analysis by Cryo-electron microscopy (CryoEM) provides direct access to the conformation of each macromolecule. However, the image's signal-to-noise ratio is low, and some form of classification is usually performed at the image processing level to allow structural modeling. Classical classification methods imply the existence of a discrete number of structural conformations. However, new heterogeneity algorithms introduce a novel reconstruction paradigm, where every state is represented by a lower number of particles, potentially just one, allowing the estimation of conformational landscapes representing the different structural states a biomolecule explores. In this work, we present a novel deep learning-based method called HetSIREN. HetSIREN can fully reconstruct or refine a CryoEM volume in real space based on the structural information summarized in a conformational latent space. The unique characteristics that set HetSIREN apart start with the definition of the approach as a real space-based only method, a fact that allows spatially focused analysis, but also the introduction of a novel network architecture specifically designed to make use of meta-sinusoidal activations, with proven high analytics capacities. Continuing with innovations, HetSIREN can also refine the pose parameters of the images at the same time that it conditions the network with prior information/constraints on the maps, such as Total Variation and <ns0:math> <ns0:mrow><ns0:msub><ns0:mi>L</ns0:mi> <ns0:mn>1</ns0:mn></ns0:msub> </ns0:mrow> </ns0:math> denoising, ultimately yielding cleaner volumes with high-quality structural features. Finally, but very importantly, HetSIREN addresses one of the most confusing issues in heterogeneity analysis, as it is the fact that real structural heterogeneity estimation is entangled with pose estimation (and to a lesser extent with CTF estimation), in this way, HetSIREN introduces a novel encoding architecture able to decouple pose and CTF information from the conformational landscape, resulting in more accurate and interpretable conformational latent spaces. We present results on computer-simulated data, public data from EMPIAR, and data from experimental systems currently being studied in our laboratories. An important finding is the sensitivity of the structure and dynamics of the SARS-CoV-2 Spike protein on the storage temperature.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Herreros</LastName><ForeName>D</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1509-1649</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centro Nacional de Biotecnologia-CSIC, C/ Darwin, 3, 28049, Cantoblanco, Madrid, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mata</LastName><ForeName>C P</ForeName><Initials>CP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centro Nacional de Biotecnologia-CSIC, C/ Darwin, 3, 28049, Cantoblanco, Madrid, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Noddings</LastName><ForeName>C</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0890-9035</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Altos Labs, 1300 Island Dr., Redwood City, CA 94065, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Irene</LastName><ForeName>D</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0009-1602-6057</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Biological Chemistry, Academia Sinica, Taipei 115, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Krieger</LastName><ForeName>J</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6194-6244</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centro Nacional de Biotecnologia-CSIC, C/ Darwin, 3, 28049, Cantoblanco, Madrid, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Agard</LastName><ForeName>D A</ForeName><Initials>DA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3512-695X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biochemistry Biophysics, University of California, San Francisco, CA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Chan Zuckerberg Imaging Institute, Redwood City, CA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tsai</LastName><ForeName>M-D</ForeName><Initials>MD</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1374-0414</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Biological Chemistry, Academia Sinica, Taipei 115, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sorzano</LastName><ForeName>C O S</ForeName><Initials>COS</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9473-283X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centro Nacional de Biotecnologia-CSIC, C/ Darwin, 3, 28049, Cantoblanco, Madrid, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Carazo</LastName><ForeName>J M</ForeName><Initials>JM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0788-8447</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centro Nacional de Biotecnologia-CSIC, C/ Darwin, 3, 28049, Cantoblanco, Madrid, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>R01 GM136780</GrantID><Acronym>GM</Acronym><Agency>NIGMS NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D000076942">Preprint</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>19</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>bioRxiv</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101680187</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2692-8205</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Cryo-Electron Microscopy (CryoEM)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Deep Learning</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Heterogenous Reconstruction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Principal Component Analysis (PCA)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2 Spike protein</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sinusoidal Representation Network (SIREN)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Uniform Manifold Approximation and Projection (UMAP)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">temperature dependence</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Competing Interests The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>37</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39345408</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11429808</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/2024.09.16.613176</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">2024.09.16.613176</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Carroni M. and Saibil H.R.. Cryo-electron microscopy to determine the structure of macromolecular complexes. Methods, 95:78–85, 2016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5405050</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26638773</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scheres S.H.W., Nuñez-Ramirez R., Gomez-Yorente Y., San Martin C., Eggermont P.P.B., and Carazo J.M.. Modeling Experimental Image Formation for Likelihood-Based Classification of Electron Microscopy Data. Structure, 15(10):1167–1177, 2007.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2277044</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17937907</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toader B., Sigworth F.J., Lederman R.R.. Methods for Cryo-EM single particle reconstruction of macromolecules having continuous heterogeneity J. Molecular Biology 435(9): 168020 (2023)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10164696</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36863660</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dashti A., Schwander P., Langlois R., Fung R., Li W., Hosseinizadeh A., Liao H., Pallesen J., Sharma G., Stupina V. A., Simon A. E., Dinman J. D., Frank J., Ourmazd A.. Trajectories of the ribosome as a Brownian nanomachine. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 111: 7492–17497 (2014)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4267381</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25422471</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin Q., Sorzano C.O.S., de la Rosa-Trevín J.M., Bilbao-Castro J.R., Núñez-Ramírez R., Llorca O., Tama F., Jonić S.. Iterative Elastic 3D-to-2D Alignment Method Using Normal Modes for Studying Structural Dynamics of Large Macromolecular Complexes. Structure, 22: 496–506 (2014)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24508340</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhong E.D., Bepler T., Berger B., and Davis J.H.. Cryodrgn: reconstruction of heterogeneous CryoEM structures using neural networks. Nature Methods, 18:176–185, 2021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8183613</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33542510</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>J Ludtke S. and Muyuan C.. Deep learning-based mixed-dimensional gaussian mixture model for characterizing variability in CryoEM. Nature Methods, 18:930–936, 2021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8363932</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34326541</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo Z., Ni F., Wang Q., and Ma J.. OPUS-DSD: deep structural disentanglement for CryoEM single-particle analysis. Nature Methods, 20:1729–1738, 2023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10630141</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37813988</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schwab J., Kimanius D., Burt A., Dendooven T., and Scheres DynaMight S.H.W.: estimating molecular motions with improved reconstruction from CryoEM images bioRxiv, 2023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11466895</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39123079</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Punjani A. and Fleet D.J.. 3DFlex: determining structure and motion of flexible proteins from CryoEM. Nature Methods, 20:860–870, 2023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10250194</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37169929</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herreros D., Lederman R.R., Krieger J., Jiménez-Moreno A., Martínez M., Myška D., Strelak D., Filipovic J., Bahar I., Carazo J.M., and Sorzano C.O.S.. Approximating deformation fields for the analysis of continuous heterogeneity of biological macromolecules by 3D Zernike polynomials. IUCrJ, 8(6):992–1005, 2021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8562670</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34804551</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vuillemot R., Mirzaei A., Harastani M., Hamitouche I., Frechin L., Klaholz B.P., Miyashita O., Tama F., Rouiller I., and Jonic S.. MDSPACE: Extracting Continuous Conformational Landscapes from CryoEM Single Particle Datasets Using 3D-to-2D Flexible Fitting based on Molecular Dynamics Simulation. Journal of Molecular Biology, 435:167951, 2023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36638910</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sitzmann V., Martel J.N.P., Bergman A.W., Lindell D.B., and Wetzstein G.. Implicit Neural Representations with Periodic Activation Functions. arXiv, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wolterink J.M., Zwienenberg J.C., and Brune C. Implicit Neural Representations for Deformable Image Registration Medical Imaging with Deep Learning 2022, 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klindt D.A., Hyvarinen A., Levy A., Miolane N., and Poitevin F. Towards Interpretable Cryo-EM: Disentangling Latent Spaces of Molecular Conformations bioarXiv, 2024.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11263974</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39044842</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harastani M., Eltsov M., Leforestier A., and Jonic HEMNMA- S. 3D: Cryo Electron Tomography Method Based on Normal Mode Analysis to Study Continuous Conformational Variability of Macromolecular Complexes Front. Mol. Biosci., 8:663121, 2021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8170028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34095222</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de la Rosa-Trevín J.M., Quintana A., del Cano L., Zaldívar A., Foche I., Gutiérrez J., Gómez-Blanco J., Burguet-Castell J., Cuenca-Alba J., Abrishami V., Vargas J., Otón J., Sharov G., Vilas J.L., Navas J., Conesa P., Kazemi M., Marabini R., Sorzano C.O.S., and Carazo J.M.. Scipion: A software framework toward integration, reproducibility and validation in 3D electron microscopy. Journal of Structural Biology, 195(1):93–99, 2016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27108186</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong W., Bai X., Brown A., Fernandez I.S., Hanssen E., Condron M., Tan Y.H., Baum J., and Scheres S.H.W.. CryoEM structure of the Plasmodium falciparum 80s ribosome bound to the anti-protozoan drug emetine. eLife, 3:e03080, 2014.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4086275</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24913268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herreros D., Krieger J.M., Fonseca Y., Conesa P., Harastani M., Vuillemot R., Hamitouche I., Serrano Gutierrez R., Gragera M., Melero R., Jonic S., Carazo J.M., Sorzano C.O.S.. Scipion Flexibility Hub: an integrative framework for advanced analysis of conformational heterogeneity in cryoEM. Acta Crystallogr D Struct Biol,, 79:569–584, 2023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10306064</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37326585</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McInnes L., Healy J., Saul N, and Großberger L.. Umap: Uniform manifold approximation and projection. Journal of Open Source Software, 3(29):861, 2018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramirez Aportela E., Mota J., Conesa P., Carazo J.M., and COS Sorzano DeepRes: a new deep-learning- and aspect-based local resolution method for electron-microscopy maps. IUCrJ, 6:1054–1066, 2019.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6830216</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31709061</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noddings CM, Johnson J.L., and Agard D. CryoEM reveals how Hsp90 and FKBP immunophilins co-regulate the glucocorticoid receptor. Nature Structural &amp; Molecular Biology, 30:1867–1877, 2023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10716051</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37945740</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jolliffe I. and Cadima J.. Principal component analysis: A review and recent developments. Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society A: Mathematical, Physical and Engineering Sciences, 374:20150202, 2016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4792409</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26953178</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou P., Yang X.L., Wang X.G., Hu B., Zhang L., Zhang W., Si H.R., Zhu Y., Li B., Huang C.L., Chen H.D., Chen J., Luo Y., Guo H., Jiang R.D., Liu M.Q., Chen Y., Shen X.R., Wang X., Zheng X.S., Zhao K., Chen Q.J., Deng F., Liu L.L., Yan B., Zhan F.X., Wang Y.Y., Xiao G.F., and Shi Z.L.. A pneumonia outbreak associated with a new coronavirus of probable bat origin. Nature, 579(7798):270–273, 2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7095418</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32015507</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan R., Zhang Y., Li Y., Xia L., Guo Y., and Zhou Q.. Structural basis for the recognition of SARS-CoV-2 by full-length human ACE2. Science, 367(6485):1444–1448, 2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7164635</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32132184</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ginex T., Marco-Marín C., Wieczór M., Mata C. P., Krieger J., Ruiz-Rodriguez P., López-Redondo M. L., Francés-Gómez C., Melero R., Óscar Sánchez-Sorzano C., Martínez M., Gougeard N., Forcada-Nadal A., Zamora-Caballero S., Gozalbo-Rovira R., Sanz-Frasquet C., Arranz R., Bravo J., Rubio V., Marina A., IBV-Covid19-Pipeline, Geller R., Comas Iñaki, Gil C., Coscolla M., Orozco M., Llácer J. L., and Carazo J.M.. The structural role of SARS-CoV-2 genetic background in the emergence and success of Spike mutations: The case of the Spike A222V mutation. PLoS Pathogens, 18(7):e1010631, 2022.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9302720</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35816514</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edwards R. J., Mansouri K., Stalls V., Manne K., Watts B., Parks R., Janowska K., Gobeil S. M. C., Kopp M., Li D., Lu X., Mu Z., Deyton M., Oguin T. H. 3rd, Sprenz J., Williams W., Saunders K. O., Montefiori D., Sempowski G. D., Henderson R., Munir Alam S., Haynes B. F., and Acharya P.. Cold sensitivity of the SARS-CoV-2 Spike ectodomain. Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol., 28(2):128–131, 2021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7878407</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33402708</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang T. J., Yu P. Y., Chang Y. C., and Hsu S. T. D.. D614G mutation in the SARS-CoV-2 Spike protein enhances viral fitness by desensitizing it to temperature-dependent denaturation. J. Biol. Chem., 297(4):101238, 2021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8460419</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34563540</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen C.-Y., Chang Y.-C., Lin B.-L., Huang C.-H., and Tsai M.-D.. Temperature-resolved cryo-EM uncovers structural bases of temperature-dependent enzyme functions. J. Am. Chem. Soc., 141(51):19983–19987, 2019.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31829582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang Y.-C., Chen C.-Y., and Tsai M.-D.. Preparation of high-temperature sample grids for cryo-EM. J. Vis. Exp., (173), Jul. 2021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34369929</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krieger J. M., Sorzano C. O. S., and Carazo J. M.. Scipion-EM-ProDy: A graphical interface for the ProDy Python package within the Scipion workflow engine enabling integration of databases, simulations and cryo-electron microscopy image processing. Int. J. Mol. Sci., 24(18):14245, Sep 2023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10532346</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37762547</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jamali K., Käll L., Zhang R., Brown A., Kimanius D., and Scheres S. H. W.. Automated model building and protein identification in cryo-EM maps. Nature, 628(8007):450–457, Apr 2024.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11006616</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38408488</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benton D. J., Wrobel A. G., Roustan C., Borg A., Xu P., Martin S. R., Rosenthal P. B., Skehel J. J., and Gamblin S. J.. The effect of the D614G substitution on the structure of the Spike glycoprotein of SARS-CoV-2. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A., 118(9):e2022586118, 2021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7936381</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33579792</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bruch E. M., Zhu S., Szymkowicz L., Blake T., Kiss T., James D. A., Rak A., Narayan K., Balmer M. T., and Chicz R. M.. Structural and biochemical rationale for Beta variant protein booster vaccine broad cross-neutralization of SARS-CoV-2. Sci. Rep., 14(1):2038, 2024.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10805794</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38263191</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chauhan, Chauhan V. K., Molaei S., Clifton D. A., Lu P., and Zhou J.. A brief review of hypernetworks in deep learning. arXiv, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Punjani A., Rubinstein J.L., Fleet D.J., and Brubaker M.A.. CryoSPARC: algorithms for rapid unsupervised CryoEM structure determination. Nature Methods, 14:290–296, 2017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28165473</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de la Rosa-Trevín J.M., Otón J., Marabini R., Zaldívar A., Vargas J., Carazo J.M., and Sorzano C.O.S.. Xmipp 3.0: An improved software suite for image processing in electron microscopy. Journal of Structural Biology, 184:321–328, 2013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24075951</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abrishami V., Ilca S. L., Gomez-Blanco J., Rissanen I., de la Rosa-Trevín J. M., Reddy V. S., Carazo J. -M., and Huiskonen J. T.. Localized reconstruction in Scipion expedites the analysis of symmetry mismatches in cryo-EM data. Prog. Biophys. Mol. Biol., 160:43–52, 2021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32470354</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kimanius D., Dong L., Sharov G., Nakane T., and Scheres S.H.W.. New tools for automated CryoEM single-particle analysis in RELION-4.0. Biochemical Journal, 478:4169–4185, 2021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8786306</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34783343</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pettersen E.F., Goddard T.D., Huang C.C., Meng E.C., Couch G.S., Croll T.I., Morris J.H., and Ferrin T.E.. Ucsf chimerax: Structure visualization for researchers, educators, and developers. Protein Science, 30(1):70–82, 2021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7737788</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32881101</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y., Xu C., Wang Y., Hong Q., Zhang C., Li Z., Xu S., Zuo Q., Liu C., Huang Z., and Cong Y.. Conformational dynamics of the Beta and Kappa SARS-CoV-2 spike proteins and their complexes with ACE2 receptor revealed by cryo-EM. Nat. Commun., 12(1):7345, 2021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8688474</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34930910</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Emsley P. and Cowtan K., Coot: model-building tools for molecular graphics. Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr., vol. 60, no. Pt 12 Pt 1, pp. 2126–2132, 2004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15572765</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen V. B., Arendall III W. B., Headd J. J., Keedy D. A., Immormino R. M., Kapral G. J., Murray L. W., Richardson J. S., and Richardson D. C.. MolProbity: all-atom structure validation for macromolecular crystallography. Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr., 66(Pt 1):12–21, 2010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2803126</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20057044</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams C. J., Headd J. J., Moriarty N. W., Prisant M. G., Videau L. L., Deis L. N., Verma V., Keedy D. A., Hintze B. J., Chen V. B., Jain S., Lewis S. M., Arendall W. B. III, Snoeyink J., Adams P. D., Lovell S. C., Richardson J. S., and Richardson D. C.. MolProbity: More and better reference data for improved all-atom structure validation. Protein Sci., 27(1):293–315, 2018.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5734394</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29067766</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lederman R.R., Anden J., and Singer A.. Hyper-molecules: on the representation and recovery of dynamical structures for applications in flexible macro-molecules in CryoEM. Inverse Problems, 36, 2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10831863</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38304203</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>