<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39340586</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>28</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1438-7948</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>24</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>28</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Functional &amp; integrative genomics</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Funct Integr Genomics</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Exploring the potential of nanomedicine for gene therapy across the physicochemical and cellular barriers.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>177</StartPage><MedlinePgn>177</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s10142-024-01459-z</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>After COVID-19, a turning point in the way of pharmaceutical technology is gene therapy with beneficial potential to start a new medical era. However, commercialization of such pharmaceuticals would never be possible without the help of nanotechnology. Nanomedicine can fulfill the growing needs linked to safety, efficiency, and site-specific targeted delivery of Gene therapy-based pharmaceuticals. This review's goal is to investigate how nanomedicine may be used to transfer nucleic acids by getting beyond cellular and physicochemical barriers. Firstly, we provide a full description of types of gene therapy, their mechanism, translation, transcription, expression, type, and details of diseases with possible mechanisms that can only be treated with genes-based pharmaceuticals. Additionally, we also reviewed different types of physicochemical barriers, physiological and cellular barriers in nucleic acids (DNA/RNA) based drug delivery. Finally, we highlight the need and importance of cationic lipid-based nanomedicine/nanocarriers in gene-linked drug delivery and how nanotechnology can help to overcome the above-discussed barrier in gene therapy and their biomedical applications.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hameed</LastName><ForeName>Huma</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences, University of Central Punjab (UCP), Lahore, 54000, Pakistan. huma.hameed@ucp.edu.pk.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sarwar</LastName><ForeName>Hafiz Shoaib</ForeName><Initials>HS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences, University of Central Punjab (UCP), Lahore, 54000, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Younas</LastName><ForeName>Komel</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Pharmacy, University Paris Saclay, 17 Avenue des sciences, 91190, Orsay, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zaman</LastName><ForeName>Muhammad</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences, University of Central Punjab (UCP), Lahore, 54000, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jamshaid</LastName><ForeName>Muhammad</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences, University of Central Punjab (UCP), Lahore, 54000, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Irfan</LastName><ForeName>Ali</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Chemistry, Government College University Faisalabad, Faisalabad, 38000, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khalid</LastName><ForeName>Maha</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences, University of Central Punjab (UCP), Lahore, 54000, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sohail</LastName><ForeName>Muhammad Farhan</ForeName><Initials>MF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Chemistry, SBASSE, Lahore University of Management Sciences (LUMS), Lahore, 54000, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Alliant College of Pharmacy and Allied Health Sciences, Lahore, 54000, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Funct Integr Genomics</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100939343</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1438-793X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015316" MajorTopicYN="Y">Genetic Therapy</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D050997" MajorTopicYN="Y">Nanomedicine</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D053758" MajorTopicYN="N">Nanoparticles</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016503" MajorTopicYN="N">Drug Delivery Systems</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018014" MajorTopicYN="N">Gene Transfer Techniques</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000628" MajorTopicYN="N">therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Barriers</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Cationic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Gene</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Lipids</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Nanomedicine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Therapy</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39340586</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10142-024-01459-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s10142-024-01459-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Abbott KW (2011) An international framework agreement on scientific and technological innovation and regulation. The Growing Gap between Emerging Technologies and Legal-Ethical Oversight: The Pacing Problem, pp 127–156</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alhariri M, Majrashi MA, Bahkali AH, Almajed FS, Azghani AO, Khiyami MA, Alyamani EJ, Aljohani SM, Halwani MA (2017) Efficacy of neutral and negatively charged liposome-loaded gentamicin on planktonic bacteria and biofilm communities. Int J Nanomedicine 12:6949–6961. https://doi.org/10.2147/IJN.S141709</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/IJN.S141709</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29075113</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5609801</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baden LR, El Sahly HM, Essink B, Kotloff K, Frey S, Novak R, Diemert D, Spector SA, Rouphael N, Creech CB (2021) Efficacy and safety of the mRNA-1273 SARS-CoV-2 vaccine. N Engl J Med 384:403–416</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33378609</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barani M, Nematollahi MH, Zaboli M, Mirzaei M, Torkzadeh-Mahani M, Pardakhty A, Karam GA (2019) In silico and in vitro study of magnetic niosomes for gene delivery: the effect of ergosterol and cholesterol. Mater Sci Eng: C 94:234–246</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berg JM, Tymoczko JL, Stryer L (2015) Biochemistry, 7th edn. W H Freeman, New York, NY</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bishop NA, Guarente L (2007) Genetic links between diet and lifespan: shared mechanisms from yeast to humans. Nat Rev Genet 8:835–844</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17909538</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bromberg JS, Debruyne LA, Qin L (1998) Interactions between the immune system and gene therapy vectors: bidirectional regulation of response and expression. Adv Immunol 69:353–409</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9646848</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bueren JA, Quintana-Bustamante O, Almarza E, Navarro S, Río P, Segovia JC, Guenechea G (2020) Advances in the gene therapy of monogenic blood cell diseases. Clin Genet 97:89–102</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31231794</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Butt MH, Zaman M, Ahmad A, Khan R, Mallhi TH, Hasan MM, Khan YH, Hafeez S, Massoud EES, Rahman MH, Cavalu S (2022) Appraisal for the potential of viral and nonviral vectors in gene therapy: a review. Genes (Basel) 13:1370</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36011281</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cai M, Yang Y (2014) Targeted genome editing tools for disease modeling and gene therapy. Curr Gene Ther 14:2–9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24665839</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaplin DD (2010) Overview of the immune response. J Allergy Clin Immunol 125:S3–S23</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20176265</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2923430</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen J, Guo Z, Tian H, Chen X (2016) Production and clinical development of nanoparticles for gene delivery. Mol Ther-Methods Clin Dev 3:16023</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27088105</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4822651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choudhury NN, He H (2012) Nanocarriers for the simultaneous co-delivery of therapeutic genes and anticancer drugs. Curr Pharm Biotechnol 13:1317–1331</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22201588</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choulika A, Perrin A, Dujon B, Nicolas J-F (1995) Induction of homologous recombination in mammalian chromosomes by using the I-SceI system of Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Mol Cell Biol 15:1968–1973</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7891691</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">230423</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crommelin DJ, Anchordoquy TJ, Volkin DB, Jiskoot W, Mastrobattista E (2021) Addressing the cold reality of mRNA vaccine stability. J Pharm Sci 110:997–1001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33321139</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daneman R, Prat A (2015) The blood-brain barrier. Cold Spring Harb Perspect Biol 7:a020412</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25561720</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4292164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>David RM, Doherty AT (2017) Viral vectors: the road to reducing genotoxicity. Toxicol Sci 155:315–325</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27803388</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dolatabadi JEN, Valizadeh H, Hamishehkar H (2015) Solid lipid nanoparticles as efficient drug and gene delivery systems: recent breakthroughs. Adv Pharm Bull 5:151</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doroud D, Vatanara A, Zahedifard F, Gholami E, Vahabpour R, Najafabadi AR, Rafati S (2010) Cationic solid lipid nanoparticles loaded by cysteine proteinase genes as a novel anti-leishmaniasis DNA vaccine delivery system: characterization and in vitro evaluations. J Pharm Pharm Sci 13:320–335</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21092706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dugo K, Bruno F, Sturiale V, Brancato D, Saccone S, Federico C (2022) Hereditary transthyretin-related amyloidosis: genetic heterogeneity and early personalized gene therapy. Biomedicines 10:2394</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36289657</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9598525</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dunbar CE, High KA, Joung JK, Kohn DB, Ozawa K, Sadelain M (2018) Gene therapy comes of age. Science 359:eaan4672</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29326244</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edelstein ML, Abedi MR, Wixon J, Edelstein RM (2004) Gene therapy clinical trials worldwide 1989–2004—an overview. J Gene Med: Cross-Discip J Res Sci Gene Transf Clin Appl 6:597–602</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ediriweera GR, Chen L, Yerbury JJ, Thurecht KJ, Vine KL (2021) Non-viral vector-mediated gene therapy for ALS: Challenges and future perspectives. Mol Pharm 18:2142–2160</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34010004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eggenhofer E, Doenecke A, Renner P, Slowik P, Piso P, Geissler EK, Schlitt HJ, Dahlke MH, Popp FC (2010) High volume naked DNA tail-vein injection restores liver function in Fah-knock out mice. J Gastroenterol Hepatol 25:1002–1008</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20546455</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erdal C, Ali Demir S, EmreŞefik CAL (2012) Gene delivery systems: recent progress in viral and non-viral therapy. In: Ali Demir S (ed) Recent advances in novel drug carrier systems. Rijeka, IntechOpen</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ewert KK, Scodeller P, Simón-Gracia L, Steffes VM, Wonder EA, Teesalu T, Safinya CR (2021) Cationic liposomes as vectors for nucleic acid and hydrophobic drug therapeutics. Pharmaceutics 13:1365</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34575441</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8465808</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fang RH, Jiang Y, Fang JC, Zhang L (2017) Cell membrane-derived nanomaterials for biomedical applications. Biomaterials 128:69–83</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28292726</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5417338</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fattal E, Barratt G (2009) Nanotechnologies and controlled release systems for the delivery of antisense oligonucleotides and small interfering RNA. Br J Pharmacol 157:179–194</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19366348</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2697810</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Félétou M (2011) The endothelium, Part I: Multiple functions of the endothelial cells–focus on endothelium-derived vasoactive mediators. Colloq Ser Integr Syst Physiol Mol Funct 3(4):1–306</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Felgner PL, Gadek TR, Holm M, Roman R, Chan HW, Wenz M, Northrop JP, Ringold GM, Danielsen M (1987) Lipofection: a highly efficient, lipid-mediated DNA-transfection procedure. Proc Natl Acad Sci 84:7413–7417</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2823261</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">299306</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fihurka O, Sanchez-Ramos J, Sava V (2018) Optimizing nanoparticle design for gene therapy: protection of oligonucleotides from degradation without impeding release of cargo. Nanomedicine Nanosci Res 2. https://doi.org/10.29011/2577-1477.100055</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Foroozandeh P, Aziz AA (2018) Insight into cellular uptake and intracellular trafficking of nanoparticles. Nanoscale Res Lett 13:1–12</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Forster R, Liew A, Bhattacharya V, Shaw J, Stansby G (2018) Gene therapy for peripheral arterial disease. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 2018. https://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.CD012058.pub2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gabizon AA, Patil Y, La-Beck NM (2016) New insights and evolving role of pegylated liposomal doxorubicin in cancer therapy. Drug Resist Updat 29:90–106</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27912846</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao F, Yu B, Cong H, Shen Y (2022) Delivery process and effective design of vectors for cancer therapy. J Mater Chem B 10:6896–6921</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36048171</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gertz MA, Mauermann ML, Grogan M, Coelho T (2019) Advances in the treatment of hereditary transthyretin amyloidosis: a review. Brain Behav 9:e01371</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31368669</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6749475</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gómez-Aguado I, Rodríguez-Castejón J, Vicente-Pascual M, Rodríguez-Gascón A, Solinís MÁ, Del Pozo-Rodríguez A (2020) Nanomedicines to deliver mRNA: state of the art and future perspectives. Nanomaterials 10:364</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32093140</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7075285</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta J, Gupta V, Yadav AK, Singh SK, Sharma PK (2021) Nanostructures in Health Care. The Era of Nanotechnology. Apple Academic Press, New York</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han S-O, Mahato RI, Sung YK, Kim SW (2000) Development of biomaterials for gene therapy. Mol Ther 2:302–317</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11020345</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han X, Zhao C, Wang S, Pan Z, Jiang Z, Tang X (2022) Multifunctional TiO2/C nanosheets derived from 3D metal–organic frameworks for mild-temperature-photothermal-sonodynamic-chemodynamic therapy under photoacoustic image guidance. J Colloid Interface Sci 621:360–373</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35462177</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hara T, Tan Y, Huang L (1997) In vivo gene delivery to the liver using reconstituted chylomicron remnants as a novel nonviral vector. Proc Natl Acad Sci 94:14547–14552</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9405650</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">25050</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hattori Y, Tamaki K, Ozaki K-I, Kawano K, Onishi H (2019) Optimized combination of cationic lipids and neutral helper lipids in cationic liposomes for siRNA delivery into the lung by intravenous injection of siRNA lipoplexes. J Drug Deliv Sci Technol 52:1042–1050</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>He X, Jiang Z, Akakuru OU, Li J, Wu A (2021) Nanoscale covalent organic frameworks: from controlled synthesis to cancer therapy. Chem Commun 57:12417–12435</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hekele A, Bertholet S, Archer J, Gibson DG, Palladino G, Brito LA, Otten GR, Brazzoli M, Buccato S, Bonci A (2013) Rapidly produced SAM® vaccine against H7N9 influenza is immunogenic in mice. Emerg Microbes Infect 2:1–7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holzer FS (2015) The iterative informed consent model for the feedback of incidental findings in human health research using WGS procedures El modelo iterativo de consentimiento informado para hallazgos incidentales en la investigación clínica con secuenciación genómica completa. Universidad de Buenos Aires</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hou X, Zaks T, Langer R, Dong Y (2021) Lipid nanoparticles for mRNA delivery. Nat Rev Mater 6:1078–1094</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34394960</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8353930</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Houacine C, Yousaf SS, Khan I, Khurana RK, Singh KK (2018) Potential of natural biomaterials in nano-scale drug delivery. Curr Pharm Des 24:5188–5206</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30657035</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackson LA, Anderson EJ, Rouphael NG, Roberts PC, Makhene M, Coler RN, McCullough MP, Chappell JD, Denison MR, Stevens LJ (2020a) An mRNA vaccine against SARS-CoV-2—preliminary report. N Engl J Med 383:1920–1931</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32663912</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackson NA, Kester KE, Casimiro D, Gurunathan S, DeRosa F (2020b) The promise of mRNA vaccines: a biotech and industrial perspective. Npj Vaccines 5:11</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32047656</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7000814</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin S, Ye K (2007) Nanoparticle-mediated drug delivery and gene therapy. Biotechnol Prog 23:32–41</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17269667</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jones CH, Chen C-K, Ravikrishnan A, Rane S, Pfeifer BA (2013) Overcoming nonviral gene delivery barriers: perspective and future. Mol Pharm 10:4082–4098</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24093932</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5232591</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karponi G, Zogas N (2019) Gene therapy for beta-thalassemia: updated perspectives. Appl Clin Genet 12:167–180</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31576160</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6765258</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim DY, Kwon JS, Lee JH, Jin LM, Kim JH, Kim MS (2015) Effects of the surface charge of stem cell membranes and DNA/Polyethyleneimine nanocomplexes on gene transfection efficiency. J Biomed Nanotechnol 11:522–530</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26307834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kowalski PS, Rudra A, Miao L, Anderson DG (2019) Delivering the messenger: advances in technologies for therapeutic mRNA delivery. Mol Ther 27:710–728</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30846391</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6453548</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kranz LM, Diken M, Haas H, Kreiter S, Loquai C, Reuter KC, Meng M, Fritz D, Vascotto F, Hefesha H (2016) Systemic RNA delivery to dendritic cells exploits antiviral defence for cancer immunotherapy. Nature 534:396–401</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27281205</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lai SK, Wang Y-Y, Hanes J (2009) Mucus-penetrating nanoparticles for drug and gene delivery to mucosal tissues. Adv Drug Deliv Rev 61:158–171</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19133304</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Langer R (1998) Drug delivery and targeting. Nature 392:5–10</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9579855</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li C, Wang J, Wang Y, Gao H, Wei G, Huang Y, Yu H, Gan Y, Wang Y, Mei L (2019) Recent progress in drug delivery. Acta Pharma Sin B 9:1145–1162</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu C-H, Yu S-Y (2010) Cationic nanoemulsions as non-viral vectors for plasmid DNA delivery. Colloids Surf b: Biointerfaces 79:509–515</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20541375</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu C-X, Ye J-S, Zhang N, Ma C, Luan F (2008) Preliminary studies on cationic solid lipid nanoparticles/pDNA binary complex. Chin Pharm J 43:1050–1056</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu C, Chen Z, Yu W, Zhang N (2011) Novel cationic 6-lauroxyhexyl lysinate modified poly (lactic acid)–poly (ethylene glycol) nanoparticles enhance gene transfection. J Colloid Interface Sci 354:528–535</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21094495</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu D, Gao S, Zhai Y, Yang X, Zhai G (2022) Research progress of tumor targeted drug delivery based on PD-1/PD-L1. Int J Pharm 616:121527</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35104594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lutz J, Lazzaro S, Habbeddine M, Schmidt KE, Baumhof P, Mui BL, Tam YK, Madden TD, Hope MJ, Heidenreich R (2017) Unmodified mRNA in LNPs constitutes a competitive technology for prophylactic vaccines. Npj Vaccines 2:29</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29263884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5648897</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma Z, Li J, He F, Wilson A, Pitt B, Li S (2005) Cationic lipids enhance siRNA-mediated interferon response in mice. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 330:755–759</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15809061</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maeder ML, Gersbach CA (2016) Genome-editing technologies for gene and cell therapy. Mol Ther 24:430–446</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26755333</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4786923</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Magini D, Giovani C, Mangiavacchi S, Maccari S, Cecchi R, Ulmer JB, De Gregorio E, Geall AJ, Brazzoli M, Bertholet S (2016) Self-amplifying mRNA vaccines expressing multiple conserved influenza antigens confer protection against homologous and heterosubtypic viral challenge. PLoS ONE 11:e0161193</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27525409</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4985159</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mali S (2013) Delivery systems for gene therapy. Indian J Hum Genet 19:3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23901186</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3722627</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mater E (2021) Let’s talk about lipid nanoparticles. Nat Rev Mater 6:99</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matthew DB (2019) Two threats to precision medicine equity. Ethn Dis 29:629</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31889768</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6919972</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mayor S, Pagano RE (2007) Pathways of clathrin-independent endocytosis. Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol 8:603–612</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17609668</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McConnell EL, Fadda HM, Basit AW (2008) Gut instincts: explorations in intestinal physiology and drug delivery. Int J Pharm 364:213–226</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18602774</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCormack MP, Rabbitts TH (2004) Activation of the T-cell oncogene LMO2 after gene therapy for X-linked severe combined immunodeficiency. N Engl J Med 350:913–922</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14985489</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Medina-Kauwe L, Xie J, Hamm-Alvarez S (2005a) Intracellular trafficking of nonviral vectors. Gene Ther 12:1734–1751</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16079885</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Medina-Kauwe L, Xie J, Hamm-Alvarez S (2005b) Intracellular trafficking of nonviral vectors. Gene Ther 12:1734–1751</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16079885</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mendes BB, Conniot J, Avital A, Yao D, Jiang X, Zhou X, Sharf-Pauker N, Xiao Y, Adir O, Liang H (2022) Nanodelivery of nucleic acids. Nat Rev Methods Prim 2:24</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mercuri E, Sumner CJ, Muntoni F, Darras BT, Finkel RS (2022) Spinal muscular atrophy. Nat Rev Dis Primers 8:52</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35927425</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mével M, Kamaly N, Carmona S, Oliver MH, Jorgensen MR, Crowther C, Salazar FH, Marion PL, Fujino M, Natori Y (2010) DODAG; a versatile new cationic lipid that mediates efficient delivery of pDNA and siRNA. J Control Release 143:222–232</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19969034</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Milane L, Amiji M (2021) Clinical approval of nanotechnology-based SARS-CoV-2 mRNA vaccines: impact on translational nanomedicine. Drug Deliv Transl Res 11:1309–1315</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33512669</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7845267</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mirón-Barroso S, Domènech EB, Trigueros S (2021) Nanotechnology-based strategies to overcome current barriers in gene delivery. Int J Mol Sci 22:8537</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34445243</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8395193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mukherjee S, Ray S, Thakur RS (2009) Solid lipid nanoparticles: a modern formulation approach in drug delivery system. Indian J Pharm Sci 71:349</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20502539</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2865805</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nabhan JF, Wood KM, Rao VP, Morin J, Bhamidipaty S, Labranche TP, Gooch RL, Bozal F, Bulawa CE, Guild BC (2016) Intrathecal delivery of frataxin mRNA encapsulated in lipid nanoparticles to dorsal root ganglia as a potential therapeutic for Friedreich’s ataxia. Sci Rep 6:20019</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26883577</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4756688</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nafee N, Taetz S, Schneider M, Schaefer UF, Lehr C-M (2007) Chitosan-coated PLGA nanoparticles for DNA/RNA delivery: effect of the formulation parameters on complexation and transfection of antisense oligonucleotides. Nanomedicine: Nanotechnol Biol Med 3:173–183</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nathwani A, Benjamin R, Nienhuis A, Davidoff A (2004) Current status and prospects for gene therapy. Vox Sang 87:73–81</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15355497</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nathwani AC (2019) Gene therapy for hemophilia. Hematology 2014, the American Society of Hematology Education Program Book, pp 1–8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nóbrega C, Mendonça L, Matos CA (2020) A handbook of gene and cell therapy. Springers International Publishing, Cham</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nuzbrokh Y, Ragi SD, Tsang SH (2021) Gene therapy for inherited retinal diseases. Ann Transl Med 9. https://doi.org/10.21037/atm-20-4726</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Neill MJ, Bourre L, Melgar S, O’Driscoll CM (2011) Intestinal delivery of non-viral gene therapeutics: physiological barriers and preclinical models. Drug Discov Today 16:203–218</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21262379</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ogbonmide T, Rathore R, Rangrej SB, Hutchinson S, Lewis M, Ojilere S, Carvalho V, Kelly I (2023) Gene therapy for spinal muscular atrophy (SMA): A review of current challenges and safety considerations for onasemnogene abeparvovec (Zolgensma). Cureus 15. https://doi.org/10.7759/cureus.36197</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ohno H (2016) Intestinal M cells. J Biochem 159:151–160</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26634447</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osman N, Devnarain N, Omolo CA, Fasiku V, Jaglal Y, Govender T (2022) Surface modification of nano-drug delivery systems for enhancing antibiotic delivery and activity. Wiley Interdiscip Rev: Nanomedicine Nanobiotechnol 14:e1758</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Panday R, Poudel AJ, Li X, Adhikari M, Ullah MW, Yang G (2018) Amphiphilic core-shell nanoparticles: synthesis, biophysical properties, and applications. Colloids Surf b: Biointerfaces 172:68–81</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30138789</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Panyam J, Labhasetwar V (2003) Biodegradable nanoparticles for drug and gene delivery to cells and tissue. Adv Drug Deliv Rev 55:329–347</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12628320</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park JW, Lagniton PN, Liu Y, Xu R-H (2021) mRNA vaccines for COVID-19: what, why and how. Int J Biol Sci 17:1446</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33907508</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8071766</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patel M, Patel K, Patel D (2020) Oral gene delivery: an innovative approach for colorectal center therapy. J Drug Deliv Ther 10:186–188</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peer D, Karp JM, Hong S, Farokhzad OC, Margalit R, Langer R (2007) Nanocarriers as an emerging platform for cancer therapy. Nat Nanotechnol 2:751–760</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18654426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pichon C, Billiet L, Midoux P (2010) Chemical vectors for gene delivery: uptake and intracellular trafficking. Curr Opin Biotechnol 21:640–645</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20674331</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polack FP, Thomas SJ, Kitchin N, Absalon J, Gurtman A, Lockhart S, Perez JL, Pérez Marc G, Moreira ED, Zerbini C (2020) Safety and efficacy of the BNT162b2 mRNA Covid-19 vaccine. N Engl J Med 383:2603–2615</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33301246</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ponti F, Campolungo M, Melchiori C, Bono N, Candiani G (2021) Cationic lipids for gene delivery: many players, one goal. Chem Phys Lipids 235:105032</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33359210</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramamoorth M, Narvekar A (2015) Non viral vectors in gene therapy-an overview. J Clin Diagn Res: JCDR 9:GE01</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25738007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4347098</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robertson KE, McDonald RA, Oldroyd KG, Nicklin SA, Baker AH (2012) Prevention of coronary in-stent restenosis and vein graft failure: does vascular gene therapy have a role? Pharmacol Ther 136:23–34</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22796519</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubanyi GM (2001) The future of human gene therapy. Mol Asp Med 22:113–142</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sack BK, Herzog RW (2009) Evading the immune response upon in vivo gene therapy with viral vectors. Curr Opin Mol Ther 11:493</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19806497</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3584155</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saffari M, Moghimi HR, Dass CR (2016) Barriers to liposomal gene delivery: from application site to the target. Iran J Pharm Res: IJPR 15:3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28228799</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5242347</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Safinya CR (2001) Structures of lipid–DNA complexes: supramolecular assembly and gene delivery. Curr Opin Struct Biol 11:440–448</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11495736</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sahay G, Alakhova DY, Kabanov AV (2010) Endocytosis of nanomedicines. J Control Release 145:182–195</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20226220</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2902597</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sahay G, Querbes W, Alabi C, Eltoukhy A, Sarkar S, Zurenko C, Karagiannis E, Love K, Chen D, Zoncu R (2013) Efficiency of siRNA delivery by lipid nanoparticles is limited by endocytic recycling. Nat Biotechnol 31:653–658</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23792629</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3814166</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sayour EJ, De Leon G, Pham C, Grippin A, Kemeny H, Chua J, Huang J, Sampson JH, Sanchez-Perez L, Flores C (2017) Systemic activation of antigen-presenting cells via RNA-loaded nanoparticles. Oncoimmunology 6:e1256527</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28197373</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schätzlein AG (2003) Targeting of synthetic gene delivery systems. BioMed Res Int 2003:149</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma M, Khan S, Rahman S, Singh LR (2019) The extracellular protein, transthyretin is an oxidative stress biomarker. Front Physiol 10:5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30733681</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6353848</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shupe J, Zhang A, Odenwelder DC, Dobrowsky T (2022) Gene therapy: challenges in cell culture scale-up. Curr Opin Biotechnol 75:102721</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35398708</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sikora J (2007) Novel aspects of molecular biology and pathology of lysosomal storage disorders. Studies with partial use of caenorhabditis elegans. Dissertation thesis, supervisor Elleder, Milan. Charles University, 1st Faculty of Medicine, Institute of Inherited Metabolic Disorders, 1st Faculty of Medicine and General University Hospital in Prague</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silva AL, Marcelino HR, Veríssimo LM, Araujo IB, Agnez-Lima LF, do Egito ES (2016) Stearylamine-containing cationic nanoemulsion as a promising carrier for gene delivery. J Nanosci Nanotechnol 16:1339–1345</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27433584</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh AK, Yadav TP, Pandey B, Gupta V, Singh SP (2019) Engineering nanomaterials for smart drug release: recent advances and challenges. Appl Target Nano Drugs Deliv Syst 411–449. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-12-814029-1.00015-6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Touitou Y, Portaluppi F, Smolensky MH, Rensing L (2004) Ethical principles and standards for the conduct of human and animal biological rhythm research. Chronobiol Int 21:161–170</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15129830</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Truong B, Allegri G, Liu X-B, Burke KE, Zhu X, Cederbaum SD, Häberle J, Martini PG, Lipshutz GS (2019) Lipid nanoparticle-targeted mRNA therapy as a treatment for the inherited metabolic liver disorder arginase deficiency. Proc Natl Acad Sci 116:21150–21159</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31501335</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6800360</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uhl P, Pantze S, Storck P, Parmentier J, Witzigmann D, Hofhaus G, Huwyler J, Mier W, Fricker G (2017) Oral delivery of vancomycin by tetraether lipid liposomes. Eur J Pharm Sci 108:111–118</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28716758</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Varkouhi AK, Scholte M, Storm G, Haisma HJ (2011a) Endosomal escape pathways for delivery of biologicals. J Control Release 151:220–228</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21078351</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Varkouhi AK, Scholte M, Storm G, Haisma HJ (2011b) Endosomal escape pathways for delivery of biologicals. J Control Release 151:220–228</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21078351</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verbeke R, Lentacker I, De Smedt SC, Dewitte H (2021) The dawn of mRNA vaccines: the COVID-19 case. J Control Release 333:511–520</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33798667</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8008785</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vighi E, Ruozi B, Montanari M, Battini R, Leo E (2010) pDNA condensation capacity and in vitro gene delivery properties of cationic solid lipid nanoparticles. Int J Pharm 389:254–261</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20100555</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waddington-Cruz M, Ackermann EJ, Polydefkis M, Heitner SB, Dyck PJ, Barroso FA, Wang AK, Berk JL, Dyck PJB, Monia BP (2018) Hereditary transthyretin amyloidosis: baseline characteristics of patients in the NEURO-TTR trial. Amyloid 25:180–188</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30169969</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wagstaff KM, Fan JY, de Jesus MA, Tremethick DJ, Jans DA (2008) Efficient gene delivery using reconstituted chromatin enhanced for nuclear targeting. FASEB J 22:2232–2242</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18356302</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walsh EE, Frenck RW Jr, Falsey AR, Kitchin N, Absalon J, Gurtman A, Lockhart S, Neuzil K, Mulligan MJ, Bailey R (2020) Safety and immunogenicity of two RNA-based Covid-19 vaccine candidates. N Engl J Med 383:2439–2450</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33053279</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J, Lu Z, Wientjes MG, Au JL-S (2010) Delivery of siRNA therapeutics: barriers and carriers. AAPS J 12:492–503</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20544328</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2977003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu P, Chen H, Jin R, Weng T, Ho JK, You C, Zhang L, Wang X, Han C (2018) Non-viral gene delivery systems for tissue repair and regeneration. J Transl Med 16:29</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29448962</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5815227</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu Y, Shrestha N, Préat V, Beloqui A (2020) Overcoming the intestinal barrier: A look into targeting approaches for improved oral drug delivery systems. J Control Release 322:486–508</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32276004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu Y, Michalowski CB, Beloqui A (2021) Advances in lipid carriers for drug delivery to the gastrointestinal tract. Curr Opin Colloid Interface Sci 52:101414</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang J (2019) Patisiran for the treatment of hereditary transthyretin-mediated amyloidosis. Expert Rev Clin Pharmacol 12:95–99</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30644768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang S, Chen Y, Ahmadie R, Ho EA (2013) Advancements in the field of intravaginal siRNA delivery. J Control Release 167:29–39</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23298612</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yin H, Kanasty RL, Eltoukhy AA, Vegas AJ, Dorkin JR, Anderson DG (2014) Non-viral vectors for gene-based therapy. Nat Rev Genet 15:541–555</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25022906</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang X, Zhao W, Nguyen GN, Zhang C, Zeng C, Yan J, Du S, Hou X, Li W, Jiang J (2020) Functionalized lipid-like nanoparticles for in vivo mRNA delivery and base editing. Sci Adv 6:eabc2315</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32937374</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7442477</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhi D, Bai Y, Yang J, Cui S, Zhao Y, Chen H, Zhang S (2018) A review on cationic lipids with different linkers for gene delivery. Adv Colloid Interface Sci 253:117–140</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29454463</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>