<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39354932</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">0915-5287</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>36</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of physical therapy science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Phys Ther Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Correlation between psychological stress and depressive symptoms among Japanese university students: a cross-sectional analysis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>656</StartPage><EndPage>661</EndPage><MedlinePgn>656-661</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1589/jpts.36.656</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>[Purpose] Higher education students face significant environmental changes, placing them at heightened risk of developing depressive symptoms that have been exacerbated by the coronavirus infectious disease pandemic. This study examined the association between psychological stress and depressive symptoms among Japanese university students. [Participants and Methods] We conducted an online and face-to-face questionnaire survey with 145 Japanese university students studying rehabilitation sciences. Depressive symptoms and psychological stress were evaluated using the Self-rating Depression Scale and Stress Response Scale-18, respectively. [Results] Among the participants, 88 had depressive symptoms. Compared to the non-depressive symptom group, the depressive symptom group experienced higher psychological stress and comprised significantly more women and individuals with insomnia. Logistic regression analysis revealed that psychological stress and insomnia were independent predictors of depressive symptoms. [Conclusion] Psychological stress is independently associated with depressive symptoms. The correlation between insomnia, stress, and depressive symptoms requires further investigation. Future research should explore the causal relationship between psychological stress and depressive symptoms and consider the factors that may influence this relationship.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>2024©by the Society of Physical Therapy Science. Published by IPEC Inc.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ashizawa</LastName><ForeName>Ryota</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Rehabilitation, Seirei Mikatahara General Hospital, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hamaoka</LastName><ForeName>Katsumi</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physical Therapy, Faculty of Health Science, Osaka Yukioka College of Health Science: 1-1-41 Sojiji, Ibaraki-shi, Osaka 567-0801, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Honda</LastName><ForeName>Hiroya</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Rehabilitation Sciences, Seirei Christopher University Graduate School, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Rehabilitation, Hanadaira Care Center, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yoshimoto</LastName><ForeName>Yoshinobu</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Rehabilitation Sciences, Seirei Christopher University Graduate School, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Japan</Country><MedlineTA>J Phys Ther Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9105359</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0915-5287</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Depressive symptoms</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Psychological stress</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">University students</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>There is no conflict of interest to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39354932</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11441886</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1589/jpts.36.656</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">2024-058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Auerbach RP, Mortier P, Bruffaerts R, et al. WHO WMH-ICS Collaborators: WHO World Mental Health Surveys International College Student Project: Prevalence and distribution of mental disorders. J Abnorm Psychol, 2018, 127: 623–638.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6193834</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30211576</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Recabarren RE, Gaillard C, Guillod M, et al. : Short-term effects of a multidimensional stress prevention program on quality of life, well-being and psychological resources. a randomized controlled trial. Front Psychiatry, 2019, 10: 88.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6422882</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30914974</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Wang A, Wu Y, et al. : Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on the mental health of college students: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Front Psychol, 2021, 12: 669119.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8316976</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34335381</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang JJ, Ji Y, Li YH, et al. : Prevalence of anxiety symptom and depressive symptom among college students during COVID-19 pandemic: a meta-analysis. J Affect Disord, 2021, 292: 242–254.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8595068</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34134022</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haikalis M, Doucette H, Meisel MK, et al. : Changes in college student anxiety and depression from pre- to during-COVID-19: perceived stress, academic challenges, loneliness, and positive perceptions. Emerg Adulthood, 2022, 10: 534–545.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8919103</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35382515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y, Wu X, Tao S, et al. : Associations between screen time, physical activity, and depressive symptoms during the 2019 coronavirus disease (COVID-19) outbreak among Chinese college students. Environ Health Prev Med, 2021, 26: 107.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8562930</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34727892</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarokhani D, Delpisheh A, Veisani Y, et al. : Prevalence of depression among university students: a systematic review and meta-analysis study. Depress Res Treat, 2013, 2013: 373857.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3800630</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24187615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bravo AJ, Sotelo M, Pilatti A, et al. Cross-Cultural Addictions Study Team: Depressive symptoms, ruminative thinking, marijuana use motives, and marijuana outcomes: a multiple mediation model among college students in five countries. Drug Alcohol Depend, 2019, 204: 107558.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6878192</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31586807</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moskow DM, Lipson SK, Tompson MC: Anxiety and suicidality in the college student population. J Am Coll Health, 2024, 72: 881–888.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9568619</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35427461</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fabbri C: Genetic and environmental contribution to major depressive disorder and self-declared depression. EBioMedicine, 2016, 14: 7–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5161433</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27916549</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu XB, Zhang HN, Dai Y, et al. : Simvastatin prevents and ameliorates depressive behaviors via neuroinflammatory regulation in mice. J Affect Disord, 2019, 245: 939–949.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30699879</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ganjoo M, Farhadi A, Baghbani R, et al. : Association between health locus of control and perceived stress in college student during the COVID-19 outbreak: a cross-sectional study in Iran. BMC Psychiatry, 2021, 21: 529.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8547728</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34702220</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tripathi MN, Kumari S, Ganpat TS: Psychophysiological effects of yoga on stress in college students. J Educ Health Promot, 2018, 7: 43.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5868218</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29619394</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu S, Adamsk K: Intervention effect of cognitive behaviour therapy under suicidology on psychological stress and emotional depression of college students. Work, 2021, 69: 697–709.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34120946</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Z, Liu R, Zhang Y, et al. : Association between perceived stress and depression among medical students during the outbreak of COVID-19: the mediating role of insomnia. J Affect Disord, 2021, 292: 89–94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8595067</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34107425</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sprung JM, Rogers A: Work-life balance as a predictor of college student anxiety and depression. J Am Coll Health, 2021, 69: 775–782.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31971892</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heinen I, Bullinger M, Kocalevent RD: Perceived stress in first year medical students—associations with personal resources and emotional distress. BMC Med Educ, 2017, 17: 4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5216588</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28056972</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moon JH, Kong MH, Kim HJ: Low muscle mass and depressed mood in Korean adolescents: a cross-sectional analysis of the Fourth and Fifth Korea National Health and Nutrition Examination Surveys. J Korean Med Sci, 2018, 33: e320.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6281954</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30534032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao J, Zhao F, Ren Z: Association between changes in muscle strength and risk of depressive symptoms among Chinese female college students: a prospective cohort study. Front Public Health, 2021, 9: 616750.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8060500</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33898372</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kato T: Effect of psychological inflexibility on depressive symptoms and sleep disturbance among Japanese young women with chronic pain. Int J Environ Res Public Health, 2020, 17: 7426.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7600104</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33053863</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhong Y, Schroeder E, Gao Y, et al. : Social support, health literacy and depressive symptoms among medical students: an analysis of mediating effects. Int J Environ Res Public Health, 2021, 18: 633.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7828636</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33451118</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vieira FD, Muraro AP, Rodrigues PR, et al. : Lifestyle-related behaviors and depressive symptoms in college students. Cad Saude Publica, 2021, 37: e00202920.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34644759</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zung WW: A self-rating depression scale. Arch Gen Psychiatry, 1965, 12: 63–70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14221692</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campo-Arias A, Díaz-Martínez LA, Eduardo G, et al. : Validation of Zung’s Self-Rating Depression Scale among the Colombian general population. Soc Behav Personal, 2006, 34: 87–94.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suzuki S: Stress Response Scale-18 (SRS-18). In: Public Health Research Center, ed. Stress scale guidebook. Tokyo: Jitsumu Kyouiku Shupan, 2006, pp 423–427.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okajima I, Nakajima S, Kobayashi M, et al. : Development and validation of the Japanese version of the Athens Insomnia Scale. Psychiatry Clin Neurosci, 2013, 67: 420–425.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23910517</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soldatos CR, Dikeos DG, Paparrigopoulos TJ: The diagnostic validity of the Athens Insomnia Scale. J Psychosom Res, 2003, 55: 263–267.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12932801</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun JL, Chiou JF, Lin CC: Validation of the Taiwanese version of the Athens Insomnia Scale and assessment of insomnia in Taiwanese cancer patients. J Pain Symptom Manage, 2011, 41: 904–914.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21420272</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doi Y, Minowa M, Uchiyama M, et al. : Psychometric assessment of subjective sleep quality using the Japanese version of the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI-J) in psychiatric disordered and control subjects. Psychiatry Res, 2000, 97: 165–172.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11166088</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sørensen K, Pelikan JM, Röthlin F, et al. HLS-EU Consortium: Health literacy in Europe: comparative results of the European health literacy survey (HLS-EU). Eur J Public Health, 2015, 25: 1053–1058.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4668324</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25843827</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakayama K, Osaka W, Togari T, et al. : Comprehensive health literacy in Japan is lower than in Europe: a validated Japanese-language assessment of health literacy. BMC Public Health, 2015, 15: 505.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4491868</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26001385</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sullivan MJ, Bishop SR, Pivik J: The Pain Catastrophizing Scale: development and validation. Psychol Assess, 1995, 7: 524–532.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matsuoka H, Sakano Y: Assessment of cognitive aspect of pain: development, reliability, and validation of Japanese version of Pain Catastrophizing Scale. Psychosom Med, 2007, 47: 95–102.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Craig CL, Marshall AL, Sjöström M, et al. : International physical activity questionnaire: 12-country reliability and validity. Med Sci Sports Exerc, 2003, 35: 1381–1395.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12900694</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sember V, Meh K, Sorić M, et al. : Validity and reliability of International Physical Activity Questionnaires for adults across EU countries: systematic review and meta analysis. Int J Environ Res Public Health, 2020, 17: 7161.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7579664</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33007880</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Syed SA, Beurel E, Loewenstein DA, et al. : Defective inflammatory pathways in never-treated depressed patients are associated with poor treatment response. Neuron, 2018, 99: 914–924.e3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6151182</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30146307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Milenkovic VM, Stanton EH, Nothdurfter C, et al. : The role of chemokines in the pathophysiology of major depressive disorder. Int J Mol Sci, 2019, 20: 2283.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6539240</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31075818</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seo JS, Wei J, Qin L, et al. : Cellular and molecular basis for stress-induced depression. Mol Psychiatry, 2017, 22: 1440–1447.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5269558</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27457815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Warner-Schmidt JL, Flajolet M, Maller A, et al. : Role of p11 in cellular and behavioral effects of 5-HT4 receptor stimulation. J Neurosci, 2009, 29: 1937–1946.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6666274</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19211900</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams AB, Dzierzewski JM, Griffin SC, et al. : Insomnia disorder and behaviorally induced insufficient sleep syndrome: prevalence and relationship to depression in college students. Behav Sleep Med, 2020, 18: 275–286.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6814500</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30789063</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamaoka K, Ashizawa R, Hida M, et al. : Chronic lumbar pain and insomnia in college-aged students. Healthcare (Basel), 2022, 10: 701.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9031783</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35455878</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Riemann D, Krone LB, Wulff K, et al. : Sleep, insomnia, and depression. Neuropsychopharmacology, 2020, 45: 74–89.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6879516</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31071719</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hertenstein E, Feige B, Gmeiner T, et al. : Insomnia as a predictor of mental disorders: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Sleep Med Rev, 2019, 43: 96–105.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30537570</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li L, Wu C, Gan Y, et al. : Insomnia and the risk of depression: a meta-analysis of prospective cohort studies. BMC Psychiatry, 2016, 16: 375.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5097837</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27816065</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fang H, Tu S, Sheng J, et al. : Depression in sleep disturbance: a review on a bidirectional relationship, mechanisms and treatment. J Cell Mol Med, 2019, 23: 2324–2332.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6433686</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30734486</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin YS, Wang CC, Chen CY: GWAS meta-analysis reveals shared genes and biological pathways between major depressive disorder and insomnia. Genes (Basel), 2021, 12: 1506.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8536096</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34680902</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benson KL, Bottary R, Schoerning L, et al. : 1H MRS measurement of cortical GABA and glutamate in primary insomnia and major depressive disorder: relationship to sleep quality and depression severity. J Affect Disord, 2020, 274: 624–631.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10662933</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32663996</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duman RS, Sanacora G, Krystal JH: Altered connectivity in depression: GABA and glutamate neurotransmitter deficits and reversal by novel treatments. Neuron, 2019, 102: 75–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6450409</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30946828</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balbo M, Leproult R, Van Cauter E: Impact of sleep and its disturbances on hypothalamo-pituitary-adrenal axis activity. Int J Endocrinol, 2010, 2010: 759234.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2902103</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20628523</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernandez-Mendoza J, Vgontzas AN: Insomnia and its impact on physical and mental health. Curr Psychiatry Rep, 2013, 15: 418.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3972485</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24189774</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>