<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39352717</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>01</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2198-3844</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Advanced science (Weinheim, Baden-Wurttemberg, Germany)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Adv Sci (Weinh)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A Dual-Adjuvanted Parenteral-Intranasal Subunit Nanovaccine generates Robust Systemic and Mucosal Immunity Against SARS-CoV-2 in Mice.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e2402792</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e2402792</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/advs.202402792</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Existing parenteral SARS-CoV-2 vaccines produce only limited mucosal responses, essential for reducing transmission and achieving sterilizing immunity. Appropriately designed mucosal boosters can overcome the shortcomings of parenteral vaccines and enhance pre-existing systemic immunity. Here, a new protein subunit nanovaccine is developed by utilizing dual-adjuvanted (RIG-I: PUUC RNA and TLR-9: CpG DNA) polysaccharide-amino acid-lipid nanoparticles (PAL-NPs) along with SARS-CoV-2 S1 trimer protein, that can be delivered both intramuscularly (IM) and intranasally (IN) to generate balanced mucosal-systemic SARS-CoV-2 immunity. Mice receiving IM-Prime PUUC+CpG PAL subunit nanovaccine, followed by an IN-Boost, developed high levels of IgA, IgG, and cellular immunity in the lungs and showed robust systemic humoral immunity. Interestingly, as a purely intranasal subunit vaccine (IN-Prime/IN-Boost), PUUC+CpG PAL-NPs induced stronger lung-specific T cell immunity than IM-Prime/IN-Boost, and a comparable IgA and neutralizing antibodies, although with a lower systemic antibody response, indicating that a fully mucosal delivery route for SARS-CoV-2 vaccination may also be feasible. The data suggest that PUUC+CpG PAL subunit nanovaccine is a promising candidate for generating SARS-CoV-2 specific mucosal immunity.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Advanced Science published by Wiley‐VCH GmbH.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pandey</LastName><ForeName>Bhawana</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4090-2618</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wallace H. Coulter Department of Biomedical Engineering, Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Zhengying</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wallace H. Coulter Department of Biomedical Engineering, Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jimenez</LastName><ForeName>Angela</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wallace H. Coulter Department of Biomedical Engineering, Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bhatia</LastName><ForeName>Eshant</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Woodruff School of Mechanical Engineering, Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jain</LastName><ForeName>Ritika</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wallace H. Coulter Department of Biomedical Engineering, Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Beach</LastName><ForeName>Alexander</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wallace H. Coulter Department of Biomedical Engineering, Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Maniar</LastName><ForeName>Drishti</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wallace H. Coulter Department of Biomedical Engineering, Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hosten</LastName><ForeName>Justin</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wallace H. Coulter Department of Biomedical Engineering, Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>O'Farrell</LastName><ForeName>Laura</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Physiological Research Laboratory, Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vantucci</LastName><ForeName>Casey</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wallace H. Coulter Department of Biomedical Engineering, Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hur</LastName><ForeName>David</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wallace H. Coulter Department of Biomedical Engineering, Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Noel</LastName><ForeName>Richard</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Physiological Research Laboratory, Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rinqguist</LastName><ForeName>Rachel</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Parker H. Petit Institute for Bioengineering and Biosciences, School of Chemical &amp; Biomolecular Engineering, Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Smith</LastName><ForeName>Clinton</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wallace H. Coulter Department of Biomedical Engineering, Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ochoa</LastName><ForeName>Miguel A</ForeName><Initials>MA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wallace H. Coulter Department of Biomedical Engineering, Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Roy</LastName><ForeName>Krishnendu</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9972-0950</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wallace H. Coulter Department of Biomedical Engineering, The Parker H. Petit Institute for Bioengineering and Biosciences, Marcus Center for Therapeutic Cell Characterization and Manufacturing, Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Engineering, Department of Chemical and Biomolecular Engineering, School of Engineering, Department of Pathology, Microbiology and Immunology, School of Medicine, Vanderbilt University, Nashville, TN, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>U01-AI124270</GrantID><Agency>National Institutes of Health- National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Disease</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Georgia Tech Foundation</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Robert A. Milton Chaired Professorship to Krishnendu Roy</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Adv Sci (Weinh)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101664569</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2198-3844</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS‐CoV‐2 subunit nanovaccine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antiviral immunity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">combination adjuvants</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mucosal immunity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">parenteral and intranasal vaccination</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">polymer nanoparticles</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39352717</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/advs.202402792</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>W. H. O. COVID, World Health Organization (WHO) 2022, https://data.who.int/dashboards/covid19/deaths.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. R. Baden, H. M. El Sahly, B. Essink, K. Kotloff, S. Frey, R. Novak, D. Diemert, S. A. Spector, N. Rouphael, C. B. Creech, N. Engl. J. Med. 2021, 384, 403.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Dagan, N. Barda, E. Kepten, O. Miron, S. Perchik, M. A. Katz, M. A. Hernán, M. Lipsitch, B. Reis, R. D. Balicer, N. Engl. J. Med. 2021, 384, 1412.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. G. Levin, Y. Lustig, C. Cohen, R. Fluss, V. Indenbaum, S. Amit, R. Doolman, K. Asraf, E. Mendelson, A. Ziv, C. Rubin, L. Freedman, Y. Kreiss, G. Regev‐Yochay, N. Engl. J. Med. 2021, 385, e84.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. C. Koff, T. Schenkelberg, T. Williams, R. S. Baric, A. McDermott, C. M. Cameron, M. J. Cameron, M. B. Friemann, G. Neumann, Y. Kawaoka, A. A. Kelvin, T. M. Ross, S. Schultz‐Cherry, T. D. Mastro, F. H. Priddy, K. A. Moore, J. T. Ostrowsky, M. T. Osterholm, J. Goudsmit, Sci. Transl. Med. 2021, 13, 1525.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. J. Siddle, L. A. Krasilnikova, G. K. Moreno, S. F. Schaffner, J. Vostok, N. A. Fitzgerald, J. E. Lemieux, N. Barkas, C. Loreth, I. Specht, C. H. Tomkins‐Tinch, J. S. Paull, B. Schaeffer, B. P. Taylor, B. Loftness, H. Johnson, P. L. Schubert, H. M. Shephard, M. Doucette, T. Fink, A. S. Lang, S. Baez, J. Beauchamp, S. Hennigan, E. Buzby, S. Ash, J. Brown, S. Clancy, S. Cofsky, L. Gagne, et al., Cell 2022, 185, 485.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. R. Bourgonje, A. E. Abdulle, W. Timens, J. Hillebrands, G. J. Navis, S. J. Gordijn, M. C. Bolling, G. Dijkstra, A. A. Voors, A. D. Osterhaus, P. H. Voort, D. J. Mulder, H. Goor, J. Pathol. 2020, 251, 228.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Tang, C. Zeng, T. M. Cox, C. Li, Y. M. Son, I. S. Cheon, Y. Wu, S. Behl, J. J. Taylor, R. Chakaraborty, A. J. Johnson, D. N. Shiavo, J. P. Utz, J. S. Reisenauer, D. E. Midthun, J. J. Mullon, E. S. Edell, M. G. Alameh, L. Borish, W. G. Teague, M. H. Kaplan, D. Weissman, R. Kern, H. Hu, R. Vassallo, S.‐L. Liu, J. Sun, Sci. Immunol. 2022, 7, 4853.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Wang, F. Schmidt, Y. Weisblum, F. Muecksch, C. O. Barnes, S. Finkin, D. Schaefer‐Babajew, M. Cipolla, C. Gaebler, J. A. Lieberman, Nature 2021, 592, 616.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Focosi, F. Maggi, A. Casadevall, Viruses 2022, 14, 187.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Iwasaki, Annu. Rev. Immunol. 2016, 34, 575.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Waltz, Nature 2022, 609, 240.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. M. Knisely, L. E. Buyon, R. Mandt, R. Farkas, S. Balasingam, K. Bok, U. J. Buchholz, M. P. D'Souza, J. L. Gordon, D. F. L. King, T. T. Le, W. W. Leitner, R. A. Seder, A. Togias, S. Tollefsen, D. W. Vaughn, D. N. Wolfe, K. L. Taylor, A. S. Fauci, NPJ Vaccines 2023, 8, 53.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Israelow, T. Mao, J. Klein, E. Song, B. Menasche, S. B. Omer, A. Iwasaki, Sci Immunol 2021, 6, eabl4509.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Silva‐Sanchez, T. D. Randall, Trends Immunol. 2023, 44, 87.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Mao, B. Israelow, M. A. Peña‐Hernández, A. Suberi, L. Zhou, S. Luyten, M. Reschke, H. Dong, R. J. Homer, W. M. Saltzman, A. Iwasaki, Science 2022, 1979, 378.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Suberi, M. K. Grun, T. Mao, B. Israelow, M. Reschke, J. Grundler, L. Akhtar, T. Lee, K. Shin, A. S. Piotrowski‐Daspit, R. J. Homer, A. Iwasaki, H.‐W. Suh, W. M. Saltzman, Sci. Transl. Med. 2023, 15, abq0603.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Y. Wong, K. S. Lee, B. P. Russ, A. M. Horspool, J. Kang, M. T. Winters, M. A Wolf, N. A. Rader, O. A. Miller, M. Shiflett, J. Izac, D. Varisco, E. Sen‐Kilic, C. Cunningham, M. Cooper, H. A. Cyphert, M. Barbier, I. Martinez, J. R. Bevere, R. K. Ernst, F. H. Damron, NPJ Vaccines 2022, 7, 36.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Li, A. Y. Jiang, I. Raji, C. Atyeo, T. M. Raimondo, A. G. R. Gordon, L. H. Rhym, T. Samad, C. MacIsaac, J. Witten, H. Mughal, T. M. Chicz, Y. Xu, R. P. McNamara, S. Bhatia, G. Alter, R. Langer, D. G. Anderson, Nat. Biomed. Eng. 2023, 7, 1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Mekonnen, H. M. Mengist, T. Jin, Expert Rev. Vaccines 2022, 21, 69.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. G. Reed, M. T. Orr, C. B. Fox, Nat. Med. 2013, 19, 1597.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Pulendran, P. S. Arunachalam, D. T. O'Hagan, Nat. Rev. Drug. Discov. 2021, 20, 454.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Jangra, J. J. Landers, R. Rathnasinghe, J. J. O'Konek, K. W. Janczak, M. Cascalho, A. A. Kennedy, A. W. Tai, J. R. Baker, M. Schotsaert, P. T. Wong, Front. Immunol. 2021, 12, 729189.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. G. Nguyen, S. M. Mantooth, M. R. Vrabel, D. A. Zaharoff, Front. Immunol. 2022, 13, 858904.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. K. Routhu, N. Cheedarla, V. S. Bollimpelli, S. Gangadhara, V. V. Edara, L. Lai, A. Sahoo, A. Shiferaw, T. M. Styles, K. Floyd, S. Fischinger, C. Atyeo, S. A. Shin, S. Gumber, S. Kirejczyk, K. H. Dinnon, P.‐Y. Shi, V. D. Menachery, M. Tomai, C. B. Fox, G. Alter, T. H. Vanderford, L. Gralinski, M. S. Suthar, R. R. Amara, Nat. Commun. 2021, 12, 3587.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. B. Belshe, K. M. Edwards, T. Vesikari, S. V. Black, R. E. Walker, M. Hultquist, G. Kemble, E. M. Connor, N. Engl. J. Med. 2007, 356, 685.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Wibowo, S. H. T. Jorritsma, Z. J. Gonzaga, B. Evert, S. Chen, B. H. A. Rehm, Biomaterials 2021, 268, 120597.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Pradhan, R. Toy, N. Jhita, A. Atalis, B. Pandey, A. Beach, E. L. Blanchard, S. G. Moore, D. A. Gaul, P. J. Santangelo, D. M. Shayakhmetov, K. Roy, Sci. Adv. 2021, 7, abd4235.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Toy, M. C. Keenum, P. Pradhan, K. Phang, P. Chen, C. Chukwu, L. A. H. Nguyen, J. Liu, S. Jain, G. Kozlowski, J. Hosten, M. S. Suthar, K. Roy, J. Controlled Release 2021, 330, 866.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Atalis, M. C. Keenum, B. Pandey, A. Beach, P. Pradhan, C. Vantucci, L. O'Farrell, R. Noel, R. Jain, J. Hosten, C. Smith, L. Kramer, A. Jimenez, M. A. Ochoa, D. Frey, K. Roy, J. Controlled Release 2022, 347, 476.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Wang, L. Wang, H. Cao, C. Liu, J. Med. Virol. 2021, 93, 892.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Cromer, M. Steain, A. Reynaldi, T. E. Schlub, A. K. Wheatley, J. A. Juno, S. J. Kent, J. A. Triccas, D. S. Khoury, M. P. Davenport, Lancet Microbe 2022, 3, e52.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. M. L. Poon, K. Rybkina, Y. Kato, M. Kubota, R. Matsumoto, N. I. Bloom, Z. Zhang, K. M. Hastie, A. Grifoni, D. Weiskopf, Sci. Immunol. 2021, 6, eabl9105.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Cibrián, F. Sánchez‐Madrid, Eur. J. Immunol. 2017, 47, 946.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. C. Rosato, L. K. Beura, D. Masopust, Curr. Opin. Virol. 2017, 22, 44.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. R. Allie, J. E. Bradley, U. Mudunuru, M. D. Schultz, B. A. Graf, F. E. Lund, T. D. Randall, Nat. Immunol. 2019, 20, 97.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Zhang, K. Li, Z. Liu, K. S. Nandakumar, S. Jiang, Viruses 2022, 14, 387.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. N. Vu, H. G. Kelly, S. J. Kent, A. K. Wheatley, EBioMedicine 2021, 74, 103699.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Huang, E. Kon, X. Han, X. Zhang, N. Kong, M. J. Mitchell, D. Peer, W. Tao, Nat. Nanotechnol. 2022, 17, 1027.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. H. Park, H. K. Lee, Vaccines 2021, 9, 524.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Purwada, K. Roy, A. Singh, Acta Biomater. 2014, 10, 1728.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Zhao, Y. Xie, X. Lin, W. Xu, Int J Nanomedicine 2022, 17, 4579.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Rohrer, N. Lupo, A. Bernkop‐Schnürch, Int. J. Pharm. 2018, 8, 553.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Smith, E. Wood, M. Dornish, Pharm. Res. 2004, 21, 43.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Artursson, T. Lindmark, S. S. Davis, L. Illum, Pharm. Res. 1994, 11, 1358.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Toy, P. Pradhan, V. Ramesh, N. C. Di Paolo, B. Lash, J. Liu, E. L. Blanchard, C. J. Pinelli, P. J. Santangelo, D. M. Shayakhmetov, K. Roy, Biomaterials 2019, 225, 119512.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Salel, B. Iyisan, Discover Nano 2023, 18, 114.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Li, T. Luo, R. Sheng, J. Sun, Z. Wang, A. Cao, Colloids Surf. B Biointerfaces 2016, 148, 73.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K.‐L. Chang, Y. Higuchi, S. Kawakami, F. Yamashita, M. Hashida, Bioconjug. Chem. 2010, 21, 1087.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. D. Peterson, L. A. Herzenberg, K. Vasquez, C. Waltenbaugh, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 1998, 95, 3071.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K.‐L. Chang, Y. Higuchi, S. Kawakami, F. Yamashita, M. Hashida, J. Controlled Release 2011, 156, 195.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Helft, J. Böttcher, P. Chakravarty, S. Zelenay, J. Huotari, B. U. Schraml, D. Goubau, C. Reis e Sousa, Immunity 2015, 42, 1197.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. A. K. Warren, C. K. Payne, RSC Adv. 2015, 5, 13660.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Liu, L. Zhang, D. Joo, S.‐C. Sun, Signal Transduct Target Ther 2017, 2, 17023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. L. Engel, G. E. Holt, H. Lu, Expert Rev. Clin. Pharmacol. 2011, 4, 275.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Madan‐Lala, P. Pradhan, K. Roy, Sci. Rep. 2017, 7, 2530.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Su, L. Du, S. Jiang, Nat. Rev. Microbiol. 2021, 19, 211.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Havervall, U. Marking, J. Svensson, N. Greilert‐Norin, P. Bacchus, P. Nilsson, S. Hober, M. Gordon, K. Blom, J. Klingström, M. Åberg, A. Smed‐Sörensen, C. Thålin, N. Engl. J. Med. 2022, 387, 1333.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. Beljanski, C. Chiang, G. A. Kirchenbaum, D. Olagnier, C. E. Bloom, T. Wong, E. K. Haddad, L. Trautmann, T. M. Ross, J. Hiscott, J. Virol. 2015, 89, 10612.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. R. Holdsworth, A. R. Kitching, P. G. Tipping, Kidney Int. 1999, 55, 1198.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. M. E. Lim, A. T. Tan, N. Le Bert, S. K. Hang, J. G. H. Low, A. Bertoletti, J. Exp. Med. 2022, 219, e20220780.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. M. Son, J. Sun, Cells 2021, 10, 2355,</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. W. Kim, J. G. Canchola, C. D. Brandt, G. Pyles, R. M. Chanock, K. Jensen, R. H. Parrott, Am. J. Epidemiol. 1969, 89, 422.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Bolles, D. Deming, K. Long, S. Agnihothram, A. Whitmore, M. Ferris, W. Funkhouser, L. Gralinski, A. Totura, M. Heise, R. S. Baric, J. Virol. 2011, 85, 12201.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Lei, A. Alu, J. Yang, W. Ren, C. He, T. Lan, X. He, L. Yang, J. Li, Z. Wang, X. Song, W. Wang, G. Lu, X. Wei, Signal Transduct. Target. Ther. 2022, 7, 159.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Grifoni, D. Weiskopf, S. I. Ramirez, J. Mateus, J. M. Dan, C. R. Moderbacher, S. A. Rawlings, A. Sutherland, L. Premkumar, R. S. Jadi, D. Marrama, A. M. de Silva, A. Frazier, A. F. Carlin, J. A. Greenbaum, B. Peters, F. Krammer, D. M. Smith, S. Crotty, A. Sette, Cell 2020, 181, 1489.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>