<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39355408</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2287-2892</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of lipid and atherosclerosis</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Lipid Atheroscler</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Therapeutic Vaccines and Nucleic Acid Drugs for Cardiovascular Disease.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>328</StartPage><EndPage>337</EndPage><MedlinePgn>328-337</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.12997/jla.2024.13.3.328</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>To combat the spread of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), novel vaccine modalities, such as messenger RNA vaccines, were rapidly developed and have shown high efficacy. This new vaccine technology, underpinned by intensive immunological analysis, is now being applied to the production of other vaccines. For over 10 years, we have been developing therapeutic vaccines for non-infectious diseases. The epitope vaccine approach, which combines a B-cell epitope with exogenous T-cell epitopes presented through major histocompatibility complex molecules, has been proposed to induce antibody production. This vaccine type is designed to efficiently induce a blocking antibody response against the self-antigen without activating cytotoxic T cells. If therapeutic vaccines become established as treatment options for conditions such as hypertension or dyslipidemia, their administration-potentially only a few times per year-could replace the need for daily medication. Nucleic acid drugs, including small interfering RNA and antisense oligonucleotides, have recently received attention as long-term agonists, similar to vaccines. Therefore, therapeutic vaccines or nucleic acid drugs could represent a novel strategy for controlling the progression of cardiovascular diseases. It is hoped that the accumulation of immunological findings and advances in vaccine technology will provide valuable insights into the development of vaccines for treating cardiovascular diseases.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Korean Society of Lipid and Atherosclerosis.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nakagami</LastName><ForeName>Hironori</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4494-3601</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Development and Medicine, Osaka University Graduate School of Medicine, Suita, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hayashi</LastName><ForeName>Hiroki</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5722-3764</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Development and Medicine, Osaka University Graduate School of Medicine, Suita, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Morishita</LastName><ForeName>Ryuichi</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8855-0730</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Gene Therapy, Osaka University Graduate School of Medicine, Suita, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Korea (South)</Country><MedlineTA>J Lipid Atheroscler</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101610890</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2287-2892</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Cardiovascular disease</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Epitope</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Nucleic acid</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Vaccine</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflict of Interest: The Department of Health Development and Medicine is supported by Anges, Daicel, and Funpep. The Department of Geriatric and General Medicine has been awarded funding for clinical study by Anges. The Department of Clinical Gene Therapy is financially supported by Novartis, AnGes, Shionogi, Boeringher, Fancl, Saisei Mirai Clinics, Rohto, and Funpep. R.M. is a stockholder of FunPep and AnGes. H.N. is a scientific advisor of Funpep.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>31</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39355408</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11439748</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.12997/jla.2024.13.3.328</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Nakagami H. Development of COVID-19 vaccines utilizing gene therapy technology. Int Immunol. 2021;33:521–527.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8083619</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33772572</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corbett KS, Edwards DK, Leist SR, Abiona OM, Boyoglu-Barnum S, Gillespie RA, et al. SARS-CoV-2 mRNA vaccine design enabled by prototype pathogen preparedness. Nature. 2020;586:567–571.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7581537</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32756549</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao Q, Bao L, Mao H, Wang L, Xu K, Yang M, et al. Development of an inactivated vaccine candidate for SARS-CoV-2. Science. 2020;369:77–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7202686</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32376603</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krammer F. SARS-CoV-2 vaccines in development. Nature. 2020;586:516–527.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32967006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakagami H. Design of therapeutic vaccines as a novel antibody therapy for cardiovascular diseases. J Cardiol. 2017;70:201–205.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28400080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoshida S, Nakagami H, Hayashi H, Ikeda Y, Sun J, Tenma A, et al. The CD153 vaccine is a senotherapeutic option for preventing the accumulation of senescent T cells in mice. Nat Commun. 2020;11:2482.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7235045</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32424156</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pang Z, Nakagami H, Osako MK, Koriyama H, Nakagami F, Tomioka H, et al. Therapeutic vaccine against DPP4 improves glucose metabolism in mice. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2014;111:E1256–E1263.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3977240</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24639549</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kitsuka T, Shiraki A, Oyama JI, Nakagami H, Tanaka A, Node K. A novel soluble epoxide hydrolase vaccine protects murine cardiac muscle against myocardial infarction. Sci Rep. 2022;12:6923.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9051153</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35484372</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suda M, Shimizu I, Katsuumi G, Yoshida Y, Hayashi Y, Ikegami R, et al. Senolytic vaccination improves normal and pathological age-related phenotypes and increases lifespan in progeroid mice. Nat Aging. 2021;1:1117–1126.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37117524</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wardemann H, Yurasov S, Schaefer A, Young JW, Meffre E, Nussenzweig MC. Predominant autoantibody production by early human B cell precursors. Science. 2003;301:1374–1377.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12920303</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harris JR, Markl J. Keyhole limpet hemocyanin (KLH): a biomedical review. Micron. 1999;30:597–623.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10544506</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crotty S. Follicular helper CD4 T cells (TFH) Annu Rev Immunol. 2011;29:621–663.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21314428</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang J, Wu Q, Liu Z, Wang Q, Wu J, Hu Y, et al. Spike-specific circulating T follicular helper cell and cross-neutralizing antibody responses in COVID-19-convalescent individuals. Nat Microbiol. 2021;6:51–58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33199863</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tenma A, Nakagami H, Tomioka H, Sakaguchi M, Ide R, Koriyama H, et al. AJP001, a novel helper T-cell epitope, induces a humoral immune response with activation of innate immunity when included in a peptide vaccine. FASEB Bioadv. 2019;1:760–772.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6996369</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32123820</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakamaru R, Nakagami H, Hayashi H, Sun J, Tenma A, Yamamoto K, et al. A novel angiotensin II peptide vaccine without an adjuvant in mice. J Hypertens. 2021;39:181–189.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7752219</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32667158</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferrer I, Boada Rovira M, Sánchez Guerra ML, Rey MJ, Costa-Jussá F. Neuropathology and pathogenesis of encephalitis following amyloid-beta immunization in Alzheimer’s disease. Brain Pathol. 2004;14:11–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8095815</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14997933</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ambühl PM, Tissot AC, Fulurija A, Maurer P, Nussberger J, Sabat R, et al. A vaccine for hypertension based on virus-like particles: preclinical efficacy and phase I safety and immunogenicity. J Hypertens. 2007;25:63–72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17143175</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown MJ, Coltart J, Gunewardena K, Ritter JM, Auton TR, Glover JF. Randomized double-blind placebo-controlled study of an angiotensin immunotherapeutic vaccine (PMD3117) in hypertensive subjects. Clin Sci (Lond) 2004;107:167–173.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15040783</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tissot AC, Maurer P, Nussberger J, Sabat R, Pfister T, Ignatenko S, et al. Effect of immunisation against angiotensin II with CYT006-AngQb on ambulatory blood pressure: a double-blind, randomised, placebo-controlled phase IIa study. Lancet. 2008;371:821–827.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18328929</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakagami F, Koriyama H, Nakagami H, Osako MK, Shimamura M, Kyutoku M, et al. Decrease in blood pressure and regression of cardiovascular complications by angiotensin II vaccine in mice. PLoS One. 2013;8:e60493.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3609829</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23544146</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koriyama H, Nakagami H, Nakagami F, Osako MK, Kyutoku M, Shimamura M, et al. Long-term reduction of high blood pressure by angiotensin II DNA vaccine in spontaneously hypertensive rats. Hypertension. 2015;66:167–174.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26015450</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watanabe R, Suzuki JI, Wakayama K, Maejima Y, Shimamura M, Koriyama H, et al. A peptide vaccine targeting angiotensin II attenuates the cardiac dysfunction induced by myocardial infarction. Sci Rep. 2017;7:43920.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5339733</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28266578</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wakayama K, Shimamura M, Suzuki JI, Watanabe R, Koriyama H, Akazawa H, et al. Angiotensin II peptide vaccine protects ischemic brain through reducing oxidative stress. Stroke. 2017;48:1362–1368.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28364024</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakagami H, Ishihama T, Daikyoji Y, Sasakura C, Yamada E, Morishita R. Brief report on a phase I/IIa study to assess the safety, tolerability, and immune response of AGMG0201 in patients with essential hypertension. Hypertens Res. 2022;45:61–65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8668431</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34657138</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fredrikson GN, Hedblad B, Berglund G, Alm R, Ares M, Cercek B, et al. Identification of immune responses against aldehyde-modified peptide sequences in apoB associated with cardiovascular disease. Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol. 2003;23:872–878.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12649091</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fredrikson GN, Andersson L, Söderberg I, Dimayuga P, Chyu KY, Shah PK, et al. Atheroprotective immunization with MDA-modified apo B-100 peptide sequences is associated with activation of Th2 specific antibody expression. Autoimmunity. 2005;38:171–179.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16040338</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rittershaus CW, Miller DP, Thomas LJ, Picard MD, Honan CM, Emmett CD, et al. Vaccine-induced antibodies inhibit CETP activity in vivo and reduce aortic lesions in a rabbit model of atherosclerosis. Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol. 2000;20:2106–2112.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10978256</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davidson MH, Maki K, Umporowicz D, Wheeler A, Rittershaus C, Ryan U. The safety and immunogenicity of a CETP vaccine in healthy adults. Atherosclerosis. 2003;169:113–120.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12860257</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Catapano AL, Papadopoulos N. The safety of therapeutic monoclonal antibodies: implications for cardiovascular disease and targeting the PCSK9 pathway. Atherosclerosis. 2013;228:18–28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23466067</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koren MJ, Scott R, Kim JB, Knusel B, Liu T, Lei L, et al. Efficacy, safety, and tolerability of a monoclonal antibody to proprotein convertase subtilisin/kexin type 9 as monotherapy in patients with hypercholesterolaemia (MENDEL): a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled, phase 2 study. Lancet. 2012;380:1995–2006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23141812</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kazi DS, Moran AE, Coxson PG, Penko J, Ollendorf DA, Pearson SD, et al. Cost-effectiveness of PCSK9 inhibitor therapy in patients with heterozygous familial hypercholesterolemia or atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease. JAMA. 2016;316:743–753.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27533159</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kawakami R, Nozato Y, Nakagami H, Ikeda Y, Shimamura M, Yoshida S, et al. Development of vaccine for dyslipidemia targeted to a proprotein convertase subtilisin/kexin type 9 (PCSK9) epitope in mice. PLoS One. 2018;13:e0191895.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5811007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29438441</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fukami H, Morinaga J, Nakagami H, Hayashi H, Okadome Y, Matsunaga E, et al. Vaccine targeting ANGPTL3 ameliorates dyslipidemia and associated diseases in mouse models of obese dyslipidemia and familial hypercholesterolemia. Cell Rep Med. 2021;2:100446.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8606905</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34841293</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakagami H. Challenges in the development of novel therapies, vaccines and siRNAs for the treatment of hypertension. Hypertens Res. 2023;46:1812–1815.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37169884</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ranasinghe P, Addison ML, Dear JW, Webb DJ. Small interfering RNA: Discovery, pharmacology and clinical development-an introductory review. Br J Pharmacol. 2023;180:2697–2720.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36250252</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheu-Gruttadauria J, MacRae IJ. Structural foundations of RNA silencing by Argonaute. J Mol Biol. 2017;429:2619–2639.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5576611</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28757069</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Setten RL, Rossi JJ, Han SP. The current state and future directions of RNAi-based therapeutics. Nat Rev Drug Discov. 2019;18:421–446.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30846871</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jinek M, Doudna JA. A three-dimensional view of the molecular machinery of RNA interference. Nature. 2009;457:405–412.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19158786</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ray KK, Landmesser U, Leiter LA, Kallend D, Dufour R, Karakas M, et al. Inclisiran in patients at high cardiovascular risk with elevated LDL cholesterol. N Engl J Med. 2017;376:1430–1440.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28306389</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Springer AD, Dowdy SF. GalNAc-siRNA conjugates: leading the way for delivery of RNAi therapeutics. Nucleic Acid Ther. 2018;28:109–118.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5994659</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29792572</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raal FJ, Rosenson RS, Reeskamp LF, Hovingh GK, Kastelein JJP, Rubba P, et al. Evinacumab for homozygous familial hypercholesterolemia. N Engl J Med. 2020;383:711–720.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32813947</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Desai AS, Webb DJ, Taubel J, Casey S, Cheng Y, Robbie GJ, et al. Zilebesiran, an RNA interference therapeutic agent for hypertension. N Engl J Med. 2023;389:228–238.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37467498</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kawano T, Shimamura M, Nakagami H, Iso T, Koriyama H, Takeda S, et al. Therapeutic vaccine against S100A9 (S100 calcium-binding protein A9) inhibits thrombosis without increasing the risk of bleeding in ischemic stroke in mice. Hypertension. 2018;72:1355–1364.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30571223</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bussian TJ, Aziz A, Meyer CF, Swenson BL, van Deursen JM, Baker DJ. Clearance of senescent glial cells prevents tau-dependent pathology and cognitive decline. Nature. 2018;562:578–582.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6206507</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30232451</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>