<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39350146</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1477-9560</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>22</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>30</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Thrombosis journal</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Thromb J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Heparin therapy in sepsis and sepsis-associated disseminated intravascular coagulation: a systematic review and meta-analysis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>84</StartPage><MedlinePgn>84</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">84</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12959-024-00653-0</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Sepsis is a life-threatening condition that affects 49 million people annually. Managing sepsis-associated coagulopathy poses a significant challenge due to its high mortality rates in intensive care. Recent reports suggest that administering heparin may offer potential survival benefits in sepsis and coronavirus disease cases. However, there is currently no established evidence supporting the use of heparin for sepsis. Thus, in this study, we aimed to assess the efficacy of heparin administration in patients with sepsis.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A systematic review was conducted following the PRISMA guidelines. The searches included MEDLINE, Cochrane, and Japanese databases up to January 2023. The inclusion criteria consisted of randomized control trials (RCTs) involving adult sepsis patients receiving heparin. The risk of bias was assessed using RoB2, and the data extraction included 28-day mortality and bleeding complications.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Out of 1733 initial articles, only three studies met the inclusion criteria. The analysis, which included 426 patients, showed no significant difference in 28-day and in-hospital mortality between the heparin and control groups (risk ratio [RR] = 0.86, 95% confidence interval [CI]: 0.60-1.24). Subgroup analysis of sepsis-associated disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC) patients (n = 109) also did not show a significant reduction in mortality (RR = 0.84, 95% CI: 0.51-1.38). Heterogeneity was zero, and no publication bias was observed. Additionally, there was significant difference in bleeding complications (RR = 0.49, 95% CI: 0.24-0.99, p = 0.047).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">This meta-analysis did not demonstrate a survival benefit of heparin administration in patients with sepsis and sepsis-associated DIC. Further investigation into the potential benefits of heparin is warranted. Moreover, the analysis revealed no increase in bleeding risks with heparin administration; instead, a significant reduction in the risk of bleeding was noted.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="TRIAL REGISTRATION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">This review was preregistered with PROSPERO (registration: CRD42023385091).</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Totoki</LastName><ForeName>Takaaki</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Emergency and Critical Care Medicine, Osaka Medical and Pharmaceutical University, Osaka, Japan. ttktkak@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Koami</LastName><ForeName>Hiroyuki</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Advanced Emergency Care Center, Saga University Hospital, Saga, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Makino</LastName><ForeName>Yuto</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Anesthesiology and Intensive Care Medicine, Nagoya City University Graduate School of Medical Sciences, Nagoya, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wada</LastName><ForeName>Takeshi</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Acute and Critical Care Medicine, Department of Anesthesiology and Critical Care Medicine, Hokkaido University Faculty of Medicine, Sapporo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ito</LastName><ForeName>Takashi</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Hematology and Immunology, Faculty of Life Sciences Kumamoto University, Kumamoto, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yamakawa</LastName><ForeName>Kazuma</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Emergency and Critical Care Medicine, Osaka Medical and Pharmaceutical University, Osaka, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Iba</LastName><ForeName>Toshiaki</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Emergency and Disaster Medicine, Juntendo University Graduate School of Medicine, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>30</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Thromb J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101170542</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1477-9560</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Disseminated intravascular coagulation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Heparin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Low molecular weight heparin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sepsis</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>59</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39350146</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11440886</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12959-024-00653-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12959-024-00653-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Rudd KE, Johnson SC, Agesa KM, Shackelford KA, Tsoi D, Kievlan DR, Colombara DV, Ikuta KS, Kissoon N, Finfer S, et al. Global, regional, and national sepsis incidence and mortality, 1990–2017: analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study. Lancet. 2020;395(10219):200–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6970225</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31954465</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spyropoulos AC, Goldin M, Giannis D, Diab W, Wang J, Khanijo S, Mignatti A, Gianos E, Cohen M, Sharifova G, et al. Efficacy and safety of therapeutic-dose heparin vs standard prophylactic or intermediate-dose heparins for thromboprophylaxis in high-risk hospitalized patients with COVID-19: The HEP-COVID randomized clinical trial. JAMA Intern Med. 2021;181(12):1612–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8498934</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34617959</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Billett HH, Reyes-Gil M, Szymanski J, Ikemura K, Stahl LR, Lo Y, Rahman S, Gonzalez-Lugo JD, Kushnir M, Barouqa M, et al. Anticoagulation in COVID-19: Effect of Enoxaparin, Heparin, and Apixaban on Mortality. Thromb Haemost. 2020;120(12):1691–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7869055</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33186991</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Z, Yan T, Ren D, Zhou J, Liu L, Li J, Fu S, Ni T, Xu W, Yang Y, et al. Low-molecular-weight heparin therapy reduces 28-day mortality in patients with sepsis-3 by improving inflammation and coagulopathy. Front Med (Lausanne). 2023;10:1157775.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10289000</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37359014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beurskens DMH, Huckriede JP, Schrijver R, Hemker HC, Reutelingsperger CP, Nicolaes GAF. The Anticoagulant and nonanticoagulant properties of heparin. Thromb Haemost. 2020;120(10):1371–83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32820487</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li X, Li X, Zheng Z, Liu Y, Ma X. Unfractionated heparin suppresses lipopolysaccharide-induced monocyte chemoattractant protein-1 expression in human microvascular endothelial cells by blocking Krüppel-like factor 5 and nuclear factor-κB pathway. Immunobiology. 2014;219(10):778–85.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25023776</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evans L, Rhodes A, Alhazzani W, Antonelli M, Coopersmith CM, French C, Machado FR, McIntyre L, Ostermann M, Prescott HC, et al. Surviving Sepsis Campaign: International Guidelines for Management of Sepsis and Septic Shock 2021. Crit Care Med. 2021;49(11):e1063–143.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34605781</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu XL, Wang XZ, Liu XX, Hao D, Jaladat Y, Lu F, Sun T, Lv CJ. Low-dose heparin as treatment for early disseminated intravascular coagulation during sepsis: A prospective clinical study. Exp Ther Med. 2014;7(3):604–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3919907</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24520253</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang JJ, Zou ZY, Zhou ZP, Liu Y, Yang ZJ, Zhang JJ, Luan YY, Yao YM, Wu M. Effectiveness of early heparin therapy on outcomes in critically ill patients with sepsis-induced coagulopathy. Front Pharmacol. 2023;14:1173893.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10225678</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37256226</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang C, Chi C, Guo L, Wang X, Guo L, Sun J, Sun B, Liu S, Chang X, Li E. Heparin therapy reduces 28-day mortality in adult severe sepsis patients: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Crit Care. 2014;18(5):563.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4213495</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25318353</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zarychanski R, Abou-Setta AM, Kanji S, Turgeon AF, Kumar A, Houston DS, Rimmer E, Houston BL, McIntyre L, Fox-Robichaud AE, et al. The efficacy and safety of heparin in patients with sepsis: a systematic review and metaanalysis. Crit Care Med. 2015;43(3):511–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25493972</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan Y, Jiang M, Gong D, Zou C. Efficacy and safety of low-molecular-weight heparin in patients with sepsis: a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. Sci Rep. 2016;6:25984.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4867648</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27181297</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li X, Liu Z, Luo M, Xi Y, Li C, Wang S, Yang R. Therapeutic effect of low-molecular-weight heparin on adult sepsis: a meta-analysis. Ann Palliat Med. 2021;10(3):3115–27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33849098</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fu S, Yu S, Wang L, Ma X, Li X. Unfractionated heparin improves the clinical efficacy in adult sepsis patients: a systematic review and meta-analysis. BMC Anesthesiol. 2022;22(1):28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8777179</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35062871</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Page MJ, McKenzie JE, Bossuyt PM, Boutron I, Hoffmann TC, Mulrow CD, Shamseer L, Tetzlaff JM, Akl EA, Brennan SE, et al. The PRISMA 2020 statement: an updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews. BMJ. 2021;372: n71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8005924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33782057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sterne JAC, Savović J, Page MJ, Elbers RG, Blencowe NS, Boutron I, Cates CJ, Cheng HY, Corbett MS, Eldridge SM, et al. RoB 2: a revised tool for assessing risk of bias in randomised trials. BMJ. 2019;366:l4898.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31462531</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaimes F, De La Rosa G, Morales C, Fortich F, Arango C, Aguirre D, Muñoz A. Unfractioned heparin for treatment of sepsis: A randomized clinical trial (The HETRASE Study). Crit Care Med. 2009;37(4):1185–96.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19242322</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oudemans-van Straaten HM, Bosman RJ, Koopmans M, van der Voort PH, Wester JP, van der Spoel JI, Dijksman LM, Zandstra DF. Citrate anticoagulation for continuous venovenous hemofiltration. Crit Care Med. 2009;37(2):545–52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19114912</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weng J, Chen M, Fang D, Liu D, Guo R, Yang S. Therapeutic plasma exchange protects patients with sepsis-associated disseminated intravascular coagulation by improving endothelial function. Clin Appl Thromb Hemost. 2021;27:10760296211053312.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8597066</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34775801</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zarbock A, Küllmar M, Kindgen-Milles D, Wempe C, Gerss J, Brandenburger T, Dimski T, Tyczynski B, Jahn M, Mülling N, et al. Effect of regional citrate anticoagulation vs systemic heparin anticoagulation during continuous kidney replacement therapy on dialysis filter life span and mortality among critically ill patients with acute kidney injury: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA. 2020;324(16):1629–39.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7585036</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33095849</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonaventura A, Vecchié A, Dagna L, Martinod K, Dixon DL, Van Tassell BW, Dentali F, Montecucco F, Massberg S, Levi M, et al. Endothelial dysfunction and immunothrombosis as key pathogenic mechanisms in COVID-19. Nat Rev Immunol. 2021;21(5):319–29.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8023349</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33824483</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iba T, Levy JH. Sepsis-induced coagulopathy and disseminated intravascular coagulation. Anesthesiology. 2020;132(5):1238–45.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32044801</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>To KF, Lo AW. Exploring the pathogenesis of severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS): the tissue distribution of the coronavirus (SARS-CoV) and its putative receptor, angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2). J Pathol. 2004;203(3):740–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7167902</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15221932</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iba T, Levy JH, Levi M, Thachil J. Coagulopathy in COVID-19. J Thromb Haemost. 2020;18(9):2103–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7323352</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32558075</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Umemura Y, Yamakawa K, Ogura H, Yuhara H, Fujimi S. Efficacy and safety of anticoagulant therapy in three specific populations with sepsis: a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. J Thromb Haemost. 2016;14(3):518–30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26670422</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iba T, Gando S, Saitoh D, Wada H, Di Nisio M, Thachil J. Antithrombin supplementation and risk of bleeding in patients with sepsis-associated disseminated intravascular coagulation. Thromb Res. 2016;145:46–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27479532</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morita N, Nakahara K, Morita R, Suetani K, Michikawa Y, Sato J, Tsuji K, Ikeda H, Matsunaga K, Watanabe T, et al. Efficacy of combined thrombomodulin and antithrombin in anticoagulant therapy for acute cholangitis-induced disseminated intravascular coagulation. Intern Med. 2019;58(7):907–14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6478986</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30449812</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liasidis P, Benjamin ER, Jakob D, Ding L, Lewis M, Demetriades D. Race does matter: venous thromboembolism in trauma patients with isolated severe pelvic fractures. Eur J Trauma Emerg Surg. 2023;49(1):241–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35836009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shimada YJ, Nakra NC, Fox JT, Kanei Y. Relation of race (Asian, African-American, European-American, and Hispanic) to activated clotting time after weight-adjusted bolus of heparin during percutaneous coronary intervention. Am J Cardiol. 2010;105(5):629–32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20185008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>American College of Chest Physicians/Society of Critical Care Medicine Consensus Conference: Definitions for sepsis and organ failure and guidelines for the use of innovative therapies in sepsis. Critical Care Medicine. 1992, 20(6):864–874.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1597042</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levy MM, Fink MP, Marshall JC, Abraham E, Angus D, Cook D, Cohen J, Opal SM, Vincent JL, Ramsay G. 2001 SCCM/ESICM/ACCP/ATS/SIS International Sepsis Definitions Conference. Intensive Care Med. 2003;29(4):530–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12664219</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singer M, Deutschman CS, Seymour CW, Shankar-Hari M, Annane D, Bauer M, Bellomo R, Bernard GR, Chiche JD, Coopersmith CM, et al. The third international consensus definitions for Sepsis and Septic shock (Sepsis-3). JAMA. 2016;315(8):801–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4968574</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26903338</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>