<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39350908</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2219-2808</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>09</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>World journal of clinical pediatrics</Title><ISOAbbreviation>World J Clin Pediatr</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Perception, use of social media, and its impact on the mental health of Indian adolescents: A qualitative study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>97501</StartPage><MedlinePgn>97501</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">97501</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.5409/wjcp.v13.i3.97501</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Mental illness is a health challenge faced by adolescents that has grown worse after the Coronavirus disease 2019 pandemic. Research on social media and young people's mental health has recently increased, and numerous studies have examined whether frequent use of social media is linked to issues such as anxiety, stress, depression, eating disorders, insomnia, frustration, feeling alone, and externalizing problems among adolescents. This influence of social media on adolescents' lives is clear, with many platforms like Facebook, Instagram, and YouTube playing an important role in daily interactions and self-expression. Even though social media offers numerous benefits, such as connectivity and information sharing, excessive usage can have detrimental effects on mental health, particularly among adolescents.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="AIM" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To study the impact of social media on the mental wellbeing of adolescents, and the associated potential dangers in India.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A total of 204 adolescents aged 14 years to 23 years were included in the study. This study explored the intricate relationship between social media usage and adolescent mental health in India. The study employs a cross-sectional survey design to capture a snapshot of adolescent mental health and social media usage patterns. Data collection involved administering structured questionnaires and the analysis utilized quantitative methods, including descriptive statistics.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Excessive use of social media is correlated with increased stress, anxiety, and depression. Adolescents engage in compulsive behaviors such as scrolling in the middle of the night, which negatively impacts their mental and physical health, and leads to significant sleep disruption. Findings from the study aim to provide insights into the current state of adolescent mental health and inform strategies to promote positive wellbeing in the Indian population.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The study underscores the need for further research to better understand the complex interplay between social media and adolescent mental health, and need for effective strategies to combat online harassment.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>©The Author(s) 2024. Published by Baishideng Publishing Group Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Taddi</LastName><ForeName>Vishnu V</ForeName><Initials>VV</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Amity Institute of Forensic Sciences, Amity University, Noida 201313, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kohli</LastName><ForeName>Ravshish K</ForeName><Initials>RK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Amity Institute of Forensic Sciences, Amity University, Noida 201313, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Puri</LastName><ForeName>Pooja</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Amity Institute of Forensic Sciences, Amity University, Noida 201313, India. pmalik1@amity.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>09</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>World J Clin Pediatr</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101627548</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2219-2808</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescents</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Anxiety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Cyberbullying</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Depression</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mental health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Social media</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflict-of-interest statement: The authors declare that there is no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>15</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39350908</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11438920</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5409/wjcp.v13.i3.97501</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Bozzola E, Spina G, Agostiniani R, Barni S, Russo R, Scarpato E, Di Mauro A, Di Stefano AV, Caruso C, Corsello G, Staiano A. The Use of Social Media in Children and Adolescents: Scoping Review on the Potential Risks. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19:9960.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9407706</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36011593</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma R, Vyas R. Social Media Usage Among Adolescents in India: A Study on its Influences on Social Behavior and Mental Health. Indian J Soc Psychiatry. 2023;35:13–20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O'Reilly M. Social Media and Adolescent Mental Health: The Good, the Bad and the Ugly. J Ment Health. 2020;27:81–89.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31989847</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hunt MG, Marx R, Lipson C, Young J. No More FOMO: Limiting Social Media Decreases Loneliness and Depression. J Soc Clin Psychol. 2018;37:751–768.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh A, Gupta R. Online Support Groups and Adolescent Mental Health: A Longitudinal Study. J Ment Health Res. 2024;25:210–223.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boer M, Stevens GWJM, Finkenauer C, de Looze ME, van den Eijnden RJJM. “Social media use intensity, social media use problems, and mental health among adolescents: Investigating directionality and mediating processes”. Computers in Human Behavior. 2021;116</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farooq HO, Farrukh H, khan Z. “The Influence of Social Media on Adolescents' Self-Esteem”. QJSSH. 2023;4:173–182.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hinduja S, Patchin J.  Cyberbullying identification, prevention, and response. 2018. Available from: https://cyberbullying.org/Cyberbullying-Identification-Prevention-Response-2018.pdf .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma S. ‘Body image issues faced by adolescents in India’. Int J Indian Psychol. 2017;4:176–182.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woods HC, Scott H. Sleepyteens: Social media use in adolescence is associated with poor sleep quality, anxiety, depression and low self-esteem. J Adolesc. 2016;51:41–49.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27294324</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Council on Communications and Media. From the American Academy of Pediatrics: Policy statement--Media violence. Pediatrics. 2009;124:1495–1503.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19841118</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pasquini C, Amerini I, Boato G. Media forensics on social media platforms: a survey. EURASIP J on Info Security. 2021;2021:4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zannettou S, Sirivianos M, Blackburn J, Kourtellis N. The Web of False Information. J Data and Information Quality. 2019;11:1–37.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kouokam EK, Dirik AE. PRNU-based source device attribution for YouTube videos. Digital Investigation. 2019;29:91–100.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verdoliva L. Media Forensics and DeepFakes: An Overview. IEEE J Sel Top Signal Process. 2020;14:910–932.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mayer O, Stamm MC. Exposing Fake Images With Forensic Similarity Graphs. IEEE J Sel Top Signal Process. 2020;14:1049–1064.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khalaf AM, Alubied AA, Khalaf AM, Rifaey AA. The Impact of Social Media on the Mental Health of Adolescents and Young Adults: A Systematic Review. Cureus. 2023;15:e42990.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10476631</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37671234</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faqihi FA, Qutob RA, Subh RHM, Aljathalin LAM, Alshalan LZ, Yati SMA, Alaryni A, Alghamdi A, Alsolamy E, Bukhari A, Alanazi A, Hazazi BHA, Abuhemid HA, Alassaf RA, Alzahrani SSM. Examining the Effects of Social Media on Mental Health Among Adolescents in Saudi Arabia. Cureus. 2024;16:e53261.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10904877</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38435934</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Towers S, Gomez-Lievano A, Khan M, Mubayi A, Castillo-Chavez C. Contagion in Mass Killings and School Shootings. PLoS One. 2015;10:e0117259.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4489652</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26135941</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Popat A, Tarrant C. Exploring adolescents' perspectives on social media and mental health and well-being - A qualitative literature review. Clin Child Psychol Psychiatry. 2023;28:323–337.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9902994</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35670473</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prabhakararao S. Overuse of Social Media Affects the Mental Health of Adolescents and Early Youth. IJIP. 2024;3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zsila Á, Reyes MES. Pros &amp; cons: impacts of social media on mental health. BMC Psychol. 2023;11:201.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10327389</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37415227</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jabbar J, Dharmarajan S, Raveendranathan RP, Syamkumar D, Jasseer A. Influence of Social Media on Adolescent Mental Health. IJELS. 2022;7:072–076.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaur R. Social Media and Teenagers: A Study of Mental Health. Vidhyayana. 2023;8:821–842.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation> “The Double-Edged Sword of Social Media: Exploring the Complex Relationships Between Social Media Use and Youth Mental Health.” 2024. Available from: https://www.psychiatrictimes.com/view/the-double-edged-sword-of-social-media .</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>