<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39365745</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1538-0254</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>04</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of biomolecular structure &amp; dynamics</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Biomol Struct Dyn</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Viral fingerprints of the ion channel evolution: compromise of complexity and function.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1</StartPage><EndPage>20</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1-20</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1080/07391102.2024.2411523</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Evolution from precellular supramolecular assemblies to cellular world originated from the ability to make a barrier between the interior of the cell and the outer environment. This step resulted from the possibility to form a membrane, which preserves the cell like a wall of the castle. However, every castle needs gates for trading, i.e. in the case of cell, for controlled exchange of substances. These 'gates' should have the mechanism of opening and closing, guards, entry rules, and so on. Different structures are known to be able to make membrane permeable to various substances, from ions to macromolecules. They are amphipathic peptides, their assemblies, sophisticated membrane channels with numerous transmembrane domains, etc. Upon evolving, cellular world preserved and selected many variants, which, finally, have provided both prokaryotes and eukaryotes with highly selective and regulated ion channels. However, various simpler variants of ion channels are found in viruses. Despite the origin of viruses is still under debates, they have evolved parallelly with the cellular forms of life. Being initial form of the enveloped organisms, reduction of protocells or their escaped parts, viruses might be fingerprints of the evolutionary steps of cellular structures like ion channels. Therefore, viroporins may provide us a necessary information about selection between high functionality and less complex structure in supporting all the requirements for controlled membrane permeability. In this review we tried to elucidate these compromises and show the possible way of the evolution of ion channels, from peptides to complex multi-subunit structures, basing on viral examples.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Volovik</LastName><ForeName>Marta V</ForeName><Initials>MV</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Bioelectrochemistry, A.N. Frumkin Institute of Physical Chemistry and Electrochemistry, Russian Academy of Sciences, Moscow, Russia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Batishchev</LastName><ForeName>Oleg V</ForeName><Initials>OV</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Bioelectrochemistry, A.N. Frumkin Institute of Physical Chemistry and Electrochemistry, Russian Academy of Sciences, Moscow, Russia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Biomol Struct Dyn</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8404176</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0739-1102</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Ion channel</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">coronavirus SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">hepatitis C virus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">influenza A virus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">viroporin</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39365745</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/07391102.2024.2411523</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>