<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39378001</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>11</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2197-7364</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>11</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>08</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>EJNMMI physics</Title><ISOAbbreviation>EJNMMI Phys</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>SPECT-MPI iterative denoising during the reconstruction process using a two-phase learned convolutional neural network.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>82</StartPage><MedlinePgn>82</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">82</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s40658-024-00687-3</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="PURPOSE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">The problem of image denoising in single-photon emission computed tomography (SPECT) myocardial perfusion imaging (MPI) is a fundamental challenge. Although various image processing techniques have been presented, they may degrade the contrast of denoised images. The proposed idea in this study is to use a deep neural network as the denoising procedure during the iterative reconstruction process rather than the post-reconstruction phase. This method could decrease the background coefficient of variation (COV_bkg) of the final reconstructed image, which represents the amount of random noise, while improving the contrast-to-noise ratio (CNR).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">In this study, a generative adversarial network is used, where its generator is trained by a two-phase approach. In the first phase, the network is trained by a confined image region around the heart in transverse view. The second phase improves the network's generalization by tuning the network weights with the full image size as the input. The network was trained and tested by a dataset of 247 patients who underwent two immediate serially high- and low-noise SPECT-MPI.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Quantitative results show that compared to post-reconstruction low pass filtering and post-reconstruction deep denoising methods, our proposed method can decline the COV_bkg of the images by up to 10.28% and 12.52% and enhance the CNR by up to 54.54% and 45.82%, respectively.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The iterative deep denoising method outperforms 2D low-pass Gaussian filtering with an 8.4-mm FWHM and post-reconstruction deep denoising approaches.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yousefzadeh</LastName><ForeName>Farnaz</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0006-2976-7709</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Computer Science and Engineering and IT, School of Electrical and Computer Engineering, Shiraz University, Shiraz, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yazdi</LastName><ForeName>Mehran</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8889-7048</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Electrical and Computer Engineering, Shiraz University, Shiraz, Iran. yazdi@shirazu.ac.ir.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Entezarmahdi</LastName><ForeName>Seyed Mohammad</ForeName><Initials>SM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5368-8916</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nuclear Medicine, School of Medicine, Shiraz University of Medical Sciences, Shiraz, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Faghihi</LastName><ForeName>Reza</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nuclear Engineering, Shiraz University, Shiraz, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ghasempoor</LastName><ForeName>Sadegh</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nuclear Medicine, Alzahra Hospital, Shiraz University of Medical Sciences, Shiraz, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shahamiri</LastName><ForeName>Negar</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mehrizi</LastName><ForeName>Zahra Abuee</ForeName><Initials>ZA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nuclear Medicine, School of Medicine, Shiraz University of Medical Sciences, Shiraz, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Haghighatafshar</LastName><ForeName>Mahdi</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nuclear Medicine, School of Medicine, Shiraz University of Medical Sciences, Shiraz, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>EJNMMI Phys</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101658952</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2197-7364</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Convolutional neural networks</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Deep learning</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Image denoising</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Iterative image reconstruction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SPECT-MPI</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>25</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>16</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39378001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11461437</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40658-024-00687-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s40658-024-00687-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Malek H. Nuclear cardiology. In: Practical cardiology. Elsevier; 2018. p. 167–72. 10.1016/B978-0-323-51149-0.00009-2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jerome SD, Tilkemeier PL, Farrell MB, Shaw LJ. Nationwide laboratory adherence to myocardial perfusion imaging radiation dose reduction practices: a report from the intersocietal accreditation commission data repository. Cardiovasc Imaging. 2015;8:1170–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26363837</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wells RG. Dose reduction is good but it is image quality that matters. J Nucl Cardiol. 2020;27:238–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30043253</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Juan Ramon A, Yang Y, Pretorius PH, Slomka PJ, Johnson KL, King MA, Wernick MN. Investigation of dose reduction in cardiac perfusion SPECT via optimization and choice of the image reconstruction strategy. J Nucl Cardiol. 2018;25:2117–28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9407649</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28537039</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramon AJ, Yang Y, Wernick MN, Hendrik Pretorius P, Johnson KL, Slomka PJ, King MA. Evaluation of the effect of reducing administered activity on assessment of function in cardiac gated SPECT. J Nucl Cardiol. 2020;27(2):562–72. 10.1007/s12350-018-01505-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11407505</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30406608</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeraatkar N, Sajedi S, Farahani MH, Arabi H, Sarkar S, Ghafarian P, Rahmim A, Ay MR. Resolution-recovery-embedded image reconstruction for a high-resolution animal SPECT system. Phys Med. 2014;30:774–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24986422</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arabi H, Zaidi H. Improvement of image quality in PET using post-reconstruction hybrid spatial-frequency domain filtering. Phys Med Biol. 2018;63:215010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30272565</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arabi H, Zaidi H. Non-local mean denoising using multiple PET reconstructions. Ann Nucl Med. 2021;35:176–86.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7895794</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33244745</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng Z, Wen J, Huang G, Yan J. Applications of artificial intelligence in nuclear medicine image generation. Quant Imaging Med Surg. 2021;11:2792–822.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8107336</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34079744</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramon AJ, Yang Y, Pretorius PH, Johnson KL, King MA, Wernick MN. Improving diagnostic accuracy in low-dose SPECT myocardial perfusion imaging with convolutional denoising networks. IEEE Trans Med Imaging. 2020;39:2893–903.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9472754</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32167887</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song C, Yang Y, Wernick MN, Pretorius PH, King MA, Low-dose cardiac-gated spect studies using a residual convolutional neural network. in 2019 IEEE 16th international symposium on biomedical imaging (ISBI 2019), pp. 653–656, 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olia NA, Kamali-Asl A, Tabrizi SH, Geramifar P, Sheikhzadeh P, Farzanefar S, Arabi H, Zaidi H. Deep learning–based denoising of low-dose SPECT myocardial perfusion images: quantitative assessment and clinical performance. Eur J Nucl Med Mol Imaging. 2022;49(5):1508–22. 10.1007/s00259-021-05614-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8940834</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34778929</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hashimoto F, Onishi Y, Ote K, Tashima H, Reader AJ, Yamaya T. Deep learning-based PET image denoising and reconstruction: a review. Radiol Phys Technol. 2024;17(1):24–46. 10.1007/s12194-024-00780-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10902118</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38319563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mustafovic S, Thielemans K. Object dependency of resolution in reconstruction algorithms with interiteration filtering applied to PET data. IEEE Trans Med Imaging. 2004;23(4):433–46.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15084069</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shepp LA, Vardi Y. Maximum likelihood reconstruction for emission tomography. IEEE Trans Med Imaging. 1982;1:113–22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18238264</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gengsheng LZ. Medical image reconstruction: a conceptual tutorial. Beijing: Higher Education Press; 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shiri I, Sabet KA, Arabi H, Pourkeshavarz M, Teimourian B, Ay MR, Zaidi H. Standard SPECT myocardial perfusion estimation from half-time acquisitions using deep convolutional residual neural networks. J Nucl Cardiol. 2021;28(6):2761–79. 10.1007/s12350-020-02119-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32347527</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hudson HM, Larkin RS. Accelerated image reconstruction using ordered subsets of projection data. IEEE Trans Med Imaging. 1994;13:601–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18218538</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mao X, Shen C, Yang Y-B. Image restoration using very deep convolutional encoder-decoder networks with symmetric skip connections. Adv Neural Inf Process Syst. 2016;29:2802–10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yousefzadeh F, Yazdi M, Entezarmahdi M, Faghihi R, Dehghan F, Shiri I. Improving the efficiency of deep learning-based denoising in SPECT myocardial perfusion image by two-phase learning algorithm. J Nucl Med. 2022;63:3227–3227.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shahamiri N, Yazdi M, Entezarmahdi SM, Faghihi R, Dehghan F, Shiri I. An empirical update of left ventricular 3D segmentation algorithm in myocardial perfusion SPECT imaging. J Nucl Med. 2021;62:1691–1691.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Entezarmahdi SM, Faghihi R, Yazdi M, Shahamiri N, Geramifar P, Haghighatafshar M. QCard-NM: developing a semiautomatic segmentation method for quantitative analysis of the right ventricle in non-gated myocardial perfusion SPECT imaging. EJNMMI Phys. 2023;10:1–24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10036722</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36959409</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahimian A, Etehadtavakol M, Moslehi M, Ng EYK. Myocardial perfusion single-photon emission computed tomography (SPECT) image denoising: a comparative study. Diagnostics. 2023;13(4):611. 10.3390/diagnostics13040611.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9954870</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36832099</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sattar F, Floreby L, Salomonsson G, Lovstrom B. Image enhancement based on a nonlinear multiscale method. IEEE Trans Image Process. 1997;6(6):888–95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18282982</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun J, Jiang H, Du Y, Li C-Y, Wu T-H, Liu Y-H, et al. Deep learning-based denoising in projection-domain and reconstruction-domain for low-dose myocardial perfusion SPECT. J Nucl Cardiol. 2023;30:970–85.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35982208</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sohlberg A, Kangasmaa T, Constable C, Tikkakoski A. Comparison of deep learning-based denoising methods in cardiac SPECT. EJNMMI Phys. 2023;10:9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9908801</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36752847</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim K, Wu D, Gong K, Dutta J, Kim JH, Son YD, et al. Penalized PET reconstruction using deep learning prior and local linear fitting. IEEE Trans Med Imaging. 2018;37:1478–87.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6375088</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29870375</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gong K, Guan J, Kim K, Zhang X, Yang J, Seo Y, et al. Iterative PET image reconstruction using convolutional neural network representation. IEEE Trans Med Imaging. 2018;38:675–85.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6472985</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30222554</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lyra M, Ploussi A. Filtering in SPECT image reconstruction. J Biomed Imaging. 2011;2011:1–14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3132528</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21760768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu J, Yang Y, Wernick MN, Pretorius PH, King MA. Deep learning with noise-to-noise training for denoising in SPECT myocardial perfusion imaging. Med Phys. 2021;48:156–68.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7902415</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33145782</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanaat A, Shiri I, Arabi H, Mainta I, Nkoulou R, Zaidi H. Deep learning-assisted ultra-fast/low-dose whole-body PET/CT imaging. Eur J Nucl Med Mol Imaging. 2021;48:2405–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8241799</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33495927</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu W, Onofrey JA, Lu Y, Shi L, Ma T, Liu Y, et al. An investigation of quantitative accuracy for deep learning based denoising in oncological PET. Phys Med Biol. 2019;64:165019.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31307019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ladefoged CN, Hasbak P, Hornnes C, Højgaard L, Andersen FL. Low-dose PET image noise reduction using deep learning: application to cardiac viability FDG imaging in patients with ischemic heart disease. Phys Med Biol. 2021;66:054003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33524958</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Slomka PJ, Miller RJH, Lien-Hsin H, Berman DS. Novel techniques: solid-state detectors, dose reduction (SPECT/CT). In: Nekolla SG, Rischpler C, editors. Hybrid cardiac imaging. Cham: Springer International Publishing; 2022. p. 103–29. 10.1007/978-3-030-83167-7_7.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>