<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39385504</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1099-1573</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>09</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Phytotherapy research : PTR</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Phytother Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Exploring Bioactive Phytomedicines for Advancing Pulmonary Infection Management: Insights and Future Prospects.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/ptr.8334</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Pulmonary infections have a profound influence on global mortality rates. Medicinal plants offer a promising approach to address this challenge, providing nontoxic alternatives with higher levels of public acceptance and compliance, particularly in regions where access to conventional medications or diagnostic resources may be limited. Understanding the pathophysiology of viruses and bacteria enables researchers to identify biomarkers essential for triggering diseases. This knowledge allows the discovery of biological molecules capable of either preventing or alleviating symptoms associated with these infections. In this review, medicinal plants that have an effect on COVID-19, influenza A, bacterial and viral pneumonia, and tuberculosis are discussed. Drug delivery has been briefly discussed as well. It examines the effect of bioactive constituents of these plants and synthesizes findings from in vitro, in vivo, and clinical studies conducted over the past decade. In conclusion, many medicinal plants can be used to treat pulmonary infections, but further in-depth studies are needed as most of the current studies are only at preliminary stages. Extensive investigation and clinical studies are warranted to fully elucidate their mechanisms of action and optimize their use in clinical practice.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Phytotherapy Research published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ho</LastName><ForeName>Joyce Siaw Syuen</ForeName><Initials>JSS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmaceutical Chemistry, School of Pharmacy, International Medical University, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ping</LastName><ForeName>Teh Li</ForeName><Initials>TL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmaceutical Chemistry, School of Pharmacy, International Medical University, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Paudel</LastName><ForeName>Keshav Raj</ForeName><Initials>KR</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3591-2080</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Inflammation, School of Life Sciences, Faculty of Science, Centenary Institute and the University of Technology Sydney, Sydney, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>El Sherkawi</LastName><ForeName>Tammam</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Discipline of Pharmacy, Graduate School of Health, University of Technology Sydney, Sydney, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>De Rubis</LastName><ForeName>Gabriele</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7088-396X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Discipline of Pharmacy, Graduate School of Health, University of Technology Sydney, Sydney, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Australian Research Centre in Complementary and Integrative Medicine, Faculty of Health, University of Technology Sydney, Ultimo, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yeung</LastName><ForeName>Stewart</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Discipline of Pharmacy, Graduate School of Health, University of Technology Sydney, Sydney, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hansbro</LastName><ForeName>Philip M</ForeName><Initials>PM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Inflammation, School of Life Sciences, Faculty of Science, Centenary Institute and the University of Technology Sydney, Sydney, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Oliver</LastName><ForeName>Brian Gregory George</ForeName><Initials>BGG</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Life Science, University of Technology Sydney, Ultimo, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research, Macquarie University, Sydney, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chellappan</LastName><ForeName>Dinesh Kumar</ForeName><Initials>DK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Life Sciences, School of Pharmacy, International Medical University, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sin</LastName><ForeName>Keng Pei</ForeName><Initials>KP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmaceutical Chemistry, School of Pharmacy, International Medical University, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dua</LastName><ForeName>Kamal</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7507-1159</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Discipline of Pharmacy, Graduate School of Health, University of Technology Sydney, Sydney, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Australian Research Centre in Complementary and Integrative Medicine, Faculty of Health, University of Technology Sydney, Ultimo, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Maridulu Budyari Gumal-The Sydney Partnership for Health, Education, Research and Enterprise (SPHERE)</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Triple I Skills Advancement Grant 2023</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>University of Technology Sydney Key Technology Partner (UTS-KTP)</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>UMCG Research Funds</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>09</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Phytother Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8904486</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0951-418X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">influenza</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">medicinal plants</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pneumonia</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pulmonary infection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">tuberculosis</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39385504</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ptr.8334</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>Abdallah, H. M., A. M. El‐Halawany, K. M. Darwish, et al. 2022. “Bio‐Guided Isolation of SARS‐CoV‐2 Main Protease Inhibitors From Medicinal Plants: In Vitro Assay and Molecular Dynamics.” Plants 11, no. 15: 1914. https://doi.org/10.3390/plants11151914.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adepu, S., and S. Ramakrishna. 2021. “Controlled Drug Delivery Systems: Current Status and Future Directions.” Molecules 26, no. 19: 5905. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules26195905.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ait‐Ouazzou, A., S. Lorán, M. Bakkali, et al. 2011. “Chemical Composition and Antimicrobial Activity of Essential Oils of Thymus algeriensis, Eucalyptus globulus and Rosmarinus officinalis From Morocco.” Journal of the Science of Food and Agriculture 91, no. 14: 2643–2651. https://doi.org/10.1002/jsfa.4505.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akanchise, T., and A. Angelova. 2023. “Ginkgo biloba and Long COVID: In Vivo and In Vitro Models for the Evaluation of Nanotherapeutic Efficacy.” Pharmaceutics 15, no. 5: 1562. https://doi.org/10.3390/pharmaceutics15051562.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alharbi, N. S., A. S. Alenizi, A. M. Al‐Olayan, et al. 2018. “Herbs Use in Saudi Children With Acute Respiratory Illnesses.” Sudanese Journal of Paediatrics 18, no. 2: 20–24. https://doi.org/10.24911/SJP.106‐1538457624.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al‐Kuraishy, H. M., A. I. Al‐Gareeb, A. Kaushik, M. Kujawska, and G. E.‐S. Batiha. 2022. “Ginkgo biloba in the Management of the COVID‐19 Severity.” Archiv der Pharmazie 355, no. 10: e2200188. https://doi.org/10.1002/ardp.202200188.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almeida‐Bezerra, J. W., F. C. Rodrigues, J. J. Lima Bezerra, et al. 2022. “Traditional Uses, Phytochemistry, and Bioactivities of Mesosphaerum suaveolens (L.) Kuntze.” Evidence‐Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine: eCAM 2022: 3829180. https://doi.org/10.1155/2022/3829180.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alonso‐Castro, A. J., F. Domínguez, A. J. Ruiz‐Padilla, et al. 2017. “Medicinal Plants From North and Central America and the Caribbean Considered Toxic for Humans: The Other Side of the Coin.” Evidence‐Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine: eCAM 2017: 9439868. https://doi.org/10.1155/2017/9439868.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alzohairy, M. A. 2016. “Therapeutics Role of Azadirachta indica (Neem) and Their Active Constituents in Diseases Prevention and Treatment.” Evidence‐Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine: eCAM 2016: 7382506. https://doi.org/10.1155/2016/7382506.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amenya, H. Z., P. K. Gathumbi, J. M. Mbaria, A. G. Thaiyah, and G. N. Thoithi. 2014. “Sub‐Acute Toxicity of the Chloroformic Extract of Rapanea melanophloeos (L.) Mez in Rats.” Journal of Ethnopharmacology 154, no. 3: 593–599. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jep.2014.04.001.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ansari, S., I. Ahmad, M. Ali, and M. Maaz. 2020. “‘Tiryaq Arba’ (a Polyherbal Unani Formulation) as Prophylactic Medicine Against Epidemics of Acute Respiratory Viral Infections.” Middle East Journal of Rehabilitation and Health Studies 7, no. 3: 3. https://doi.org/10.5812/mejrh.102965.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aranda‐Ledesma, N. E., M. D. González‐Hernández, R. Rojas, et al. 2022. “Essential Oil and Polyphenolic Compounds of Flourensia cernua Leaves: Chemical Profiling and Functional Properties.” Agronomy 12, no. 10: 10. https://doi.org/10.3390/agronomy12102274.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arenas, E. H., and T. P. Trinidad. 2017. “Heavy Metal and Microbiological Profiles of Defatted Pili (Canarium ovatum, Engl.) Pulp Meal Residue and Acute Oral Toxicity of Its Ethanolic Extract in Mice.” International Food Research Journal 24: 1763–1770.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashafa, A. O. T., L. O. Orekoya, and M. T. Yakubu. 2012. “Toxicity Profile of Ethanolic Extract of Azadirachta indica Stem Bark in Male Wistar Rats.” Asian Pacific Journal of Tropical Biomedicine 2, no. 10: 811–817. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2221‐1691(12)60234‐2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashique, S., K. Gupta, G. Gupta, et al. 2023. “Vitamin D‐A Prominent Immunomodulator to Prevent COVID‐19 Infection.” International Journal of Rheumatic Diseases 26, no. 1: 13–30. https://doi.org/10.1111/1756‐185X.14477.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashraf, S., S. Ashraf, M. Ashraf, et al. 2023. “Honey and Nigella sativa Against COVID‐19 in Pakistan (HNS‐COVID‐PK): A Multicenter Placebo‐Controlled Randomized Clinical Trial.” Phytotherapy Research: PTR 37, no. 2: 627–644. https://doi.org/10.1002/ptr.7640.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Astani, A., J. Reichling, and P. Schnitzler. 2010. “Comparative Study on the Antiviral Activity of Selected Monoterpenes Derived From Essential Oils.” Phytotherapy Research: PTR 24, no. 5: 673–679. https://doi.org/10.1002/ptr.2955.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Astani, A., J. Reichling, and P. Schnitzler. 2011. “Screening for Antiviral Activities of Isolated Compounds From Essential Oils.” Evidence‐Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine 2011: enep187. https://doi.org/10.1093/ecam/nep187.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Astutik, S., J. Pretzsch, and J. Ndzifon Kimengsi. 2019. “Asian Medicinal Plants' Production and Utilization Potentials: A Review.” Sustainability 11, no. 19: 19. https://doi.org/10.3390/su11195483.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aswad, M., H. Hamza, A. Pechkovsky, et al. 2022. “High‐CBD Extract (CBD‐X) Downregulates Cytokine Storm Systemically and Locally in Inflamed Lungs.” Frontiers in Immunology 13: 875546. https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2022.875546.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bahramsoltani, R., and R. Rahimi. 2020. “An Evaluation of Traditional Persian Medicine for the Management of SARS‐CoV‐2.” Frontiers in Pharmacology 11: 571434. https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2020.571434.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bani Saeid, A., V. K. Patel, S. Mehndiratta, et al. 2023. “Dissecting the In Vitro Fate of Plant‐Derived Bioactive Encapsulated Nanoparticles in Lung Diseases.” Food Bioscience 56: 103205. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fbio.2023.103205.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bin Abdulrahman, K. A., A. O. Bamosa, A. I. Bukhari, et al. 2022. “The Effect of Short Treatment With Nigella sativa on Symptoms, the Cluster of Differentiation (CD) Profile, and Inflammatory Markers in Mild COVID‐19 Patients: A Randomized, Double‐Blind Controlled Trial.” International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 19, no. 18: 11798. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph191811798.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Binsuwaidan, R., A. A. Sultan, W. A. Negm, et al. 2022. “Bilosomes as Nanoplatform for Oral Delivery and Modulated In Vivo Antimicrobial Activity of Lycopene.” Pharmaceuticals (Basel, Switzerland) 15, no. 9: 1043. https://doi.org/10.3390/ph15091043.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonifácio, B. V., P. B. da Silva, M. A. d. S. Ramos, K. M. S. Negri, T. M. Bauab, and M. Chorilli. 2013. “Nanotechnology‐Based Drug Delivery Systems and Herbal Medicines: A Review.” International Journal of Nanomedicine 9: 1–15. https://doi.org/10.2147/IJN.S52634.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonifácio, B. V., P. B. da Silva, M. A. d. S. Ramos, K. M. S. Negri, T. M. Bauab, and M. Chorilli. 2014. “Nanotechnology‐Based Drug Delivery Systems and Herbal Medicines: A Review.” International Journal of Nanomedicine 9: 1–15. https://doi.org/10.2147/IJN.S52634.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brink, D. S. 2012. “Pathology of Lung Infections.” In Respiratory: An Integrated Approach to Disease, edited by A. J. Lechner, G. M. Matuschak, and D. S. Brink. New York: McGraw‐Hill Education. accessmedicine.mhmedical.com/content.aspx?aid=1120132504.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buder, F., S.‐R. Selejan, M. Hohl, et al. 2022. “Glycyrrhizin Through Liquorice Intake Modulates ACE2 and HMGB1 Levels—A Pilot Study in Healthy Individuals With Implications for COVID‐19 and ARDS.” PLoS One 17, no. 10: e0275181. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0275181.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cai, S., S. Batra, F. Del Piero, and S. Jeyaseelan. 2016. “NLRP12 Modulates Host Defense Through IL‐17A‐CXCL1 Axis.” Mucosal Immunology 9, no. 2: 503–514. https://doi.org/10.1038/mi.2015.80.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campolina‐Silva, G., A. C. D. S. P. Andrade, M. Couto, et al. 2023. “Dietary Vitamin D Mitigates Coronavirus‐Induced Lung Inflammation and Damage in Mice.” Viruses 15, no. 12: 2434. https://doi.org/10.3390/v15122434.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cardona, P.‐J. 2018. “Pathogenesis of Tuberculosis and Other Mycobacteriosis.” Enfermedades Infecciosas Y Microbiologia Clinica (English Ed.) 36, no. 1: 38–46. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eimc.2017.10.015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carl, J. W., and X.‐F. Bai. 2008. “IL27: Its Roles in the Induction and Inhibition of Inflammation.” International Journal of Clinical and Experimental Pathology 1, no. 2: 117–123.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CDC. 2024. “National Center for Health Statistics.” https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/fastats/flu.htm.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CDCTB. 2023. World TB Day History. Atlanta: Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. https://www.cdc.gov/tb/worldtbday/history.htm.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, X., Y. Wu, C. Chen, et al. 2021. “Identifying Potential Anti‐COVID‐19 Pharmacological Components of Traditional Chinese Medicine Lianhuaqingwen Capsule Based on Human Exposure and ACE2 Biochromatography Screening.” Acta Pharmaceutica Sinica B 11, no. 1: 222–236. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apsb.2020.10.002.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, Y.‐R., W.‐P. Jiang, J.‐S. Deng, et al. 2023. “Anisomeles indica Extracts and Their Constituents Suppress the Protein Expression of ACE2 and TMPRSS2 In Vivo and In Vitro.” International Journal of Molecular Sciences 24, no. 20: 20. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms242015062.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng, P., L. Ng, L. Chiang, and C. Lin. 2006. “Antiviral Effects of Saikosaponins on Human Coronavirus 229E In Vitro.” Clinical and Experimental Pharmacology &amp; Physiology 33, no. 7: 612–616. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1440‐1681.2006.04415.x.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cho, W.‐K., H. Kim, Y. J. Choi, N.‐H. Yim, H. J. Yang, and J. Y. Ma. 2012. “Epimedium koreanum Nakai Water Extract Exhibits Antiviral Activity Against Porcine Epidermic Diarrhea Virus In Vitro and In Vivo.” Evidence‐Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine: Ecam 2012: 985151. https://doi.org/10.1155/2012/985151.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choi, M., S. H. Lee, and G. T. Chang. 2020. “Herbal Medicine Treatment for Influenza: A Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis of Randomized Controlled Trials.” American Journal of Chinese Medicine 48, no. 7: 1553–1576. https://doi.org/10.1142/S0192415X20500779.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chung, D. R., and K. Huh. 2015. “Novel Pandemic Influenza A (H1N1) and Community‐Associated Methicillin‐Resistant Staphylococcus aureus Pneumonia.” Expert Review of Anti‐Infective Therapy 13, no. 2: 197–207. https://doi.org/10.1586/14787210.2015.999668.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cock, I. E., and S. F. Van Vuuren. 2020. “The Traditional Use of Southern African Medicinal Plants in the Treatment of Viral Respiratory Diseases: A Review of the Ethnobotany and Scientific Evaluations.” Journal of Ethnopharmacology 262: 113194. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jep.2020.113194.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Conte, R., I. D. Luca, A. D. Luise, O. Petillo, A. Calarco, and G. Peluso. 2016. “New Therapeutic Potentials of Nanosized Phytomedicine.” Journal of Nanoscience and Nanotechnology 16, no. 8: 8176–8187. https://doi.org/10.1166/jnn.2016.12809.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coperchini, F., A. Greco, M. Denegri, et al. 2022. “Vitamin D and Interferon‐γ Co‐Operate to Increase the ACE‐2 Receptor Expression in Primary Cultures of Human Thyroid Cells.” Journal of Endocrinological Investigation 45, no. 11: 2157–2163. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40618‐022‐01857‐9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Darmarajan, T., K. R. Paudel, M. Candasamy, et al. 2022. “Autoantibodies and Autoimmune Disorders in SARS‐CoV‐2 Infection: Pathogenicity and Immune Regulation.” Environmental Science and Pollution Research International 29, no. 36: 54072–54087. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11356‐022‐20984‐7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Rubis, G., K. R. Paudel, L. Corrie, et al. 2023. “Applications and Advancements of Nanoparticle‐Based Drug Delivery in Alleviating Lung Cancer and Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease.” Naunyn‐Schmiedeberg's Archives of Pharmacology 397: 2793–2833. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00210‐023‐02830‐w.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delogu, G., M. Sali, and G. Fadda. 2013. “The Biology of Mycobacterium tuberculosis Infection.” Mediterranean Journal of Hematology and Infectious Diseases 5, no. 1: e2013070. https://doi.org/10.4084/MJHID.2013.070.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Devkota, H. P., K. R. Paudel, N. K. Jha, et al. 2021. “Applications of Drug‐Delivery Systems Targeting Inflammasomes in Pulmonary Diseases.” Nanomedicine (London, England) 16, no. 27: 2407–2410. https://doi.org/10.2217/nnm‐2021‐0275.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Devkota, H. P., K. R. Paudel, N. Lall, M. Tomczyk, and A. G. Atanasov. 2022. “Editorial: Pharmacology of Plant Polyphenols in Human Health and Diseases.” Frontiers in Pharmacology 13: 945033. https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2022.945033.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dewi, M. K., A. Y. Chaerunisaa, M. Muhaimin, and I. M. Joni. 2022. “Improved Activity of Herbal Medicines through Nanotechnology.” Nanomaterials 12: 4073. https://doi.org/10.3390/nano12224073.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding, Y., L. Zeng, R. Li, et al. 2017. “The Chinese Prescription Lianhuaqingwen Capsule Exerts Anti‐Influenza Activity Through the Inhibition of Viral Propagation and Impacts Immune Function.” BMC Complementary and Alternative Medicine 17: 130. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906‐017‐1585‐7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dioguardi, M., A. Ballini, D. Sovereto, et al. 2022. “Application of the Extracts of Punica granatum in Oral Cancer: Scoping Review.” Dentistry Journal 10, no. 12: 234. https://doi.org/10.3390/dj10120234.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dong, G., N. Xu, M. Wang, et al. 2021. “Anthocyanin Extract From Purple Sweet Potato Exacerbate Mitophagy to Ameliorate Pyroptosis in Klebsiella pneumoniae Infection.” International Journal of Molecular Sciences 22, no. 21: 11422. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms222111422.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doustimotlagh, A. H., and M. Eftekhari. 2021. “Glucose‐6‐Phosphate Dehydrogenase Inhibitor for Treatment of Severe COVID‐19: Polydatin.” Clinical Nutrition ESPEN 43: 197–199. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.clnesp.2021.02.021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dua, K., V. K. Rapalli, S. D. Shukla, et al. 2018. “Multi‐Drug Resistant Mycobacterium tuberculosis &amp; Oxidative Stress Complexity: Emerging Need for Novel Drug Delivery Approaches.” Biomedicine &amp; Pharmacotherapy 107: 1218–1229. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biopha.2018.08.101.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dwivedi, V. P., D. Bhattacharya, M. Singh, et al. 2019. “Allicin Enhances Antimicrobial Activity of Macrophages During Mycobacterium tuberculosis Infection.” Journal of Ethnopharmacology 243: 111634. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jep.2018.12.008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ekor, M. 2014. “The Growing Use of Herbal Medicines: Issues Relating to Adverse Reactions and Challenges in Monitoring Safety.” Frontiers in Pharmacology 4: 177. https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2013.00177.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>El Gizawy, H. A., S. A. Boshra, A. Mostafa, et al. 2021. “Pimenta dioica (L.) Merr. Bioactive Constituents Exert Anti‐SARS‐CoV‐2 and Anti‐Inflammatory Activities: Molecular Docking and Dynamics, In Vitro, and In Vivo Studies.” Molecules (Basel, Switzerland) 26, no. 19: 5844. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules26195844.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elkordy, A., R. R. Haj‐Ahmad, A. S. Awaad, and R. M. Zaki. 2021. “An Overview on Natural Product Drug Formulations from Conventional Medicines to Nanomedicines: Past, Present and Future.” Journal of Drug Delivery Science and Technology 63: 102459.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Esposito, G., M. Pesce, L. Seguella, et al. 2020. “The Potential of Cannabidiol in the COVID‐19 Pandemic.” British Journal of Pharmacology 177, no. 21: 4967–4970. https://doi.org/10.1111/bph.15157.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fang, R., K. Tsuchiya, I. Kawamura, et al. 2011. “Critical Roles of ASC Inflammasomes in Caspase‐1 Activation and Host Innate Resistance to Streptococcus pneumoniae Infection.” Journal of Immunology 187, no. 9: 4890–4899. https://doi.org/10.4049/jimmunol.1100381.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farah, M. H., R. Edwards, M. Lindquist, C. Leon, and D. Shaw. 2000. “International Monitoring of Adverse Health Effects Associated With Herbal Medicines.” Pharmacoepidemiology and Drug Safety 9, no. 2: 105–112. https://doi.org/10.1002/(SICI)1099‐1557(200003/04)9:2&lt;105::AID‐PDS486&gt;3.0.CO;2‐2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Franchi, L., A. Amer, M. Body‐Malapel, et al. 2006. “Cytosolic Flagellin Requires Ipaf for Activation of Caspase‐1 and Interleukin 1Beta in Salmonella‐Infected Macrophages.” Nature Immunology 7, no. 6: 576–582. https://doi.org/10.1038/ni1346.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Furin, J., H. Cox, and M. Pai. 2019. “Tuberculosis.” Lancet (London, England) 393, no. 10181: 1642–1656. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140‐6736(19)30308‐3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gautam, S., K. A. Qureshi, S. B. Jameel Pasha, et al. 2023. “Medicinal Plants as Therapeutic Alternatives to Combat Mycobacterium tuberculosis: A Comprehensive Review.” Antibiotics (Basel, Switzerland) 12, no. 3: 541. https://doi.org/10.3390/antibiotics12030541.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>González‐Sarrías, A., M. Larrosa, F. A. Tomás‐Barberán, P. Dolara, and J. C. Espín. 2010. “NF‐kappaB‐Dependent Anti‐Inflammatory Activity of Urolithins, Gut Microbiota Ellagic Acid‐Derived Metabolites, in Human Colonic Fibroblasts.” British Journal of Nutrition 104, no. 4: 503–512. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0007114510000826.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Govindachari, T. R., G. Suresh, G. Gopalakrishnan, B. Banumathy, and S. Masilamani. 1998. “Identification of Antifungal Compounds From the Seed Oil of Azadirachta indica.” Phytoparasitica 26, no. 2: 109–116. https://doi.org/10.1007/BF02980677.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gu, Y., X. Zuo, S. Zhang, et al. 2021. “The Mechanism Behind Influenza Virus Cytokine Storm.” Viruses 13, no. 7: 1362. https://doi.org/10.3390/v13071362.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gulati, N., D. K. Chellappan, R. MacLoughlin, K. Dua, and H. Dureja. 2021. “Inhaled Nano‐Based Therapeutics for Inflammatory Lung Diseases: Recent Advances and Future Prospects.” Life Sciences 285: 119969. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lfs.2021.119969.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gunes, H., D. Gulen, R. Mutlu, A. Gumus, T. Tas, and A. E. Topkaya. 2016. “Antibacterial Effects of Curcumin: An In Vitro Minimum Inhibitory Concentration Study.” Toxicology and Industrial Health 32, no. 2: 246–250. https://doi.org/10.1177/0748233713498458.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta, M., V. Sharma, K. Sharma, et al. 2022. “A kNGR Peptide‐Tethered Lipid‐Polymer Hybrid Nanocarrier‐Based Synergistic Approach for Effective Tumor Therapy: Development, Characterization, Ex‐Vivo, and In‐Vivo Assessment.” Pharmaceutics 14, no. 7: 1401. https://doi.org/10.3390/pharmaceutics14071401.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hafezi, S., F. Saheb Sharif‐Askari, N. Saheb Sharif‐Askari, et al. 2022. “Vitamin D Enhances Type I IFN Signaling in COVID‐19 Patients.” Scientific Reports 12, no. 1: 17778. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598‐022‐22307‐9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hajimonfarednejad, M., M. Ostovar, F. S. Hasheminasab, et al. 2023. “Medicinal Plants for Viral Respiratory Diseases: A Systematic Review on Persian Medicine.” Evidence‐Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine: eCAM 2023: 1928310. https://doi.org/10.1155/2023/1928310.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han, S., J. Xu, X. Guo, and M. Huang. 2018. “Curcumin Ameliorates Severe Influenza Pneumonia via Attenuating Lung Injury and Regulating Macrophage Cytokines Production.” Clinical and Experimental Pharmacology &amp; Physiology 45, no. 1: 84–93. https://doi.org/10.1111/1440‐1681.12848.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han, Y., Q. Yue, L. Su, et al. 2022. “Application and Prospect of Medicinal Plants Combined With Aerosol Inhalation in the Treatment of Pulmonary Diseases.” 12458: 124581X. https://doi.org/10.1117/12.2662723.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harish, V., S. Mohd, D. Tewari, et al. 2023. “Unravelling the Role of Solid Lipid Nanoparticles in Drug Delivery: Journey From Laboratory to Clinical Trial.” Journal of Drug Delivery Science and Technology 85: 104616. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jddst.2023.104616.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hensel, A., M. Maas, J. Sendker, et al. 2011. “Eupatorium perfoliatum L.: Phytochemistry, Traditional Use and Current Applications.” Journal of Ethnopharmacology 138, no. 3: 641–651. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jep.2011.10.002.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hokari, R., T. Nagai, and H. Yamada. 2012. “In Vivo Anti‐Influenza Virus Activity of Japanese Herbal (Kampo) Medicine, ‘Shahakusan’, and Its Possible Mode of Action.” Evidence‐Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine: eCAM 2012: 794970. https://doi.org/10.1155/2012/794970.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Howes, O. D., P. K. Mcguire, and S. Kapur. 2008. “Understanding Pathophysiology Is Crucial in Linking Clinical Staging to Targeted Therapeutics.” World Psychiatry 7, no. 3: 162–163.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsieh, P.‐C., Y.‐C. Chao, K.‐W. Tsai, et al. 2022. “Efficacy and Safety of Complementary Therapy With Jing Si Herbal Tea in Patients With Mild‐To‐Moderate COVID‐19: A Prospective Cohort Study.” Frontiers in Nutrition 9: 832321. https://doi.org/10.3389/fnut.2022.832321.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsu, A. C.‐Y., K. Dua, M. R. Starkey, et al. 2017. “MicroRNA‐125a and ‐b Inhibit A20 and MAVS to Promote Inflammation and Impair Antiviral Response in COPD.” JCI Insight 2, no. 7: e90443. https://doi.org/10.1172/jci.insight.90443.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu, C., B. He, F. Gong, M. Liang, D. Zhao, and G. Zhang. 2022. “The Adverse Reactions of Lianhua Qingwen Capsule/Granule Compared With Conventional Drug in Clinical Application: A Meta‐Analysis.” Frontiers in Pharmacology 13: 764774. https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2022.764774.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu, K., W. Guan, Y. Bi, et al. 2021. “Efficacy and Safety of Lianhuaqingwen Capsules, a Repurposed Chinese Herb, in Patients With Coronavirus Disease 2019: A Multicenter, Prospective, Randomized Controlled Trial.” Phytomedicine 85: 153242. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phymed.2020.153242.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hughes, L. J., L. J. Black, J. L. Sherriff, et al. 2018. “Vitamin D Content of Australian Native Food Plants and Australian‐Grown Edible Seaweed.” Nutrients 10, no. 7: 876. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu10070876.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imran, M., L. A. Jha, N. Hasan, et al. 2022. “‘Nanodecoys’—Future of Drug Delivery by Encapsulating Nanoparticles in Natural Cell Membranes.” International Journal of Pharmaceutics 621: 121790. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijpharm.2022.121790.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Indriana, M., and S. Salman. 2020. “Utilization of Nemba Stem as an Antituberculosis Compared With Rifampicin and Etambutol.” Journal of Pharmaceutical and Sciences 3, no. 2: 114–119. https://doi.org/10.36490/journal‐jps.com.v3i2.92.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iqbal, J., A. Kumar, and N. Islam. 2008. “Azadirachta indica Induced Suppression of Mycobacterium tuberculosis Secreted Proteins in Human Monocyte.” Nature Precedings 2008.1562.1. https://doi.org/10.1038/npre.2008.1562.1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackson, C. B., M. Farzan, B. Chen, and H. Choe. 2022. “Mechanisms of SARS‐CoV‐2 Entry Into Cells.” Nature Reviews Molecular Cell Biology 23, no. 1: 3–20. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41580‐021‐00418‐x.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jain, K. K. 2020. “An Overview of Drug Delivery Systems.” Methods in Molecular Biology (Clifton, N.J.) 2059: 1–54. https://doi.org/10.1007/978‐1‐4939‐9798‐5_1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jakhmola Mani, R., N. Sehgal, N. Dogra, S. Saxena, and D. Pande Katare. 2020. “Deciphering Underlying Mechanism of SARS‐CoV‐2 Infection in Humans and Revealing the Therapeutic Potential of Bioactive Constituents From Nigella sativa to Combat COVID19: In‐Silico Study.” Journal of Biomolecular Structure &amp; Dynamics 1–13: 2417–2429. https://doi.org/10.1080/07391102.2020.1839560.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaswal, A., S. Sharma, C. Uthra, D. Yadav, S. Shrivastava, and S. Shukla. 2022. “Defensive Role of Nigella sativa Against Antituberculosis Drugs Induced Renal Toxicity.” Toxicology Research 11, no. 2: 367–373. https://doi.org/10.1093/toxres/tfac014.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jesus, R. S., M. Piana, R. B. Freitas, et al. 2018. “In Vitro Antimicrobial and Antimycobacterial Activity and HPLC‐DAD Screening of Phenolics From Chenopodium ambrosioides L.” Brazilian Journal of Microbiology: [Publication of the Brazilian Society for Microbiology] 49, no. 2: 296–302. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bjm.2017.02.012.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ji, S., Q. Bai, X. Wu, et al. 2020. “Unique Synergistic Antiviral Effects of Shufeng Jiedu Capsule and Oseltamivir in Influenza A Viral‐Induced Acute Exacerbation of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease.” Biomedicine &amp; Pharmacotherapy 121: 109652. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biopha.2019.109652.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiao, Y., Y. Yang, L. Zhou, D. Chen, and Y. Lu. 2022. “Two Natural Flavonoid Substituted Polysaccharides From Tamarix chinensis: Structural Characterization and Anticomplement Activities.” Molecules 27, no. 14: 14. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules27144532.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiao, Y., L. Zhou, J. Huo, et al. 2023. “Flavonoid Substituted Polysaccharides From Tamarix chinensis Lour. Alleviate H1N1‐Induced Acute Lung Injury via Inhibiting Complement System.” Journal of Ethnopharmacology 322: 117651. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jep.2023.117651.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joshi, V., and R. P. Joshi. 2013. “Some Plants Used in Ayurvedic and Homoeopathic Medicine.” Journal of Pharmacognosy and Phytochemistry 2, no. 1: 269–275.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalil, A. C., and P. G. Thomas. 2019. “Influenza Virus‐Related Critical Illness: Pathophysiology and Epidemiology.” Critical Care 23: 258. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13054‐019‐2539‐x.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalita, N., and M. C. Kalita. 2014. “Ethnomedicinal Plants of Assam, India as an Alternative Source of Future Medicine for Treatment of Pneumonia.” International Research Journals 3: 76–82.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamelnia, E., R. Mohebbati, R. Kamelnia, H. R. El‐Seedi, and M. H. Boskabady. 2023. “Anti‐Inflammatory, Immunomodulatory and Anti‐Oxidant Effects of Ocimum basilicum L. and Its Main Constituents: A Review.” Iranian Journal of Basic Medical Sciences 26, no. 6: 617–627. https://doi.org/10.22038/IJBMS.2023.67466.14783.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kanneganti, T.‐D., M. Body‐Malapel, A. Amer, et al. 2006. “Critical Role for Cryopyrin/Nalp3 in Activation of Caspase‐1 in Response to Viral Infection and Double‐Stranded RNA.” Journal of Biological Chemistry 281, no. 48: 36560–36568. https://doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M607594200.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kasali, F. M., J. N. Kadima, J. Tusiimire, C. O. Ajayi, and A. G. Agaba. 2022. “Effects of the Oral Administration of Aqueous and Methanolic Leaf Extracts of Chenopodium ambrosioides L. (Amaranthaceae) on Blood Glucose Levels in Wistar Rats.” Journal of Experimental Pharmacology 14: 139–148. https://doi.org/10.2147/JEP.S356564.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaur, J., M. Gulati, P. Famta, et al. 2022. “Polymeric Micelles Loaded With Glyburide and Vanillic Acid: I. Formulation Development, In‐Vitro Characterization and Bioavailability Studies.” International Journal of Pharmaceutics 624: 121987. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijpharm.2022.121987.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaur, J., M. Gulati, N. K. Pandey, et al. 2023. “Antidiabetic Evaluation of Vanillic Acid‐Glyburide Loaded Polymeric Micelles in High Fat Diet and Streptozotocin Induced Diabetic Rat.” https://doi.org/10.21203/rs.3.rs‐3138446/v1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khairani, A. F., Y. Pamela, N. Oktavia, et al. 2022. “Acute and Sub‐Chronic Oral Toxicity Study of Purple Sweet Potato (Ipomoea batatas [L.] lam) Yogurt in Mice (Mus musculus).” Veterinary WORLD 15, no. 3: 789–796. https://doi.org/10.14202/vetworld.2022.789‐796.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan, A. A., F. Bashir, and J. Akhtar. 2020. “TIRYAQ E ARBA: A Classical Unani Formulation to Boost Immunity.” Journal of Drug Delivery and Therapeutics 10, no. 4‐s: 259–263. https://doi.org/10.22270/jddt.v10i4‐s.4312.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khatak, S., M. Mehta, R. Awasthi, et al. 2020. “Solid Lipid Nanoparticles Containing Anti‐Tubercular Drugs Attenuate the Mycobacterium marinum Infection.” Tuberculosis (Edinburgh, Scotland) 125: 102008. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tube.2020.102008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khazdair, M. R., S. Ghafari, and M. Sadeghi. 2021. “Possible Therapeutic Effects of Nigella sativa and Its Thymoquinone on COVID‐19.” Pharmaceutical Biology 59, no. 1: 696–703. https://doi.org/10.1080/13880209.2021.1931353.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khursheed, R., K. Dua, S. Vishwas, et al. 2022. “Biomedical Applications of Metallic Nanoparticles in Cancer: Current Status and Future Perspectives.” Biomedicine &amp; Pharmacotherapy 150: 112951. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biopha.2022.112951.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khursheed, R., K. R. Paudel, M. Gulati, et al. 2022. “Expanding the Arsenal Against Pulmonary Diseases Using Surface‐Functionalized Polymeric Micelles: Breakthroughs and Bottlenecks.” Nanomedicine (London, England) 17, no. 12: 881–911. https://doi.org/10.2217/nnm‐2021‐0451.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, H., J.‐Y. Choi, M. Hong, and H. S. Suh. 2021. “Traditional Medicine for the Treatment of Common Cold in Korean Adults: A Nationwide Population‐Based Study.” Integrative Medicine Research 10, no. 1: 100458. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.imr.2020.100458.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kiran, G., L. Karthik, M. S. Shree Devi, et al. 2020. “In Silico Computational Screening of Kabasura Kudineer—Official Siddha Formulation and JACOM Against SARS‐CoV‐2 Spike Protein.” Journal of Ayurveda and Integrative Medicine 13, no. 1: 100324. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jaim.2020.05.009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kivihall, A., A. Aab, J. Soja, et al. 2019. “Reduced Expression of miR‐146a in Human Bronchial Epithelial Cells Alters Neutrophil Migration.” Clinical and Translational Allergy 9: 62. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13601‐019‐0301‐8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kokkinis, S., M. Singh, K. R. Paudel, et al. 2024. “Plant‐Based Therapeutics for Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Diseases: Nanoformulation Strategies to Overcome Delivery Challenges.” Food Bioscience 58: 103761. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fbio.2024.103761.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koshak, A. E., E. A. Koshak, A. F. Mobeireek, et al. 2021. “Nigella sativa for the Treatment of COVID‐19: An Open‐Label Randomized Controlled Clinical Trial.” Complementary Therapies in Medicine 61: 102769. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ctim.2021.102769.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kradin, R. L., and E. J. Mark. 2018. “Pathology of Pulmonary Infection.” In Diagnostic Pathology of Infectious Disease, Chapter 8, 143–206. Philadelphia, PA: Elsevier.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumadoh, D., and K. Ofori‐Kwakye. 2017. “Dosage Forms of Herbal Medicinal Products and Their Stability Considerations—An Overview.” Journal of Critical Reviews 4, no. 4: 1–8. https://doi.org/10.22159/jcr.2017v4i4.16077.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar, R., J. Rai, N. C. Kajal, and P. Devi. 2018. “Comparative Study of Effect of Withania somnifera as an Adjuvant to DOTS in Patients of Newly Diagnosed Sputum Smear Positive Pulmonary Tuberculosis.” Indian Journal of Tuberculosis 65, no. 3: 246–251. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijtb.2017.05.005.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar, V. 2017. “Influenza in Children.” Indian Journal of Pediatrics 84, no. 2: 139–143. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12098‐016‐2232‐x.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumbhar, P., J. Kaur, G. De Rubis, et al. 2023. “Inhalation Drug Delivery in Combating Pulmonary Infections: Advances and Challenges.” Journal of Drug Delivery Science and Technology 89: 105022. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jddst.2023.105022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Labella, A. M., and S. E. Merel. 2013. “Influenza.” Medical Clinics of North America 97, no. 4: 621–645. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.mcna.2013.03.001.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, L., Q. Xie, G. Bian, et al. 2020. “Anti‐H1N1 Viral Activity of Three Main Active Ingredients From Zedoary Oil.” Fitoterapia 142: 104489. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fitote.2020.104489.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, P., L. Zhang, Z. Guo, et al. 2022. “Epimedium koreanum Nakai–Induced Liver Injury—A Mechanistic Study Using Untargeted Metabolomics.” Frontiers in Pharmacology 13: 934057. https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2022.934057.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, R., and L. Wang. 2019. “Baicalin Inhibits Influenza Virus A Replication via Activation of Type I IFN Signaling by Reducing miR‐146a.” Molecular Medicine Reports 20, no. 6: 5041–5049. https://doi.org/10.3892/mmr.2019.10743.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, Z., G. Lu, and G. Meng. 2019. “Pathogenic Fungal Infection in the Lung.” Frontiers in Immunology 10: 1524. https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2019.01524.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang, C., N. Hui, Y. Liu, et al. 2021. “Insights Into Forsythia Honeysuckle (Lianhuaqingwen) Capsules: A Chinese Herbal Medicine Repurposed for COVID‐19 Pandemic.” Phytomedicine Plus 1, no. 2: 100027. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phyplu.2021.100027.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin, L. L., J. J. Shan, T. Xie, et al. 2016. “Application of Traditional Chinese Medical Herbs in Prevention and Treatment of Respiratory Syncytial Virus.” Evidence‐Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine: Ecam 2016: 6082729. https://doi.org/10.1155/2016/6082729.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin, Y.‐E., M.‐H. Lin, T.‐Y. Yeh, et al. 2022. “Genotoxicity and 28‐Day Repeated Dose Oral Toxicity Study of Garlic Essential Oil in Mice.” Journal of Traditional and Complementary Medicine 12, no. 6: 536–544. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtcme.2022.05.001.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Linares Braham, A., L. Palomo‐Ligas, and S. Nery‐Flores. 2023. “Bioactive Compounds and Pharmacological Potential of Hojasen (Flourensia cernua): A Mini Review.” Plant Science Today 10, no. sp2: 304–312. https://doi.org/10.14719/pst.2546.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ling, X.‐Y. 2020. “Exploring Material Basis and Mechanism of Lianhua Qingwen Prescription Against Coronavirus Based on Network Pharmacology.” Chinese Traditional and Herbal Drugs 24: 1723–1730.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Linh, N. T. T., N. T. Son, N. T. T. Ha, et al. 2021. “Biologically Active Constituents From Plants of the Genus Xanthium.” Progress in the Chemistry of Organic Natural Products 116: 135–209. https://doi.org/10.1007/978‐3‐030‐80560‐9_4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, C., F. Cheng, H. A. Aisa, and M. Maiwulanjiang. 2023. “Comprehensive Study of Components and Antimicrobial Properties of Essential Oil Extracted From Carum carvi L. Seeds.” Antibiotics 12, no. 3: 591–601. https://doi.org/10.3390/antibiotics12030591.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, M., Y. Gao, Y. Yuan, et al. 2021. “Efficacy and Safety of Herbal Medicine (Lianhuaqingwen) for Treating COVID‐19: A Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis.” Integrative Medicine Research 10, no. 1: 100644. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.imr.2020.100644.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, T., L. Zhang, D. Joo, and S.‐C. Sun. 2017. “NF‐κB Signaling in Inflammation.” Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy 2, no. 1: 17023. https://doi.org/10.1038/sigtrans.2017.23.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu, N., Y. Yang, X. Li, et al. 2021. “The Protective Action of Piperlongumine Against Mycobacterial Pulmonary Tuberculosis in Its Mitigation of Inflammation and Macrophage Infiltration in Male BALB/c Mice.” Journal of Veterinary Research 65, no. 4: 431–440. https://doi.org/10.2478/jvetres‐2021‐0061.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Madia, V. N., W. Toscanelli, D. De Vita, et al. 2022. “Ultrastructural Damages to H1N1 Influenza Virus Caused by Vapor Essential Oils.” Molecules 27, no. 12: 3718. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules27123718.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahboubi, M. 2019. “Caraway as Important Medicinal Plants in Management of Diseases.” Natural Products and Bioprospecting 9, no. 1: 1–11. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13659‐018‐0190‐x.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahmoudvand, H., M. Pakravanan, F. Kheirandish, et al. 2020. “Efficacy and Safety Curcuma zedoaria L. to Inactivate the Hydatid Cyst Protoscoleces.” Current Clinical Pharmacology 15, no. 1: 64–71. https://doi.org/10.2174/1574884714666190918155147.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahmud, H. A., H. Seo, S. Kim, et al. 2017. “Thymoquinone (TQ) Inhibits the Replication of Intracellular Mycobacterium tuberculosis in Macrophages and Modulates Nitric Oxide Production.” BMC Complementary and Alternative Medicine 17: 279. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906‐017‐1786‐0.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Majumder, R., M. B. Alam, K. R. Paudel, et al. 2022. “Anti‐Influenza Virus Potential of Probiotic Strain Lactiplantibacillus plantarum YML015 Isolated From Korean Fermented Vegetable.” Fermentation 8, no. 11: 572. https://doi.org/10.3390/fermentation8110572.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manayi, A., S. M. Nabavi, M. Khayatkashani, S. Habtemariam, and H. R. Khayat Kashani. 2021. “Arglabin Could Target Inflammasome‐Induced ARDS and Cytokine Storm Associated With COVID‐19.” Molecular Biology Reports 48, no. 12: 8221–8225. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11033‐021‐06827‐7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marrelli, M. 2021. “Medicinal Plants.” Plants 10, no. 7: 1355. https://doi.org/10.3390/plants10071355.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mashayekhi‐Sardoo, H., R. Rezaee, and G. Karimi. 2020. “(Black Seed) Safety: An Overview.” Asian Biomedicine 14, no. 4: 127–137. https://doi.org/10.1515/abm‐2020‐0020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McAuley, J. L., M. D. Tate, C. J. MacKenzie‐Kludas, et al. 2013. “Activation of the NLRP3 Inflammasome by IAV Virulence Protein PB1‐F2 Contributes to Severe Pathophysiology and Disease.” PLoS Pathogens 9, no. 5: e1003392. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1003392.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehrbod, P., M. A. Abdalla, E. M. Njoya, et al. 2018. “South African Medicinal Plant Extracts Active Against Influenza A Virus.” BMC Complementary and Alternative Medicine 18, no. 1: 112. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906‐018‐2184‐y.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehrbod, P., D. Hudy, D. Shyntum, J. Markowski, M. J. Łos, and S. Ghavami. 2021. “Quercetin as a Natural Therapeutic Candidate for the Treatment of Influenza Virus.” Biomolecules 11, no. 1: 10–39. https://doi.org/10.3390/biom11010010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehta, M., D. S. Dhanjal, K. R. Paudel, et al. 2020. “Cellular Signalling Pathways Mediating the Pathogenesis of Chronic Inflammatory Respiratory Diseases: An Update.” Inflammopharmacology 28, no. 4: 795–817. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10787‐020‐00698‐3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehta, M., D. S. Dhanjal, S. Satija, et al. 2020. “Advancing of Cellular Signaling Pathways in Respiratory Diseases Using Nanocarrier Based Drug Delivery Systems.” Current Pharmaceutical Design 26, no. 42: 5380–5392. https://doi.org/10.2174/1381612826999201116161143.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehta, M., K. R. Paudel, N. Panth, et al. 2021. “Drug Delivery Advances in Mitigating Inflammation via Matrix Metalloproteinases in Respiratory Diseases.” Nanomedicine (London, England) 16, no. 6: 437–439. https://doi.org/10.2217/nnm‐2021‐0016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehta, M., S. Satija, K. R. Paudel, et al. 2020. “Incipient Need of Targeting Airway Remodeling Using Advanced Drug Delivery in Chronic Respiratory Diseases.” Future Medicinal Chemistry 12: 873–875. https://doi.org/10.4155/fmc‐2020–0091.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehta, M., P. Sharma, S. Kaur, et al. 2020. “Chapter 24—Plant‐Based Drug Delivery Systems in Respiratory Diseases.” In Targeting Chronic Inflammatory Lung Diseases Using Advanced Drug Delivery Systems, edited by K. Dua, P. M. Hansbro, R. Wadhwa, M. Haghi, L. G. Pont, and K. A. Williams, 517–539. Cambridge, Massachussets, USA: Academic Press. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978‐0‐12‐820658‐4.00024‐8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mieres‐Castro, D., S. Ahmar, R. Shabbir, and F. Mora‐Poblete. 2021. “Antiviral Activities of Eucalyptus Essential Oils: Their Effectiveness as Therapeutic Targets Against Human Viruses.” Pharmaceuticals 14, no. 12: 1210–1227. https://doi.org/10.3390/ph14121210.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mishra, B., and J. Singh. 2020. “Chapter 4—Novel Drug Delivery Systems and Significance in Respiratory Diseases.” In Targeting Chronic Inflammatory Lung Diseases Using Advanced Drug Delivery Systems, edited by K. Dua, P. M. Hansbro, R. Wadhwa, M. Haghi, L. G. Pont, and K. A. Williams, 57–95. Cambridge, Massachussets, USA: Academic Press. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978‐0‐12‐820658‐4.00004‐2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mody, V., J. Ho, S. Wills, et al. 2021. “Identification of 3‐Chymotrypsin Like Protease (3CLPro) Inhibitors as Potential Anti‐SARS‐CoV‐2 Agents.” Communications Biology 4, no. 1: 93. https://doi.org/10.1038/s42003‐020‐01577‐x.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moghadami, M. 2017. “A Narrative Review of Influenza: A Seasonal and Pandemic Disease.” Iranian Journal of Medical Sciences 42, no. 1: 2–13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Molina‐Salinas, G. M., L. M. Peña‐Rodríguez, B. D. Mata‐Cárdenas, et al. 2011. “Flourensia cernua: Hexane Extracts a Very Active Mycobactericidal Fraction From an Inactive Leaf Decoction Against Pansensitive and Panresistant Mycobacterium tuberculosis.” Evidence‐Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine: Ecam 2011: 782503. https://doi.org/10.1155/2011/782503.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Molina‐Salinas, G. M., M. C. Ramos‐Guerra, J. Vargas‐Villarreal, B. D. Mata‐Cárdenas, P. Becerril‐Montes, and S. Said‐Fernández. 2006. “Bactericidal Activity of Organic Extracts From Flourensia cernua DC Against Strains of Mycobacterium tuberculosis.” Archives of Medical Research 37, no. 1: 45–49. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.arcmed.2005.04.010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mousa, H. A.‐L. 2017. “Prevention and Treatment of Influenza, Influenza‐Like Illness, and Common Cold by Herbal, Complementary, and Natural Therapies.” Journal of Evidence‐Based Complementary &amp; Alternative Medicine 22, no. 1: 166–174. https://doi.org/10.1177/2156587216641831.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munoz, F. M. 2003. “Influenza Virus Infection in Infancy and Early Childhood.” Paediatric Respiratory Reviews 4, no. 2: 99–104.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murase, L. S., J. V. Perez de Souza, J. E. Meneguello, et al. 2019. “Possible Binding of Piperine in Mycobacterium tuberculosis RNA Polymerase and Rifampin Synergism.” Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy 63, no. 11: e02520–e02518. https://doi.org/10.1128/AAC.02520‐18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nagasree, K. P., B. H. Bindu, I. Priyanka, T. Divya, and S. M. Afroz. 2022. “Anti‐Tubercular Activity of Neem Flower Extract.” Current Trends in Biotechnology and Pharmacy 16, no. s2: 75–77. https://doi.org/10.5530/ctbp.2022.3s.65.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nair, S. S., S. S. Gaikwad, S. P. Kulkarni, and A. P. Mukne. 2017. “Allium sativum Constituents Exhibit Anti‐Tubercular Activity In Vitro and in RAW 264.7 Mouse Macrophage Cells Infected With Mycobacterium tuberculosis H37Rv.” Pharmacognosy Magazine 13, no. Suppl 2: S209–S215. https://doi.org/10.4103/pm.pm_435_16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nasim, N., I. S. Sandeep, and S. Mohanty. 2022. “Plant‐Derived Natural Products for Drug Discovery: Current Approaches and Prospects.” Nucleus 65, no. 3: 399–411. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13237‐022‐00405‐3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Natarajan, A., P. M. Beena, A. V. Devnikar, and S. Mali. 2020. “A Systemic Review on Tuberculosis.” Indian Journal of Tuberculosis 67, no. 3: 295–311. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijtb.2020.02.005.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguenang, G. S., A. S. M. Ntyam, and V. Kuete. 2020. “Acute and Subacute Toxicity Profiles of the Methanol Extract of Lycopersicon esculentum L. Leaves (Tomato), a Botanical With Promising In Vitro Anticancer Potential.” Evidence‐Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine: eCAM 2020: 8935897. https://doi.org/10.1155/2020/8935897.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguta, J. M., R. Appiah‐Opong, A. K. Nyarko, D. Yeboah‐Manu, and P. G. A. Addo. 2015. “Medicinal Plants Used to Treat TB in Ghana.” International Journal of Mycobacteriology 4, no. 2: 116–123. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijmyco.2015.02.003.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguta, J. M., R. Appiah‐Opong, A. K. Nyarko, et al. 2016. “Antimycobacterial and Cytotoxic Activity of Selected Medicinal Plant Extracts.” Journal of Ethnopharmacology 182: 10–15. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jep.2016.02.010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>NIBIB. 2022. Drug Delivery Systems. Bethesda, MD: National Institute of Biomedical Imaging and Bioengineering. https://www.nibib.nih.gov/science‐education/science‐topics/drug‐delivery‐systems‐getting‐drugs‐their‐targets‐controlled‐manner.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>NIH. 2022. “Pneumonia—Causes and Risk Factors | NHLBI, NIH.” https://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/pneumonia/causes.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nile, S. H., D. H. Kim, A. Nile, G. S. Park, E. Gansukh, and G. Kai. 2020. “Probing the Effect of Quercetin 3‐Glucoside From Dianthus superbus L. Against Influenza Virus Infection—In Vitro and In Silico Biochemical and Toxicological Screening.” Food and Chemical Toxicology 135: 110985. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fct.2019.110985.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niu, Q.‐Q., Y. Chen, Y. Liu, et al. 2017. “Efficacy and Safety of Lianhua Qingwen Capsule for Influenza: A Systematic Review.” China Journal of Chinese Materia Medica 42, no. 8: 1474–1481. https://doi.org/10.19540/j.cnki.cjcmm.2017.0044.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nyagumbo, E., W. Pote, B. Shopo, et al. 2022. “Medicinal Plants Used for the Management of Respiratory Diseases in Zimbabwe: Review and Perspectives Potential Management of COVID‐19.” Physics and Chemistry of the Earth, Parts A/B/C 128: 103232. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pce.2022.103232.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olivianto, E., A. T. Endharti, H. Kusuma, S. Santoso, and K. Handono. 2021. “Effect of Thymoquinone on Th1 and Th2 Balance in Rats Infected with Mycobacterium tuberculosis.” https://oamjms.eu/index.php/mjms/article/view/6560.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ombito, J. O., G. F. Chi, and J. D. Wansi. 2021. “Ethnomedicinal Uses, Phytochemistry, and Pharmacology of the Genus Vepris (Rutaceae): A Review.” Journal of Ethnopharmacology 267: 113622. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jep.2020.113622.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oriola, A. O., and A. O. Oyedeji. 2022. “Essential Oils and Their Compounds as Potential Anti‐Influenza Agents.” Molecules (Basel, Switzerland) 27, no. 22: 7797. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules27227797.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parasher, A. 2021. “COVID‐19: Current Understanding of Its Pathophysiology, Clinical Presentation and Treatment.” Postgraduate Medical Journal 97, no. 1147: 312–320. https://doi.org/10.1136/postgradmedj‐2020‐138577.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patel, V. K., K. R. Paudel, S. D. Shukla, et al. 2022. “Toll‐Like Receptors, Innate Immune System, and Lung Diseases: A Vital Trilateral Association.” EXCLI Journal 21: 519–523. https://doi.org/10.17179/excli2022‐4688.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paudel, K. R., G. De Rubis, N. Panth, et al. 2022. “Nanomedicine and Medicinal Plants: Emerging Symbiosis in Managing Lung Diseases and Associated Infections.” EXCLI Journal 21: 1299–1303. https://doi.org/10.17179/excli2022‐5376.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paudel, K. R., V. Patel, S. Vishwas, et al. 2022. “Nutraceuticals and COVID‐19: A Mechanistic Approach Toward Attenuating the Disease Complications.” Journal of Food Biochemistry 46, no. 12: e14445. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfbc.14445.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paudel, K. R., R. Wadhwa, M. Mehta, D. K. Chellappan, P. M. Hansbro, and K. Dua. 2020. “Rutin Loaded Liquid Crystalline Nanoparticles Inhibit Lipopolysaccharide Induced Oxidative Stress and Apoptosis in Bronchial Epithelial Cells In Vitro.” Toxicology In Vitro: An International Journal Published in Association With BIBRA 68: 104961. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tiv.2020.104961.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paudel, K. R., R. Wadhwa, X. N. Tew, et al. 2021. “Rutin Loaded Liquid Crystalline Nanoparticles Inhibit Non‐small Cell Lung Cancer Proliferation and Migration In Vitro.” Life Sciences 276: 119436. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lfs.2021.119436.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peteranderl, C., S. Herold, and C. Schmoldt. 2016. “Human Influenza Virus Infections.” Seminars in Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine 37, no. 4: 487–500. https://doi.org/10.1055/s‐0036‐1584801.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prakash, P., R. Meena, L. Stanley Abraham, et al. 2021. “Evidence‐Based Traditional Siddha Formulations for Prophylaxis and Management of Respiratory Symptoms in COVID‐19 Pandemic—A Review.” Biocatalysis and Agricultural Biotechnology 35: 102056. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bcab.2021.102056.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pranskuniene, Z., R. Balciunaite, Z. Simaitiene, and J. Bernatoniene. 2022. “Herbal Medicine Uses for Respiratory System Disorders and Possible Trends in New Herbal Medicinal Recipes During COVID‐19 in Pasvalys District, Lithuania.” International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 19, no. 15: 8905. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph19158905.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prasher, P., M. Sharma, M. Mehta, et al. 2020. “Plants Derived Therapeutic Strategies Targeting Chronic Respiratory Diseases: Chemical and Immunological Perspective.” Chemico‐Biological Interactions 325: 109125. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cbi.2020.109125.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prasher, P., M. Sharma, M. Mehta, et al. 2021. “Current‐Status and Applications of Polysaccharides in Drug Delivery Systems.” Colloid and Interface Science Communications 42: 100418. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.colcom.2021.100418.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prasher, P., M. Sharma, S. K. Singh, et al. 2022. “Advances and Applications of Dextran‐Based Nanomaterials Targeting Inflammatory Respiratory Diseases.” Journal of Drug Delivery Science and Technology 74: 103598. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jddst.2022.103598.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Preteroti, M., E. T. Wilson, D. H. Eidelman, and C. J. Baglole. 2023. “Modulation of Pulmonary Immune Function by Inhaled Cannabis Products and Consequences for Lung Disease.” Respiratory Research 24: 95. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12931‐023‐02399‐1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qian, H., D. Wu, C. Li, et al. 2024. “A Systematic Review of Traditional Uses, Phytochemistry, Pharmacology and Toxicity of Epimedium koreanum Nakai.” Journal of Ethnopharmacology 318: 116957. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jep.2023.116957.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quereshi, S., A. K. Pandey, and S. S. Sandhu. 2010. “Evaluation of Antibacterial Activity of Different Ganoderma Lucidum Extracts.”</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rad, J. S., S. M. H. Alfatemi, M. S. Rad, and M. Iriti. 2013. “In‐Vitro Antioxidant and Antibacterial Activities of Xanthium strumarium L. Extracts on Methicillin‐Susceptible and Methicillin‐Resistant Staphylococcus aureus.” Ancient Science of Life 33, no. 2: 109–113. https://doi.org/10.4103/0257‐7941.139050.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahman, H. S., H. H. Othman, N. I. Hammadi, et al. 2020. “Novel Drug Delivery Systems for Loading of Natural Plant Extracts and Their Biomedical Applications.” International Journal of Nanomedicine 15: 2439–2483. https://doi.org/10.2147/IJN.S227805.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahman, M. M., S. Bibi, M. S. Rahaman, et al. 2022. “Natural Therapeutics and Nutraceuticals for Lung Diseases: Traditional Significance, Phytochemistry, and Pharmacology.” Biomedicine &amp; Pharmacotherapy 150: 113041. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biopha.2022.113041.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rakers, C., S.‐M. Schwerdtfeger, J. Mortier, et al. 2014. “Inhibitory Potency of Flavonoid Derivatives on Influenza Virus Neuraminidase.” Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry Letters 24, no. 17: 4312–4317. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bmcl.2014.07.010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reed, M. B., V. K. Pichler, F. McIntosh, et al. 2009. “Major Mycobacterium tuberculosis Lineages Associate With Patient Country of Origin.” Journal of Clinical Microbiology 47, no. 4: 1119–1128. https://doi.org/10.1128/JCM.02142‐08.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reynolds, J. H., G. McDonald, H. Alton, and S. B. Gordon. 2010. “Pneumonia in the Immunocompetent Patient.” British Journal of Radiology 83, no. 996: 998–1009. https://doi.org/10.1259/bjr/31200593.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadati, S. M., N. Gheibi, S. Ranjbar, and M. S. Hashemzadeh. 2019. “Docking Study of Flavonoid Derivatives as Potent Inhibitors of Influenza H1N1 Virus Neuraminidase.” Biomedical Reports 10, no. 1: 33–38. https://doi.org/10.3892/br.2018.1173.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saggam, A., K. Limgaokar, S. Borse, et al. 2021. “Withania somnifera (L.) Dunal: Opportunity for Clinical Repurposing in COVID‐19 Management.” Frontiers in Pharmacology 12: 623795. https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2021.623795.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saiga, H., N. Nieuwenhuizen, M. Gengenbacher, et al. 2015. “The Recombinant BCG ΔureC::Hly Vaccine Targets the AIM2 Inflammasome to Induce Autophagy and Inflammation.” Journal of Infectious Diseases 211, no. 11: 1831–1841. https://doi.org/10.1093/infdis/jiu675.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santin, J. R., L. Benvenutti, M. F. Broering, et al. 2022. “Sambucus nigra: A Traditional Medicine Effective in Reducing Inflammation in Mice.” Journal of Ethnopharmacology 283: 114736. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jep.2021.114736.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma, A., D. Kumar, K. Dahiya, et al. 2021. “Advances in Pulmonary Drug Delivery Targeting Microbial Biofilms in Respiratory Diseases.” Nanomedicine 16, no. 21: 1905–1923. https://doi.org/10.2217/nnm‐2021‐0057.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shastri, M. D., V. S. R. R. Allam, S. D. Shukla, et al. 2021. “Interleukin‐13: A Pivotal Target Against Influenza‐Induced Exacerbation of Chronic Lung Diseases.” Life Sciences 283: 119871. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lfs.2021.119871.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen, S., M. Gong, G. Wang, et al. 2022. “COVID‐19 and Gut Injury.” Nutrients 14, no. 20: 4409–4427. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu14204409.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen, X., and F. Yin. 2021. “The Mechanisms and Clinical Application of Traditional Chinese Medicine Lianhua‐Qingwen Capsule.” Biomedicine &amp; Pharmacotherapy 142: 111998. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biopha.2021.111998.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shukla, U., S. Srivastava, P. Gupta, and N. Ujjaliya. 2019. “A Retrospective Analysis of the Effect of the Intervention of Arogya Kashayam in COVID‐19 Positive Cases in Madhya Pradesh.” Ayu 40, no. 4: 209–215. https://doi.org/10.4103/ayu.ayu_365_20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shukla, U., and N. Ujjaliya. 2023. “Evaluation of Addon Effectiveness of Arogya Kashayam‐20 in Mild‐To‐Moderate COVID‐19 Cases—A Randomized Controlled Study.” AYUHOM 10: 28. https://doi.org/10.4103/AYUHOM.AYUHOM_52_22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh, N., M. Bhalla, P. de Jager, and M. Gilca. 2011. “An Overview on Ashwagandha: A Rasayana (Rejuvenator) of Ayurveda.” African Journal of Traditional, Complementary, and Alternative Medicines: AJTCAM 8, no. 5 Suppl: 208–213. https://doi.org/10.4314/ajtcam.v8i5S.9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song, J.‐W., J.‐Y. Long, L. Xie, et al. 2020. “Applications, Phytochemistry, Pharmacological Effects, Pharmacokinetics, Toxicity of Scutellaria baicalensis Georgi. And Its Probably Potential Therapeutic Effects on COVID‐19: A Review.” Chinese Medicine 15: 102. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13020‐020‐00384‐0.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Subbarao, K., and S. Mahanty. 2020. “Respiratory Virus Infections: Understanding COVID‐19.” Immunity 52, no. 6: 905–909. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.immuni.2020.05.004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suryavanshi, S. V., M. Zaiachuk, N. Pryimak, I. Kovalchuk, and O. Kovalchuk. 2022. “Cannabinoids Alleviate the LPS‐Induced Cytokine Storm via Attenuating NLRP3 Inflammasome Signaling and TYK2‐Mediated STAT3 Signaling Pathways In Vitro.” Cells 11, no. 9: 1391. https://doi.org/10.3390/cells11091391.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Talbot, H. K. 2017. “Influenza in Older Adults.” Infectious Disease Clinics of North America 31, no. 4: 757–766. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.idc.2017.07.005.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang, S., J. Ren, L. Kong, et al. 2023. “Ephedrae herba: A Review of Its Phytochemistry, Pharmacology, Clinical Application, and Alkaloid Toxicity.” Molecules (Basel, Switzerland) 28, no. 2: 663. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules28020663.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ti, H., Z. Mai, Z. Wang, et al. 2021. “Bisabolane‐Type Sesquiterpenoids From Curcuma longa L. Exert Anti‐Influenza and Anti‐Inflammatory Activities Through NF‐κB/MAPK and RIG‐1/STAT1/2 Signaling Pathways.” Food &amp; Function 12, no. 15: 6697–6711. https://doi.org/10.1039/d1fo01212f.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tilwani, K., A. Patel, H. Parikh, D. J. Thakker, and G. Dave. 2023. “Investigation on Anti‐Corona Viral Potential of Yarrow Tea.” Journal of Biomolecular Structure &amp; Dynamics 41, no. 11: 5217–5229. https://doi.org/10.1080/07391102.2022.2082532.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tiwari, G., R. Tiwari, B. Sriwastawa, et al. 2012. “Drug Delivery Systems: An Updated Review.” International Journal of Pharmaceutical Investigation 2, no. 1: 2–11. https://doi.org/10.4103/2230‐973X.96920.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Traditional Chinese Medicine. 2019. “What You Need to Know.” NCCIH. https://www.nccih.nih.gov/health/traditional‐chinese‐medicine‐what‐you‐need‐to‐know.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uchegbu, R. I., A. A. Ahuchaogu, C. N. Mbadiugha, et al. 2016. “Antioxidant, Anti‐Inflammatory and Antibacterial Activities of the Seeds of Mucuna pruriens (UTILIS).” Chemical Science International Journal 13: 1–8. https://doi.org/10.9734/ACSJ/2016/24043.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Kempen, T. S., M. H. Wenink, E. F. A. Leijten, T. R. D. J. Radstake, and M. Boes. 2015. “Perception of Self: Distinguishing Autoimmunity From Autoinflammation.” Nature Reviews. Rheumatology 11, no. 8: 483–492. https://doi.org/10.1038/nrrheum.2015.60.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaou, N., E. Stavropoulou, C. Voidarou, C. Tsigalou, and E. Bezirtzoglou. 2021. “Towards Advances in Medicinal Plant Antimicrobial Activity: A Review Study on Challenges and Future Perspectives.” Microorganisms 9, no. 10: 2041–2068. https://doi.org/10.3390/microorganisms9102041.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vimalanathan, S., and J. Hudson. n.d. “Anti‐Influenza Virus Activity of Essential Oils and Vapors.”</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Viswanathan, V., A. G. Phadatare, and A. Mukne. 2014. “Antimycobacterial and Antibacterial Activity of Allium sativum Bulbs.” Indian Journal of Pharmaceutical Sciences 76, no. 3: 256–261.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vlachojannis, C., B. F. Zimmermann, and S. Chrubasik‐Hausmann. 2015. “Efficacy and Safety of Pomegranate Medicinal Products for Cancer.” Evidence‐Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine: eCAM 2015: 1–15. https://doi.org/10.1155/2015/258598.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wadhwa, R., K. R. Paudel, L. H. Chin, et al. 2021. “Anti‐Inflammatory and Anticancer Activities of Naringenin‐Loaded Liquid Crystalline Nanoparticles In Vitro.” Journal of Food Biochemistry 45, no. 1: e13572. https://doi.org/10.1111/jfbc.13572.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wachtel‐Galor, S., and I. F. F. Benzie. 2011. “Herbal Medicine: An Introduction to Its History, Usage, Regulation, Current Trends, and Research Needs.” In Herbal Medicine: Biomolecular and Clinical Aspects, edited by I. F. F. Benzie, et al., 2nd ed. Boca Raton, FL: CRC Press/Taylor &amp; Francis.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wadhwa, R., K. R. Paudel, M. Mehta, et al. 2020. “Beyond the Obvious: Smoking and Respiratory Infection Implications on Alzheimer's Disease.” CNS &amp; Neurological Disorders Drug Targets 19, no. 9: 698–708. https://doi.org/10.2174/1871527319999200817112427.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, L., X. Zhao, F. Yang, et al. 2019. “Enhanced Bioaccessibility In Vitro and Bioavailability of Ginkgo biloba Extract Nanoparticles Prepared by Liquid Anti‐Solvent Precipitation.” International Journal of Food Science &amp; Technology 54, no. 6: 2266–2276. https://doi.org/10.1111/ijfs.14141.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, X., W. Jia, A. Zhao, and X. Wang. 2006. “Anti‐Influenza Agents From Plants and Traditional Chinese Medicine.” Phytotherapy Research: PTR 20, no. 5: 335–341. https://doi.org/10.1002/ptr.1892.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Y., Q. Han, S. Zhang, X. Xing, and X. Sun. 2023a. “New Perspective on the Immunomodulatory Activity of Ginsenosides: Focus on Effective Therapies for Post‐COVID‐19.” Biomedicine &amp; Pharmacotherapy 165: 115154. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biopha.2023.115154.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Y.‐S., Z.‐Q. Wen, B.‐T. Li, H.‐B. Zhang, and J.‐H. Yang. 2016. “Ethnobotany, Phytochemistry, and Pharmacology of the Genus Litsea: An Update.” Journal of Ethnopharmacology 181: 66–107. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jep.2016.01.032.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wawrocki, S., and M. Druszczynska. 2017. “Inflammasomes in Mycobacterium tuberculosis‐Driven Immunity.” Canadian Journal of Infectious Diseases &amp; Medical Microbiology 2017: 2309478. https://doi.org/10.1155/2017/2309478.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. n.d. “Tuberculosis.” https://www.who.int/health‐topics/tuberculosis.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. 2021. “The True Death Toll of COVID‐19: Estimating Global Excess Mortality.” https://www.who.int/data/stories/the‐true‐death‐toll‐of‐covid‐19‐estimating‐global‐excess‐mortality.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. 2023. Global Tuberculosis Report 2023. USA: World Health Organisation.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. 2023. “Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD).” https://www.who.int/news‐room/fact‐sheets/detail/chronic‐obstructive‐pulmonary‐disease‐(copd).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wiersinga, W. J., A. Rhodes, A. C. Cheng, S. J. Peacock, and H. C. Prescott. 2020. “Pathophysiology, Transmission, Diagnosis, and Treatment of Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID‐19): A Review.” JAMA 324, no. 8: 782–793. https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2020.12839.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Witzenrath, M., F. Pache, D. Lorenz, et al. 2011. “The NLRP3 Inflammasome Is Differentially Activated by Pneumolysin Variants and Contributes to Host Defense in Pneumococcal Pneumonia.” Journal of Immunology (Baltimore, MD: 1950) 187, no. 1: 434–440. https://doi.org/10.4049/jimmunol.1003143.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, S., K. B. Patel, L. J. Booth, J. P. Metcalf, H.‐K. Lin, and W. Wu. 2010. “Protective Essential oil Attenuates Influenza Virus Infection: An in Vitro Study in MDCK Cells.” BMC Complementary and Alternative Medicine 10: 69. https://doi.org/10.1186/1472‐6882‐10‐69.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xia, L., Y. Shi, J. Su, et al. 2021. “Shufeng Jiedu, a Promising Herbal Therapy for Moderate COVID‐19: Antiviral and Anti‐Inflammatory Properties, Pathways of Bioactive Compounds, and a Clinical Real‐World Pragmatic Study.” Phytomedicine: International Journal of Phytotherapy and Phytopharmacology 85: 153390. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phymed.2020.153390.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao, M., B. Lim‐Ho Kong, Y. Zhang, et al. 2022. “Anti‐Influenza Mechanism of Phenolic Phytochemicals From Canarium album (Lour.) DC. Leaf Extract.” Journal of Ethnopharmacology 292: 115175. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jep.2022.115175.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao, M., T. Zhang, F. Cao, et al. 2023. “Anti‐Influenza Properties of Tiliroside Isolated From Hibiscus mutabilis L.” Journal of Ethnopharmacology 303: 115918. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jep.2022.115918.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu, J., C. Xiao, H. Xu, et al. 2021. “Anti‐Inflammatory Effects of Ganoderma lucidum Sterols Via Attenuation of the p38 MAPK and NF‐κB Pathways in LPS‐Induced RAW 264.7 Macrophages.” Food and Chemical Toxicology 150: 112073. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fct.2021.112073.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu, Y., L. Yang, L. Wang, and F. Chen. 2022. “Potential Therapeutic Effect of Shufeng Jiedu Capsule and Its Major Herbs on Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID‐19): A Review.” Drug Discoveries &amp; Therapeutics 15, no. 6: 289–299. https://doi.org/10.5582/ddt.2021.01099.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, D.‐Q., L.‐P. You, P.‐H. Song, L.‐X. Zhang, and Y.‐P. Bai. 2012. “A Randomized Controlled Trial Comparing Total Glucosides of Paeony Capsule and Compound Glycyrrhizin Tablet for Alopecia Areata.” Chinese Journal of Integrative Medicine 18, no. 8: 621–625. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11655‐012‐1173‐0.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, F., R. Chen, W. Li, et al. 2021. “D‐Limonene Is a Potential Monoterpene to Inhibit PI3K/Akt/IKK‐α/NF‐κB p65 Signaling Pathway in Coronavirus Disease 2019 Pulmonary Fibrosis.” Frontiers in Medicine 8: 591830. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmed.2021.591830.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yasmin, A. R., S. L. Chia, Q. H. Looi, A. R. Omar, M. M. Noordin, and A. Ideris. 2020. “Chapter 7—Herbal Extracts as Antiviral Agents.” In Feed Additives, edited by P. Florou‐Paneri, E. Christaki, and I. Giannenas, 115–132. Cambridge, MA: Academic Press. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978‐0‐12‐814700‐9.00007‐8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoshida, R., G. Takaesu, H. Yoshida, et al. 2008. “TRAF6 and MEKK1 Play a Pivotal Role in the RIG‐I‐Like Helicase Antiviral Pathway.” Journal of Biological Chemistry 283, no. 52: 36211–36220. https://doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M806576200.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu, H., L. Lin, Z. Zhang, H. Zhang, and H. Hu. 2020. “Targeting NF‐κB Pathway for the Therapy of Diseases: Mechanism and Clinical Study. Signal Transduction and Targeted.” Therapy 5, no. 1: 1. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41392‐020‐00312‐6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu, X., Y. Mao, J. L. Shergis, et al. 2019. “Effectiveness and Safety of Oral Cordyceps sinensis on Stable COPD of GOLD Stages 2–3: Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis.” Evidence‐Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine 2019: 1–12. https://doi.org/10.1155/2019/4903671.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zarfeshany, A., S. Asgary, and S. H. Javanmard. 2014. “Potent Health Effects of Pomegranate.” Advanced Biomedical Research 3: 100. https://doi.org/10.4103/2277‐9175.129371.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zarubaev, V. V., E. A. Pushkina, S. S. Borisevich, et al. 2018. “Selection of Influenza Virus Resistant to the Novel Camphor‐Based Antiviral Camphecene Results in Loss of Pathogenicity.” Virology 524: 69–77. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.virol.2018.08.011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng, L., T. Yang, K. Yang, et al. 2022. “Efficacy and Safety of Curcumin and Curcuma Longa Extract in the Treatment of Arthritis: A Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis of Randomized Controlled Trial.” Frontiers in Immunology 13: 891822. https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2022.891822.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, B., S. Swamy, S. Balijepalli, et al. 2019. “Direct Pulmonary Delivery of Solubilized Curcumin Reduces Severity of Lethal Pneumonia.” FASEB Journal 33, no. 12: 13294–13309. https://doi.org/10.1096/fj.201901047RR.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, J., R. Zhao, L. Jin, L. Pan, and D. Lei. 2022. “Xanthanolides in Xanthium L.: Structures, Synthesis and Bioactivity.” Molecules 27, no. 23: 8136. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules27238136.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, L., and W. Wei. 2020. “Anti‐Inflammatory and Immunoregulatory Effects of Paeoniflorin and Total Glucosides of Paeony.” Pharmacology &amp; Therapeutics 207: 107452. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pharmthera.2019.107452.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, X., D. Wu, Y. Tian, et al. 2022. “Ganoderma lucidum Polysaccharides Ameliorate Lipopolysaccharide‐Induced Acute Pneumonia via Inhibiting NRP1‐Mediated Inflammation.” Pharmaceutical Biology 60, no. 1: 2201–2209. https://doi.org/10.1080/13880209.2022.2142615.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, Y.‐L., Z.‐P. Gou, J.‐H. Shang, et al. 2021. “Anti‐Microbial Effects In Vitro and In Vivo of Alstonia scholaris.” Natural Products and Bioprospecting 11, no. 1: 127–135. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13659‐020‐00294‐6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou, F., G.‐Z. Zhao, B. Li, et al. 2023. “Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis of Efficacy and Safety of Shufeng Jiedu Capsules in Treatment of Influenza.” Zhongguo Zhong Yao Za Zhi = Zhongguo Zhongyao Zazhi = China Journal of Chinese Materia Médica 48, no. 22: 6216–6224. https://doi.org/10.19540/j.cnki.cjcmm.20230804.501.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu, H., X. Lu, L. Ling, et al. 2018. “Houttuynia cordata Polysaccharides Ameliorate Pneumonia Severity and Intestinal Injury in Mice With Influenza Virus Infection.” Journal of Ethnopharmacology 218: 90–99. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jep.2018.02.016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zielińska, A., P. Eder, J. Karczewski, et al. 2023. “Tocilizumab‐Coated Solid Lipid Nanoparticles Loaded With Cannabidiol as a Novel Drug Delivery Strategy for Treating COVID‐19: A Review.” Frontiers in Immunology 14: 1147991. https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2023.1147991.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zigangirova, N. A., E. Y. Morgunova, E. D. Fedina, et al. 2017. “Lycopene Inhibits Propagation of Chlamydia Infection.” Scientifica 2017: 1478625. https://doi.org/10.1155/2017/1478625.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>