<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39386528</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2692-8205</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>26</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>bioRxiv</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The coronavirus nsp14 exoribonuclease interface with the cofactor nsp10 is essential for efficient virus replication and enzymatic activity.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">2024.09.26.615217</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1101/2024.09.26.615217</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="UNLABELLED">Coronaviruses (CoVs) encode nonstructural proteins (nsps) 1-16, which assemble to form replication-transcription complexes that function in viral RNA synthesis. All CoVs encode a proofreading 3'-5' exoribonuclease (ExoN) in nsp14 (nsp14-ExoN) that mediates proofreading and high-fidelity replication and is critical for other roles in replication and pathogenesis. The <i>in vitro</i> enzymatic activity of nsp14 ExoN is enhanced in the presence of the cofactor nsp10. We introduced alanine substitutions in nsp14 of murine hepatitis virus (MHV) at the nsp14-10 interface and recovered mutant viruses with a range of impairments in replication and <i>in vitro</i> biochemical exonuclease activity. Two of these substitutions, nsp14 K7A and D8A, had impairments intermediate between WT-MHV nsp14 and the known ExoN(-) D89A/E91A nsp14 catalytic inactivation mutant. All introduced nsp14-10 interface alanine substitutions impaired <i>in vitro</i> exonuclease activity. Passage of the K7A and D8A mutant viruses selected second-site non-synonymous mutations in nsp14 associated with improved mutant virus replication and exonuclease activity. These results confirm the essential role of the nsp14-nsp10 interaction for efficient enzymatic activity and virus replication, identify proximal and long-distance determinants of nsp14-nsp10 interaction, and support targeting the nsp14-10 interface for viral inhibition and attenuation.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="IMPORTANCE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">Coronavirus replication requires assembly of a replication transcription complex composed of nonstructural proteins (nsp), including polymerase, helicase, exonuclease, capping enzymes, and non-enzymatic cofactors. The coronavirus nsp14 exoribonuclease mediates several functions in the viral life cycle including genomic and subgenomic RNA synthesis, RNA recombination, RNA proofreading and high-fidelity replication, and native resistance to many nucleoside analogs. The nsp-14 exonuclease activity <i>in vitro</i> requires the non-enzymatic co-factor nsp10, but the determinants and importance the nsp14-10 interactions during viral replication have not been defined. Here we show that for the coronavirus murine hepatitis virus, nsp14 residues at the nsp14-10 interface are essential for efficient viral replication and <i>in vitro</i> exonuclease activity. These results shed new light on the requirements for protein interactions within the coronavirus replication transcription complex, and they may reveal novel non active-site targets for virus inhibition and attenuation.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Grimes</LastName><ForeName>Samantha L</ForeName><Initials>SL</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1124-2956</Identifier></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Heaton</LastName><ForeName>Brook E</ForeName><Initials>BE</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Anderson</LastName><ForeName>Mackenzie L</ForeName><Initials>ML</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Burke</LastName><ForeName>Katie</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Stevens</LastName><ForeName>Laura</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lu</LastName><ForeName>Xiaotao</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Heaton</LastName><ForeName>Nicholas S</ForeName><Initials>NS</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5307-3428</Identifier></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Denison</LastName><ForeName>Mark R</ForeName><Initials>MR</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9275-4330</Identifier></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Anderson-Daniels</LastName><ForeName>Jordan</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D000076942">Preprint</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>bioRxiv</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101680187</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2692-8205</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>7</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39386528</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11463354</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/2024.09.26.615217</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">2024.09.26.615217</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>