<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39380083</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>11</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1598-866X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>22</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>08</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Genomics &amp; informatics</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Genomics Inform</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A prediction of mutations in infectious viruses using artificial intelligence.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>15</StartPage><MedlinePgn>15</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">15</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s44342-024-00019-y</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Many subtypes of SARS-CoV-2 have emerged since its early stages, with mutations showing regional and racial differences. These mutations significantly affected the infectivity and severity of the virus. This study aimed to predict the mutations that occur during the evolution of SARS-CoV-2 and identify the key characteristics for making these predictions. We collected and organized data on the lineage, date, clade, and mutations of SARS-CoV-2 from publicly available databases and processed them to predict the mutations. In addition, we utilized various artificial intelligence models to predict newly emerging mutations and created various training sets based on clade information. Using only mutation information resulted in low performance of the learning models, whereas incorporating clade differentiation resulted in high performance in machine learning models, including XGBoost (accuracy: 0.999). However, mutations fixed in the receptor-binding motif (RBM) region of Omicron resulted in decreased predictive performance. Using these models, we predicted potential mutation positions for 24C, following the recently emerged 24A and 24B clades. We identified a mutation at position Q493 in the RBM region. Our study developed effective artificial intelligence models and characteristics for predicting new mutations in continuously evolving infectious viruses.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Choi</LastName><ForeName>Won Jong</ForeName><Initials>WJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Precision Medicine and Big Data, College of Medicine, The Catholic University of Korea, Seoul, 06591, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Informatics, The Catholic University of Korea, Seoul, 06591, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Park</LastName><ForeName>Jongkeun</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Informatics, The Catholic University of Korea, Seoul, 06591, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Seong</LastName><ForeName>Do Young</ForeName><Initials>DY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Precision Medicine and Big Data, College of Medicine, The Catholic University of Korea, Seoul, 06591, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Informatics, The Catholic University of Korea, Seoul, 06591, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chung</LastName><ForeName>Dae Sun</ForeName><Initials>DS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Informatics, The Catholic University of Korea, Seoul, 06591, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Sciences, Graduate Schoolof, College of Medicine , The Catholic University of Korea, Seoul, 06591, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hong</LastName><ForeName>Dongwan</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Precision Medicine and Big Data, College of Medicine, The Catholic University of Korea, Seoul, 06591, Republic of Korea. dwhong@catholic.ac.kr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Informatics, The Catholic University of Korea, Seoul, 06591, Republic of Korea. dwhong@catholic.ac.kr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Sciences, Graduate Schoolof, College of Medicine , The Catholic University of Korea, Seoul, 06591, Republic of Korea. dwhong@catholic.ac.kr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Precision Medicine Research Center, College of Medicine, The Catholic University of Korea, Seoul, 06591, Republic of Korea. dwhong@catholic.ac.kr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cancer Evolution Research Center, College of Medicine, The Catholic University of Korea, Seoul, 06591, Republic of Korea. dwhong@catholic.ac.kr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Medicine, CMC Institute for Basic Medical Science, The Catholic University of Korea, Seoul, 06591, Republic of Korea. dwhong@catholic.ac.kr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>08</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Genomics Inform</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101223836</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1598-866X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Clade</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Deep learning</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Machine learning</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mutation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Prediction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.
</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>57</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39380083</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11463117</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s44342-024-00019-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s44342-024-00019-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Ghafari M, Hall M, Golubchik T, Ayoubkhani D, House T, MacIntyre-Cockett G, Fryer HR, Thomson L, Nurtay A, Kemp SA, et al. Prevalence of persistent SARS-CoV-2 in a large community surveillance study. Nature. 2024;626:1094–101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10901734</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38383783</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Team C-F. Past SARS-CoV-2 infection protection against re-infection: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Lancet. 2023;401:833–42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9998097</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36930674</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xue S, Han Y, Wu F, Wang Q. Mutations in the SARS-CoV-2 spike receptor binding domain and their delicate balance between ACE2 affinity and antibody evasion. Protein Cell. 2024;15:403–18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11131022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38442025</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lan J, Ge J, Yu J, Shan S, Zhou H, Fan S, Zhang Q, Shi X, Wang Q, Zhang L, Wang X. Structure of the SARS-CoV-2 spike receptor-binding domain bound to the ACE2 receptor. Nature. 2020;581:215–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32225176</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harvey WT, Carabelli AM, Jackson B, Gupta RK, Thomson EC, Harrison EM, Ludden C, Reeve R, Rambaut A, Consortium C-GU. Rambaut A,SARS-CoV-2 variants, spike mutations and immune escape. Nat Rev Microbiol. 2021;19:409–24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8167834</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34075212</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu Z, Wei D, Zeng Q, Zhang H, Sun Y, Demongeot J. More or less deadly? A mathematical model that predicts SARS-CoV-2 evolutionary direction. Comput Biol Med. 2023;153: 106510.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9816089</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36630829</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oh J, Apio C, Park T. Mathematical modeling of the impact of Omicron variant on the COVID-19 situation in South Korea. Genomics Inform. 2022;20: e22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9299565</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35794702</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang L, Zhang Y, Wang D, Tong X, Liu T, Zhang S, Huang J, Zhang L, Chen L, Fan H, Clarke M. Artificial intelligence for COVID-19: a systematic review. Front Med (Lausanne). 2021;8: 704256.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8514781</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34660623</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chadaga K, Prabhu S, Sampathila N, Chadaga R, Umakanth S, Bhat D. G SS: Explainable artificial intelligence approaches for COVID-19 prognosis prediction using clinical markers. Sci Rep. 2024;14:1783.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10799946</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38245638</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mei X, Lee HC, Diao KY, Huang M, Lin B, Liu C, Xie Z, Ma Y, Robson PM, Chung M, et al. Artificial intelligence-enabled rapid diagnosis of patients with COVID-19. Nat Med. 2020;26:1224–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7446729</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32427924</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Obermeyer F, Jankowiak M, Barkas N, Schaffner SF, Pyle JD, Yurkovetskiy L, Bosso M, Park DJ, Babadi M, MacInnis BL, et al. Analysis of 6.4 million SARS-CoV-2 genomes identifies mutations associated with fitness. Science. 2022;376:1327–32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9161372</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35608456</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou B, Zhou H, Zhang X, Xu X, Chai Y, Zheng Z, Kot AC, Zhou Z. TEMPO: a transformer-based mutation prediction framework for SARS-CoV-2 evolution. Comput Biol Med. 2023;152: 106264.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9747230</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36535209</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patro S, Sahu KK. Normalization: a preprocessing stage. arXiv preprint arXiv:1503.06462. 2015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ke G, Meng Q, Finley T, Wang T, Chen W, Ma W, Ye Q, Liu T-Y. LightGBM: a highly efficient gradient boosting decision tree. Adv Neural Info Process Sys. 2017;30:52.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yogesh K, Apeksha K, Sukhpreet K, Yu-Chen H. Machine learning and deep learning based time series prediction and forecasting of ten nations’ COVID-19 pandemic. SN Comput Sci. 2023;4(1):91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9748400</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36532634</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen T, Guestrin C. Xgboost: A scalable tree boosting system. In Proceedings of the 22nd ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining. 2016:785–94.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Breiman L. Random forests Machine learning. 2001;45:5–32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olson DL, Delen D. Advanced data mining techniques. Springer Science &amp; Business Media. 2008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almehdi AM, Khoder G, Alchakee AS, Alsayyid AT, Sarg NH, Soliman SSM. SARS-CoV-2 spike protein: pathogenesis, vaccines, and potential therapies. Infection. 2021;49(5):855–76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8326314</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34339040</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peiris JS, Guan Y, Yuen KY. Severe acute respiratory syndrome. Nat Med. 2004;10:S88-97.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7096017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15577937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cho SY, Kang JM, Ha YE, Park GE, Lee JY, Ko JH, Lee JY, Kim JM, Kang CI, Jo IJ, et al. MERS-CoV outbreak following a single patient exposure in an emergency room in South Korea: an epidemiological outbreak study. Lancet. 2016;388:994–1001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7159268</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27402381</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ebrahim SH, Maher AD, Kanagasabai U, Alfaraj SH, Alzahrani NA, Alqahtani SA, Assiri AM, Memish ZA. MERS-CoV confirmation among 6,873 suspected persons and relevant epidemiologic and clinical features, Saudi Arabia - 2014 to 2019. EClinicalMedicine. 2021;41: 101191.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8590843</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34805807</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leung K, Lau EHY, Wong CKH, Leung GM, Wu JT. Estimating the transmission dynamics of SARS-CoV-2 Omicron BF.7 in Beijing after adjustment of the zero-COVID policy in November-December 2022. Nat Med. 2023;29:579–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36638825</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walensky RP, Walke HT, Fauci AS. SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern in the United States-challenges and opportunities. JAMA. 2021;325:1037–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9009864</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33595644</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dong R, Hu T, Zhang Y, Li Y, Zhou XH. Assessing the transmissibility of the new SARS-CoV-2 variants: from Delta to Omicron. Vaccines (Basel). 2022;10(4):496.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9026126</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35455246</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jalali N, Brustad HK, Frigessi A, MacDonald EA, Meijerink H, Feruglio SL, Nygard KM, Ro G, Madslien EH, de Blasio BF. Increased household transmission and immune escape of the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron compared to Delta variants. Nat Commun. 2022;13:5706.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9520116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36175424</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>da Costa CHS, de Freitas CAB, Alves CN, Lameira J. Assessment of mutations on RBD in the spike protein of SARS-CoV-2 Alpha. Delta and Omicron variants Sci Rep. 2022;12:8540.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9121086</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35595778</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gangavarapu K, Latif AA, Mullen JL, Alkuzweny M, Hufbauer E, Tsueng G, Haag E, Zeller M, Aceves CM, Zaiets K, et al. Outbreak.info genomic reports: scalable and dynamic surveillance of SARS-CoV-2 variants and mutations. Nat Methods. 2023;20:512–22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10399614</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36823332</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li W, Shi Z, Yu M, Ren W, Smith C, Epstein JH, Wang H, Crameri G, Hu Z, Zhang H, et al. Bats are natural reservoirs of SARS-like coronaviruses. Science. 2005;310:676–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16195424</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong LR, Zheng J, Sariol A, Lowery S, Meyerholz DK, Gallagher T, Perlman S. Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus spike protein variants exhibit geographic differences in virulence. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2021;118(24):e2102983118.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8214665</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34099556</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kleine-Weber H, Elzayat MT, Wang L, Graham BS, Muller MA, Drosten C, Pohlmann S, Hoffmann M. Mutations in the spike protein of Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus transmitted in Korea increase resistance to antibody-mediated neutralization. J Virol. 2019;93(2):e01381-18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6321919</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30404801</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lau JJ, Cheng SMS, Leung K, Lee CK, Hachim A, Tsang LCH, Yam KWH, Chaothai S, Kwan KKH, Chai ZYH, et al. Real-world COVID-19 vaccine effectiveness against the Omicron BA.2 variant in a SARS-CoV-2 infection-naive population. Nat Med. 2023;29:348–57.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9941049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36652990</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andrews N, Stowe J, Kirsebom F, Toffa S, Rickeard T, Gallagher E, Gower C, Kall M, Groves N, O’Connell AM, et al. Covid-19 vaccine effectiveness against the Omicron (B.1.1.529) variant. N Engl J Med. 2022;386:1532–46.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8908811</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35249272</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bajema KL, Berry K, Streja E, Rajeevan N, Li Y, Mutalik P, Yan L, Cunningham F, Hynes DM, Rowneki M, et al. Effectiveness of COVID-19 treatment with nirmatrelvir-ritonavir or molnupiravir among U.S. veterans: target trial emulation studies with one-month and six-month outcomes. Ann Intern Med. 2023;176:807–16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10243488</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37276589</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pochtovyi AA, Kustova DD, Siniavin AE, Dolzhikova IV, Shidlovskaya EV, Shpakova OG, Vasilchenko LA, Glavatskaya AA, Kuznetsova NA, Iliukhina AA, et al. In vitro efficacy of antivirals and monoclonal antibodies against SARS-CoV-2 Omicron lineages XBB.1.9.1, XBB.1.9.3, XBB.1.5, XBB.1.16, XBB.2.4, BQ.1.1.45, CH.1.1, and CL.1. Vaccines (Basel). 2023;11(10):1533.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10611309</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37896937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takashita E, Kinoshita N, Yamayoshi S, Sakai-Tagawa Y, Fujisaki S, Ito M, Iwatsuki-Horimoto K, Halfmann P, Watanabe S, Maeda K, et al. Efficacy of antiviral agents against the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron subvariant BA.2. N Engl J Med. 2022;386:1475–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8929374</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35263535</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhowmick S, Jing T, Wang W, Zhang EY, Zhang F, Yang Y. In silico protein folding prediction of COVID-19 mutations and variants. Biomolecules. 2022;12(11):1665.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9688002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36359015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saldivar-Espinoza B, Macip G, Garcia-Segura P, Mestres-Truyol J, Puigbo P, Cereto-Massague A, Pujadas G, Garcia-Vallve S. Prediction of recurrent mutations in SARS-CoV-2 using artificial neural networks. Int J Mol Sci. 2022;23:14683.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9736107</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36499005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>