<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39397907</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2405-8440</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>19</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>15</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Heliyon</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Heliyon</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Antibody response to SARS-CoV-2 natural and breakthrough infection in patients undergoing maintenance hemodialysis: A prospective cohort study over 4 months.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e38545</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e38545</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e38545</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e38545</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Patients undergoing maintenance hemodialysis (MHD) are susceptible to severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) infection. However, the antibody response of these patients to natural and breakthrough infections remains poorly understood.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Between January 15, 2023, and February 15, 2023, a total of 53 patients undergoing MHD and diagnosed with SARS-CoV-2 infection at The Affiliated Hospital of Hangzhou Normal University were enrolled. They were categorized into the natural (n = 40) and breakthrough infection groups (n = 13) based on their vaccination status before infection. Comprehensive data, including basic clinical information, vaccination status, and routine post-infection blood parameters, were collected from all participants. Blood specimens were drawn monthly after infection, and SARS-CoV-2 receptor-binding domain (RBD) immunoglobulin (Ig) G and IgM tests were conducted. The study included continuous follow-up over 4 months.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">During the acute phase of infection, the SARS-CoV-2 RBD IgM positivity was 5 % in patients undergoing MHD who were naturally infected and 15.4 % in those with breakthrough infections. Four months after infection, SARS-CoV-2 RBD IgG positivity in patients with natural and breakthrough infection was 77.5 % and 100 %, respectively. Patients undergoing MHD with breakthrough infection exhibited higher SARS-CoV-2 RBD IgG titers (751.21 signal-to cutoff ratio, S/CO [interquartile range, IQR, 30.54-1173.63]) than those with natural infections (3.43 S/CO [IQR, 1.12-15.6]) (p &lt; 0.0001). No significant differences were observed in SARS-CoV-2 RBD IgG between males and females or among those aged &lt;70 and ≥70 years. Patients who received three doses of the inactivated vaccine produced significantly higher SARS-CoV-2 RBD IgG levels after infection than those who received one or two doses; these differences were significant.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Although patients undergoing MHD exhibit a low rate of SARS-CoV-2 RBD IgM positivity following infection, those vaccinated with inactivated vaccines can generate elevated SARS-CoV-2 RBD IgG levels, particularly those who receive three doses.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Yingji</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nephrology, The Affiliated Hospital of Hangzhou Normal University, Hangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Xiaming</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nephrology, The Affiliated Hospital of Hangzhou Normal University, Hangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Mi</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nephrology, The Affiliated Hospital of Hangzhou Normal University, Hangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wu</LastName><ForeName>Ping</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nephrology, The Affiliated Hospital of Hangzhou Normal University, Hangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yan</LastName><ForeName>Juzhen</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nephrology, The Affiliated Hospital of Hangzhou Normal University, Hangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sun</LastName><ForeName>Chen</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nephrology, The Affiliated Hospital of Hangzhou Normal University, Hangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Yinghong</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nephrology, The Affiliated Hospital of Hangzhou Normal University, Hangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zheng</LastName><ForeName>Xiaoyin</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Laboratory, The Affiliated Hospital of Hangzhou Normal University, Hangzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Heliyon</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101672560</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2405-8440</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Breakthrough infection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Hemodialysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">IgG</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Natural infection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>35</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39397907</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11470422</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e38545</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2405-8440(24)14576-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Wang Haidong, Paulson Katherine R., Pease Spencer A., Watson Stefanie, Comfort Haley, Peng Zheng, et al. Estimating excess mortality due to the COVID-19 pandemic: a systematic analysis of COVID-19-related mortality, 2020-21. Lancet. 2022;399(10334):1513–1536.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8912932</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35279232</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taji L., Thomas D., Oliver M.J., Ip J., Tang Y., Yeung A., et al. COVID-19 in patients undergoing long-term dialysis in Ontario. CMAJ (Can. Med. Assoc. J.) 2021;193(8):E278–E284.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8034346</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33542093</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williamson E.J., Walker A.J., Bhaskaran K., Bacon S., Bates C., Morton C.E., et al. Factors associated with COVID-19-related death using OpenSAFELY. Nature. 2020;584(7821):430–436.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7611074</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32640463</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jager K.J., Kramer A., Chesnaye N.C., Couchoud C., Sanchez-Alvarez J.E., Garneata L., et al. Results from the ERA-EDTA Registry indicate a high mortality due to COVID-19 in dialysis patients and kidney transplant recipients across Europe. Kidney Int. 2020;98(6):1540–1548.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7560263</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32979369</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kato S., Chmielewski M., Honda H., Pecoits-Filho R., Matsuo S., Yuzawa Y., et al. Aspects of immune dysfunction in end-stage renal disease. Clin. J. Am. Soc. Nephrol. 2008;3(5):1526–1533.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4571158</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18701615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anand S., Montez-Rath M., Han J., Bozeman J., Kerschmann R., Beyer P., et al. Prevalence of SARS-CoV-2 antibodies in a large nationwide sample of patients on dialysis in the USA: a cross-sectional study. Lancet. 2020;396(10259):1335–1344.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7518804</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32987007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grupper A., Sharon N., Finn T., Cohen R., Israel M., Agbaria A., et al. Humoral response to the Pfizer BNT162b2 vaccine in patients undergoing maintenance hemodialysis. Clin. J. Am. Soc. Nephrol. 2021;16(7):1037–1042.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8425628</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33824157</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agur T., Zingerman B., Ben-Dor N., Alkeesh W., Steinmetz T., Rachamimov R., et al. Humoral response to the third dose of BNT162b2 COVID-19 vaccine among hemodialysis patients. Nephron. 2023;147(3–4):185–192.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9747736</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35896080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ikizler T.A., Coates P.T., Rovin B.H., Ronco P. Immune response to SARS-CoV-2 infection and vaccination in patients receiving kidney replacement therapy. Kidney Int. 2021;99(6):1275–1279.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8055920</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33931226</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yau K., Abe K.T., Naimark D., Oliver M.J., Perl J., Leis J.A., et al. Evaluation of the SARS-CoV-2 antibody response to the BNT162b2 vaccine in patients undergoing hemodialysis. JAMA Netw. Open. 2021;4(9)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8414193</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34473256</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu X., Wang J., Xu X., Liao G., Chen Y., Hu C.H. Patterns of IgG and IgM antibody response in COVID-19 patients. Emerg. Microb. Infect. 2020;9(1):1269–1274.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7448841</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32515684</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma H., Zeng W., He H., Zhao D., Jiang D., Zhou P., et al. Serum IgA, IgM, and IgG responses in COVID-19. Cell. Mol. Immunol. 2020;17(7):773–775.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7331804</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32467617</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seow J., Graham C., Merrick B., Acors S., Pickering S., Steel K.J.A., et al. Longitudinal observation and decline of neutralizing antibody responses in the three months following SARS-CoV-2 infection in humans. Nat Microbiol. 2020;5(12):1598–1607.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7610833</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33106674</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hansen C.B., Dvoncova K., Perez-Alos L., Fogh K., Madsen J.R., Garred C.H., et al. SARS-CoV-2 antibody dynamics over time and risk factors associated with infection and long COVID-19 symptoms in large working environments. J. Intern. Med. 2023;293(6):763–781.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37024264</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bergwerk M., Gonen T., Lustig Y., Amit S., Lipsitch M., Cohen C., et al. Covid-19 breakthrough infections in vaccinated health care workers. N. Engl. J. Med. 2021;385(16):1474–1484.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8362591</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34320281</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lustig Y., Sapir E., Regev-Yochay G., Cohen C., Fluss R., Olmer L., et al. BNT162b2 COVID-19 vaccine and correlates of humoral immune responses and dynamics: a prospective, single-centre, longitudinal cohort study in health-care workers. Lancet Respir. Med. 2021;9(9):999–1009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8253545</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34224675</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Premkumar Lakshmanane, Segovia-Chumbez Bruno, Ramesh Jadi, Martinez David R., Raut Rajendra, Markmann A. The receptor-binding domain of the viral spike protein is an immunodominant and highly specific target of antibodies in SARS-CoV-2 patients. Sci Immunol. 2020;5(48)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7292505</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32527802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abou-Saleh H., Abo-Halawa B.Y., Younes S., Younes N., Al-Sadeq D.W., Shurrab F.M., et al. Neutralizing antibodies against SARS-CoV-2 are higher but decline faster in mRNA vaccinees compared to individuals with natural infection. J. Trav. Med. 2022;29(8)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9793397</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36342115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krueger K.M., Ison M.G., Ghossein C. Practical guide to vaccination in all stages of CKD, including patients treated by dialysis or kidney transplantation. Am. J. Kidney Dis. 2020;75(3):417–425.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31585683</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Magen O., Waxman J.G., Makov-Assif M., Vered R., Dicker D., Hernán M.A., et al. Fourth dose of BNT162b2 mRNA Covid-19 vaccine in a nationwide setting. N. Engl. J. Med. 2022;386(17):1603–1614.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9020581</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35417631</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pilishvili T., Gierke R., Fleming-Dutra K.E., Farrar J.L., Mohr N.M., Talan D.A., et al. Effectiveness of mRNA Covid-19 vaccine among U.S. Health care personnel. N. Engl. J. Med. 2021;385(25)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8482809</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34551224</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin D.-Y., Gu Y., Xu Y., Wheeler B., Young H., Sunny S.K., et al. Association of primary and booster vaccination and prior infection with SARS-CoV-2 infection and severe COVID-19 outcomes. JAMA. 2022;328(14)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9513711</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36155617</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al Kaabi N., Zhang Y., Xia S., Yang Y., Al Qahtani M.M., Abdulrazzaq N., et al. Effect of 2 inactivated SARS-CoV-2 vaccines on symptomatic COVID-19 infection in adults: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA. 2021;326(1):35–45.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8156175</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34037666</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang X., Xia J., Jin L., Wu Y., Zheng X., Cao X., et al. Effectiveness of homologous or heterologous immunization regimens against SARS-CoV-2 after two doses of inactivated COVID-19 vaccine: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Hum. Vaccines Immunother. 2023;19(2)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10288895</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37344370</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang S., Gao Z., Wang S. China's COVID-19 reopening measures—warriors and weapons. Lancet. 2023;401(10377):643–644.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9949835</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36841613</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lumley S.F., O'Donnell D., Stoesser N.E., Matthews P.C., Howarth A., Hatch S.B., et al. Antibody status and incidence of SARS-CoV-2 infection in health care workers. N. Engl. J. Med. 2021;384(6):533–540.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7781098</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33369366</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boudhabhay I., Serris A., Servais A., Planas D., Hummel A., Guery B., et al. COVID-19 outbreak in vaccinated patients from a haemodialysis unit: antibody titres as a marker of protection from infection. Nephrol. Dial. Transplant. 2022;37(7):1357–1365.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8903345</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35104884</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adjobimey T., Meyer J., Sollberg L., Bawolt M., Berens C., Kovacevic P., et al. Comparison of IgA, IgG, and neutralizing antibody responses following immunization with Moderna, BioNTech, AstraZeneca, Sputnik-V, Johnson and Johnson, and Sinopharm's COVID-19 vaccines. Front. Immunol. 2022;13</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9254618</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35799790</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng F., Wu M., Wang J., Li J., Hu G., Wang L. Over 1-year duration and age difference of SARS-CoV-2 antibodies in convalescent COVID-19 patients. J. Med. Virol. 2021;93(12):6506–6511.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8426830</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34170519</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dobano C., Ramirez-Morros A., Alonso S., Rubio R., Ruiz-Olalla G., Vidal-Alaball J., et al. Sustained seropositivity up to 20.5 months after COVID-19. BMC Med. 2022;20(1):379.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9556137</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36224590</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>