<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39398895</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2055-2076</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>10</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Season>Jan-Dec</Season></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Digital health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Digit Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Sleep well, worry less: A co-design study for the development of the SMILE app.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>20552076241283242</StartPage><MedlinePgn>20552076241283242</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">20552076241283242</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1177/20552076241283242</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">With the coronavirus disease 2019 pandemic exacerbating mental health concerns, the prevalence rates of anxiety and sleep problems have increased alarmingly among youth. Although 90% of patients with anxiety experience sleep problems, current interventions for anxiety often do not target sleep problems in youth. Given this lack, we designed the SMILE app, an intervention that addresses both anxiety and sleep problems simultaneously.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">As users' perspectives are essential to ensure app engagement and uptake, the features, designs, and functions of the SMILE app were evaluated using a participatory app design approach. Participants (<i>N </i>= 17) were youth aged 15 to 25 who reported co-morbid anxiety and sleep issues above clinical thresholds. After completing an online screening survey assessing demographics, anxiety, and sleep problems, participants shared app feedback through group-based, semi-structured co-design sessions. Qualitative analyses were conducted to identify common themes from participants' feedback.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">While participants expressed enthusiasm for the SMILE app's features, particularly the <i>Visualization, Journaling, and Psychoeducation</i> features, and their variety, they criticized the design aspects of the app, such as the font and text amount. Most participants stated they would use the SMILE app or recommend it to a friend.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">By actively involving the target population in the design process, the SMILE app has the potential to notably improve the mental well-being of youth, though further research and development are required to realize this potential fully.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s) 2024.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cormier</LastName><ForeName>Marcus</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0003-6259-9565</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, Dalhousie University, Halifax, Canada.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="RINGGOLD">3688</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Orr</LastName><ForeName>Matt</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychology, Acadia University, Wolfville, Canada.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="RINGGOLD">8689</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kaser</LastName><ForeName>Alanna</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, Dalhousie University, Halifax, Canada.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="RINGGOLD">3688</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>MacDonald</LastName><ForeName>Hannah</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health Science, School of Medicine, Queen's University, Kingston, Canada.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="RINGGOLD">4257</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chorney</LastName><ForeName>Jill</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, Dalhousie University, Halifax, Canada.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="RINGGOLD">3688</Identifier></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Mental Health and Addictions Program, IWK Health, Halifax, Canada.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="RINGGOLD">545971</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Meier</LastName><ForeName>Sandra</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3287-5894</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, Dalhousie University, Halifax, Canada.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="RINGGOLD">3688</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Digit Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101690863</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2055-2076</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Anxiety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">eHealth</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mobile apps</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mobile sensing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sleep problems</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">youths</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39398895</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11468482</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/20552076241283242</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1177_20552076241283242</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Willis TA, Gregory AM. Anxiety disorders and sleep in children and adolescents. Sleep Med Clin 2015; 10: 125–131.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26055860</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Panchal U, Salazar De Pablo G, Franco M, et al. The impact of COVID-19 lockdown on child and adolescent mental health: systematic review. Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry 2023; 32: 1151–1177.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8371430</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34406494</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Madigan S, Racine N, Vaillancourt T, et al. Changes in depression and anxiety among children and adolescents from before to during the covid-19 pandemic: a systematic review and meta-analysis. JAMA Pediatr 2023; 177: 567.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10152379</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37126337</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kessler RC, Berglund PA, Bruce ML, et al. The prevalence and correlates of untreated serious mental illness. Health Serv Res 2001; 36: 987–1007.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1089274</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11775672</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meier SM, Mattheisen M, Mors O, et al. Increased mortality among people with anxiety disorders: total population study. Br J Psychiatry 2016; 209: 216–221.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5082973</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27388572</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vilaplana-Pérez A, Pérez-Vigil A, Sidorchuk A, et al. Much more than just shyness: the impact of social anxiety disorder on educational performance across the lifespan. Psychol Med 2021; 51: 861–869.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8108394</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31907098</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim DS, Lee CL, Ahn YM. Sleep problems in children and adolescents at pediatric clinics. Korean J Pediatr 2017; 60: 158.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5461280</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28592979</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haugland BSM, Hysing M, Hoffart A, et al. Effect of early intervention for anxiety on sleep outcomes in adolescents: a randomized trial. Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry 2022; 31: 1–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9532314</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33961115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Bruin EJ, Oort FJ, Bögels SM, et al. Efficacy of internet and group-administered cognitive behavioral therapy for insomnia in adolescents: a pilot study. Behav Sleep Med 2014; 12: 235–254.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23767888</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>MHASEF Research Team. ICES | the mental health of children and youth in Ontario: a baseline scorecard. ICES, https://www.ices.on.ca/publications/research-reports/the-mental-health-of-children-and-youth-in-ontario-a-baseline-scorecard/ (accessed 28 February 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Children’s Mental Health Ontario. Kids can’t wait: 2020 report on wait lists and wait times for child and youth mental health care in Ontario.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown SA, Parker JD, Godding PR. Administrative, clinical, and ethical issues surrounding the use of waiting lists in the delivery of mental health services. J Behav Health Serv Res 2002; 29: 217–228.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12032979</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schellenberg M, Hatcher S, Thapliyal A, et al. E-mental health in Canada: Transforming the mental health system using technology.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stolz T, Schulz A, Krieger T, et al. A mobile app for social anxiety disorder: a three-arm randomized controlled trial comparing mobile and PC-based guided self-help interventions. J Consult Clin Psychol 2018; 86: 493–504.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29781648</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Domhardt M, Messner EM, Eder AS, et al. Mobile-based interventions for common mental disorders in youth: a systematic evaluation of pediatric health apps. Child Adolesc Psychiatry Ment Health 2021; 15: 49.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8438844</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34517896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garrido S, Cheers D, Boydell K, et al. Young people’s response to six smartphone apps for anxiety and depression: focus group study. JMIR Ment Health 2019; 6: e14385.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6915797</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31579023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bufano P, Laurino M, Said S, et al. Digital phenotyping for monitoring mental disorders: systematic review. J Med Internet Res 2023; 25: e46778.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10753422</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38090800</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torous J, Onnela JP, Keshavan M. New dimensions and new tools to realize the potential of RDoC: digital phenotyping via smartphones and connected devices. Transl Psychiatry 2017; 7: e1053–e1053.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5416670</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28267146</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Werner-Seidler A, Wong Q, Johnston L, et al. Pilot evaluation of the Sleep Ninja: a smartphone application for adolescent insomnia symptoms. BMJ Open 2019; 9: e026502.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6537982</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31133584</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borger JN, Huber R, Ghosh A. Capturing sleep–wake cycles by using day-to-day smartphone touchscreen interactions. Npj Digit Med 2019; 2: 73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6662846</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31372507</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>MacLeod L, Suruliraj B, Gall D, et al. A mobile sensing app to monitor youth mental health: observational pilot study. JMIR MHealth UHealth 2021; 9: e20638.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8579216</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34698650</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meyerhoff J, Liu T, Kording KP, et al. Evaluation of changes in depression, anxiety, and social anxiety using smartphone sensor features: longitudinal cohort study. J Med Internet Res 2021; 23: e22844.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8449302</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34477562</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stepanski EJ, Wyatt JK. Use of sleep hygiene in the treatment of insomnia. Sleep Med Rev 2003; 7: 215–225.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12927121</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carmona NE, Usyatynsky A, Kutana S, et al. A transdiagnostic self-management web-based app for sleep disturbance in adolescents and young adults: feasibility and acceptability study. JMIR Form Res 2021; 5: e25392.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8694239</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34723820</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boerner KE, Coulombe JA, Corkum P. Barriers and facilitators of evidence-based practice in pediatric behavioral sleep care: qualitative analysis of the perspectives of health professionals. Behav Sleep Med 2015; 13: 36–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24364693</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>LeBourgeois MK, Hale L, Chang AM, et al. Digital media and sleep in childhood and adolescence. Pediatrics 2017; 140: S92–S96.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5658795</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29093040</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orr M, Isaacs J, Godbout R, et al. A usability study of an internet-delivered behavioural intervention tailored for children with residual insomnia symptoms after obstructive sleep apnea treatment. Internet Interv 2019; 18: 100265.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6926281</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31890618</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orr M, MacLeod L, Bagnell A, et al. The comfort of adolescent patients and their parents with mobile sensing and digital phenotyping. Comput Hum Behav 2023; 140: 107603.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jacob C, Sezgin E, Sanchez-Vazquez A, et al. Sociotechnical factors affecting patients’ adoption of mobile health tools: systematic literature review and narrative synthesis. JMIR MHealth UHealth 2022; 10: e36284.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9121221</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35318189</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harris PA, Taylor R, Minor BL, et al. The REDCap consortium: building an international community of software platform partners. J Biomed Inform 2019; 95: 103208.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7254481</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31078660</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Birmaher B, Brent DA, Chiappetta L, et al. Psychometric properties of the Screen for Child Anxiety Related Emotional Disorders (SCARED): a replication study. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry 1999; 38: 1230–1236.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10517055</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Angulo M, Rooks BT, Gill M, et al. Psychometrics of the Screen for Adult Anxiety Related Disorders (SCAARED) — a new scale for the assessment of DSM-5 anxiety disorders. Psychiatry Res 2017; 253: 84–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5472098</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28359032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morin CM, Belleville G, Bélanger L, et al. The insomnia severity index: psychometric indicators to detect insomnia cases and evaluate treatment response. Sleep 2011; 34: 601–608.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3079939</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21532953</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Werner-Seidler A, O’Dea B, Shand F, et al. A smartphone app for adolescents with sleep disturbance: development of the Sleep Ninja. JMIR Ment Health 2017; 4: e28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5554352</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28754651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moreno-Peral P, Bellón JÁ, Huibers MJH, et al. Mediators in psychological and psychoeducational interventions for the prevention of depression and anxiety: a systematic review. Clin Psychol Rev 2020; 76: 101813.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32045780</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pascual-Leone A, Yeryomenko N, Morrison OP, et al. Does feeling bad, lead to feeling good? Arousal patterns during expressive writing. Rev Gen Psychol 2016; 20: 336–347.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arch JJ, Craske MG. Mechanisms of mindfulness: emotion regulation following a focused breathing induction. Behav Res Ther 2006; 44: 1849–1858.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16460668</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hilt L, Hanson J, Pollak S. Emotion dysregulation. In: Encyclopedia of adolescence. Amsterdamn, The Netherlands, Elsevier, 2011, pp.160–169.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suruliraj B, Bessenyei K, Bagnell A, et al. Mobile sensing apps and self-management of mental health during the covid-19 pandemic: web-based survey. JMIR Form Res 2021; 5: e24180.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8078366</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33872181</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Emmelkamp PMG, Meyerbröker K. Virtual reality therapy in mental health. Annu Rev Clin Psychol 2021; 17: 495–519.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33606946</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dahne J, Kustanowitz J, Lejuez CW. Development and preliminary feasibility study of a brief behavioral activation mobile application (behavioral apptivation) to be used in conjunction with ongoing therapy. Cogn Behav Pract 2018; 25: 44–56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5926244</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29725198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mazzucchelli T, Kane R, Rees C. Behavioral activation treatments for depression in adults: a meta-analysis and review. Clin Psychol Sci Pract 2009; 16: 383–411.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moretti F, Van Vliet L, Bensing J, et al. A standardized approach to qualitative content analysis of focus group discussions from different countries. Patient Educ Couns 2011; 82: 420–428.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21292424</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braun V, Clarke V. Using thematic analysis in psychology. Qual Res Psychol 2006; 3: 77–101.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsieh HF, Shannon SE. Three approaches to qualitative content analysis. Qual Health Res 2005; 15: 1277–1288.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16204405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali N, Smith I, Brine S, et al. Usability of an online intervention programme for teachers of students with autism spectrum disorder. Int J Disabil Dev Educ 2023; 70: 1147–1163.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fusch P, Ness L. Are we there yet? Data saturation in qualitative research. Qual Rep 2015; 20: 1408–1416.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>AAP-AACAP-CHA. Declaration of a national emergency in child and adolescent mental health, https://www.aap.org/en/advocacy/child-and-adolescent-healthy-mental-development/aap-aacap-cha-declaration-of-a-national-emergency-in-child-and-adolescent-mental-health/ (accessed 28 February 2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zelmer J, Van Hoof K, Notarianni M, et al. An assessment framework for e-mental health apps in Canada: results of a modified Delphi process. JMIR MHealth UHealth 2018; 6: e10016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6056739</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29986846</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei Y, Zheng P, Deng H, et al. Design features for improving mobile health intervention user engagement: systematic review and thematic analysis. J Med Internet Res 2020; 22: e21687.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7758171</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33295292</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Widnall E, Grant CE, Wang T, et al. User perspectives of mood-monitoring apps available to young people: qualitative content analysis. JMIR MHealth UHealth 2020; 8: e18140.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7585773</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33037875</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davis FD. Perceived usefulness, perceived ease of use, and user acceptance of information technology. MIS Q 1989; 13: 319.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venkatesh V, Morris MG, Davis GB, et al. User acceptance of information technology: toward a unified view. MIS Q 2003; 27: 425.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borghouts J, Eikey E, Mark G, et al. Barriers to and facilitators of user engagement with digital mental health interventions: systematic review. J Med Internet Res 2021; 23: e24387.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8074985</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33759801</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kelly JT, Campbell KL, Gong E, et al. The internet of things: impact and implications for health care delivery. J Med Internet Res 2020; 22: e20135.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7685921</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33170132</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Canzian L, Musolesi M. Trajectories of depression: unobtrusive monitoring of depressive states by means of smartphone mobility traces analysis. In: Proceedings of the 2015 ACM International Joint Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing, Osaka Japan, pp.1293–1304: ACM.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen JS, Edmunds JM, Brodman DM, et al. Using self-monitoring: implementation of collaborative empiricism in cognitive–behavioral therapy. Cogn Behav Pract 2013; 20: 419–428.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nicholas J, Fogarty AS, Boydell K, et al. The reviews are in: a qualitative content analysis of consumer perspectives on apps for bipolar disorder. J Med Internet Res 2017; 19: e105.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5400886</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28389420</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng W, Kanthawala S, Yuan S, et al. A qualitative study of user perceptions of mobile health apps. BMC Public Health 2016; 16: 1158.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5109835</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27842533</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schueller SM, Neary M, O’Loughlin K, et al. Discovery of and interest in health apps among those with mental health needs: survey and focus group study. J Med Internet Res 2018; 20: e10141.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6018235</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29891468</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohr DC, Shilton K, Hotopf M. Digital phenotyping, behavioral sensing, or personal sensing: names and transparency in the digital age. NPJ Digit Med 2020; 3: 45.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7096455</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32219186</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rogan J, Bucci S, Firth J. Health care professionals’ views on the use of passive sensing, AI, and machine learning in mental health care: systematic review with meta-synthesis. JMIR Ment Health 2024; 11: e49577.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10848143</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38261403</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bessenyei K, Suruliraj B, Bagnell A, et al. Comfortability with the passive collection of smartphone data for monitoring of mental health: an online survey. Comput Hum Behav Rep 2021; 4: 100134.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng M, Chen X, Zhao Q, et al. Attentional scope is reduced by internet use: a behavior and ERP study. PLOS ONE 2018; 13: e0198543.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5993299</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29883465</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alqahtani F, Orji R. Insights from user reviews to improve mental health apps. Health Informatics J 2020; 26: 2042–2066.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31920160</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petty RE, Cacioppo JT. The elaboration likelihood model of persuasion. Adv Exp Soc Psychol 1986; 19: 123–205.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oinas-Kukkonen H, Harjumaa M. Persuasive systems design: key issues, process model, and system features. Commun Assoc Inf Syst 2009; 24: 485–500.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stawarz K, Preist C, Tallon D, et al. User experience of cognitive behavioral therapy apps for depression: an analysis of app functionality and user reviews. J Med Internet Res 2018; 20: e10120.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6010839</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29875087</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grist R, Porter J, Stallard P. Mental health mobile apps for preadolescents and adolescents: a systematic review. J Med Internet Res 2017; 19: e176.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5465380</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28546138</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCurdie T, Taneva S, Casselman M, et al. Mhealth consumer apps: the case for user-centered design. Biomed Instrum Technol 2012; 46: 49–56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23039777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jacob C, Sanchez-Vazquez A, Ivory C. Social, organizational, and technological factors impacting clinicians’ adoption of mobile health tools: systematic literature review. JMIR MHealth UHealth 2020; 8: e15935.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7059085</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32130167</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goswami A, Dutta S. Gender differences in technology usage—a literature review. Open J Bus Manag 2016; 04: 51–59.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venkatesh V, Morris MG. Why don’t men ever stop to ask for directions? Gender, social influence, and their role in technology acceptance and usage behavior. MIS Q 2000; 24: 115.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cameron EE, et al. Parental socioeconomic status and childhood sleep: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Sleep Epidemiol 2022; 2: e100047.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu Y, et al. Socioeconomic status disparities affect children’s anxiety and stress-sensitive cortisol awakening response through parental anxiety. PNEC 2019; 103: 96–103.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30665044</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>