<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39397970</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2405-8440</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>19</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>15</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Heliyon</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Heliyon</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>N-alkylation of amines for the synthesis of potential antiviral agents: A structural modification approach.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e38587</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e38587</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e38587</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e38587</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The threat of emerging viral outbreaks has increased the need for fast and effective development of therapeutics against emerging pathogens. One approach is to modify the structure of existing therapeutic agents to achieve the desired antiviral properties. Here, we attempted to synthesize a new antiviral compound by modifying the structure of chloroquine using the <i>N-alkylation</i> of the primary amine (N1,N1-diethylpentane-1,4-diamine) that is used in chloroquine synthesis. Chloroquine is commonly used to treat malaria. Like chloroquine, chloroquine is used for treating conditions such as rheumatoid arthritis, lupus, and malaria. For instance, in malaria treatment, it targets and inhibits the growth of the malaria parasite, aiding in its elimination from the body. The synthesized compounds MP1, C1, and TT1 were further tested in vitro against the B.1 lineage of SARS-CoV-2. One of the compounds, MP1, demonstrated minor effectiveness, with an IC50 of XX at only a high concentration (at a concentration of 60 μM) and decreased both the number of SARS-CoV-2 copies and the amount of infectious virus. Although the synthesized compounds failed to markedly inhibit SARS-CoV-2, this could be a pontial mechanism for manipulating the drug structure against other pathogens. MP1, TT1, C1, and chloroquine diphosphate were used as ligands for molecular docking to determine the principal interactions between these compounds and the active site of the protein downloaded from the Protein Data Bank (PDB ID: 6lzg). Finally, ADMET assays were performed on the synthesized compounds to determine their pharmacokinetics and bioavailability.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Arrousse</LastName><ForeName>Nadia</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Science and Engineering, Al Akhawayn University in Ifrane, Hassan II avenue, 53000 Ifrane, Morocco.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Engineering, Electrochemistry, Modelling and Environment (LIEME), Faculty of Sciences, University Sidi Mohamed Ben Abdellah, Fez, Morocco.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Berdimurodov</LastName><ForeName>Elyor</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Chemistry, National University of Uzbekistan, Tashkent, 100034, Uzbekistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Physics and Chemistry, Western Caspian University, AZ-1001, Baku, Azerbaijan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Tashkent for Applied Sciences, Str. Gavhar 1, 100149, Tashkent, Uzbekistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Physics and Chemistry, Tashkent Institute of Irrigation and Agricultural Mechanization Engineers" National Research University, 100000, Tashkent, Uzbekistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bogacheva</LastName><ForeName>Mariia</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Viral Zone Research Unit, Faculty of Medicine, University of Helsinki, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zakham</LastName><ForeName>Fathiah</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Biosciences, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Helsinki, Helsinki, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Pharmacy, University of Helsinki, 00014 Helsinki, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Esslali</LastName><ForeName>Soukaina</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Chemistry-Biology Applied to the Environment, Chemistry Department, Faculty of Sciences, Moulay-Ismail University, B.P. 11201, Zitoune, Meknes, Morocco.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>El Kadiri</LastName><ForeName>Sghir</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Applied Chemistry &amp; Environment (LCAE), Faculty of Science, Mohammed First University, Oujda, Morocco.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Taleb</LastName><ForeName>Mustapha</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Engineering, Electrochemistry, Modelling and Environment (LIEME), Faculty of Sciences, University Sidi Mohamed Ben Abdellah, Fez, Morocco.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vapalahti</LastName><ForeName>Olli</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Biosciences, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Helsinki, Helsinki, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Pharmacy, University of Helsinki, 00014 Helsinki, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Heliyon</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101672560</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2405-8440</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Chloroquine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Drug synthesis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Molecular docking</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pharmacokinetic properties</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>36</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39397970</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11470537</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e38587</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2405-8440(24)14618-X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Kreutzberger A.J.B., et al. SARS-CoV-2 requires acidic pH to infect cells. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA. 2022;119(38)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9499588</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36048924</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdolmaleki G., et al. A comparison between SARS-CoV-1 and SARS-CoV2: an update on current COVID-19 vaccines. Daru. 2022;30(2):379–406.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9436716</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36050585</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ni W., et al. Role of angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) in COVID-19. Crit. Care. 2020;24:1–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7356137</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32660650</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y., Liu Q., Guo D. Emerging coronaviruses: genome structure, replication, and pathogenesis. J. Med. Virol. 2020;92(4):418–423.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7167049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31967327</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vincent M.J., et al. Chloroquine is a potent inhibitor of SARS coronavirus infection and spread. Virol. J. 2005;2:1–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1232869</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16115318</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baildya N., Ghosh N.N., Chattopadhyay A.P. Inhibitory capacity of Chloroquine against SARS-COV-2 by effective binding with Angiotensin converting enzyme-2 receptor: an insight from molecular docking and MD-simulation studies. J. Mol. Struct. 2021;1230</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7831893</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33518803</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu J., et al. Hydroxychloroquine, a less toxic derivative of chloroquine, is effective in inhibiting SARS-CoV-2 infection in vitro. Cell discovery. 2020;6(1):16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7078228</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32194981</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao J., Tian Z., Yang X. Breakthrough: chloroquine phosphate has shown apparent efficacy in treatment of COVID-19 associated pneumonia in clinical studies. Bioscience trends. 2020;14(1):72–73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32074550</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gautret P., et al. Hydroxychloroquine and azithromycin as a treatment of COVID-19: results of an open-label non-randomized clinical trial. Int. J. Antimicrob. Agents. 2020;56(1)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7102549</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32205204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Avezum Á., et al. Hydroxychloroquine versus placebo in the treatment of non-hospitalised patients with COVID-19 (COPE–Coalition V): a double-blind, multicentre, randomised, controlled trial. The Lancet Regional Health–Americas. 2022;11</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8968238</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35378952</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thomson K., Nachlis H. Emergency use authorizations during the COVID-19 pandemic: lessons from hydroxychloroquine for vaccine authorization and approval. JAMA. 2020;324(13):1282–1283.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32870235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schwartz I.S., Boulware D.R., Lee T.C. Hydroxychloroquine for COVID19: the curtains close on a comedy of errors. The Lancet Regional Health–Americas. 2022;11</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9069223</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35531052</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Browning D.J. Springer; 2014. Hydroxychloroquine and Chloroquine Retinopathy.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11992862</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biswas P., et al. Candidate antiviral drugs for COVID-19 and their environmental implications: a comprehensive analysis. Environ. Sci. Pollut. Control Ser. 2021;28(42):59570–59593.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8435122</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34510341</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sturrock B.R.H., Chevassut T.J.T. Chloroquine and COVID-19–a potential game changer? Clin. Med. 2020;20(3):278–281.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7354053</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32303497</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pevzner M.S., et al. Heterocyclic nitro compounds. 25. 1-Hydroxymethyl-3-nitro-1, 2, 4-triazoles and their derivatives. Chem. Heterocycl. Compd. 1980;16:189–194.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rusanen J., et al. A generic, scalable, and rapid time-resolved Förster resonance energy transfer-based assay for antigen detection—SARS-CoV-2 as a proof of concept. mBio. 2021;12(3):10–1128.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8262888</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34006662</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cantuti-Castelvetri L., et al. Neuropilin-1 facilitates SARS-CoV-2 cell entry and infectivity. Science. 2020;370(6518):856–860.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7857391</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33082293</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin J.-w., et al. Genomic monitoring of SARS-CoV-2 uncovers an Nsp1 deletion variant that modulates type I interferon response. Cell Host Microbe. 2021;29(3):489–502.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7846228</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33548198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corman V.M., et al. Detection of 2019 novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) by real-time RT-PCR. Euro Surveill. 2020;25(3)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6988269</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31992387</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rudrapal M., et al. Explainable artificial intelligence-assisted virtual screening and bioinformatics approaches for effective bioactivity prediction of phenolic cyclooxygenase-2 (COX-2) inhibitors using PubChem molecular fingerprints. Mol. Divers. 2024:1–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38200203</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Issahaku A.R., et al. Characterization of the binding of MRTX1133 as an avenue for the discovery of potential KRASG12D inhibitors for cancer therapy. Sci. Rep. 2022;12(1)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9588042</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36273239</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rudrapal M., et al. Dual synergistic inhibition of COX and LOX by potential chemicals from Indian daily spices investigated through detailed computational studies. Sci. Rep. 2023;13(1):8656.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10224994</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37244921</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Issahaku A.R., et al. Discovery of potential KRAS‐SOS1 inhibitors from South African natural compounds: an in silico approach. ChemistrySelect. 2023;8(24)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ezugwu J.A., et al. Design, synthesis, molecular docking, molecular dynamics and in vivo antimalarial activity of new dipeptide‐sulfonamides. ChemistrySelect. 2022;7(5)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kouranov A., et al. The RCSB PDB information portal for structural genomics. Nucleic Acids Res. 2006;34(suppl_1):D302–D305.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1347482</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16381872</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moussa N., Hassan A., Gharaghani S. Pharmacophore model, docking, QSAR, and molecular dynamics simulation studies of substituted cyclic imides and herbal medicines as COX-2 inhibitors. Heliyon. 2021;7(4)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8047494</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33889764</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lokhande K.B., et al. Molecular docking and simulation studies on SARS-CoV-2 Mpro reveals Mitoxantrone, Leucovorin, Birinapant, and Dynasore as potent drugs against COVID-19. J. Biomol. Struct. Dyn. 2021;39(18):7294–7305.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7484567</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32815481</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tabti K., et al. Molecular modelling of antiproliferative inhibitors based on SMILES descriptors using Monte-Carlo method, docking, MD simulations and ADME/Tox studies. Mol. Simulat. 2022;48(17):1575–1591.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohammed E.-R., et al. QSAR, molecular docking, ADMET properties in silico studies for a series of 7-propanamide benzoxaboroles as potent anti-cancer agents. Chin. J. Anal. Chem. 2022;50(12)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdizadeh R., et al. Investigation of pyrimidine analogues as xanthine oxidase inhibitors to treat of hyperuricemia and gout through combined QSAR techniques, molecular docking and molecular dynamics simulations. J. Taiwan Inst. Chem. Eng. 2020;113:72–100.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>