<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39394757</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>12</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1523-536X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>11</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Birth (Berkeley, Calif.)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Birth</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Return-on-Investment Analysis of an Enhanced Community Doula Program: Pre- and Post-COVID-19 Considerations.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/birt.12886</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Community doulas are perinatal health workers who provide peer education, resource navigation, and support during pregnancy, childbirth, and the postpartum period. Evidence suggests that doulas improve the experience of care, reduce cesarean birth, and improve breastfeeding outcomes. However, people with low incomes cannot access affordable community doula support in most states due to lack of insurance reimbursement. To determine the affordability of Medicaid reimbursement for doula services, there is a need to fill a gap in research that employs real-world data and a return-on-investment (ROI) analysis approach.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">We conducted a ROI analysis from the healthcare perspective of an enhanced community doula intervention, Best Beginnings for Babies (BBB). Healthcare and program cost data were collected alongside clinical outcomes from a randomized controlled trial of routine maternity care at Boston Medical Center with and without BBB. ROI was calculated as the net healthcare savings divided by the investment costs. Post-COVID-19 program costing estimates were also performed.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Average healthcare costs per patient were $18,969 for the BBB group compared with $20,121 for routine care, a savings of $1,152. BBB program costs were an average of $971 per person. There was an 18% ROI. Lower costs for the birth hospitalization and NICU stays accounted for the largest areas of savings. Per-person program costs using proposed MassHealth fees produced a positive return on investment, although 2023 hospital doula program wages and salaries did not.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DISCUSSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The BBB-enhanced community doula program was cost-saving to payers and increased access to doula support for low-income people. Even with post-COVID-19 increases in program costs, analysis demonstrated doula support was still financially feasible. This study should reassure budget-conscious Medicaid payers that doula services are affordable.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mottl-Santiago</LastName><ForeName>Julie</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Boston Medical Center, Boston, Massachusetts, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dukhovny</LastName><ForeName>Dmitry</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Oregon Health and Sciences University, Portland, Oregon, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Feinberg</LastName><ForeName>Emily</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Services, Policy, and Practice, Brown University School of Public Health, Providence, Rhode Island, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Moore</LastName><ForeName>Jennifer</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Medicaid Innovation, Washington, DC, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, University of Michigan Medical School, Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Parker</LastName><ForeName>Victoria</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Peter T. Paul College of Business and Economics, University of New Hampshire, Durham, New Hampshire, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cabral</LastName><ForeName>Howard</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biostatistics, Boston University School of Public Health, Boston, Massachusetts, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bowser</LastName><ForeName>Diana</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Connell School of Nursing, Boston College, Chestnut Hill, Massachusetts, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Declercq</LastName><ForeName>Gene</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Health Sciences, Boston University School of Public Health, Boston, Massachusetts, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>W.K. Kellogg Foundation</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Birth</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8302042</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0730-7659</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Medicaid</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">doulas</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">economic evaluation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">healthcare costs</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">medical legal partnership</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">return‐on‐investment</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>21</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>21</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39394757</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/birt.12886</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>A. Bey, A. Brill, C. Porchia‐Albert, et al., Advancing Birth Justice: Community‐Based Doula Models as a Standard of Care for Ending Racial Disparities (New York, NY: Every Mother Counts, 2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Steel, J. Frawley, J. Adams, and H. Diezel, “Trained or Professional Doulas in the Support and Care of Pregnant and Birthing Women: A Critical Integrative Review,” Health &amp; Social Care in the Community 23, no. 3 (2015): 225–241.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. A. Bohren, G. J. Hofmeyr, C. Sakala, R. K. Fukuzawa, and A. Cuthbert, “Continuous Support for Women During Childbirth,” Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews 7 (2017): CD003766.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. A. Bohren, B. O. Berger, H. Munthe‐Kaas, and Ö. Tunçalp, “Perceptions and Experiences of Labour Companionship: A Qualitative Evidence Synthesis,” Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews 3 (2019): CD012449.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. M. Khaw, R. I. Zahroh, K. O'Rourke, R. E. Dearnley, C. Homer, and M. A. Bohren, “Community‐Based Doulas for Migrant and Refugee Women: A Mixed‐Method Systematic Review and Narrative Synthesis,” BMJ Global Health 7, no. 7 (2022): e009098.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Strauss, C. Sakala, and M. P. Corry, “Overdue: Medicaid and Private Insurance Coverage of Doula Care to Strengthen Maternal and Infant Health,” Journal of Perinatal Education 25, no. 3 (2016): 145–149.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Platt and N. Kaye, “Four State Strategies to Employ Doulas to Improve Maternal Health and Birth Outcomes in Medicaid. National Academy for State,” Health Policy (2020), accessed February 18, 2023, ww.nashp.org/wp‐content/uploads/2020/07/Doula‐Brief‐7.6.2020.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Chen, “The National Health Law Project. Current State Doula Medicaid Efforts,” accessed January 25, 2023, https://healthlaw.org/doulamedicaidproject.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. M. Ogunwole, D. G. Bozzi, K. M. Bower, L. A. Cooper, R. Hardeman, and K. Kozhimannil, “Health Equity Considerations in State Bills Related to Doula Care (2015–2020),” Women's Health Issues 32, no. 5 (2022): 440–449.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Marshall, S. Arteaga, J. Arcara, et al., “Barriers and Facilitators to the Implementation of a Community Doula Program for Black and Pacific Islander Pregnant People in San Francisco: Findings From a Partnered Process Evaluation,” Maternal and Child Health Journal 26, no. 4 (2022): 872–881.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Brewington, R. Nogales, and A. Weiss, “Sustainably Growing the Community Doula Workforce in New Jersey,” Health Affairs Forefront (2022), https://doi.org/10.1377/forefront.20221108.744438.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. S. Greiner, A. R. Hersh, S. R. Hersh, et al., “The Cost‐Effectiveness of Professional Doula Care for a Woman's First Two Births: A Decision Analysis Model,” Journal of Midwifery &amp; Women's Health 64 (2019): 410–420.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. B. Kozhimannil, R. R. Hardeman, F. Alarid‐Escudero, C. A. Vogelsang, C. Blauer‐Peterson, and E. A. Howell, “Modeling the Cost‐Effectiveness of Doula Care Associated With Reductions in Preterm Birth and Cesarean Delivery,” Birth 43, no. 1 (2016): 20–27.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. B. Kozhimannil, R. R. Hardeman, L. B. Attanasio, C. Blauer‐Peterson, and M. O'Brien, “Doula Care, Birth Outcomes, and Costs Among Medicaid Beneficiaries,” American Journal of Public Health 103, no. 4 (2013): e113–e121.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. Chapple, A. Gilliland, D. Li, E. Shier, and E. Wright, “An Economic Model of the Benefits of Professional Doula Labor Support in Wisconsin Births,” WMJ 112, no. 2 (2013): 58–64.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Brousselle and C. Lessard, “Economic Evaluation to Inform Health Care Decision Making: Promise, Pitfalls and a Proposal for an Alternative Path,” Social Science and Medicine 72, no. 6 (2011): 832–839.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Brousselle, T. Benmarhnia, and L. Benhadj, “What Are the Benefits and Risks of Using Return on Investment to Defend Public Health Programs?,” Preventive Medical Reports 3 (2016): 135–138. Epub 20160119.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. M. Brown, L. D. Cameron, and S. Ramondt, “Sustainability of Behavioral Interventions: Beyond Cost‐Effectiveness Analysis,” International Journal of Behavioral Medicine 22, no. 3 (2015): 425–433.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Mottl‐Santiago, “A Mixed Methods Economic Analysis of Doula‐Service Enhanced Maternity Care as Compared With Standard Maternity Care.” (Doctoral Dissertation, Boston University) 2020, https://open.bu.edu/handle/2144/41455.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Mottl‐Santiago, K. Herr, D. Rodrigues, C. Walker, C. Walker, and E. Feinberg, “The Birth Sisters Program: A Model of Hospital‐Based Doula Support to Promote Health Equity,” Journal of Health Care for the Poor and Underserved 31, no. 1 (2020): 43–55.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Mottl‐Santiago, D. Dukhovny, H. Cabral, et al., “Effectiveness of an Enhanced Community Doula Intervention in a Safety Net Setting: A Randomized Controlled Trial,” Health Equity 7, no. 1 (2023): 466–476.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Cui, H. Diop, S. L. Stone, M. Vu, and S. Pagnano, “Massachusetts Births 2018,” 2018 (Massachusetts Department of Public Health). https://www.mass.gov/doc/2018‐birth‐report.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Executive Office of Health and Human Services, “CMR 304.00: Rates For Community Health Centers,” accessed July 3, 2018, https://www.mass.gov/regulations/101‐CMR‐30400‐rates‐for‐community‐healthcenters‐0.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. J. Neumann, G. D. Sanders, A. Basu, et al., “Chapter 3: Recommendations on Perspectives for the Reference Case,” in Cost‐Effectiveness in Health and Medicine, 2nd ed., eds. P. J. Neumann, D. S. Gillian, L. B. Russell, J. E. Siegel, and T. G. Ganiats (New York: Oxford University Press, 2017), 67–73.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bureau of Labor Statistics, “Medical Care in U.S. City Average, All Urban Consumers, Not Seasonally Adjusted, 2015–2023,” accessed August 26, 2023, https://data.bls.gov/cgi‐bin/surveymost.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Internal Revenue Service, “Standard Mileage Rates,” https://www.irs.gov/tax‐professionals/standard‐mileage‐rates. accessed July 18, 2018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. J. Dunlap, M. R. Kuklinski, A. Cowell, et al., “Economic Evaluation Design Within the HEAL Prevention Cooperative,” Prevention Science 10 (2022): 1–11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality, “Quality Indicators Toolkit. Return on Investment Estimation,” accessed October 13, 2023, https://www.ahrq.gov/sites/default/files/wysiwyg/professionals/systems/hospital/qitoolkit/combined/f1_combo_returnoninvestment.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Stepanek, M. Hafner, J. Taylor, S. Grand‐Clement, and C. Van Stolk, The Return of Investment for Preventive Healthcare Programmes: A Calculation Framework for GSK's Partnership for Prevention (P4P) (Santa Monica, CA: RAND Corporation, 2017) accessed October 18, 2023, https://www.rand.org/pubs/research_reports/RR1787.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Masters, E. Anwar, B. Collins, R. Cookson, and S. Capewell, “Return on Investment of Public Health Interventions: A Systematic Review,” Journal of Epidemiology and Community Health 71, no. 8 (2017): 827–834.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. H. Rush, “Return on Investment From Employment of Community Health Workers,” Journal of Ambulatory Care Management 35, no. 2 (2012): 133–137.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. E. Hamilton, J. A. Martin, and M. J. K. Osterman, “Births: Provisional Data for 2023,” Vital Statistics Rapid Release 35 (2024), https://doi.org/10.15620/cdc:151797.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Chen, “Doula Medicaid Project: February 2024 State Roundup,” 2024 accessed June 3, 2024, https://healthlaw.org/wp‐content/uploads/2024/03/Feb‐2024‐Update‐on‐State‐Doula‐Medicaid‐Implementation‐Efforts‐updated‐03‐06‐2024.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. L. Nerlinger, P. M. Alberti, A. L. Gilbert, et al., “Evaluating the Efficacy of Medical‐Legal Partnerships That Address Social Determinants of Health,” Progress in Community Health Partnerships: Research, Education, and Action 15, no. 2 (2021): 255–264.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Sege, G. Preer, S. J. Morton, et al., “Medical‐Legal Strategies to Improve Infant Health Care: A Randomized Trial,” Pediatrics 136, no. 1 (2015): 97–106.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Hasan, “National Academy for State Health Policy. State Medicaid Approaches to Doula Service Benefits,” accessed September 29, 2023, https://nashp.org/state‐medicaid‐approaches‐to‐doula‐service‐benefits/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. M. Gomez, S. Arteaga, J. Arcara, et al., ““My 9 to 5 Job Is Birth Work”: A Case Study of Two Compensation Approaches for Community Doula Care,” International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 18, no. 20 (2021): 10817.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blue Cross Blue Shield Foundation of Massachusetts, “Faces of MassHealth: Portrait of a Diverse Population,” accessed February 26, 2020, https://bluecrossmafoundation.org/publication/faces‐masshealth‐portrait‐diverse‐population.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>