<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39394754</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>12</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1523-536X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>11</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Birth (Berkeley, Calif.)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Birth</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Birth Outcomes and Prenatal Care Use in the U.S. During the COVID-19 Pandemic in 2020 and 2021.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/birt.12890</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The COVID-19 pandemic has posed substantial social and economic disruptions that may have had adverse effects on maternal and infant health. This study examines the changes in birth outcomes and prenatal care use during the COVID-19 pandemic in 2020 and 2021 compared to pre-pandemic years.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Data come from birth certificates from the U.S. Vital Statistics Natality Files. The analytical sample includes 18,678,327 births in the 50 states and Washington, DC between 2017 and 2021. An event study is employed to examine changes in multiple birth outcomes and prenatal care use over years adjusting for demographic/socioeconomic characteristics and state of residence.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">There were very small changes in birth outcomes during pandemic years in 2020 and 2021. Specifically, low birth weight odds were lower in 2020 (OR = 0.99; 95 CI: 0.98-0.99) but higher in 2021 (OR = 1.03; 95% CI: 1.03-1.04) compared to 2019. C-section odds were higher in 2021 (OR = 1.01, 95% CI: 1.002-1.008) than in 2019. The mean number of prenatal visits in both 2020 and 2021 relative to 2019 was lower by about 0.3 visits (95% CI: -0.31 to -0.30 in 2021).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Overall, there is no evidence of broad pandemic effects on low birth weight and preterm birth in 2020-2021.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lyu</LastName><ForeName>Wei</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7441-9961</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Services Administration, University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, Alabama, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wehby</LastName><ForeName>George L</ForeName><Initials>GL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Management and Policy, University of Iowa, Iowa City, Iowa, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Economics, University of Iowa, Iowa City, Iowa, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Preventive and Community Dentistry, University of Iowa, Iowa City, Iowa, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Public Policy Center, University of Iowa, Iowa City, Iowa, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Bureau of Economic Research, Cambridge, Massachusetts, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Birth</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8302042</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0730-7659</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19 pandemic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">infant health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">prenatal care use</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>21</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>21</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39394754</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/birt.12890</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>J. Allotey, E. Stallings, M. Bonet, et al., “Clinical Manifestations, Risk Factors, and Maternal and Perinatal Outcomes of Coronavirus Disease 2019 in Pregnancy: Living Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis,” BMJ 370 (2020): m3320.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Y. Ko, C. L. DeSisto, R. M. Simeone, et al., “Adverse Pregnancy Outcomes, Maternal Complications, and Severe Illness Among US Delivery Hospitalizations With and Without a Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID‐19) Diagnosis,” Clinical Infectious Diseases 73, no. Suppl 1 (2021): S24–S31.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Chmielewska, I. Barratt, R. Townsend, et al., “Effects of the COVID‐19 Pandemic on Maternal and Perinatal Outcomes: A Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis,” Lancet Global Health 9, no. 6 (2021): e759–e772.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. L. DeSisto, B. Wallace, R. M. Simeone, et al., “Risk for Stillbirth Among Women With and Without COVID‐19 at Delivery Hospitalization—United States, March 2020–September 2021,” Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report 70, no. 47 (2021): 1640–1645.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. M. Harvey, E. McNeer, M. F. McDonald, et al., “Association of Preterm Birth Rate With COVID‐19 Statewide Stay‐At‐Home Orders in Tennessee,” JAMA Pediatrics 175, no. 6 (2021): 635–637.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. S. Hwang, B. W. Weikel, K. E. Hannan, and S. L. Bourque, “Impact of Coronavirus Disease‐19 “Stay‐At‐Home” Orders on Preterm Birth in Colorado,” Journal of Pediatrics 242 (2022): 238–241.e1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Gemmill, J. A. Casey, R. Catalano, D. Karasek, C. E. Margerison, and T. Bruckner, “Changes in Preterm Birth and Caesarean Deliveries in the United States During the SARS‐CoV‐2 Pandemic,” Paediatric and Perinatal Epidemiology 36, no. 4 (2022): 485–489.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. J. Osterman, B. E. Hamilton, J. A. Martin, A. K. Driscoll, and C. P. Valenzuela, “Births: Final Data for 2020,” National Vital Statistics Reports 70, no. 17 (2022): 1–50.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Dench, T. Joyce, and H. Minkoff, “United States Preterm Birth Rate and COVID‐19,” Pediatrics 149, no. 5 (2022): e2021055495.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. E. Margerison, T. A. Bruckner, C. MacCallum‐Bridges, R. Catalano, J. A. Casey, and A. Gemmill, “Exposure to the Early COVID‐19 Pandemic and Early, Moderate and Overall Preterm Births in the United States: A Conception Cohort Approach,” Paediatric and Perinatal Epidemiology 37 (2022): 104–112.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Chen, C. Ferre, L. Ouyang, Y. Mohamoud, W. Barfield, and S. Cox, “Changes and Geographic Variation in Rates of Preterm Birth and Stillbirth During the Prepandemic Period and COVID‐19 Pandemic, According to Health Insurance Claims in the United States, April–June 2019 and April–June 2020,” American Journal of Obstetrics &amp; Gynecology MFM 4, no. 1 (2022): 100508.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. M. Simeone, K. F. Downing, B. Wallace, et al., “Changes in Rates of Adverse Pregnancy Outcomes During the COVID‐19 Pandemic: A Cross‐Sectional Study in the United States, 2019–2020,” Journal of Perinatology 42, no. 5 (2022): 617–623.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. C. Handley, A. M. Mullin, M. A. Elovitz, et al., “Changes in Preterm Birth Phenotypes and Stillbirth at 2 Philadelphia Hospitals During the SARS‐CoV‐2 Pandemic, March–June 2020,” JAMA 325, no. 1 (2021): 87–89.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Richter, A. S. Strasser, M. Suarez‐Farinas, et al., “Neonatal Outcomes During the COVID‐19 Pandemic in New York City,” Pediatric Research 91, no. 3 (2022): 477–479.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Wood, C. Sinnott, I. Goldfarb, M. Clapp, T. McElrath, and S. Little, “Preterm Birth During the Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID‐19) Pandemic in a Large Hospital System in the United States,” Obstetrics &amp; Gynecology 137, no. 3 (2021): 403–404.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. K. Main, S. C. Chang, A. M. Carpenter, et al., “Singleton Preterm Birth Rates for Racial and Ethnic Groups During the Coronavirus Disease 2019 Pandemic in California,” American Journal of Obstetrics and Gynecology 224, no. 2 (2021): 239–241.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Gerace, G. Rigney, and J. R. Anderson, “Predicting Attitudes Towards Easing COVID‐19 Restrictions in the United States of America: The Role of Health Concerns, Demographic, Political, and Individual Difference Factors,” PLoS One 17, no. 2 (2022): e0263128.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Mervosh, J. C. Lee, L. Gamio, and N. Popovich, “See How All 50 States Are Reopening. New York Times,” 2021, https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/us/states‐reopen‐map‐coronavirus.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Jarrett, Quarterly Services Survey Shows Pandemic Had Greater Effect on Some Health Care Services (Washington, DC: Census Bureau, 2021), https://www.census.gov/library/stories/2021/09/pandemic‐disrupts‐some‐trends‐in‐health‐care‐services.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Gallagher, J. Gerhart, K. Amin, M. Rae, and C. Cox, “Early 2021 Data Show No Rebound in Health Care Utilization. Peterson Center on Healthcare and KFF,” 2021, https://www.healthsystemtracker.org/brief/early‐2021‐data‐show‐no‐rebound‐in‐health‐care‐utilization/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Office of the Assistant Secretary for Planning and Evaluation, Impact of the COVID‐19 Pandemic on the Hospital and Outpatient Clinician Workforce: Challenges and Policy Responses (Washington, DC: U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, 2021), https://aspe.hhs.gov/sites/default/files/documents/9cc72124abd9ea25d58a22c7692dccb6/aspe‐covid‐workforce‐report.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Cantor, C. Whaley, K. Simon, and T. Nguyen, “US Health Care Workforce Changes During the First and Second Years of the COVID‐19 Pandemic,” JAMA Health Forum 3, no. 2 (2022): e215217.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Annenberg Public Policy Center, Despite Awareness of Covid‐19 Risks, Many Americans Say They're Back to ‘Normal’ (Philadelphia, PA: University of Pennsylvania, 2022), https://www.annenbergpublicpolicycenter.org/despite‐awareness‐of‐covid‐19‐risks‐many‐americans‐say‐theyre‐back‐to‐normal/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Housing Law Project, “Federal Moratorium on Evictions for Nonpayment of Rent. San Francisco, CA,” 2021, https://nlihc.org/sites/default/files/Overview‐of‐National‐Eviction‐Moratorium.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Raifman, K. Nocka, D. Jones, et al., “COVID‐19 US State Policy Database,” 2020, https://statepolicies.com/data/library/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Nagele‐Piazza, States and Cities Update COVID‐19 Paid‐Sick‐Leave Laws (Alexandria, VA: Society for Human Resource Management, 2021), https://www.shrm.org/resourcesandtools/legal‐and‐compliance/state‐and‐local‐updates/pages/states‐and‐cities‐update‐covid‐19‐paid‐sick‐leave‐laws.aspx.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Department of Labor, Temporary Rule: Paid Leave Under the Families First Coronavirus Response Act (Washington, DC: U.S. Department of Labor, 2020), https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/ffcra#:~:text=FFCRA%20helps%20the%20United%20States,reasons%20related%20to%20COVID%2D19.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Center on Budget and Policy Priorities Policy Basics, How Many Weeks of Unemployment Compensation Are Available?, (Washington, DC: Center on Budget and Policy Priorities Policy Basics, 2023), https://www.cbpp.org/research/economy/how‐many‐weeks‐of‐unemployment‐compensation‐are‐available.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. L. Crandall‐Hollick, The Child Tax Credit: Temporary Expansion for 2021 Under the American Rescue Plan Act of 2021 (ARPA; P.L. 117‐2) (Washington DC: Congressional Research Service, 2021), https://crsreports.congress.gov/product/pdf/IN/IN11613.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Pollitz, How the American Rescue Plan Will Improve Affordability of Private Health Coverage (San Francisco, CA: Kaiser Family Foundation, 2021), https://www.kff.org/health‐reform/issue‐brief/how‐the‐american‐rescue‐plan‐will‐improve‐affordability‐of‐private‐health‐coverage/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics, Civilian Unemployment Rate (Washington, DC: U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics, 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. J. Holmberg and L. W. Andersen, “Estimating Risk Ratios and Risk Differences: Alternatives to Odds Ratios,” JAMA 324, no. 11 (2020): 1098–1099.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. V. Been, L. B. Ochoa, L. C. Bertens, et al., “Impact of COVID‐19 Mitigation Measures on the Incidence of Preterm Birth: A National Quasi‐Experimental Study,” Lancet Public Health 5, no. 11 (2020): e604–e611.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Hedermann, P. L. Hedley, M. Bækvad‐Hansen, et al., “Danish Premature Birth Rates During the COVID‐19 Lockdown,” Archives of Disease in Childhood. Fetal and Neonatal Edition 106, no. 1 (2021): 93–95.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Einarsdóttir, E. M. Swift, and H. Zoega, “Changes in Obstetric Interventions and Preterm Birth During COVID‐19: A Nationwide Study From Iceland,” Acta Obstetricia et Gynecologica Scandinavica 100, no. 10 (2021): 1924–1930.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. McDonnell, E. McNamee, S. W. Lindow, and M. P. O'Connell, “The Impact of the Covid‐19 Pandemic on Maternity Services: A Review of Maternal and Neonatal Outcomes Before, During and After the Pandemic,” European Journal of Obstetrics, Gynecology, and Reproductive Biology 255 (2020): 172–176.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Khalil, P. von Dadelszen, T. Draycott, A. Ugwumadu, P. O'Brien, and L. Magee, “Change in the Incidence of Stillbirth and Preterm Delivery During the COVID‐19 Pandemic,” JAMA 324, no. 7 (2020): 705–706.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. K. Philip, H. Purtill, E. Reidy, et al., “Unprecedented Reduction in Births of Very Low Birthweight (VLBW) and Extremely Low Birthweight (ELBW) Infants During the COVID‐19 Lockdown in Ireland: A ‘Natural Experiment’ Allowing Analysis of Data From the Prior Two Decades,” BMJ Global Health 5, no. 9 (2020): e003075.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Simon, S. John, S. Lisonkova, et al., “Obstetric Intervention and Perinatal Outcomes During the Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID‐19) Pandemic,” Obstetrics &amp; Gynecology 142, no. 6 (2023): 1405–1415.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. C. Guarnizo‐Herreño, G. Buitrago, and G. L. Wehby, “Changes in Birth Outcomes and Utilization of Prenatal Care During the COVID‐19 Pandemic in 2020: A Secondary Analysis of Vital Statistics in Colombia,” BMC Pediatrics 23, no. 1 (2023): 234.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Center for Health Statistics, “Percentage of Having a Doctor Visit for Any Reason in the Past 12 Months for Adults Aged 18 and Over, United States, 2019—2021,” 2023, (National Health Interview Survey. Centers for Disease Prevention and Control), https://wwwn.cdc.gov/NHISDataQueryTool/SHS_adult/index.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. Lyu and G. L. Wehby, “Children's Oral Health and Oral Health Care Use During the First 2 Years of the COVID‐19 Pandemic,” Journal of the American Dental Association 154, no. 10 (2023): 930–936.e7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. Lyu and G. L. Wehby, “Changes in Children's Health Care Access and Utilization in the United States in the First 2 Years of the COVID‐19 Pandemic,” Academic Pediatrics 23, no. 8 (2023): 1572–1578.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Lisonkova and K. S. Joseph, “Why Did Preterm Birth Rates Fall During the COVID‐19 Pandemic?,” Paediatric and Perinatal Epidemiology 37, no. 2 (2023): 113–116.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>