<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39400154</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2165-0497</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>14</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Microbiology spectrum</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Microbiol Spectr</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Direct genome sequencing of respiratory viruses from low viral load clinical specimens using the target capture sequencing technology.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e0098624</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e0098624</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1128/spectrum.00986-24</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The use of metagenomic next-generation sequencing technology to obtain complete viral genome sequences directly from clinical samples with low viral load remains challenging-especially in the case of respiratory viruses-due to the low copy number of viral versus host genomes. To overcome this limitation, target capture sequencing for the enrichment of specific genomes has been developed and applied for direct genome sequencing of viruses. However, as the efficiency of enrichment varies depending on the probes, the type of clinical sample, etc., validation is essential before target capture sequencing can be applied to clinical diagnostics. In this study, we evaluated the utility of target capture sequencing with a comprehensive viral probe panel for clinical respiratory specimens collected from patients diagnosed with SARS-CoV-2 or influenza type A. We focused on clinical specimens containing low copy numbers of viral genomes. Target capture sequencing yielded approximately 180- and 2,000-fold higher read counts of SARS-CoV-2 and influenza A virus, respectively, than metagenomic sequencing when the RNA extracted from specimens contained 59.3 copies/µL of SARS-CoV-2 or 625.1 copies/µL of influenza A virus. In addition, the target capture sequencing identified sequence reads in all SARS-CoV-2- or influenza type A-positive specimens with &lt;26 RNA copies/µL, some of which also yielded &gt;70% of the full-length genomes of SARS-CoV-2 or influenza A virus. Furthermore, the target capture sequencing using comprehensive probes identified co-infections with viruses other than SARS-CoV-2, suggesting that this approach will not only detect a wide range of viruses but also contribute to epidemiological studies.IMPORTANCETarget capture sequencing has been developed and applied for direct genome sequencing of viruses in clinical specimens to overcome the low detection sensitivity of metagenomic next-generation sequencing. In this study, we evaluated the utility of target capture sequencing with a comprehensive viral probe panel for clinical respiratory specimens collected from patients diagnosed with SARS-CoV-2 or influenza type A, focusing on clinical specimens containing low copy numbers of viral genomes. Our results showed that the target capture sequencing yielded dramatically higher read counts than metagenomic sequencing for both viruses. Furthermore, the target capture sequencing using comprehensive probes identified co-infections with other viruses, suggesting that this approach will not only detect a wide range of viruses but also contribute to epidemiological studies.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Takemae</LastName><ForeName>Nobuhiro</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5152-8938</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Emergency Preparedness and Response, National Institute of Infectious Diseases, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Kuba</LastName><ForeName>Yumani</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Emergency Preparedness and Response, National Institute of Infectious Diseases, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Oba</LastName><ForeName>Kunihiro</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Showa General Hospital, Kodaira, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kageyama</LastName><ForeName>Tsutomu</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0000-1829-5124</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Emergency Preparedness and Response, National Institute of Infectious Diseases, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Microbiol Spectr</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101634614</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2165-0497</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">direct genome sequencing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">influenza A virus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">next-generation sequencing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">respiratory virus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">target capture sequencing</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39400154</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/spectrum.00986-24</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>