<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39400473</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2192-2659</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>14</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Advanced healthcare materials</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Adv Healthc Mater</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Protein Nanoparticles for Targeted SARS-CoV-2 Trapping and Neutralization.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e2402744</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e2402744</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/adhm.202402744</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic, caused by the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), continues to challenge global health despite widespread vaccination efforts, underscoring the need for innovative strategies to combat emerging infectious diseases effectively. Herein, LCB1-NPs and LCB3-NPs are engineered as a novel class of protein-only nanoparticles formed through coiled coil-driven self-assembly and tailored to interact specifically with the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein. The multivalency of LCB1-NPs and LCB3-NPs offers a strategy for efficiently targeting and neutralizing SARS-CoV-2 both in solution and when immobilized on surfaces. It is demonstrated that LCB1-NPs and LCB3-NPs bind to the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein's receptor-binding domain (RBD) with high affinity, effectively blocking the entry of SARS-CoV-2 virus-like particles into angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2)-coated human cells. The cost-effectiveness, scalability, and straightforward production process of these protein nanoparticles make them suitable for developing novel anti-viral materials. Accordingly, it is shown how these nanostructures can be packed into columns to build up economic and highly potent trapping devices for SARS-CoV-2 adsorption.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Advanced Healthcare Materials published by Wiley‐VCH GmbH.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fornt-Suñé</LastName><ForeName>Marc</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1197-2836</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institut de Biotecnologia i de Biomedicina (IBB), Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona, Bellaterra, 08193, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Departament de Bioquímica i Biologia Molecular, Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona, Bellaterra, 08193, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Puertas</LastName><ForeName>Maria C</ForeName><Initials>MC</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6750-2318</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>IrsiCaixa, Badalona, 08916, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Germans Trias i Pujol Research Institute (IGTP), Badalona, 08916, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biomedical Research Networking Center on Infectious Diseases (CIBERINFEC), Madrid, 28029, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Martinez-Picado</LastName><ForeName>Javier</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4916-2129</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>IrsiCaixa, Badalona, 08916, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Germans Trias i Pujol Research Institute (IGTP), Badalona, 08916, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biomedical Research Networking Center on Infectious Diseases (CIBERINFEC), Madrid, 28029, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Infectious Diseases and Immunity Department, University of Vic-Central University of Catalonia, Vic (UVic-UCC), Vic, 08500, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Catalan Institution for Research and Advanced Studies (ICREA), Barcelona, 08010, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>García-Pardo</LastName><ForeName>Javier</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9179-6371</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institut de Biotecnologia i de Biomedicina (IBB), Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona, Bellaterra, 08193, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Departament de Bioquímica i Biologia Molecular, Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona, Bellaterra, 08193, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ventura</LastName><ForeName>Salvador</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9652-6351</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institut de Biotecnologia i de Biomedicina (IBB), Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona, Bellaterra, 08193, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Departament de Bioquímica i Biologia Molecular, Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona, Bellaterra, 08193, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Catalan Institution for Research and Advanced Studies (ICREA), Barcelona, 08010, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institut d'Investigació i Innovació Parc Taulí (I3PT CERCA), Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona, Sabadell, 08208, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>PID2022-137963OB-I00</GrantID><Agency>Spanish Ministry of Science and Innovation</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>FPU20/02897</GrantID><Agency>Spanish Ministry of Science and Innovation</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>IJC2019-041039-I</GrantID><Agency>Spanish Ministry of Science and Innovation</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>PID2022-139271OB-I00</GrantID><Agency>Spanish Ministry of Science and Innovation</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>CB21/13/00063</GrantID><Agency>Spanish Ministry of Science and Innovation</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>202120-30-31-32</GrantID><Agency>Fundació la Marató de TV3</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Adv Healthc Mater</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101581613</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2192-2640</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS‐CoV‐2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS‐CoV‐2 trapping</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antiviral nanomaterials</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">coiled coil protein nanoparticles</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">viral neutralization</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>54</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39400473</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/adhm.202402744</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>“COVID‐19 deaths | WHO COVID‐19 dashboard,”, can be found under https://data.who.int/dashboards/covid19/cases.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Hu, H. Guo, P. Zhou, Z.‐L. Shi, Nat. Rev. Microbiol. 2021, 19, 141.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID‐19 Mental Disorders Collaborators, Lancet 2021, 398, 1700.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. M. Altmann, E. M. Whettlock, S. Liu, D. J. Arachchillage, R. J. Boyton, Nat. Rev. Immunol. 2023, 23, 618.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. D. Kaye, C. N. Okeagu, A. D. Pham, R. A. Silva, J. J. Hurley, B. L. Arron, N. Sarfraz, H. N. Lee, G. E. Ghali, J. W. Gamble, H. Liu, R. D. Urman, E. M. Cornett, Best Pract. Res. Clin. Anaesthesiol. 2021, 35, 293.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. H. Barouch, N. Engl. J. Med. 2022, 387, 1011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. S. Byun, S. W. Heo, G. Jo, J. W. Kim, S. Kim, S. Lee, H. E. Park, J.‐H. Baek, Environ. Res. 2021, 196, 110972.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>“Tracking SARS‐CoV‐2 variants,”, can be found under https://www.who.int/activities/tracking‐SARS‐CoV‐2‐variants.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. V. Markov, M. Ghafari, M. Beer, K. Lythgoe, P. Simmonds, N. I. Stilianakis, A. Katzourakis, Nat. Rev. Microbiol. 2023, 21, 361.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. A. Jamison, S. Anand Narayanan, N. S. Trovão, J. W. Guarnieri, M. J. Topper, P. M. Moraes‐Vieira, V. Zaksas, K. K. Singh, E. S. Wurtele, A. Beheshti, Eur. J. Hum. Genet. EJHG 2022, 30, 889.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. B. Jackson, M. Farzan, B. Chen, H. Choe, Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol. 2022, 23, 3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Hoffmann, H. Kleine‐Weber, S. Schroeder, N. Krüger, T. Herrler, S. Erichsen, T. S. Schiergens, G. Herrler, N.‐H. Wu, A. Nitsche, M. A. Müller, C. Drosten, S. Pöhlmann, Cell 2020, 181, 271.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Ou, Y. Liu, X. Lei, P. Li, D. Mi, L. Ren, L. Guo, R. Guo, T. Chen, J. Hu, Z. Xiang, Z. Mu, X. Chen, J. Chen, K. Hu, Q. Jin, J. Wang, Z. Qian, Nat. Commun. 2020, 11, 1620.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Letko, A. Marzi, V. Munster, Nat. Microbiol. 2020, 5, 562.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. H. Ahn, J. Kim, S. P. Hong, S. Y. Choi, M. J. Yang, Y. S. Ju, Y. T. Kim, H. M. Kim, M. T. Rahman, M. K. Chung, S. D. Hong, H. Bae, C.‐S. Lee, G. Y. Koh, J. Clin. Invest. 2021, 131, e148517.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Wang, Y. Wang, W. Luo, L. Huang, J. Xiao, F. Li, S. Qin, X. Song, Y. Wu, Q. Zeng, F. Jin, Y. Wang, Int. J. Med. Sci. 2020, 17, 1522.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Zou, K. Chen, J. Zou, P. Han, J. Hao, Z. Han, Front. Med. 2020, 14, 185.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Liu, X. Long, B. Zhang, W. Zhang, X. Chen, Z. Zhang, Clin. Gastroenterol. Hepatol. Off. Clin. Pract. J. Am. Gastroenterol. Assoc. 2020, 18, 2128.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Chen, X. Zhao, H. Zhou, H. Zhu, S. Jiang, P. Wang, Nat. Rev. Immunol. 2023, 23, 189.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Bhattacharya, S. Chatterjee, S.‐S. Lee, C. Chakraborty, Int. J. Biol. Macromol. 2023, 229, 70.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Q. Zhang, A. Honko, J. Zhou, H. Gong, S. N. Downs, J. H. Vasquez, R. H. Fang, W. Gao, A. Griffiths, L. Zhang, Nano Lett. 2020, 20, 5570.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Mali, G. Franci, C. Zannella, A. Chianese, S. Anthiya, A. M. López‐Estévez, A. Monti, A. De Filippis, N. Doti, M. J. Alonso, M. Galdiero, Pharmaceutics 2023, 15, 1621.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Guo, W. Song, Y. Dong, X. Wang, G. Nie, F. Li, Nano Lett. 2024, 24, 3614.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Sun, S. Liu, T. Song, F. Chen, J. Zhang, J.‐A. Huang, S. Wan, Y. Lu, H. Chen, W. Tan, Y. Song, C. Yang, J. Am. Chem. Soc. 2021, 143, 21541.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Zhang, Y. Xu, Y. Huang, M. Sun, S. Liu, S. Wan, H. Chen, C. Yang, Y. Yang, Y. Song, J. Am. Chem. Soc. 2022, 144, 13146.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. D. D. P. de Moraes Segundo, J. S. F. Constantino, G. B. Calais, C. F. de Moura Junior, M. O. S. de Moraes, J. H. L. da Fonseca, J. Tsukamoto, R. R. D. C. Monteiro, F. K. Andrade, M. A. d'vila, C. W. Arns, M. M. Beppu, R. S. Vieira, Polymers 2022, 14, 4157.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. T. Lam, T. S. Babra, J. H. D. Smith, M. C. Bagley, J. Spencer, E. Wright, B. W. Greenland, Polymers 2022, 14, 4172.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W. Ahmed, A. H. Al‐Marzouqi, M. H. Nazir, T. A. Rizvi, E. Zaneldin, M. Khan, Int. J. Mol. Sci. 2022, 23, 11235.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Gil‐Garcia, S. Ventura, Acta Biomater. 2021, 131, 472.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Gil‐Garcia, S. Navarro, S. Ventura, Microb. Cell Fact. 2020, 19, 117.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Ebersbach, E. Galli, J. Møller‐Jensen, J. Löwe, K. Gerdes, Mol. Microbiol. 2008, 68, 720.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Fornt‐Suñé, G. L. Bermejo, M. Gil‐Garcia, A. Aran, J. Garcia‐Pardo, M. Martí, S. Ventura, ACS Appl. Nano Mater. 2024, 7, 6669.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Cao, B. Coventry, I. Goreshnik, B. Huang, W. Sheffler, J. S. Park, K. M. Jude, I. Markovic, R. U. Kadam, K. H. G. Verschueren, K. Verstraete, S. T. R. Walsh, N. Bennett, A. Phal, A. Yang, L. Kozodoy, M. DeWitt, L. Picton, L. Miller, E.‐M. Strauch, N. D. DeBouver, A. Pires, A. K. Bera, S. Halabiya, B. Hammerson, W. Yang, S. Bernard, L. Stewart, I. A. Wilson, H. Ruohola‐Baker, et al., Nature 2022, 605, 551.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Cao, I. Goreshnik, B. Coventry, J. B. Case, L. Miller, L. Kozodoy, R. E. Chen, L. Carter, A. C. Walls, Y.‐J. Park, E.‐M. Strauch, L. Stewart, M. S. Diamond, D. Veesler, D. Baker, Science 2020, 370, 426.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. B. Case, R. E. Chen, L. Cao, B. Ying, E. S. Winkler, M. Johnson, I. Goreshnik, M. N. Pham, S. Shrihari, N. M. Kafai, A. L. Bailey, X. Xie, P.‐Y. Shi, R. Ravichandran, L. Carter, L. Stewart, D. Baker, M. S. Diamond, Cell Host Microbe 2021, 29, 1151.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Gil‐Garcia, S. Ventura, Front. Bioeng. Biotechnol. 2021, 9, 734068.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Behbahanipour, R. Benoit, S. Navarro, S. Ventura, ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces 2023, 15, 11444.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Alves, L. Engel, R. de Vasconcelos Cabral, E. L. Rodrigues, L. de Jesus Ribeiro, L. M. Higa, O. da Costa Ferreira Júnior, T. M. P. P. Castiñeiras, I. de Carvalho Leitão, A. Tanuri, S. A. Goueli, H. Zegzouti, Sci. Rep. 2021, 11, 18428.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Kallem, H. Hegab, H. Alsafar, S. W. Hasan, F. Banat, Emerg. Microbes Infect. 2023, 12, 2222850.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K.‐H. Chan, S. Sridhar, R. R. Zhang, H. Chu, A. Y.‐F. Fung, G. Chan, J. F.‐W. Chan, K. K.‐W. To, I. F.‐N. Hung, V. C.‐C. Cheng, K.‐Y. Yuen, J. Hosp. Infect. 2020, 106, 226.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Forés, S. Bofill‐Mas, M. Itarte, S. Martínez‐Puchol, A. Hundesa, M. Calvo, C. M. Borrego, L. L. Corominas, R. Girones, M. Rusiñol, Sci. Total Environ. 2021, 768, 144786.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Isaka, T. Yoshiya, C. Ono, A. Uchiyama, H. Hirata, S. Hamaguchi, S. Kutsuna, Y. Takabatake, R. Saita, T. Yamada, A. Takahashi, M. Yamato, Y. Nohara, S. Tsuda, I. Anzai, T. Kimura, Y. Takeda, K. Tomono, Y. Matsuura, Clin. Exp. Nephrol. 2023, 27, 279.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. L. Watson, D. Juergens, N. R. Bennett, B. L. Trippe, J. Yim, H. E. Eisenach, W. Ahern, A. J. Borst, R. J. Ragotte, L. F. Milles, B. I. M. Wicky, N. Hanikel, S. J. Pellock, A. Courbet, W. Sheffler, J. Wang, P. Venkatesh, I. Sappington, S. V. Torres, A. Lauko, V. De Bortoli, E. Mathieu, S. Ovchinnikov, R. Barzilay, T. S. Jaakkola, F. DiMaio, M. Baek, D. Baker, Nature 2023, 620, 1089.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Vázquez Torres, P. J. Y. Leung, P. Venkatesh, I. D. Lutz, F. Hink, H.‐H. Huynh, J. Becker, A. H.‐W. Yeh, D. Juergens, N. R. Bennett, A. N. Hoofnagle, E. Huang, M. J. MacCoss, M. Expòsit, G. R. Lee, A. K. Bera, A. Kang, J. De La Cruz, P. M. Levine, X. Li, M. Lamb, S. R. Gerben, A. Murray, P. Heine, E. N. Korkmaz, J. Nivala, L. Stewart, J. L. Watson, J. M. Rogers, D. Baker, Nature 2024, 626, 435.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. A. Schneider, W. S. Rasband, K. W. Eliceiri, Nat. Methods 2012, 9, 671.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. M. Corman, O. Landt, M. Kaiser, R. Molenkamp, A. Meijer, D. K. Chu, T. Bleicker, S. Brünink, J. Schneider, M. L. Schmidt, D. G. Mulders, B. L. Haagmans, B. Vander Veer, S. Van der Brink, L. Wijsman, G. Goderski, J.‐L. Romette, J. Ellis, M. Zambon, M. Peiris, H. Goossens, C. Reusken, M. P. Koopmans, C. Drosten, Eurosurveillance 2020, 25, 2000045.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Scotti, 2013, http://doi.org/10.13140/2.1.4777.1209.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>