<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39401157</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1668-3501</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>17</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Archivos argentinos de pediatria</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Arch Argent Pediatr</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Massive pulmonary thromboembolism in an adolescent with SARS-CoV-2 infection.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e202410474</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e202410474</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.5546/aap.2024-10474.eng</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Thromboembolic events incidence is low in pediatrics; high suspicion and explicit management algorithms are essential. We present a 12-year-old female patient with two weeks of dyspnea, orthopnea, and ankle edema. Tests showed metabolic acidosis, hyperlactatemia, elevated D-dimer, and positive SARS-CoV-2 CRP. The echocardiogram showed severe right ventricular dysfunction and supra-systemic pulmonary hypertension. Chest CT angiography showed extensive bilateral pulmonary thromboembolism. Anticoagulant therapy was started. She presented with hemodynamic instability. Adrenaline, norepinephrine, milrinone, and nitric oxide were started. The clinical picture was extremely severe in the first 24 hours. It was decided to perform systemic thrombolysis with alteplase, which led to an improvement. Cardiorespiratory stabilization and anticoagulation are the mainstays of therapy in massive pulmonary thromboembolism. Fibrinolytic therapy is used in selected high-risk cases. In this patient, systemic reperfusion therapy with alteplase was performed with no significant complications.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Sociedad Argentina de Pediatría.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chauriye Kuncar</LastName><ForeName>Verónica</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6954-0983</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Critical Patient Unit, Hospital Luis Calvo Mackenna, Santiago, Chile. ´.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Castillo Acevedo</LastName><ForeName>Cecilia</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Critical Patient Unit, Hospital Luis Calvo Mackenna, Santiago, Chile. ´.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Acuña Aguirre</LastName><ForeName>Carlos</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Critical Patient Unit, Hospital Luis Calvo Mackenna, Santiago, Chile. ´.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Díaz Espejo</LastName><ForeName>Piaignacia</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatric Critical Patient Unit, Hospital Luis Calvo Mackenna, Santiago, Chile. ´.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><Language>spa</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D002363">Case Reports</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><VernacularTitle>Tromboembolismo pulmonar masivo en adolescente con infección por SARS–CoV-2.</VernacularTitle><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Argentina</Country><MedlineTA>Arch Argent Pediatr</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0372460</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0325-0075</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="spa"><AbstractText>La incidencia de eventos tromboembólicos es baja en pediatría; es importante la alta sospecha y algoritmos claros de manejo. Presentamos una paciente de 12 años, con 2 semanas de disnea, ortopnea y edema de tobillos. Exámenes evidenciaron acidosis metabólica, hiperlactatemia, dímero D elevado y PCR SARS-CoV-2 positiva. Ecocardiograma con disfunción grave de ventrículo derecho e hipertensión pulmonar suprasistémica. Angio-TAC de tórax mostró extenso tromboembolismo pulmonar bilateral. Se inició terapia anticoagulante. Evolucionó con inestabilidad hemodinámica. Inició adrenalina, norepinefrina, milrinona y óxido nítrico. Primeras 24 horas de extrema gravedad. Se decidió realización de trombólisis sistémica con alteplasa, y evolucionó con progresión a la mejoría. Los pilares de terapia en tromboembolismo pulmonar (TEP) masivo son la estabilización cardiorrespiratoria y la anticoagulación. En casos seleccionados como de alto riesgo, se utiliza terapia fibrinolítica. En esta paciente, se realizó terapia de reperfusión sistémica con alteplasa, sin complicaciones de importancia en el procedimiento.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Sociedad Argentina de Pediatría.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">multiorgan failure</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pulmonary embolism</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">thrombolytic therapy</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39401157</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5546/aap.2024-10474.eng</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>