<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39404662</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1461-4448</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Mar</Month><Day>15</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>New media &amp; society</Title><ISOAbbreviation>New Media Soc</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>'Conspiracy theories should be called spoiler alerts': Conspiracy, Coronavirus, and affective community on Russell Brand's YouTube Comment Section.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>14614448241237489</StartPage><MedlinePgn>14614448241237489</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">14614448241237489</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1177/14614448241237489</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>This paper examines how conspiracy theories anchor affective communities through an analysis of the YouTube comment section for the actor and comedian turned political influencer Russell Brand. Comparing videos before and after Brand's shift to covid scepticism, I explore like counts, reply networks, and other commenting patterns in a dataset of 217,157 comments and conduct an in-depth analysis of 2000 top comments. The findings show first, a shift toward right-wing viewpoints; second, a reduction in comment length and comment replies alongside an increase in likes; third, a sharp rise in proclamations of Brand fandom; and fourth, a steep increase in references to conspiracy. The in-depth analysis reveals that comments focused not on narrating the content of conspiracies but on celebrating conspiracy as the basis of a political community and as a defence against accusations of paranoia. I argue that conspiracy theories can function as formal categories that anchor affective communities.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Birkbeck</LastName><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of London, UK.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/04cw6st05</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>15</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>New Media Soc</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101677185</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1461-4448</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Affect</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Comment section</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Conspiracy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Coronavirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Ideology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Micro-celebrity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Paranoid style</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Politics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Social media</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">YouTube</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39404662</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="mid">EMS196782</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7616556</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/14614448241237489</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Argentino MA. Pastel QAnon. GNET. 2021. Mar 17,  [accessed 2 March 2023].  Available at:  https://gnet-research.org/2021/03/17/pastel-qanon/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barkun M. A Culture of Conspiracy: Apocalyptic Visions in Contemporary America. University of California Press; Berkeley: 2013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Belew K. Bring the War Home: The White Power Movement in Paramilitary America. Harvard University Press; Boston: 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Birchall C, Knight P. Conspiracy Theories in the Time of Covid-19. Routledge; London: 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Birchall C, Knight P. Do your own research: conspiracy theories and the internet. Social Research. 2022;89:579–605.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bloom M, Moskalenko S. Pastels and Pedophiles: Inside the Mind of QAnon. Stanford University Press; Stanford: 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burgess J, Green J. YouTube: Online Video and Participatory Culture. 2nd. Wiley; New York: 2018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chadwick A, Kaiser J, Vaccari C, Freeman D, Lambe S, Loe BS, Vanderslott S, Lewandowsky S, Conroy M, Ross ARN, Innocenti S, et al. Online social endorsement and Covid-19 vaccine hesitancy in the United Kingdom. Social Media + Society. 2021;7(2) doi: 10.1177/20563051211008817.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/20563051211008817</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Charmaz K. Constructing grounded theory. SAGE; London: 2006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chun WHK. Discriminating Data: Correlation, Neighborhoods, and the New Politics of Recognition. MIT Press; Boston: 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daniels J. Cyber Racism: White Supremacy Online and the New Attack on Civil Rights. Rowman and Littlefield; New York: 2009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Michallon C. Russell Brand is the new Joe Rogan – and I’m the one he warned you about. The Independent. 2022. Mar 14,  [accessed 17 February 2023].  Available at:  https://www.independent.co.uk/author/clemence-michallon.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Callison W, Slobodian Q. Coronapolitics from the Reichstag to the Capitol. Boston. 2021.  [accessed 18 January 2023].  Review, 12 Janaury. Available at:  https://bostonreview.net/politics/william-callison-quinn-slobodian-coronapolitics-reichstag-capitol.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edelman L. On solidarity. Representations. 2022;158:93–105.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fenster M. Conspiracy Theories: Secrecy and Power in American Culture. 2nd. University of Minnesota Press; Minneapolis: 2008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Finlayson A. YouTube and political Ideologies: technology, populism and rhetorical form. Political Studies. 2022;(70):62–80.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ganesh B. Weaponizing white thymos: flows of rage in the online audiences of the alt-right. Cultural Studies. 2020;(34):892–924.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gray J, Sandvoss C, Harrington CL. Fandom: Identities and Communities in a Mediated World 2nd. NYU Press; New York: 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hofstadter R. The paranoid style in American politics.  [accessed 18 February 2023];Harper’s Magazine. 1964 November; Available at:  https://harpers.org/archive/1964/11/the-paranoid-style-in-american-politics/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chilton L. How did Russell Brand go from stand-up stardom to peddling YouTube conspiracy theories?  [accessed 27 January 2023];The Independent. 2022 March 25; Available at:  https://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/tv/features/russell-brand-youtube-conspiracy-theories-b2043777.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kellner D. Trump, authoritarian populism, and COVID-19 from a US Perspective. Cultural Politics. 2021;(17):28–36.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kelly A. QAnon and on: An ever-evolving conspiracy theory built on denial. Sociological Review. 2022. May 10,  [accessed 23 February 2023].  Available at:  https://thesociologicalreview.org/magazine/may-2022/belief/qanon-and-on/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laclau E. Emancipation(s) Verso; New York: 1996.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lewis R. ‘This is what the news won’t show you’: YouTube creators and the reactionary politics of micro-celebrity. Television &amp; New Media. 2020;(21):201–217.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marres N. Why we can’t have our facts back. Engaging Science, Technology, and Society. 2018;(4):423–443.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McKenzie-McHarg A. From status politics to the paranoid style: Richard Hofstadter and the pitfalls of psychologizing history. Journal of the History of Ideas. 2022;(83):451–475.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35815515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mudde C. Populist radical right parties in Europe. Cambridge University Press; Cambridge: 2007.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munger K, Phillips J. Right-wing YouTube: a supply and demand perspective. The International Journal of Press/Politics. 2022;(27):186–219.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murthy D, Sharma S. Visualizing YouTube’s comment space: online hostility as a networked phenomena. New Media &amp; Society. 2019;(21):191–213.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenblum N, Muirhead R. A Lot of People Are Saying: The New Conspiracism and the Assault on Democracy. Princeton University Press; Princeton: 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olmsted K. A conspiracy so dense: the dubious half-life of Richard Hofstadter’s ‘paranoid style’.  [accessed 16 February 2023];The Baffler. 2018 November; Available at:  https://thebaffler.com/salvos/a-conspiracy-so-dense-olmsted.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pertwee E, Simas C, Larson HJ. An epidemic of uncertainty: rumors, conspiracy theories and vaccine hesitancy. Nature Medicine. 2022;(28):456–459.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35273403</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phillips W. This Is Why We Can’t Have Nice Things: Mapping the Relationship Between Online Trolling and Mainstream Culture. MIT Press; Boston: 2015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rampin R, Rampin V. Taguette: open-source qualitative data analysis. Journal of Open Source Software. 2021;6(68):3522. doi: 10.21105/joss.03522.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21105/joss.03522</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ribuffo L. Donald Trump and the ‘paranoid style’ in American (intellectual) politics. The Robert Jervis International Security Studies Forum. 2017. Jun 13,  [accessed 16 February 2023].  Available at:  https://issforum.org/policy/1-5an-paranoid.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rieder B. YouTube Data Tools (Version 130) 2015.  [Software]. Available from:  https://tools.digitalmethods.net/netvizz/youtube/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rogers R. Digital Methods. MIT Press; Boston: 2013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rothut S, Schulze H, Hohner J, Rieger D. Ambassadors of ideology: A conceptualization and computational investigation of far-right influencers, their networking structures, and communication practices. New Media &amp; Society. 2023 doi: 10.1177/14614448231164409. 0(0)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/14614448231164409</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sedgwick EK. Touching Feeling: Affect, Pedagogy, Performativity. Duke University Press; Durham: 2003.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thompson N. Russell Brand, Fox’s Sean Hannity trade barbs over Israel-Hamas conflict. CNN. 2014. Aug 4,  [accessed 17 February 2023].  Available at:  https://www.cnn.com/2014/08/04/world/meast/russell-brand-sean-hannity-israel-hamas/index.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tuters M, Willaert T. Deep state phobia: Narrative convergence in coronavirus conspiracism on Instagram. Convergence. 2022;(28):1214–1238.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venturini T. Online Conspiracy Theories, Digital Platforms and Secondary Orality: Toward a Sociology of Online Monsters. Theory, Culture &amp; Society. 2022;(39):61–80.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wondreys J, Mudde C. Victims of the pandemic? European far-right parties and COVID-19. Nationalities Papers. 2022;(50):86–103.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>