<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39414013</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1525-3198</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>14</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of dairy science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Dairy Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Herd-level occurrence and risk factors associated with respiratory and enteric pathogens from dairy calves in Ontario: A cross-sectional study.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0022-0302(24)01220-7</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3168/jds.2024-25199</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>This cross-sectional herd-level study aimed to determine the occurrence of and risk factors for pathogens associated with neonatal calf diarrhea and bovine respiratory disease on Ontario dairy farms. From April to August 2022, a convenience sample of 100 dairy farms were visited once. A questionnaire covering farm biosecurity, calving and colostrum management, preweaning nutrition, and housing was administered on-farm. At each farm visit, approximately 5 calves between 2 and 35 d old were randomly selected for fecal sampling. Furthermore, approximately 5 calves between 21 to 122 d old were randomly selected for nasopharyngeal sampling. In total, 363 fecal samples (from 83 dairy farms) and 390 nasopharyngeal swab samples (from 80 dairy farms) were collected. Fecal samples were analyzed individually using a multiplex PCR to identify bacterial and parasitic enteric pathogens. Nasopharyngeal swabs were analyzed as one pooled sample per farm using bacterial culture and real-time PCR. The most common enteric pathogens detected at herd-level were Cryptosporidium parvum (67.4%) and Escherichia coli K99+ (13.2%). The most common respiratory pathogens detected at herd-level were Pasteurella multocida (62.5%), bovine coronavirus (42.5%), and Mycoplasma bovis (21.2%). Multivariable logistic models were built to explore associations between the most common pathogens and herd-level predictors selected from the questionnaire. Herd positivity for C. parvum was positively associated with having more than 61 preweaned calves per year and feeding mainly whole milk to calves. The presence of M. bovis was positively associated with herds that combined manual and automatic milk-feeding systems, and the presence of bovine coronavirus was positively associated with having more than 98 preweaned calves during the year. Univariable Poisson regression models were built to explore the association between the most common pathogens and preweaning calf mortality. Herds that were positive for C. parvum, M. bovis, or bovine coronavirus had a greater risk of preweaning calf mortality. These results provide insights for future research on pathogens associated with NCD and BRD and offer guidance for veterinarians and dairy farmers in implementing disease control measures in dairy calf herds.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2025, The Authors. Published by Elsevier Inc. on behalf of the American Dairy Science Association®. This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sedó</LastName><ForeName>S G Umaña</ForeName><Initials>SGU</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Population Medicine, University of Guelph, Ontario, N1G2W1, Canada; Department of Large Animal Clinical Sciences, Virginia-Maryland College of Veterinary Medicine, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, VA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Winder</LastName><ForeName>C B</ForeName><Initials>CB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Population Medicine, University of Guelph, Ontario, N1G2W1, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Perry</LastName><ForeName>K V</ForeName><Initials>KV</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Population Medicine, University of Guelph, Ontario, N1G2W1, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Caswell</LastName><ForeName>J L</ForeName><Initials>JL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathobiology, University of Guelph, Ontario, N1G2W1, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mee</LastName><ForeName>J F</ForeName><Initials>JF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Teagasc, Moorepark Research Centre, Fermoy Co. Cork, P61 C997, Ireland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>MacNicol</LastName><ForeName>J</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Animal Sciences, University of Guelph, Ontario, N1G2W1, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Renaud</LastName><ForeName>D L</ForeName><Initials>DL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Population Medicine, University of Guelph, Ontario, N1G2W1, Canada. Electronic address: renaudd@uoguelph.ca.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Dairy Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>2985126R</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-0302</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">dairy youngstock</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">diarrhea</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pneumonia</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">surveillance</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39414013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3168/jds.2024-25199</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0022-0302(24)01220-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>