<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39419614</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2044-6055</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>14</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>17</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMJ open</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMJ Open</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Influence of social media and the digital environment on international migration of health workforce from low- and middle-income countries post COVID-19 pandemic: a scoping review protocol.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e087213</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e087213</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e087213</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1136/bmjopen-2024-087213</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Migration of the health workforce from low- and middle-income countries (LMCIs) is increasingly becoming a phenomenon of interest within migration governance systems. The COVID-19 pandemic aggravated health workforce shortages that have created job opportunities in high-income countries such as the USA, UK, Canada and Germany among others. Conditions of service in LMCIs are unattractive, leading to the search for better opportunities. The digital environment is becoming one of the facilitators of migration intentions due to the activities of recruitment agencies and the search for job opportunities on the World Wide Web. The digital environment creates opportunities for migration but also poses a security threat, economic loss and a brain drain to departure countries. However, there is a paucity of evidence on how the proliferation of advertisements on health workforce recruitment within social media, unsolicited emails and activities of recruitment agencies in the digital environment influence the migration of the health workforce and the implications of migration governance.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHOD AND ANALYSIS" NlmCategory="METHODS">This scoping review protocol describes a comprehensive systematic extraction and examination of existing literature to map key concepts and identify previous literature, noting the gaps in how social media and the digital environment are influencing the migration of the health workforce. We lean on Arksey and O'Malley's scoping framework in developing this protocol. This involves the following: identifying research questions, searching for the literature, selecting articles or studies, charting the data and organising and reporting the outcome of the review. The review question is informed by the population, concept and context framework, which details the population as the health workforce (doctors, nurses, midwives and pharmacists), the key concepts as migration, social media and digital environment, and the context as LMICs. The search strategy was developed with the assistance of an experienced librarian who will work with the team to conduct a Peer Review of Electronic Search Strategies to evaluate titles, abstracts and full-text articles for inclusion from databases such as Scopus, PubMed, MEDLINE and Google Scholar. Additionally, we will search grey literature sources including online news media, social media platforms (Facebook, Instagram and Twitter), web pages of WHO, UN and migration-related agencies, and interfaces like EBSCO host. Two members of the team will screen titles and abstracts, and all team members will screen full text for data extraction. Data from grey sources will be converted to transcripts, coded and grouped into themes and subthemes consistent with thematic analysis strategies. All authors will be involved in the synthesis of the data. We intend to follow Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses extension for Scoping Reviews guidelines in reporting the outcome of peer-review sources.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="ETHICS AND DISSEMINATION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">This is a scoping review protocol that addresses a subject of interest that poses no risk to individuals or groups. All the information will be retrieved from open sources only. The protocol was registered with the Open Science Framework registry (osf.oi/zan3q) to serve as an audit trail. Reports from the review will be published in peer-reviewed journals and presented at conferences.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© Author(s) (or their employer(s)) 2024. Re-use permitted under CC BY-NC. No commercial re-use. See rights and permissions. Published by BMJ.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dzansi</LastName><ForeName>Gladys</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6036-811X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Adult Health, University of Ghana, Legon, Ghana gdzansi@ug.edu.gh.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Academy of International Affairs, NRW, Bonn, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abdul-Mumim</LastName><ForeName>Amankwa</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Maternal and Child Health, University of Ghana, Accra, Greater Accra, Ghana.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Menkah</LastName><ForeName>William</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health, University of Ghana, Accra, Greater Accra, Ghana.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ametefe</LastName><ForeName>Vivian</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Maternal and Child Health, University of Ghana, Accra, Greater Accra, Ghana.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xatse</LastName><ForeName>Eugenia</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Mental Health, University of Ghana, Accra, Greater Accra, Ghana.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Azanku</LastName><ForeName>Believe Adzoa</ForeName><Initials>BA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Ghana School of Nursing and Midwifery, Accra, Greater Accra, Ghana.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMJ Open</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101552874</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2044-6055</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D061108" MajorTopicYN="Y">Social Media</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003906" MajorTopicYN="Y">Developing Countries</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004641" MajorTopicYN="Y">Emigration and Immigration</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006280" MajorTopicYN="Y">Health Workforce</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006282" MajorTopicYN="N">Health Personnel</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Health Workforce</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Nurses</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Social Media</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Competing interests: None declared.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>21</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39419614</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11487823</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2024-087213</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">bmjopen-2024-087213</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Malmberg G. International migration, immobility and development. 2021. Time and space in international migration; pp. 21–48.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palinkas LA. Global Climate Change, Population Displacement, and Public Health. Springer; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Haas H. A theory of migration: the aspirations-capabilities framework. Comp Migr Stud. 2021;9:8. doi: 10.1186/s40878-020-00210-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40878-020-00210-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7902564</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33680858</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McAuliffe M, Triandafyllidou A. 1 Report Overview: Technological, Geopolitical and Environmental Transformations Shaping Our Migration and Mobility Futures. World Migr Rep. 2022;2022:e00022. doi: 10.1002/wom3.22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/wom3.22</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Causa O. The post-covid-19 rise in labour shortages. 2022</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Makuku R, Mosadeghrad AM. Health workforce retention in low-income settings: an application of the Root Stem Model. J Public Health Policy. 2022;43:445–55. doi: 10.1057/s41271-022-00361-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1057/s41271-022-00361-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9385095</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35978036</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walton-Roberts M, Bourgeault IL. Health workforce data needed to minimize inequities associated with health-worker migration. Bull World Health Organ. 2024;102:117–22. doi: 10.2471/BLT.23.290028.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2471/BLT.23.290028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10835628</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38313146</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sumption M, Strain-Fajth Z. ReWage and Migration Observatory Evidence Paper, COMPAS. University of Oxford; 2023. Migration and the health and care workforce.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bakhshi M. CGFNS International Inc; 2023. CGFNS 2023 nurse migration report: navigating nursing shortages and immigration barriers.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kikkawa A, Justo CJ. LABOR MIGRATION IN ASIA; 2021. Sirivunnabood, migtech: how technology is reshaping labor mobility and the landscape of international migration.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robinson C. In: The New ‘UN Migration Agency’ in Critical Perspective. Geiger M, Pécoud A, editors. Springer International Publishing: Cham; 2020. Measuring ‘well-governed’ migration: the iom’s migration governance indicators, in the international organization for migration; pp. 123–43.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Obi C, Bartolini F, D’Haese M. International migration, remittance and food security during food crises: the case study of Nigeria. Food Sec. 2020;12:207–20. doi: 10.1007/s12571-019-00990-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12571-019-00990-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaffer FA, Bakhshi M, Cook K, et al. International Nurse Recruitment Beyond the COVID-19 Pandemic: Considerations for the Nursing Workforce Leader. Nurse Lead. 2022;20:161–7. doi: 10.1016/j.mnl.2021.12.001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.mnl.2021.12.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8850103</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35194412</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Preiss C. In: An Interactive Guide to the Literatures on Migration and Diversity. Scholten P, editor. International Publishing: Cham; 2022. Digital migration infrastructures, in introduction to migration studies; pp. 99–109.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dijstelbloem H, Broeders D. Border surveillance, mobility management and the shaping of non-publics in Europe. Eur J Soc Theory. 2015;18:21–38. doi: 10.1177/1368431014534353.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1368431014534353</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beyer A, Brekke JP, Thorbjørnsrud K. Communicating borders: informing migrants and potential asylum seekers through social media. Rapport-Institutt for samfunnsforskning. 2017 doi: 10.1093/migration/mny027.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/migration/mny027</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization . World Health Organization; 2022. Working for health 2022-2030 action plan.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peters MDJ, Godfrey CM, Khalil H, et al. Guidance for conducting systematic scoping reviews. Int J Evid Based Healthc. 2015;13:141–6. doi: 10.1097/XEB.0000000000000050.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/XEB.0000000000000050</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26134548</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arksey H, O’Malley L. Scoping studies: towards a methodological framework. Int J Soc Res Methodol. 2005;8:19–32. doi: 10.1080/1364557032000119616.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/1364557032000119616</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tricco AC, et al. PRISMA extension for scoping reviews (PRISMA-ScR): checklist and explanation. Ann Intern Med. 2018;169:467–73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30178033</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>JBI . South Australia, Australia: Joanna Briggs Institute; 2015. Joanna Briggs Institute reviewers’ manual: 2015 edition/supplement, in methodology for jbi scoping reviews.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Page MJ, McKenzie JE, Bossuyt PM, et al. The PRISMA 2020 statement: an updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews. BMJ. 2021;372:71. doi: 10.1136/bmj.n71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.n71</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8005924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33782057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>