<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39410877</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2573-8348</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>7</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cancer reports (Hoboken, N.J.)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cancer Rep (Hoboken)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Unusual Presentation of Metastatic Medullary Thyroid Cancer Involving Bone Marrow, Kidneys, and Adrenal Gland: A Literature Review Based on a Case Report.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70022</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70022</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e70022</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/cnr2.70022</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Medullary thyroid cancer (MTC) is one of the rare neuroendocrine malignancies. This cancer is hereditary in approximately 20% of cases. Although lymph node (LN) metastasis is prevalent in MTC, distant metastasis is not commonly seen in these patients. The most common locations for metastasis are the lungs, liver, and bones. This study presents an extremely rare MTC metastasis to bone marrow (BM) and adrenal gland, which has not been reported before.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CASE" NlmCategory="METHODS">The patient was a 50-year-old man with a diagnosis of MTC and total thyroidectomy 2 months before his presentation. He came to the emergency department (ED) complaining of dyspnea, diffuse bone pain, nonbloody diarrhea, and abdominal cramps starting in the last month before. Initial treatment with intravenous fluid infusion and loperamide, due to the provisional diagnosis of infectious diarrhea, was ineffective. Further assessments revealed severe pancytopenia and a massive tumor above the left kidney. Bone marrow aspiration (BMA) and biopsy (BMB) led to the diagnosis of invasive metastasis of the MTC to the BM and the left adrenal gland. In the initial evaluations, his COVID-19 test became positive, and despite all efforts, his condition deteriorated, and he died 5 days after admission due to respiratory distress.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Most MTC cases present with thyroid nodules in the initial steps and are confined to the thyroid gland or the adjacent LNs. These cases are mostly cured by thyroidectomy and LN dissection. This neuroendocrine cancer infrequently becomes aggressive and involves other parts of the body. However, involving BM or adrenal gland has been scarcely reported. Due to ineffective red and white blood cell production, BM metastasis can cause pancytopenia and, consequently, pallor, fatigue, dyspnea, and susceptibility to infections. High calcitonin levels can also cause diarrhea. The initial diagnosis is mostly with neck ultrasound (US) and fine needle aspiration (FNA). Total thyroidectomy is the main therapeutic option for these patients. Calcitonin and carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA) are sensitive indicators of recurrence or remaining tumors, which might be helpful for the initial diagnosis and postoperation follow-up. Although extremely rare, invasive metastasis of MTC might involve unusual body organs such as the BM or adrenal glands. In cases of unjustifiable pancytopenia or adrenal dysfunction in MTC-positive patients, these possibilities should be considered and ruled out by some specific evaluations, such as bone marrow biopsy and contrast-enhanced imaging.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Cancer Reports published by Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ebrahimi</LastName><ForeName>Pouya</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0005-3694-6863</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Tehran Heart Center, Cardiovascular Disease Research Institute, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Payab</LastName><ForeName>Moloud</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Non-Communicable Diseases Research Center, Endocrinology and Metabolism Population Sciences Institute, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shariati</LastName><ForeName>Alireza</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Shariati Hospital, School of Medicine, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alipour</LastName><ForeName>Neda</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Non-Communicable Diseases Research Center, Endocrinology and Metabolism Population Sciences Institute, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nozheh</LastName><ForeName>Aysan</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0007-8862-3008</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pathology Resident, Shariati Hospital, School of Medicine, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tavangar</LastName><ForeName>Seyed Mohammad</ForeName><Initials>SM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathology, Dr. Shariati Hospital, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Chronic Diseases Research Center, Endocrinology and Metabolism Population Sciences Institute, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Taheri</LastName><ForeName>Homa</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cedars-Sinai Cardiology Department, Los Angeles, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ebrahimpur</LastName><ForeName>Mahbube</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Endocrinology and Metabolism Research Center, Endocrinology and Metabolism Clinical Sciences Institute, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Elderly Health Research Center, Endocrinology and Metabolism Population Sciences Institute, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D002363">Case Reports</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cancer Rep (Hoboken)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101747728</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2573-8348</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><SupplMeshList><SupplMeshName Type="Disease" UI="C536914">Thyroid cancer, medullary</SupplMeshName></SupplMeshList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013964" MajorTopicYN="Y">Thyroid Neoplasms</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000473" MajorTopicYN="N">pathology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018278" MajorTopicYN="Y">Carcinoma, Neuroendocrine</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000556" MajorTopicYN="N">secondary</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000473" MajorTopicYN="N">pathology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000310" MajorTopicYN="Y">Adrenal Gland Neoplasms</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000556" MajorTopicYN="N">secondary</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000473" MajorTopicYN="N">pathology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007680" MajorTopicYN="N">Kidney Neoplasms</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000473" MajorTopicYN="N">pathology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001853" MajorTopicYN="N">Bone Marrow</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000473" MajorTopicYN="N">pathology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019046" MajorTopicYN="N">Bone Marrow Neoplasms</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000556" MajorTopicYN="N">secondary</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013965" MajorTopicYN="N">Thyroidectomy</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017809" MajorTopicYN="N">Fatal Outcome</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">adrenal gland</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">bone marrow</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">case report</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">medullary thyroid cancer</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">metastasis</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39410877</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11480645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/cnr2.70022</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Siegel R. L., Giaquinto A. N., and Jemal A., “Cancer Statistics, 2024,” CA: A Cancer Journal for Clinicians 74, no. 1 (2024): 12–49.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38230766</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taheri H., Ebrahimi P., Nazari P., Kefayat A., and Mahdavian A., “An Unusual Presentation of Metastatic Prostate Cancer in a 44‐Year‐Old Man: A Case Report and Review of the Literature,” Clinical Case Reports 12, no. 2 (2024): e8447.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10822781</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38292222</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caillé S., Debreuve‐Theresette A., Vitellius G., Deguelte S., La Manna L., and Zalzali M., “Medullary Thyroid Cancer: Epidemiology and Characteristics According to Data From the Marne–Ardennes Register 1975–2018,” Journal of the Endocrine Society 8, no. 6 (2024): bvae084.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11091837</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38745826</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang M., Hu D., Zeng W., et al., “New Proposed Tumor‐Node‐Metastasis Staging System for Medullary Thyroid Carcinoma Based on the Surveillance, Epidemiology, and end Results Database,” American Journal of Translational Research 12, no. 6 (2020): 2703–2710.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7344094</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32655802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Master S. R., Mathias P. M., and Burns B., “Medullary Thyroid Cancer,” in StatPearls (Treasure Island, FL: StatPearls Publishing, 2024), https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK459354/2023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29083765</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Angelousi A., Hayes A. R., Chatzellis E., Kaltsas G. A., and Grossman A. B., “Metastatic Medullary Thyroid Carcinoma: A New Way Forward,” Endocrine‐Related Cancer 29, no. 7 (2022): R85–R103.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9175549</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35521769</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gild M. L., Clifton‐Bligh R. J., Wirth L. J., and Robinson B. G., “Medullary Thyroid Cancer: Updates and Challenges,” Endocrine Reviews 44, no. 5 (2023): 934–946.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10656709</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37204852</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodríguez‐Bel L., Sabaté‐Llobera A., Rossi‐Seoane S., et al., “Diagnostic Accuracy of 18F‐FDG PET/CT in Patients With Biochemical Evidence of Recurrent, Residual, or Metastatic Medullary Thyroid Carcinoma,” Clinical Nuclear Medicine 44, no. 3 (2019): 194–200.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30562193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wells S. A., Asa S. L., Dralle H., et al., “Revised American Thyroid Association Guidelines for the Management of Medullary Thyroid Carcinoma,” Thyroid 25, no. 6 (2015): 567–610.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4490627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25810047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amin M. B., Greene F. L., Edge S. B., et al., “The Eighth Edition AJCC Cancer Staging Manual: Continuing to Build a Bridge From a Population‐Based to a More “Personalized” Approach to Cancer Staging,” CA: A Cancer Journal for Clinicians 67, no. 2 (2017): 93–99.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28094848</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kazakou P., Simeakis G., Alevizaki M., and Saltiki K., “Medullary Thyroid Carcinoma (MTC): Unusual Metastatic Sites,” Endocrinology, Diabetes &amp; Metabolism Case Reports 2021 (2021): 21‐0063.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8495720</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34551391</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shao Y., Li G., Wei T., et al., “Distant Metastasis in Medullary Thyroid Carcinoma: Clinical Outcomes and Implications of T Stage,” Clinical Endocrinology 97, no. 5 (2022): 676–684.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35261045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ricciato M. P., Lombardi C. P., Raffaelli M., De Rosa A., and Corsello S. M., “Metastatic Breast Involvement From Medullary Thyroid Carcinoma: A Clue to Consider the Need of Early Diagnosis and Adequate Surgical Strategy,” Thyroid 20, no. 7 (2010): 831–832.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20465531</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhatoe H. S., Badwal S., Dutta V., and Kannan N., “Pituitary Metastasis From Medullary Carcinoma of Thyroid: Case Report and Review of Literature,” Journal of Neuro‐Oncology 89, no. 1 (2008): 63–67.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18408891</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lesesve J. F. and Plénat F., “Aggressive Bbone Mmarrow Mmetastatic Mmedullary Tthyroid Ccarcinoma,” Blood 123, no. 17 (2014): 2603.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24883446</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faggiano A., Giannetta E., Modica R., et al., “Calcium‐Stimulated Calcitonin Test for the Diagnosis of Medullary Thyroid Cancer: Results of a Multicenter Study and Comparison Between Different Assays,” Minerva Endocrinology 48, no. 3 (2023): 253–260.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37326573</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mendelsohn G., Wells S. A., and Baylin S. B., “Relationship of Tissue Carcinoembryonic Antigen and Calcitonin to Tumor Virulence in Medullary Thyroid Carcinoma. An Immunohistochemical Study in Early, Localized, and Virulent Disseminated Stages of Disease,” Cancer 54, no. 4 (1984): 657–662.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6378353</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaliszewski K., Ludwig M., Ludwig B., Mikuła A., Greniuk M., and Rudnicki J., “Update on the Diagnosis and Management of Medullary Thyroid Cancer: What Has Changed in Recent Years?,” Cancers (Basel) 14, no. 15 (2022): 3643.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9332800</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35892901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Modica R., Minotta R., Liccardi A., Cannavale G., Benevento E., and Colao A., “Evaluation of Neutrophil‐To‐Lymphocyte Ratio (NLR), Platelet‐To‐Lymphocyte Ratio (PLR) and Systemic Immune–Inflammation Index (SII) as Potential Biomarkers in Patients With Sporadic Medullary Thyroid Cancer (MTC),” Journal of Personalized Medicine 13, no. 6 (2023): 953.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10304568</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37373942</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sastry R., Williams E. A., Koffie R., Fehnel K., Wirth L., and Nahed B., “Metastatic Medullary Thyroid Cancer to the Brain: A Case Report and Review of the Literature,” International Journal of Endocrine Oncology 5, no. 3 (2018): IJE11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cano J. M., Galán R., and López R., “Recurrent Metastatic Medullary Thyroid Carcinoma: A Case of Sustained Response to Prolonged Treatment With Somatostatin Analogues,” Thyroid 27, no. 11 (2017): 1450–1455.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28927353</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borcek P., Asa S. L., Gentili F., Ezzat S., and Kiehl T. R., “Brain Metastasis From Medullary Thyroid Carcinoma,” Case Reports 2010 (2010): bcr0920103301.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3029950</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22802478</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buffet C., Leboulleux S., Kraeber‐Bodéré F., et al., “Cardiac Metastasis From Medullary Thyroid Cancers With Long‐Term Survival Under Vandetanib,” European Thyroid Journal 10, no. 6 (2021): 517–522.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8647102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34956923</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Appetecchia M., Barnabei A., Pompeo V., et al., “Testicular and Inguinal Lymph Node Metastases of Medullary Thyroid Cancer: A Case Report and Review of the Literature,” BMC Endocrine Disorders 14, no. 1 (2014): 84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4271442</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25306429</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Udelsman R., Ball D., Baylin S. B., Wong C. Y., Osterman F. A., and Sostre S., “Preoperative Localization of Occult Medullary Carcinoma of the Thyroid Gland With Single‐Photon Emission Tomography Dimercaptosuccinic Acid,” Surgery 114, no. 6 (1993): 1083–1089.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8256211</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kebebew E., Greenspan F. S., Clark O. H., Woeber K. A., and Grunwell J., “Extent of Disease and Practice Patterns for Medullary Thyroid Cancer,” Journal of the American College of Surgeons 200, no. 6 (2005): 890–896.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15922202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu B., Fuchs T. L., Ahmadi S., et al., “International Medullary Thyroid Carcinoma Grading System: A Validated Grading System for Medullary Thyroid Carcinoma,” Journal of Clinical Oncology 40, no. 1 (2022): 96–104.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8683221</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34731032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fuchs T. L., Nassour A. J., Glover A., et al., “A Proposed Grading Scheme for Medullary Thyroid Carcinoma Based on Proliferative Activity (Ki‐67 and Mitotic Count) and Coagulative Necrosis,” American Journal of Surgical Pathology 44, no. 10 (2020): 1419–1428.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7641183</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32452872</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Varnaseri M., Amini F., Jamshididan R., et al., “Ivermectin as a Potential Addition to the Limited Anti‐COVID‐19 Arsenal: A Double‐Blinded Clinical Trial,” Jundishapur Journal of Health Sciences 16, no. 2 (2024): e146703.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sinha S. and Kundu C. N., “Cancer and COVID‐19: Why Are Cancer Patients More Susceptible to COVID‐19?,” Medical Oncology 38, no. 9 (2021): 101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8302962</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34302557</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>