<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39417458</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1678-4758</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>31Suppl 1</Volume><Issue>Suppl 1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Historia, ciencias, saude--Manguinhos</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Hist Cienc Saude Manguinhos</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Manguinhos hospitals: reflections on scientific politics and heritage, from tropical diseases to covid-19.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e2024054</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e2024054</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e2024054</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1590/S0104-59702024000100054</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0104-59702024000200204</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>In 2020 the world suffered from covid-19. Fundação Oswaldo Cruz faced itself again with a challenging task. One of its strategies while battling the disease was building a hospital. It was not the first time the institution would build such a healthcare facility. The first hospital, which nowadays needs preservation measures, opened in 1918 intending to study and treat tropical diseases. The second, built in 2021, was a field hospital designed to treat the new epidemic victims. This article aims to reflect upon both hospitals' construction contexts, as well as contribute to studies on the history of science and health.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Costa</LastName><ForeName>Renato da Gama-Rosa</ForeName><Initials>RDG</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2569-0912</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pesquisador e professor, chefe do Departamento de Patrimônio Histórico, Casa de Oswaldo Cruz/Fiocruz. Rio de Janeiro - RJ - Brasil renato.gamarosa@fiocruz.br.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Santos</LastName><ForeName>Renata Soares da Costa</ForeName><Initials>RSDC</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6452-7659</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pesquisadora e bolsista do Departamento de Patrimônio Histórico, Casa de Oswaldo Cruz/Fiocruz. Rio de Janeiro - RJ - Brasil rsoarescsantos@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Martire</LastName><ForeName>Giovanna Ermida</ForeName><Initials>GE</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0008-8043-2327</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Arquiteta, Departamento de Patrimônio Histórico, Casa de Oswaldo Cruz/Fiocruz. Rio de Janeiro - RJ - Brasil giovanna.martire@fiocruz.br.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>por</Language><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016456">Historical Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><VernacularTitle>Hospitais de Manguinhos: reflexões sobre políticas científicas e patrimônio, das doenças tropicais à covid-19.</VernacularTitle></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Brazil</Country><MedlineTA>Hist Cienc Saude Manguinhos</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9513999</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0104-5970</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000266" MajorTopicYN="N">history</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014330" MajorTopicYN="Y">Tropical Medicine</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000266" MajorTopicYN="N">history</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D049673" MajorTopicYN="N">History, 20th Century</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001938" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Brazil</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D049674" MajorTopicYN="N">History, 21st Century</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011057" MajorTopicYN="N">Politics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006761" MajorTopicYN="N">Hospitals</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000266" MajorTopicYN="N">history</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006749" MajorTopicYN="N">Hospital Design and Construction</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000266" MajorTopicYN="N">history</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="por"><AbstractText>Em 2020 o mundo vivenciou o flagelo da covid-19. A Fiocruz se viu novamente diante de um grande desafio. Uma das estratégias estabelecidas pela instituição para o enfrentamento da doença foi a construção de um novo hospital. Não era a primeira vez que a Fiocruz construía um espaço de assistência hospitalar. O primeiro hospital, cujas instalações necessitam de ações de preservação, foi aberto em 1918 para estudos e tratamento de doenças tropicais. O segundo foi erguido em 2021, especialmente para tratar as vítimas da nova epidemia, na lógica de um hospital de campanha. Esse artigo pretende trazer reflexões para se entender o contexto de construção de ambos os hospitais, bem como contribuir para estudos sobre história das ciências e da saúde.</AbstractText></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="eng"><AbstractText>In 2020 the world suffered from covid-19. Fundação Oswaldo Cruz faced itself again with a challenging task. One of its strategies while battling the disease was building a hospital. It was not the first time the institution would build such a healthcare facility. The first hospital, which nowadays needs preservation measures, opened in 1918 intending to study and treat tropical diseases. The second, built in 2021, was a field hospital designed to treat the new epidemic victims. This article aims to reflect upon both hospitals’ construction contexts, as well as contribute to studies on the history of science and health.</AbstractText></OtherAbstract><CoiStatement><b>Conflito de interesse:</b> Não houve conflito de interesses na realização do presente estudo.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>25</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39417458</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11472717</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/S0104-59702024000100054</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0104-59702024000200204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>ARAGÃO Henrique de B.R. Notícia histórica sobre a fundação do Instituto Oswaldo Cruz. Memórias do Instituto Oswaldo Cruz. 1950;98:1–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24539395</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>AZEVEDO Ana Lúcia. Centro da Fiocruz criado para o combate à COVID planeja virar referência pós-pandemia.  [Acesso em: 24 jun. 2024];O Globo. 2020 Oct 4; https://oglobo.globo.com/saude/coronavirus/centro-da-fiocruz-criado-para-combate-COVID-planeja-virar-referencia-pos-pandemia-24674491</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>BENCHIMOL Jaime L. Manguinhos do sonho à vida: a ciência na Belle Époque. Rio de Janeiro: Casa de Oswaldo Cruz; 1990.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>BENCHIMOL Jaime L., TEIXEIRA Luiz Antônio. Cobras, lagartos e outros bichos: uma história comparada dos institutos Oswaldo Cruz e Butantan. Rio de Janeiro: Editora da UFRJ; 1993.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>BITTENCOURT Fabio, VILAS-BOAS Doris, SILVA Emerson da. Arquitetura para emergências: experiências, vivências e reflexões. Rio de Janeiro: Rio Books; 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CENTRO HOSPITALAR da Fiocruz para Covid-19 começa a receber pacientes; veja quem são os doadores. Jornal Hoje. May 20, 2020.  [Acesso: 4 maio 2022].  
 https://g1.globo.com/jornal-hoje/noticia/2020/05/20/centro-hospitalar-da-fiocruz-para-covid-19-comeca-a-receber-pacientes-veja-quem-sao-os-doadores.ghtml
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>COSTA Renato da Gama-Rosa. Apontamentos para a arquitetura hospitalar no Brasil: entre o tradicional e o moderno. História, Ciências, Saúde - Manguinhos. 2011 Dec;18(supl.1):53–66.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22240947</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COSTA Renato da Gama-Rosa, MARTIRE Giovanna. González Servín María Lilia.org, compiler. In: Registro del sistema arquitectónico de pabellones en hospitales de América Latina. Vol. 4. Ciudad de México: Facultad de Arquitectura/Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México; 2023. Hospital Evandro Chagas: arquitectura de pabellón en Manguinhos; pp. 54–72.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>COSTA Renato Gama-Rosa, et al. Depoimento concedido ao projeto “Lugares para a ciência: evolução dos campi da Fiocruz em Manguinhos e Mata Atlântica”. Rio de Janeiro: Departamento de Patrimônio Histórico/Casa de Oswaldo Cruz/Fiocruz; Jan 28, 2022. Entrevistada: Vânia Furugem. 1 arquivo mp3 (72 min)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CUKIERMAN Henrique. Yes, nós temos Pasteur: Manguinhos, Oswaldo Cruz e história da ciência no Brasil. Rio de Janeiro: Relume Dumará; Faperj; 2007.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CUNNINGHAM Andrew, WILLIAMS Perry. In: The laboratory revolution in medicine. Cunningham Andrew, Williams Perry.ed, editors. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press; 1992. Transforming plague: the laboratory and the identity of infectious disease; pp. 209–244.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>DOSSE François. L'Histoire à l'épreuve de la guerre des mémoires. Tempo e Argumento. 2009;1(1):5–16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FERREIRA Marieta de M. História do tempo presente: desafios. Cultura Vozes. 2000;94(3):111–124.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FERREIRA Marieta de M. Notas iniciais sobre a história do tempo presente e a historiografia no Brasil. [Acesso em: 27 set. 2022];Tempo e Argumento. 2018 10(23):80–108. doi: 10.5965/2175180310232018080.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5965/2175180310232018080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>FIOCRUZ, Fundação Oswaldo Cruz  Centro hospitalar da Fiocruz entra em funcionamento. May 19, 2020.  [Acesso em: 20 jan. 2022].  
 https://portal.fiocruz.br/noticia/COVID-19-centro-hospitalar-da-fiocruz-entra-em-funcionamento
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FIOCRUZ, Fundação Oswaldo Cruz  Estudos terapêuticos e centro hospitalar. 2020.  [Acesso em: 20 jan. 2022]. https://portal.fiocruz.br/estudos-terapeuticos-e-centro-hospitalar</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FIOCRUZ, Fundação Oswaldo Cruz . Casa de Oswaldo Cruz. Política de preservação e gestão de acervos culturais das ciências e da saúde. Rio de Janeiro: Fiocruz/COC; 2013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>GHISLENI Camilla. Adaptabilidade vital: hospitais de campanha no contexto da pandemia. ArchDaily Brasil. Oct 31, 2021.  [Acesso: 11 ago. 2023].  
 https://www.archdaily.com.br/br/970203/adaptabilidade-vital-hospitais-de-campanha-no-contexto-da-pandemia
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>KROPF Simone Petraglia. Doença de Chagas, doença do Brasil: ciência, saúde e nação (1909-1962) Rio de Janeiro: Editora Fiocruz; 2009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>NIGHTINGALE Florence. Notes on hospitals. London: Longman, Roberts and Green; 1863.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>PORTO Ângela.org, compiler. In: História da saúde no Rio de Janeiro: instituições e patrimônio arquitetônico. Rio de Janeiro (1808-1958) Rio de Janeiro: Editora Fiocruz; 2008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>RELATÓRIO anual de atividades do IOC. Fiocruz . DAD/COC, Fundo IOC, Seção Serviço de Administração, Série Administração Geral, BR RJCOC O2-10-05. Departamento de Arquivo e Documentação/Casa de Oswaldo Cruz/Fiocruz; Rio de Janeiro: 1924.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>RELATÓRIO anual de atividades do IOC. Fiocruz . DAD/COC, Fundo IOC, Seção Serviço de Administração, Série Administração Geral, BR RJCOC O2-10-05. Departamento de Arquivo e Documentação/Casa de Oswaldo Cruz/Fiocruz; Rio de Janeiro: 1921.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ROSENBERG Charles, GOLDEN Janet.ed, editors. Framing disease: studies in cultural history. New Brunswick: Rutgers University Press; 1997.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>RUPRECHT Theo. Hospitais de campanha: como vão funcionar e por que são tão importantes. Apr 1, 2020.  [Acesso em: 11 ago. 2023]. https://saude.abril.com.br/medicina/hospitais-de-campanha-como-vao-funcionar</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>SANGLARD Gisele. Entre os salões e o laboratório: Guilherme Guinle, a saúde e a ciência no Rio de Janeiro, 1920-1940. Rio de Janeiro: Editora Fiocruz; 2008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>SANTOS Renata Soares C. O Instituto Oswaldo Cruz e seus hospitais: médicos, pacientes e suas mazelas rurais e urbanas (1909-1930) Casa de Oswaldo Cruz/Fiocruz; Rio de Janeiro: 2019. Tese (Doutorado em História das Ciências e da Saúde)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>STEPAN Nancy Leys. Gênese e evolução da ciência brasileira: Oswaldo Cruz e a política de investigação científica e médica. Rio de Janeiro: Artenova; Fundação Oswaldo Cruz; 1976.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>TOLEDO Luiz Carlos. Após a pandemia a arquitetura hospitalar não será mais a mesma. Rio de Janeiro: Conselho de Arquitetura e Urbanismo do Rio de Janeiro; Jun 29, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. World Health Organization  Projeto de Unidade de Tratamento de Síndrome Respiratória Aguda Grave (SRAG)  [Acesso em: 2 jan. 2024].  s.d. 
 https://openwho.org/courses/Unidades-SRAG
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. World Health Organization  WHO Covid-19 Solidarity Therapeutics Trial. 2021.  [Acesso em: 15 out. 2021]. https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/global-research-on-novel-coronavirus-2019-ncov/solidarity-clinical-trial-for-covid-19-treatments</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>