<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39415702</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1860-7187</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>17</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>ChemMedChem</Title><ISOAbbreviation>ChemMedChem</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Is it Time for Multi-Drug Therapy with Combination of Therapeutic Nucleic Acids?</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e202400493</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e202400493</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/cmdc.202400493</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Therapeutic nucleic acids (TNAs) are a new class of drugs that exhibit different properties and mechanisms of action from those of small molecules or biological drugs. Over twenty oligonucleotide drugs and several COVID-19 vaccines have received regulatory approval for clinical use. A characteristic feature of these TNAs is that they are directed against one specific biological target and one specific RNA or DNA sequence. Consequently, TNAs currently used are administered as monotherapy. Due to the known advantages of multidrug therapy with low molecular weight drugs, it may be time to intensify work on such a treatment protocol, also in the case of TNAs.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Wiley-VCH GmbH.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Leśnikowski</LastName><ForeName>Zbigniew J</ForeName><Initials>ZJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicinal Chemistry, Institute of Medical Biology PAS, Lodowa 106, 92-232, Łódź, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>015/16/W/ST5/00413</GrantID><Agency>National Science Centre in Poland</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>ChemMedChem</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101259013</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1860-7179</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Antisense oligonucleotides</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Combinations</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Drug carriers</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Multidrug therapy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Nanoparticles</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Nucleic acid therapeutics</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>14</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39415702</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/cmdc.202400493</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>D. R. Corey, M. J. Damha, M. Manoharan, Nucl. Acid Ther. 2022, 32, 8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Panigaj, E. Skelly, D. Beasock, I. Marriott, M. B. Johnson, J. Salotti, K. A. Afonin, Front. Immunol. 2023, 14, 1053550.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. C. Zamecnik, M. L. Stephenson, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A 1978, 75, 280.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Egli, M. Manoharan, Nucl. Acids Res. 2023, 51, 2529.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Belgrad, H. H. Fakih, A. Khvorova, Nucl. Acids Ther. 2024, 34, 52.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. Baylot, T. K. Le, D. Taïeb, P. Rocchi, L. Colleaux, Commun. Biol. 2024, 7, 489.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. G. Gish, P. M. Gholam, Clevel. Clin. J. Med. 2009, 76(3), 20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Skorski, M. Nieborowska-Skorska, K. Campbell, R. V. Iozzo, G. Zon, Z. Darzynkiewicz, B. Calabretta, J. Exp. Med. 1995, 182, 1645.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. R. Nourazarian, A. G. Najar, S. Farajnia, A. Y. Khosroushahi, R. Pashaei-Asl, Y. Omidi, Asian Pacific J. Cancer Prev. 2013, 13, 4751.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O. Yogev, O. Weissbrod, G. Battistoni, D. Bressan, A. Naamati, I. Falciatori, A. C. Berkyurek, R. Rasnic, R. Izuagbe, M. Hosmillo, S. Ilan, I. Grossman, L. McCormick, C. C. Honeycutt, T. Johnston, M. Gagne, D. C. Douek, I. Goodfellow, G. J. Hannon, Y. Erlich, Commun. Biol. 2023, 6, 277.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Yanagidaira, K. Yoshioka, T. Nagata, S. Nakao, K. Miyata, T. Yokota, Mol. Biol. Rep. 2023, 50, 3539.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Teng, S. Obika, K. Ueda, T. Honda, Front. Microbiol. 2019, 10, 2781.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. C. R. Bahadur, B. Thapa, J. Valencia-Serna, H. M. Aliabadi, H. Uludağ, J. Control. Release 2017, 256, 153.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. B. Mendes, J. Conniot, A. Avital, D. Yao, X. Jiang, X. Zhou, N. Sharf-Pauker, Y. Xiao, O. Adir, H. Liang, J. Shi, A. Schroeder, J. Conde, Nat. Rev. Methods Primers 2022, 2, 24.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Cai, R. Dou, C. Guo, J. Tang, X. Li, J. Chen, J. Zhang, Pharmaceutics 2023, 15, 1502.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. D. Timotievich, I. P. Shilovskiy, M. R. Khaitov, Biochem. (Moscow) 2023, 88, 1800.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Dufes, I. F. Uchegbu, A. G. Schatzlein, Adv. Drug Deliv. Rev. 2005, 57, 2177.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Sun, Z.-R. Lu, Pharm. Res. 2023, 40, 27.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Mihailescu, D. L. Worcester, C. L. Carroll, A. R. Chamberlin, S. H. White, Biophys. J. 2023, 122, 1086.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Gao, X. Liu, N. Chen, X. Yang, F. Tang, Pharmaceutics 2023, 15, 178.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Sinani, M. E. Durgun, E. Cevher, Y. Özsoy, Pharmaceutics 2023, 15, 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Ding, Z. Jiang, K. Saha, C. S. Kim, S. T. Kim, R. F. Landis, V. M. Rotello, Mol. Ther. 2014, 22, 1075.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. C. Seeman, H. F. Sleiman, Nat. Rev. Mater. 2018, 3, 17068.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Zhao, R. Wang, K. Yang, Y. Jiang, Y. Peng, Y. Li, Z. Zhang, J. Ding, S. Shi, Acta Pharm. Sin. B 2023, 13, 916e941.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. C. Roberts, R. Langer, M. J. A. Wood, Nat. Rev. 2020, 19, 673.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Lee, A. K. R. Lytton-Jean, Y. Chen, K. T. Love, A. I. Park, E. D. Karagiannis, A. Sehgal, W. Querbes, C. S. Zurenko, M. Jayaraman, C. G. Peng, K. Charisse, A. Borodovsky, M. Manoharan, J. S. Donahoe, J. Truelove, M. Nahrendorf, R. Langer, D. G. Anderson, Nat. Nanotechnol. 2012, 7, 389.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Yang, Q. Jiang, L. He, P. Zhan, Q. Liu, S. Liu, M. Fu, J. Liu, C. Li, B. Ding, ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces 2018, 10, 23693.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. A. Rahman, P. Wang, Z. Zhao, D. Wang, S. Nannapaneni, C. Zhang, Z. Chen, C. C. Griffith, S. J. Hurwitz, Z. G. Chen, Y. Ke, D. M. Shin, Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. 2017, 56, 16023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. A. Afonin, M. Viard, A. Y. Koyfman, A. N. Martins, W. K. Kasprzak, M. Panigaj, R. Desai, A. Santhanam, W. W. Grabow, L. Jaeger, E. Heldman, J. Reiser, W. Chiu, E. O. Freed, B. A. Shapiro, Nano Lett. 2014, 14, 5662.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Bednarska-Szczepaniak, K. Ebenryter-Olbińska, G. Gajek, K. Śmiałkowski, J. Suwara, L. Fiedorowicz, Z. Leśnikowski, Chem. Eur. J. 2024, e202303531.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. G. Rahul Ingle, W.-J. Fang, Pharmaceutics 2023, 15, 1158.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. A. Kulkarni, D. Witzigmann, S. B. Thomson, S. Chen, B. R. Leavitt, P. R. Cullis, R. van der Meel, Nat. Nanotechnol. 2021, 16, 630.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>