<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39417955</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1439-0973</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>17</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Infection</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Infection</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Comparison of SARS-CoV-2 related in-hospital mortality, ICU admission and mechanical ventilation of 1.4 million patients in Germany and Switzerland, 2019 to 2022.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s15010-024-02412-9</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="PURPOSE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">In the 2020 emergence of SARS-CoV-2, global response lacked unified treatment and surveillance, resulting in diverse impacts due to varied healthcare resources and national guidelines. Germany and Switzerland curbed the virus initially by promptly tracking and testing, bolstered by strong governmental capacity. This study aimed to assess country-specific healthcare disparities and their impact on ICU admission rates, mechanical ventilation, and in-hospital mortality.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">To enhance healthcare quality using real-world data, the "Initiative of Quality Medicine" (IQM) was established. Pseudonymised routine data from participating hospitals, during 01/01/2019-31/12/2022, was retrospectively analysed, focusing on patients with SARI ± SARS-CoV-2-infection (U07.1). Cohorts were matched based on various factors and multivariable analyses included logistic regression.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">1.421.922 cases of SARI ± U07.1 involving 386 German and 41 Swiss hospitals were included. Patients in Germany were older (mean: 69.4 vs. 66.5 years) and had more comorbidities than in Switzerland (p &lt; .001). Patients in Germany were also more likely to be treated on ICU (28% vs. 20%, OR 1.5 95% CI 1.5-1.6, p &lt; .001) and mechanically ventilated (20% vs. 15%, OR 1.4, 95% CI 1.4-1.5, p &lt; .001). The in-hospital mortality was significantly higher in Germany than in Switzerland (21% vs. 12%, OR 2.0, 95% CI 1.9-2.0, p &lt; .001). Matched cohorts showed reduced differences, but Germany still exhibited higher in-hospital mortality. Discrepancies were evident in both pre-pandemic and pandemic analyses, highlighting existing disparities between both countries.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">IQM data from Swiss and German hospitals reveals country-specific differences in SARI ± U07.1 outcomes, highlighting higher in-hospital mortality in Germany, with uncertain causes suggesting varied treatments and resources.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kodde</LastName><ForeName>Cathrin</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Diseases, Respiratory Medicine and Critical Care, Charité-Universitaetsmedizin Berlin, Berlin, Germany. cathrin.kodde@charite.de.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Respiratory Diseases, Lungenklinik Heckeshorn, Helios Hospital Emil-Von-Behring, Berlin, Germany. cathrin.kodde@charite.de.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hohenstein</LastName><ForeName>Sven</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Helios Health Institute, Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nachtigall</LastName><ForeName>Irit</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Diseases and Infection Prevention, Helios Hospital Emil-Von-Behring, Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine, MSB Medical School Berlin, Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cavalli</LastName><ForeName>Yvonne</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University Hospital Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Initiative Quality Medicine, Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Schuepbach</LastName><ForeName>Reto</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Intensive Care Medicine, University Hospital Zurich and University Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Graf</LastName><ForeName>Raphael</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>3M Health Information Systems, Neuss, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bollmann</LastName><ForeName>Andreas</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Helios Health Institute, Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Electrophysiology, Heart Centre Leipzig at University of Leipzig, Leipzig, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kuhlen</LastName><ForeName>Ralf</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Helios Health Institute, Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Initiative Quality Medicine, Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Infection</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0365307</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0300-8126</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ARDS</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Critical care</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Public health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Respiratory infections</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Surveillance</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39417955</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s15010-024-02412-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s15010-024-02412-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Desson Z, et al. Europe’s Covid-19 outliers: German, Austrian and Swiss policy responses during the early stages of the 2020 pandemic. Health Policy Technol. 2020;9(4):405–18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.hlpt.2020.09.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7834269</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wjst M, Wendtner C. High variability of COVID-19 case fatality rate in Germany. BMC Public Health. 2023;23(1):416.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12889-023-15112-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9977635</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmidt AE, et al. Tackling the COVID-19 pandemic: Initial responses in 2020 in selected social health insurance countries in Europe☆. Health Policy. 2022;126(5):476–84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.healthpol.2021.09.011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karagiannidis C, et al (2024) In-hospital mortality, comorbidities, and costs of one million mechanically ventilated patients in Germany: a nationwide observational study before, during, and after the COVID-19 pandemic. The Lancet Regional Health–Europe</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>RKI (2023) Wie wird die Aktivität akuter Atemwegsinfektionen in Deutschland erfasst? (accessed on 27. October 2023); Available from: https://www.rki.de/SharedDocs/FAQ/ARE-Surveillance/FAQ_Erfassung_ARE_Aktivitaet_in_Deutschland.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (2015) Regional Office for Europe: health system review. Health Systems in Transition, vol. 17 (4). 2015, Copenhagen: World Health Organization. Regional Office for Europe</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bundesamt für Gesundheit. COVID-19 Monitoring. (accessed on 30. October 2023); Available from: https://www.bag.admin.ch/bag/de/home/krankheiten/krankheiten-im-ueberblick/coronavirus/covid-19/monitoring.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Initiative Qualitätsmedizin. (accessed on 27. October 2023); Available from: https://www.initiative-qualitaetsmedizin.de/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moore BJ, et al. Identifying increased risk of readmission and in-hospital mortality using hospital administrative data. Med Care. 2017;55(7):698–705.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MLR.0000000000000735</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gilbert T, et al. Development and validation of a hospital frailty Risk Score focusing on older people in acute care settings using electronic hospital records: an observational study. The Lancet. 2018;391(10132):1775–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(18)30668-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>CNBC News (2023) Germany has a low coronavirus mortality rate: Here’s why. (accessed on 26. October 2023); Available from: https://www.cnbc.com/2020/04/03/germany-has-a-low-coronavirus-mortality-rate-heres-why.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Time News (2023) Why Is Germany’s Coronavirus Death Rate So Low? (accessed on 26. October 2023]; Available from: https://time.com/5812555/germany-coronavirus-deaths/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rhodes A, et al. The variability of critical care bed numbers in Europe. Intensive Care Med. 2012;38(10):1647–53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00134-012-2627-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>AWMF S1-Leitlinie Entscheidungen über die Zuteilung intensivmedizinischer Ressourcen im Kontext der COVID-19-Pandemie - Klinisch-ethische Empfehlungen. 2021; (accessed 23. October 2023) Available from: https://register.awmf.org/de/leitlinien/detail/040-013</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Swiss Academy Of Medical Sciences. COVID-19 pandemic: triage for intensive-care treatment under resource scarcity. Swiss Med Wkly. 2020;150: w20229.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jöbges S, et al. Recommendations on COVID-19 triage: international comparison and ethical analysis. Bioethics. 2020;34(9):948–59.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/bioe.12805</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7537413</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marckmann G, et al. Decisions on the allocation of intensive care resources in the context of the COVID-19 pandemic: clinical and ethical recommendations of DIVI, DGINA, DGAI, DGIIN, DGNI, DGP, DGP and AEM. German version Medizinische Klinik-Intensivmedizin und Notfallmedizin. 2020;115:477–85.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00063-020-00708-w</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ehni HJ, Wiesing U, Ranisch R. Saving the most lives—A comparison of European triage guidelines in the context of the COVID-19 pandemic. Bioethics. 2021;35(2):125–34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/bioe.12836</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clavien C, et al. Advance Care Planning in Switzerland: Chances and challenges of delivering high-quality ACP in a small high-income, multilingual, federally organized country. Z Evid Fortbild Qual Gesundhwes. 2023;180:115–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.zefq.2023.04.008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krones T, et al. Advance care planning for the severely ill in the hospital: a randomized trial. BMJ Support Palliat Care. 2022;12(e3):e411–23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjspcare-2017-001489</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bosisio F, et al. Planning ahead with dementia: what role can advance care planning play? a review of opportunities and challenges. Swiss Med Wkly. 2018;148(5152):w14706–w14706.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grosgurin O, et al. Role of intermediate care unit admission and noninvasive respiratory support during the COVID-19 pandemic: A retrospective cohort study. Respiration. 2021;100(8):786–93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000516329</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tobin MJ, Jubran A, Laghi F. Misconceptions of pathophysiology of happy hypoxemia and implications for management of COVID-19. Respir Res. 2020;21(1):1–2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12931-020-01520-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Butler MJ, et al. Mechanical ventilation for COVID-19: outcomes following discharge from inpatient treatment. PLoS One. 2023;18(1): e0277498.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0277498</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9821470</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Becher T, Frerichs I. Mortality in COVID-19 is not merely a question of resource availability. Lancet Respir Med. 2020;8(9):832–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(20)30312-X</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7386881</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karagiannidis C, et al. Major differences in ICU admissions during the first and second COVID-19 wave in Germany. Lancet Respir Med. 2021;9(5):e47–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(21)00101-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8078895</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karagiannidis C, et al. High in-hospital mortality rate in patients with COVID-19 receiving extracorporeal membrane oxygenation in germany: a critical analysis. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2021;204(8):991–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1164/rccm.202105-1145LE</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8534613</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeitziner M-M, et al. Critical care staffing ratio and outcome of COVID-19 patients requiring intensive care unit admission during the first pandemic wave: a retrospective analysis across Switzerland from the RISC-19-ICU observational cohort. Swiss Med Wkly. 2022;152(2526): w30183.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4414/SMW.2022.w30183</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rae PJL, et al. Outcomes sensitive to critical care nurse staffing levels: a systematic review. Intensive Crit Care Nurs. 2021;67: 103110.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.iccn.2021.103110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neuraz A, et al. Patient mortality is associated with staff resources and workload in the ICU: a multicenter observational study*. Critical Care Med. 2015;43(8):1587–94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/CCM.0000000000001015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Depasse B, et al. A profile of European ICU nursing. Intensive Care Med. 1998;24:939–45.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s001340050693</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grimm C, et al. targeted minimal staff-to-patient ratios are unachievable—a nationwide survey in German ICUs during the COVID-19 pandemic. Cureus. 2021;13(6): e15755.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8289403</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stroth LC, et al. Workforce strategies during the first wave of the COVID-19 pandemic: a retrospective online survey at intensive care units in Germany. BMC Health Serv Res. 2024;24(1):407.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12913-024-10848-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10985885</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bundesgesundheitsministerium für Gesundheit, Pflegepersonaluntergrenzen im Krankenhaus. (accessed on 14. September 2024); Available from: https://www.bundesgesundheitsministerium.de/themen/pflege/pflegepersonaluntergrenzen.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fasshauer JM, et al. Impact of COVID-19 pandemic on involuntary and urgent inpatient admissions for psychiatric disorders in a German-wide hospital network. J Psychiatr Res. 2021;142:140–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2021.07.052</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8417753</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hunger R, et al. Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on delays in surgical procedures in Germany: a multi-center analysis of an administrative registry of 176,783 patients. Patient Saf Surg. 2022;16(1):22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13037-022-00331-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9238103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fasshauer JM, et al. Emergency hospital admissions for psychiatric disorders in a German-wide hospital network during the COVID-19 outbreak. Soc Psychiatry Psychiatr Epidemiol. 2021;56(8):1469–75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00127-021-02091-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8053025</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leiner J, et al. COVID-19 and severe acute respiratory infections: monitoring trends in 421 German hospitals during the first four pandemic waves. Infect Drug Resist. 2023;16:2775–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/IDR.S402313</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10178997</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>