<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39419078</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1098-9064</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>17</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Seminars in thrombosis and hemostasis</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Semin Thromb Hemost</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Venous Thromboembolism after Hospital Discharge: Temporal Trends in Baseline Characteristics, Prevention, Treatment, and 90-day Outcomes.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1055/s-0044-1791817</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Venous thromboembolism (VTE) after hospital discharge poses a serious health risk. Assessments of patient characteristics, prophylaxis, treatment, outcomes, and over time changes lack consistency. Data on 16,901 hospitalized patients in the Registro Informatizado Enfermedad TromboEmbolica registry (2003-2022) were analyzed to evaluate trends in baseline characteristics, prophylaxis, treatments, and 90-day outcomes among medical (6,218) and surgical (10,683) patient cohorts. Multivariable logistic regression was used to assess the risks of the composite of fatal pulmonary embolism (PE) or recurrent VTE and major bleeding. The proportion of patients who presented with PE increased among medical (from 54 to 72%) and surgical patients (from 55 to 58%). Prophylaxis use increased in medical patients (from 53 to 71%), while decreasing in surgical patients (from 67 to 58%). Notably, the 90-day composite of fatal PE or recurrent VTE decreased in medical (from 3.9 to 1.8%) and surgical patients (from 2.9 to 1.2%; <i>p</i> &lt; 0.001 for both). Conversely, major bleeding increased (3.1 to 4.5%) in medical patients (<i>p</i> = 0.008), with no change in surgical patients (from 2.5 to 2.4%). Risk-adjusted analysis showed a yearly decrease in the risk for the composite outcome (subhazard ratio [sHR]: 0.95; 95% confidence interval [CI]: 0.93-0.98) in medical and surgical patients and an increase in the risk for major bleeding in medical patients only (sHR: 1.04; 95% CI: 1.01-1.07). Results were consistent after excluding coronavirus disease 2019 patients. Over 20 years, the composite of fatal PE or recurrent VTE within 90 days had significantly decreased in VTE patients after hospitalization for medical or surgical care. Medical patients, however, exhibited an increase in major bleeding.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Thieme. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Brenner</LastName><ForeName>Benjamin</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Hematology and Bone Marrow Transplantation, Rambam Health Care Campus, Haifa, Israel.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Ruth and Bruce Rappaport Faculty of Medicine, Technion, Haifa, Israel.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tzoran</LastName><ForeName>Inna</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Hematology and Bone Marrow Transplantation, Rambam Health Care Campus, Haifa, Israel.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Ruth and Bruce Rappaport Faculty of Medicine, Technion, Haifa, Israel.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bikdeli</LastName><ForeName>Behnood</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cardiovascular Medicine Division and the Thrombosis Research Group, Brigham and Women's Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Outcomes Research and Evaluation, Yale New Haven Hospital, New Haven, Connecticut.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cardiovascular Research Foundation, New York, New York.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Valle</LastName><ForeName>Reina</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Hospital Sierrallana, Santander, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Poenou</LastName><ForeName>Géraldine</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Médecine et Thérapeutique, Hôpital Nord-CHU St-Etienne, Saint-Etienne, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tirado-Miranda</LastName><ForeName>Raimundo</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Hospital Infanta Margarita, Córdoba, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pesce</LastName><ForeName>María L</ForeName><Initials>ML</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Hospital General Universitario de Elda, Alicante, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pagán-Escribano</LastName><ForeName>Javier</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Hospital General Universitario Morales Meseguer, Murcia, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Giorgi-Pierfranceschi</LastName><ForeName>Matteo</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Istituti Ospitalieri di Cremona, Cremona, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Monreal</LastName><ForeName>Manuel</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, CIBER de Enfermedades Respiratorias, Madrid, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Chair for the Study of Thromboembolic Disease, Faculty of Health Sciences, UCAM-Universidad Católica San Antonio de Murcia, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><CollectiveName>RIETE Investigators</CollectiveName></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Semin Thromb Hemost</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0431155</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0094-6176</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CoiStatement>B.B. declares receiving honoraria for lectures and advisory board contributions from Sanofi, ROVI Laboratories, Johnson &amp; Johnson, and HORIBA Medical. B.B. is supported by a Career Development Award from the American Heart Association and VIVA Physicians (#938814). B.B. was supported by the Scott Schoen and Nancy Adams IGNITE Award and is supported by the Mary Ann Tynan Research Scientist award from the Mary Horrigan Connors Center for Women's Health and Gender Biology at Brigham and Women's Hospital, and the Heart and Vascular Center Junior Faculty Award from Brigham and Women's Hospital. B.B. reports that he was a consulting expert, on behalf of the plaintiff, for litigation related to two specific brand models of inferior vena cava (IVC) filters. B.B. has not been involved in the litigation in 2022 to 2024 nor has he received any compensation in 2022 to 2024. B.B. reports that he is a member of the Medical Advisory Board for the North American Thrombosis Forum and serves in the Data Safety and Monitory Board of the NAIL-IT trial funded by the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, and Translational Sciences. B.B. is a collaborating consultant with the International Consulting Associates and the U.S. Food and Drug Administration in a study to generate knowledge about utilization, predictors, retrieval, and safety of IVC filters. Other authors disclose no potential conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39419078</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1055/s-0044-1791817</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>