<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39429046</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1747-0080</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>21</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Nutrition &amp; dietetics : the journal of the Dietitians Association of Australia</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Nutr Diet</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Risk of poor nutritional status and nutrition-related complaints in individuals attending a primary care dietitian after a COVID-19 infection: A prospective cohort study.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1747-0080.12905</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="AIMS" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To report the changes in nutritional status, nutrition-related complaints and risk of sarcopenia in individuals attending a primary care dietitian in the Netherlands after a COVID-19 infection.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">The study was registered on the clinicaltrials.gov registry (NCT04735744). Nutritional status and nutrition-related complaints were assessed with the Patient-Generated Subjective Global Assessment Short Form and body composition measurements when possible. Risk of sarcopenia was assessed with the Strength, Assistance with walking, Rise from a chair, Climb stairs and Falls questionnaire. Dietitians reported on treatment goals, content and volume of dietetic treatment. Descriptive statistics were used to describe the study population and outcomes at baseline and end of treatment. For continuous variables, paired samples t-tests were used to compare scores at the start and the end of dietetic treatment. For dichotomous variables. McNemar tests and Wilcoxon signed-rank tests were used to determine differences between the start and end of treatment.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">A total of 222 participants were included [mean age 50 (SD 13), 58% female, 34% overweight, 40% obese]. Malnutrition risk decreased from 44% (medium risk) and 20% (high risk) to 29% and 12% by the end of treatment (p &lt; 0.001). The risk of sarcopenia decreased from 31% to 22% (p &lt; 0.001). There was an imbalance between fat-free mass and fat mass in about half of the participants. The most commonly reported nutrition-related complaints were fatigue, no appetite, the feeling of being full and changed or loss of taste. Median treatment duration was 21 weeks [interquartile range (IQR) 13-26] and 5 consultations (IQR 4-7). Most participants (46%) aimed to maintain weight, with others aiming to lose (14%) or gain (14%) weight. At the end of treatment, 57% had achieved the goals.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Significant improvements in nutritional status and risk of sarcopenia were observed after dietetic treatment in primary care, and most participants achieved the treatment goals. Nevertheless, nutrition-related complaints and the risk of malnutrition or sarcopenia remained prevalent.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Nutrition &amp; Dietetics published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd on behalf of Dietitians Australia.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Slotegraaf</LastName><ForeName>Anne I</ForeName><Initials>AI</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7162-5348</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Human Nutrition and Health, Wageningen University and Research, Wageningen, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kruizenga</LastName><ForeName>Hinke M</ForeName><Initials>HM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9250-6970</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Amsterdam UMC location Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam, Department of Nutrition &amp; Dietetics, Amsterdam Movement Sciences, Aging and Vitality, Amsterdam, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Sports and Nutrition, Amsterdam University of Applied Sciences, Amsterdam, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gerards</LastName><ForeName>Marissa H G</ForeName><Initials>MHG</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7388-2356</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, Care and Public Health Institute (CAPHRI), Faculty of Health, Medicine and Life Sciences, Maastricht University, Maastricht, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physiotherapy, Maastricht University Medical Centre, Maastricht, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Verburg</LastName><ForeName>Arie C</ForeName><Initials>AC</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4068-8228</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>IQ Healthcare, Radboud University Medical Centre, Nijmegen, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hoogeboom</LastName><ForeName>Thomas J</ForeName><Initials>TJ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2103-419X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>IQ Healthcare, Radboud University Medical Centre, Nijmegen, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>de van der Schueren</LastName><ForeName>Marian A E</ForeName><Initials>MAE</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5693-0811</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Human Nutrition and Health, Wageningen University and Research, Wageningen, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nutrition, Dietetics and Lifestyle, HAN University of Applied Sciences, Nijmegen, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><CollectiveName>Dutch Consortium Allied Healthcare COVID‐19</CollectiveName></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><DataBankList CompleteYN="Y"><DataBank><DataBankName>ClinicalTrials.gov</DataBankName><AccessionNumberList><AccessionNumber>NCT04735744</AccessionNumber></AccessionNumberList></DataBank></DataBankList><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Maastricht University</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>10390062010001</GrantID><Acronym>ZONMW_</Acronym><Agency>ZonMw</Agency><Country>Netherlands</Country></Grant><Grant><Agency>Stichting Revalidatie en Wetenschap</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Nivel Netherlands Institute for Health Services Research</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Association for Quality in Physcial Therapy</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>Royal Dutch Society for Physiotherapy</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Australia</Country><MedlineTA>Nutr Diet</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101143078</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1446-6368</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">dietitian</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nutritional status</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nutrition‐related complaints</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">primary care</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39429046</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1747-0080.12905</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Ballering AV, van Zon S, Olde Hartman TC, Rosmalen JGM, Lifelines Corona Research Initiative. Persistence of somatic symptoms after COVID‐19 in the Netherlands: an observational cohort study. Lancet. 2022;400(10350):452‐461.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brugliera L, Spina A, Castellazzi P, et al. Nutritional management of COVID‐19 patients in a rehabilitation unit. Eur J Clin Nutr. 2020;74(6):860‐863.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Di Filippo L, De Lorenzo R, D'Amico M, et al. COVID‐19 is associated with clinically significant weight loss and risk of malnutrition, independent of hospitalisation: a post‐hoc analysis of a prospective cohort study. Clin Nutr. 2021;40(4):2420‐2426.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gérard M, Mahmutovic M, Malgras A, et al. Long‐term evolution of malnutrition and loss of muscle strength after COVID‐19: a major and neglected component of long COVID‐19. Nutrients. 2021;13(11):3964.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tosato M, Calvani R, Ciciarello F, et al. Malnutrition in COVID‐19 survivors: prevalence and risk factors. Aging Clin Exp Res. 2023;35(10):2257‐2265.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grund S, Bauer JM. Malnutrition and sarcopenia in COVID‐19 survivors. Clin Geriatr Med. 2022;38(3):559‐564.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morley JE, Kalantar‐Zadeh K, Anker SD. COVID‐19: a major cause of cachexia and sarcopenia? J Cachexia Sarcopenia Muscle. 2020;11(4):863‐865.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Slotegraaf AI, de van der Schueren MAE, Wierdsma NJ, Weijs PJM, Kruizenga HM. Nutritional problems of patients with COVID‐19 receiving dietetic treatment in primary care. J Hum Nutr Diet. 2023;36(1):20‐30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Welch C, Greig C, Masud T, Wilson D, Jackson TA. COVID‐19 and acute sarcopenia. Aging Dis. 2020;11(6):1345‐1351.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wierdsma NJ, Kruizenga HM, Konings LAML, et al. Poor nutritional status, risk of sarcopenia and nutrition related complaints are prevalent in COVID‐19 patients during and after hospital admission. Clinical Nutrition ESPEN. 2021;43:369‐376.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santilli V, Bernetti A, Mangone M, Paoloni M. Clinical definition of sarcopenia. Clin Cases Miner Bone Metab. 2014;11(3):177‐180.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anker MS, Landmesser U, von Haehling S, Butler J, Coats AJS, Anker SD. Weight loss, malnutrition, and cachexia in COVID‐19: facts and numbers. J Cachexia Sarcopenia Muscle. 2021;12:9‐13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Meij BS, Ligthart‐Melis GC, de van der Schueren MA. Malnutrition in patients with COVID‐19: assessment and consequences. Curr Opin Clin Nutr Metab Care. 2021;24(6):543‐554.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soares MN, Eggelbusch M, Naddaf E, et al. Skeletal muscle alterations in patients with acute Covid‐19 and post‐acute sequelae of Covid‐19. J Cachexia Sarcopenia Muscle. 2022;13(1):11‐22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barazzoni R, Bischoff SC, Breda J, et al. ESPEN expert statements and practical guidance for nutritional management of individuals with SARS‐CoV‐2 infection. Clin Nutr. 2020;39:1631‐1638.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blomberg B, Mohn KGI, Brokstad KA, et al. Long COVID in a prospective cohort of home‐isolated patients. Nat Med. 2021;27(9):1607‐1613.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee Y, Min P, Lee S, Kim SW. Prevalence and duration of acute loss of smell or taste in COVID‐19 patients. J Korean Med Sci. 2020;35(18):e174.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beaudart C, McCloskey E, Bruyère O, et al. Sarcopenia in daily practice: assessment and management. BMC Geriatr. 2016;16:170.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reber E, Gomes F, Vasiloglou MF, Schuetz P, Stanga Z. Nutritional risk screening and assessment. J Clin Med. 2019;8(7):1065.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nederlandse Vereniging van Diëtisten. Behandelplan van diëtist binnen paramedische herstelzorg COVID‐19. 2021. https://nvdietist.nl/artikelen/behandelplan-van-dietist-binnen-paramedische-herstelzorg-covid-19/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zorginstituut Nederland. Paramedische herstelzorg na COVID‐19. 2024. https://www.zorginstituutnederland.nl/Verzekerde+zorg/paramedische-herstelzorg-na-covid-19</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Bie R, Verburg AC, Agasi‐Idenburg C, et al. Evaluation of allied healthcare in patients recovering from Covid‐19: study protocol and baseline data of a National Prospective Cohort Study. J Rehabil Med. 2022;54:jrm00309.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Slotegraaf AI, Gerards MHG, Verburg AC, et al. Evaluation of primary allied health Care in Patients Recovering from COVID‐19 at 6‐month follow‐up: Dutch Nationwide prospective cohort study. JMIR Public Health Surveill. 2023;9(1):e44155.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Slotegraaf AI, de Kruif AJTCM, Agasi‐Idenburg CS, et al. Understanding recovery of people recovering from COVID‐19 receiving treatment from primary care allied health professionals: a mixed‐methods study. Disabil Rehabil. 2024:1‐10. doi:10.1080/09638288.2024.2311330</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Body Mass Index—BMI. https://www.who.int/europe/news-room/fact-sheets/item/a-healthy-lifestyle---who-recommendations</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Post MW, van der Zee CH, Hennink J, Schafrat CG, Visser‐Meily JMA, van Berlekom SB. Validity of the utrecht scale for evaluation of rehabilitation‐participation. Disabil Rehabil. 2012;34(6):478‐485.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herdman M, Gudex C, Lloyd A, et al. Development and preliminary testing of the new five‐level version of EQ‐5D (EQ‐5D‐5L). Qual Life Res. 2011;20(10):1727‐1736.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zanini A, Aiello M, Adamo D, et al. Estimation of minimal clinically important difference in EQ‐5D visual analog scale score after pulmonary rehabilitation in subjects with COPD. Respir Care. 2015;60(1):88‐95.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valko PO, Bassetti CL, Bloch KE, Held U, Baumann CR. Validation of the Fatigue Severity Scale in a Swiss cohort. Sleep. 2008;31(11):1601‐1607.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Terwee C, Roorda LD, de Vet HC, et al. Dutch‐Flemish translation of 17 item banks from the patient‐reported outcomes measurement information system (PROMIS). Qual Life Res. 2014;23(6):1733‐1741.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Snaith RP. The hospital anxiety and depression scale. Health Qual Life Outcomes. 2003;1:29.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zigmond AS, Snaith RP. The hospital anxiety and depression scale. Acta Psychiatr Scand. 1983;67(6):361‐370.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kruizenga HM, Hofsteenge GH, Weijs PJ. Predicting resting energy expenditure in underweight, normal weight, overweight, and obese adult hospital patients. Nutr Metab. 2016;13(1):85.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joint F, WHO. Protein and Amino Acid Requirements in Human Nutrition: Report of a Joint FAO/WHO/UNU Expert Consultation. World Health Organization; 2007.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gallagher D, Heymsfield SB, Heo M, Jebb SA, Murgatroyd PR, Sakamoto Y. Healthy percentage body fat ranges: an approach for developing guidelines based on body mass index. Am J Clin Nutr. 2000;72(3):694‐701.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sealy MJ, Haß U, Ottery FD, van der Schans CP, Roodenburg JLN, Jager‐Wittenaar H. Translation and cultural adaptation of the scored patient‐generated subjective global assessment: an interdisciplinary nutritional instrument appropriate for Dutch cancer patients. Cancer Nurs. 2018;41(6):450‐462.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jager‐Wittenaar H, Ottery FD. Assessing nutritional status in cancer: role of the patient‐generated subjective global assessment. Curr Opin Clin Nutr Metab Care. 2017;20(5):322‐329.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abbott J, Teleni L, McKavanagh D, Watson J, McCarthy AL, Isenring E. Patient‐generated subjective global assessment short form (PG‐SGA SF) is a valid screening tool in chemotherapy outpatients. Support Care Cancer. 2016;24:3883‐3887.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Visser M, Schaap LA, Hobbelen JSM, Perkisas S, Sipers WMWH. Sarcopenie: screening en diagnose. Ned Tijdschr Geneeskd. 2020;164(1):1‐7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woo J, Leung J, Morley JE. Validating the SARC‐F: a suitable community screening tool for sarcopenia? J Am Med Dir Assoc. 2014;15(9):630‐634.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rutten EP, Spruit MA, Wouters EF. Critical view on diagnosing muscle wasting by single‐frequency bio‐electrical impedance in COPD. Respir Med. 2010;104(1):91‐98.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kyle UG, Genton L, Slosman DO, Pichard C. Fat‐free and fat mass percentiles in 5225 healthy subjects aged 15 to 98 years. Nutrition. 2001;17(7–8):534‐541.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schutz Y, Kyle U, Pichard C. Fat‐free mass index and fat mass index percentiles in Caucasians aged 18–98 y. Int J Obes. 2002;26(7):953‐960.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao J, Purcell SA, Prado CM, Gonzalez MC. Fat mass to fat‐free mass ratio reference values from NHANES III using bioelectrical impedance analysis. Clin Nutr. 2018;37(6):2284‐2287.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cappellari GG, Guillet C, Poggiogalle E, et al. Sarcopenic obesity research perspectives outlined by the sarcopenic obesity global leadership initiative (SOGLI)–proceedings from the SOGLI consortium meeting in Rome November 2022. Clin Nutr. 2023;42(5):687‐699.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stubbs RJ, Hughes DA, Johnstone AM, et al. The use of visual analogue scales to assess motivation to eat in human subjects: a review of their reliability and validity with an evaluation of new hand‐held computerized systems for temporal tracking of appetite ratings. Br J Nutr. 2000;84(4):405‐415.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blauwhoff‐Buskermolen S, Ruijgrok C, Ostelo RW, et al. The assessment of anorexia in patients with cancer: cut‐off values for the FAACT–A/CS and the VAS for appetite. Support Care Cancer. 2016;24:661‐666.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lewis SJ, Heaton KW. Stool form scale as a useful guide to intestinal transit time. Scand J Gastroenterol. 1997;32(9):920‐924.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pironi L, Sasdelli AS, Ravaioli F, et al. Malnutrition and nutritional therapy in patients with SARS‐CoV‐2 disease. Clin Nutr. 2021;40(3):1330‐1337.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martone AM, Tosato M, Ciciarello F, et al. Sarcopenia as potential biological substrate of long COVID‐19 syndrome: prevalence, clinical features, and risk factors. J Cachexia Sarcopenia Muscle. 2022;13(4):1974‐1982.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dent E, Morley JE, Cruz‐Jentoft AJ, et al. International clinical practice guidelines for sarcopenia (ICFSR): screening, diagnosis and management. J Nutr Health Aging. 2018;22(10):1148‐1161.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Del Giorno R, Quarenghi M, Stefanelli K, et al. Nutritional risk screening and body composition in COVID‐19 patients hospitalized in an internal medicine ward. Int J Gen Med. 2020;13:1643‐1651.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kellnar A, Hoppe JM, Brunner S, Stremmel C. Hospitalization for COVID‐19 is associated with significant changes in body composition. Clin Nutr ESPEN. 2021;45:499‐502.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moonen HPFX, van Zanten F, Driessen L, et al. Association of bioelectric impedance analysis body composition and disease severity in COVID‐19 hospital ward and ICU patients: the BIAC‐19 study. Clin Nutr. 2021;40(4):2328‐2336.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lechien JR, Chiesa‐Estomba CM, Hans S, Barillari MR, Jouffe L, Saussez S. Loss of smell and taste in 2013 European patients with mild to moderate COVID‐19. Ann Intern Med. 2020;173(8):672‐675.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tran V‐T, Porcher R, Pane I, Ravaud P. Course of post COVID‐19 disease symptoms over time in the ComPaRe long COVID prospective e‐cohort. Nat Commun. 2022;13(1):1812.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burges Watson DL, Campbell M, Hopkins C, Smith B, Kelly C, Deary V. Altered smell and taste: anosmia, parosmia and the impact of long Covid‐19. PLoS One. 2021;16(9):e0256998.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen NN, Hoang VT, Dao TL, Dudouet P, Eldin C, Gautret P. Clinical patterns of somatic symptoms in patients suffering from post‐acute long COVID: a systematic review. Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis. 2022;41(4):515‐545.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D'amico F, Baumgart DC, Danese S, Peyrin‐Biroulet L. Diarrhea during COVID‐19 infection: pathogenesis, epidemiology, prevention, and management. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2020;18(8):1663‐1672.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan L, Mu M, Yang P, et al. Clinical characteristics of COVID‐19 patients with digestive symptoms in Hubei, China: a descriptive, cross‐sectional, multicenter study. Am J Gastroenterol. 2020;115:766‐773.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blackett JW, Li J, Jodorkovsky D, Freedberg DE. Prevalence and risk factors for gastrointestinal symptoms after recovery from COVID‐19. Neurogastroenterol Motil. 2022;34(3):e14251.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yusuf F, Fahriani M, Mamada SS, et al. Global prevalence of prolonged gastrointestinal symptoms in COVID‐19 survivors and potential pathogenesis: a systematic review and meta‐analysis. F1000Res. 2021;10:301.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zinger N, Meijer W. Zorg door de diëtist in de eerste lijn: jaarcijfers 2021 en trendcijfers 2019–2021. Nivel; 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meijer WM, Beekers P, van Dongen J, de Bie R. Paramedische herstelzorg na COVID‐19: verloop van mono‐en multidiscipliniaire behandelingen over de tijd. Nivel; 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. Post COVID‐19 condition (Long COVID). 2022. https://www.who.int/europe/news‐room/fact‐sheets/item/post‐covid‐19‐condition#:~:text=Definition,months%20with%20no%20other%20explanation</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>