<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39426285</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1873-2518</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>42</Volume><Issue>26</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>18</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Vaccine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Vaccine</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The risk of postherpetic neuralgia in COVID-19 vaccination-associated herpes zoster: A retrospective cohort study using TriNetX.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>126451</StartPage><MedlinePgn>126451</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.vaccine.2024.126451</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0264-410X(24)01133-2</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The administration of the COVID-19 vaccine has been linked to the development of herpes zoster (HZ). However, studies examining the clinical outcomes in COVID-19 vaccination-associated and non-COVID-19 vaccination-associated HZ are lacking.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To investigate the risk of postherpetic neuralgia (PHN) in COVID-19 vaccination associated HZ.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A total of 7200 patients with COVID-19 vaccination-associated HZ and 7200 matched controls were enrolled from the US Collaborative Network in the TriNetX database. The main outcome of this study was the development of PHN. Patients were followed-up from 3 months after HZ until PHN diagnoses, withdrawal from the database, or October 8, 2024.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">We observed that patients with COVID-19 vaccination-associated HZ had a significantly higher risk of developing PHN as compared to the control group, with hazard ratio of 1.69 (&gt; 3 months), 1.80 (&gt; 6 months), 1.86 (&gt; 1 year), and 1.93 (&gt;2 years), respectively. Additionally, the association remained significant in the stratified analysis, which included sex, age, malignancy status, and initial use of antiviral agents.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">This study showed that COVID-19 vaccination-associated HZ demonstrated a significantly higher risk of developing PHN.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024. Published by Elsevier Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ma</LastName><ForeName>Sheng-Hsiang</ForeName><Initials>SH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Public Health and Department of Public Health, National Yang Ming Chiao Tung University, Taipei, Taiwan; Department of Dermatology, Taipei Veterans General Hospital, Taipei, Taiwan; Faculty of Medicine, School of Medicine, National Yang Ming Chiao Tung University, Taipei, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Tai-Li</ForeName><Initials>TL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Public Health and Department of Public Health, National Yang Ming Chiao Tung University, Taipei, Taiwan; Department of Dermatology, Taipei Veterans General Hospital, Taipei, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ou</LastName><ForeName>Wei-Fan</ForeName><Initials>WF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Chest Medicine, Department of Internal Medicine, Taichung Veterans General Hospital, Taichung, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chao</LastName><ForeName>Wen-Cheng</ForeName><Initials>WC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Critical Care Medicine, Taichung Veterans General Hospital, Taichung, Taiwan; Department of Post-Baccalaureate Medicine, College of Medicine, National Chung Hsing University, Taichung, Taiwan; Big Data Center, Chung Hsing University, Taichung, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Hsin-Hua</ForeName><Initials>HH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine, School of Medicine, National Yang Ming Chiao Tung University, Taipei, Taiwan; Big Data Center, Chung Hsing University, Taichung, Taiwan; Division of Allergy, Immunology and Rheumatology, Department of Internal Medicine, Taichung Veterans General Hospital, Taichung, Taiwan; Division of General Medicine, Department of Internal Medicine, Taichung Veterans General Hospital, Taichung, Taiwan; Institute of Biomedical Science and Rong Hsing Research Centre for Translational Medicine, Chung Hsing University, Taichung, Taiwan; Department of Industrial Engineering and Enterprise Information, Tunghai University, Taichung, Taiwan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wu</LastName><ForeName>Chen-Yi</ForeName><Initials>CY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Public Health and Department of Public Health, National Yang Ming Chiao Tung University, Taipei, Taiwan; Department of Dermatology, Taipei Veterans General Hospital, Taipei, Taiwan; Faculty of Medicine, School of Medicine, National Yang Ming Chiao Tung University, Taipei, Taiwan; Health Innovation Center, National Yang Ming Chiao Tung University, Taipei, Taiwan. Electronic address: chenyiok@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Vaccine</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8406899</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0264-410X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19 vaccination</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Cohort study</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Herpes zoster</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Postherpetic neuralgia</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">TriNetX database</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare the following financial interests/personal relationships which may be considered as potential competing interests: Dr. Chen-Yi Wu has made payments to Ministry of Science and Technology, Taiwan and Taipei Veterans General Hospital.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>9</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39426285</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2024.126451</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0264-410X(24)01133-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>