<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39425883</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1469-7793</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>19</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Journal of physiology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Physiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The role of platelets and megakaryocytes in sepsis and ARDS.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1113/JP284879</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Since the global COVID-19 pandemic, there has been a renewed focus on lung injury during infection. Systemic inflammatory responses such as acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) and sepsis are a leading cause of morbidity and mortality for both adults and children. Improvements in clinical care have improved outcomes but mortality remains ∼40% and significant morbidity persists for those patients with severe disease. Mechanistic studies of the underlying biological processes remain essential to identifying therapeutic targets. Furthermore, methods for identifying the underlying drivers of organ failure are key to treating and preventing tissue injury. In this review, we discuss the contribution of megakaryocytes (MKs) and platelets to the pathogenesis of systemic inflammatory syndromes. We explore the role of MKs and the new identification of extramedullary MKs during sepsis. We describe the alterations in the platelet transcriptome during sepsis. Lastly, we explore platelet function as defined by aggregation, activation and the formation of heterotypic aggregates. Much more work is necessary to explore the contribution of platelets to these heterogenous syndromes, but the foundation of platelets as key contributors to inflammation has been laid.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). The Journal of Physiology published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of The Physiological Society.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Leung</LastName><ForeName>Gabriel</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Pulmonary, Department of Internal Medicine, University of Utah, Salt Lake City, Utah, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Middleton</LastName><ForeName>Elizabeth A</ForeName><Initials>EA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5120-8202</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Pulmonary, Department of Internal Medicine, University of Utah, Salt Lake City, Utah, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Molecular Medicine Program, University of Utah, Salt Lake City, Utah, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>5K08HL153953</GrantID><Agency>HHS | NIH | National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>(T32) HL105321</GrantID><Agency>HHS | NIH | National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Physiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0266262</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-3751</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ARDS</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">immunothrombosis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">megakaryocyte</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">platelet</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sepsis</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>16</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>16</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>25</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39425883</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1113/JP284879</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>Ackermann, M., Verleden, S. E., Kuehnel, M., Haverich, A., Welte, T., Laenger, F., Vanstapel, A., Werlein, C., Stark, H., Tzankov, A., Li, W. W., Li, V. W., Mentzer, S. J., &amp; Jonigk, D. (2020). Pulmonary vascular endothelialitis, thrombosis, and angiogenesis in Covid‐19. New England Journal of Medicine, 383(2), 120–128.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akashi, K., Traver, D., Miyamoto, T., &amp; Weissman, I. L. (2000). A clonogenic common myeloid progenitor that gives rise to all myeloid lineages. Nature, 404(6774), 193–197.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allen, N., Barrett, T. J., Guo, Y., Nardi, M., Ramkhelawon, B., Rockman, C. B., Hochman, J. S., &amp; Berger, J. S. (2019). Circulating monocyte‐platelet aggregates are a robust marker of platelet activity in cardiovascular disease. Atherosclerosis, 282, 11–18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allie, S. R., Bradley, J. E., Mudunuru, U., Schultz, M. D., Graf, B. A., Lund, F. E., &amp; Randall, T. D. (2019). The establishment of resident memory B cells in the lung requires local antigen encounter. Nature Immunology, 20(1), 97–108.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arman, M., &amp; Krauel, K. (2015). Human platelet IgG Fc receptor FcgammaRIIA in immunity and thrombosis. Journal of Thrombosis and Haemostasis, 13(6), 893–908.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asquith, N. L., Carminita, E., Camacho, V., Rodriguez‐Romera, A., Stegner, D., Freire, D., Becker, I. C., Machlus, K. R., Khan, A. O., &amp; Italiano, J. E. (2024). The bone marrow is the primary site of thrombopoiesis. Blood, 143(3), 272–278.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Assinger, A. (2014). Platelets and infection – an emerging role of platelets in viral infection. Frontiers in Immunology, 5, 649.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Assinger, A., Schrottmaier, W. C., Salzmann, M., &amp; Rayes, J. (2019). Platelets in sepsis: An update on experimental models and clinical data. Frontiers in Immunology, 10, 1687.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barratt, S., Medford, A. R., &amp; Millar, A. B. (2014). Vascular endothelial growth factor in acute lung injury and acute respiratory distress syndrome. Respiration, 87(4), 329–342.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beaulieu, L. M., Lin, E., Mick, E., Koupenova, M., Weinberg, E. O., Kramer, C. D., Genco, C. A., Tanriverdi, K., Larson, M. G., Benjamin, E. J., &amp; Freedman, J. E. (2014). Interleukin 1 receptor 1 and interleukin 1beta regulate megakaryocyte maturation, platelet activation, and transcript profile during inflammation in mice and humans. Arteriosclerosis, Thrombosis, and Vascular Biology, 34(3), 552–564.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beristain‐Covarrubias, N., Perez‐Toledo, M., Thomas, M. R., Henderson, I. R., Watson, S. P., &amp; Cunningham, A. F. (2019). Understanding infection‐induced thrombosis: Lessons learned from animal models. Frontiers in Immunology, 10, 2569.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonaventura, A., Vecchie, A., Dagna, L., Martinod, K., Dixon, D. L., Van Tassell, B. W., Dentali, F., Montecucco, F., Massberg, S., Levi, M., &amp; Abbate, A. (2021). Endothelial dysfunction and immunothrombosis as key pathogenic mechanisms in COVID‐19. Nature Reviews Immunology, 21(5), 319–329.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boyes, D., Holland, P. W. H., &amp; University of Oxford and Wytham Woods Genome Acquisition Lab, Darwin Tree of Life Barcoding collective, Wellcome Sanger Institute Tree of Life programme, Wellcome Sanger Institute Scientific Operations: DNA Pipelines collective, Tree of Life Core Informatics collective, &amp; Darwin Tree of Life Consortium. (2023). The genome sequence of the Red‐green Carpet, Chloroclysta siterata (Hufnagel, 1767). Wellcome Open Research, 8, 206.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bray, P. F., McKenzie, S. E., Edelstein, L. C., Nagalla, S., Delgrosso, K., Ertel, A., Kupper, J., Jing, Y., Londin, E., Loher, P., Chen, H. W., Fortina, P., &amp; Rigoutsos, I. (2013). The complex transcriptional landscape of the anucleate human platelet. BioMed Central Genomics [Electronic Resource], 14, 1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campbell, R. A., Manne, B. K., Banerjee, M., Middleton, E. A., Ajanel, A., Schwertz, H., Denorme, F., Stubben, C., Montenont, E., Saperstein, S., Page, L., Tolley, N. D., Lim, D. L., Brown, S. M., Grissom, C. K., Sborov, D. W., Krishnan, A., &amp; Rondina, M. T. (2022). IFITM3 regulates fibrinogen endocytosis and platelet reactivity in nonviral sepsis. Journal of Clinical Investigation, 132(23), e153014.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campbell, R. A., Schwertz, H., Hottz, E. D., Rowley, J. W., Manne, B. K., Washington, A. V., Hunter‐Mellado, R., Tolley, N. D., Christensen, M., Eustes, A. S., Montenont, E., Bhatlekar, S., Ventrone, C. H., Kirkpatrick, B. D., Pierce, K. K., Whitehead, S. S., Diehl, S. A., Bray, P. F., Zimmerman, G. A., … Rondina, M. T. (2019). Human megakaryocytes possess intrinsic antiviral immunity through regulated induction of IFITM3. Blood, 133(19), 2013–2026.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Camprubi‐Rimblas, M., Tantinya, N., Guillamat‐Prats, R., Bringue, J., Puig, F., Gomez, M. N., Blanch, L., &amp; Artigas, A. (2020). Effects of nebulized antithrombin and heparin on inflammatory and coagulation alterations in an acute lung injury model in rats. Journal of Thrombosis and Haemostasis, 18(3), 571–583.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao, Y., Ma, W., Liu, Z., Pei, Y., Zhu, Y., Chen, F., Zou, L., Jiang, Y., Liu, X., Huang, J., Xiao, W., &amp; Han, X. (2022). Early predictive value of platelet function for clinical outcome in sepsis. Journal of Infection, 84(5), 628–636.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caudrillier, A., Kessenbrock, K., Gilliss, B. M., Nguyen, J. X., Marques, M. B., Monestier, M., Toy, P., Werb, Z., &amp; Looney, M. R. (2012). Platelets induce neutrophil extracellular traps in transfusion‐related acute lung injury. Journal of Clinical Investigation, 122(7), 2661–2671.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Claushuis, T. A., van Vught, L. A., Scicluna, B. P., Wiewel, M. A., Klein Klouwenberg, P. M., Hoogendijk, A. J., Ong, D. S., Cremer, O. L., Horn, J., Franitza, M., Toliat, M. R., Nurnberg, P., Zwinderman, A. H., Bonten, M. J., Schultz, M. J., van der Poll, T., Molecular, D., &amp; Risk Stratification of Sepsis C. (2016). Thrombocytopenia is associated with a dysregulated host response in critically ill sepsis patients. Blood, 127(24), 3062–3072.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cremer, M., Weimann, A., Szekessy, D., Hammer, H., Buhrer, C., &amp; Dame, C. (2013). Low immature platelet fraction suggests decreased megakaryopoiesis in neonates with sepsis or necrotizing enterocolitis. Journal of Perinatology, 33(8), 622–626.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crowl, J. T., Heeg, M., Ferry, A., Milner, J. J., Omilusik, K. D., Toma, C., He, Z., Chang, J. T., &amp; Goldrath, A. W. (2022). Tissue‐resident memory CD8(+) T cells possess unique transcriptional, epigenetic and functional adaptations to different tissue environments. Nature Immunology, 23(7), 1121–1131.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Czyz, A., Kolacz, E., Angerer, D., &amp; Zawilska, K. (2005). Expression of activation antigens on lymphocyte surface and circulating platelet‐leukocyte aggregates in ischaemic heart disease. Kardiologia Polska, 62(3), 189–200; discussion 201.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dolmatova, E. V., Wang, K., Mandavilli, R., &amp; Griendling, K. K. (2021). The effects of sepsis on endothelium and clinical implications. Cardiovascular Research, 117(1), 60–73.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dor, F. J., Ramirez, M. L., Parmar, K., Altman, E. L., Huang, C. A., Down, J. D., &amp; Cooper, D. K. (2006). Primitive hematopoietic cell populations reside in the spleen: Studies in the pig, baboon, and human. Experimental Hematology, 34(11), 1573–1582.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duerschmied, D., Bode, C., &amp; Ahrens, I. (2014). Immune functions of platelets. Thrombosis and Haemostasis, 112(4), 678–691.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Engelmann, B., &amp; Massberg, S. (2013). Thrombosis as an intravascular effector of innate immunity. Nature Reviews Immunology, 13(1), 34–45.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernandez‐Garcia, V., Gonzalez‐Ramos, S., Martin‐Sanz, P., Castrillo, A., &amp; Bosca, L. (2020). Contribution of extramedullary hematopoiesis to atherosclerosis. The spleen as a neglected hub of inflammatory cells. Frontiers in Immunology, 11, 586527.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Finsterbusch, M., Schrottmaier, W. C., Kral‐Pointner, J. B., Salzmann, M., &amp; Assinger, A. (2018). Measuring and interpreting platelet‐leukocyte aggregates. Platelets, 29(7), 677–685.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Francisco, J. S., Terra, M., Klein, G. C. T., Dias de Oliveira, B., &amp; Pelajo‐Machado, M. (2022). The hepatic extramedullary hematopoiesis during experimental murine Schistosomiasis mansoni. Frontiers in Immunology, 13, 955034.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gawaz, M., Fateh‐Moghadam, S., Pilz, G., Gurland, H. J., &amp; Werdan, K. (1995). Platelet activation and interaction with leucocytes in patients with sepsis or multiple organ failure. European Journal of Clinical Investigation, 25(11), 843–851.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gehr, P., Bachofen, M., &amp; Weibel, E. R. (1978). The normal human lung: Ultrastructure and morphometric estimation of diffusion capacity. Respiration Physiology, 32(2), 121–140.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gimbrone, M. A., Jr., Aster, R. H., Cotran, R. S., Corkery, J., Jandl, J. H., &amp; Folkman, J. (1969). Preservation of vascular integrity in organs perfused in vitro with a platelet‐rich medium. Nature, 222(5188), 33–36.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guilliams, M., De Kleer, I., Henri, S., Post, S., Vanhoutte, L., De Prijck, S., Deswarte, K., Malissen, B., Hammad, H., &amp; Lambrecht, B. N. (2013). Alveolar macrophages develop from fetal monocytes that differentiate into long‐lived cells in the first week of life via GM‐CSF. Journal of Experimental Medicine, 210(10), 1977–1992.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo, L., &amp; Rondina, M. T. (2019). The era of thromboinflammation: Platelets are dynamic sensors and effector cells during infectious diseases. Frontiers in Immunology, 10, 2204.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo, L., Shen, S., Rowley, J. W., Tolley, N. D., Jia, W., Manne, B. K., McComas, K. N., Bolingbroke, B., Kosaka, Y., Krauel, K., Denorme, F., Jacob, S. P., Eustes, A. S., Campbell, R. A., Middleton, E. A., He, X., Brown, S. M., Morrell, C. N., Weyrich, A. S., &amp; Rondina, M. T. (2021). Platelet MHC class I mediates CD8+ T‐cell suppression during sepsis. Blood, 138(5), 401–416.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ho‐Tin‐Noe, B., Demers, M., &amp; Wagner, D. D. (2011). How platelets safeguard vascular integrity. Journal of Thrombosis and Haemostasis, 9(Suppl 1), 56–65.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ho‐Tin‐Noe, B., &amp; Jadoui, S. (2018). Spontaneous bleeding in thrombocytopenia: Is it really spontaneous? Transfusion Clinique Et Biologique, 25(3), 210–216.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoffmeister, K. M., &amp; Falet, H. (2016). Platelet clearance by the hepatic Ashwell‐Morrell receptor: Mechanisms and biological significance. Thrombosis Research, 141(Suppl 2), S68–S72.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hottz, E. D., Martins‐Goncalves, R., Palhinha, L., Azevedo‐Quintanilha, I. G., de Campos, M. M., Sacramento, C. Q., Temerozo, J. R., Soares, V. C., Dias, S. S. G., Teixeira, L., Castro, I., Righy, C., Souza, T. M. L., Kurtz, P., Andrade, B. B., Nakaya, H. I., Monteiro, R. Q., Bozza, F. A., &amp; Bozza, P. T. (2022). Platelet‐monocyte interaction amplifies thromboinflammation through tissue factor signaling in COVID‐19. Blood Advances, 6(17), 5085–5099.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Howell, W. H., &amp; Donahue, D. D. (1937). The production of blood platelets in the lungs. Journal of Experimental Medicine, 65(2), 177–203.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang, Z., Lin, B., Han, D., Wang, X., Zhong, J., Wagenaar, G. T. M., Yang, C., &amp; Chen, X. (2022). Platelets are indispensable for alveolar development in neonatal mice. Frontiers in Pediatrics, 10, 943054.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iba, T., Levy, J. H., Warkentin, T. E., Thachil, J., van der Poll, T., Levi, M., &amp; Scientific and Standardization Committee on DIC, and the Scientific and Standardization Committee on Perioperative and Critical Care of the International Society on Thrombosis and Haemostasis. (2019). Diagnosis and management of sepsis‐induced coagulopathy and disseminated intravascular coagulation. Journal of Thrombosis and Haemostasis, 17(11), 1989–1994.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jentzer, J. C., Bhat, A. G., Patlolla, S. H., Sinha, S. S., Miller, P. E., Lawler, P. R., van Diepen, S., Khanna, A. K., Zhao, D. X., &amp; Vallabhajosyula, S. (2022). Concomitant sepsis diagnoses in acute myocardial infarction‐cardiogenic shock: 15‐year national temporal trends, management, and outcomes. Critical Care Explorations, 4(2), e0637.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang, J., Li, W., Zhou, L., Liu, D., Wang, Y., An, J., Qiao, S., &amp; Xie, Z. (2023). Platelet ITGA2B inhibits caspase‐8 and Rip3/Mlkl‐dependent platelet death though PTPN6 during sepsis. Iscience, 26(8), 107414.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Junt, T., Schulze, H., Chen, Z., Massberg, S., Goerge, T., Krueger, A., Wagner, D. D., Graf, T., Italiano, J. E., Jr., Shivdasani, R. A., &amp; von Andrian, U. H. (2007). Dynamic visualization of thrombopoiesis within bone marrow. Science, 317(5845), 1767–1770.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaiser, R., Escaig, R., Kranich, J., Hoffknecht, M. L., Anjum, A., Polewka, V., Mader, M., Hu, W., Belz, L., Gold, C., Titova, A., Lorenz, M., Pekayvaz, K., Kaab, S., Gaertner, F., Stark, K., Brocker, T., Massberg, S., &amp; Nicolai, L. (2022). Procoagulant platelet sentinels prevent inflammatory bleeding through GPIIBIIIA and GPVI. Blood, 140(2), 121–139.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaplan, D., Casper, T. C., Elliott, C. G., Men, S., Pendleton, R. C., Kraiss, L. W., Weyrich, A. S., Grissom, C. K., Zimmerman, G. A., &amp; Rondina, M. T. (2015). VTE incidence and risk factors in patients with severe sepsis and septic shock. Chest, 148(5), 1224–1230.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karnik, S. J., Nazzal, M. K., Kacena, M. A., &amp; Bruzzaniti, A. (2023). Megakaryocyte secreted factors regulate bone marrow niche cells during skeletal homeostasis, aging, and disease. Calcified Tissue International, 113(1), 83–95.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaser, A., Brandacher, G., Steurer, W., Kaser, S., Offner, F. A., Zoller, H., Theurl, I., Widder, W., Molnar, C., Ludwiczek, O., Atkins, M. B., Mier, J. W., &amp; Tilg, H. (2001). Interleukin‐6 stimulates thrombopoiesis through thrombopoietin: Role in inflammatory thrombocytosis. Blood, 98(9), 2720–2725.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaushansky, K. (2009). Determinants of platelet number and regulation of thrombopoiesis. Hematology‐American Society of Hematology‐Education Program, 147–152.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koupenova, M., Corkrey, H. A., Vitseva, O., Tanriverdi, K., Somasundaran, M., Liu, P., Soofi, S., Bhandari, R., Godwin, M., Parsi, K. M., Cousineau, A., Maehr, R., Wang, J. P., Cameron, S. J., Rade, J., Finberg, R. W., &amp; Freedman J. E. (2021). SARS‐CoV‐2 initiates programmed cell death in platelets. Circulation Research, 129(6), 631–646.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koupenova, M., Vitseva, O., MacKay, C. R., Beaulieu, L. M., Benjamin, E. J., Mick, E., Kurt‐Jones, E. A., Ravid, K., &amp; Freedman, J. E. (2014). Platelet‐TLR7 mediates host survival and platelet count during viral infection in the absence of platelet‐dependent thrombosis. Blood, 124(5), 791–802.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kreutz, R. P., Bliden, K. P., Tantry, U. S., &amp; Gurbel, P. A. (2005). Viral respiratory tract infections increase platelet reactivity and activation: An explanation for the higher rates of myocardial infarction and stroke during viral illness. Journal of Thrombosis and Haemostasis, 3(9), 2108–2109.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lefrancais, E., Ortiz‐Munoz, G., Caudrillier, A., Mallavia, B., Liu, F., Sayah, D. M., Thornton, E. E., Headley, M. B., David, T., Coughlin, S. R., Krummel, M. F., Leavitt, A. D., Passegue, E., &amp; Looney, M. R. (2017). The lung is a site of platelet biogenesis and a reservoir for haematopoietic progenitors. Nature, 544(7648), 105–109.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, M. F., Li, X. L., Fan, K. L., Yu, Y. Y., Gong, J., Geng, S. Y., Liang, Y. F., Huang, L., Qiu, J. H., Tian, X. H., Wang, W. T., Zhang, X. L., Yu, Q. X., Zhang, Y. F., Lin, P., Wang, L. N., Li, X., Hou, M., Liu, L. Y., &amp; Peng, J. (2017). Platelet desialylation is a novel mechanism and a therapeutic target in thrombocytopenia during sepsis: An open‐label, multicenter, randomized controlled trial. Journal of Hematology &amp; Oncology, 10(1), 104.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, N., Ji, Q., &amp; Hjemdahl, P. (2006). Platelet‐lymphocyte conjugation differs between lymphocyte subpopulations. Journal of Thrombosis and Haemostasis, 4(4), 874–881.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, T., Yang, Y., Li, Y., Wang, Z., Ma, F., Luo, R., Xu, X., Zhou, G., Wang, J., Niu, J., Lv, G., Crispe, I. N., &amp; Tu, Z. (2022). Platelets mediate inflammatory monocyte activation by SARS‐CoV‐2 spike protein. Journal of Clinical Investigation, 132(4), e150101.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lichtman, M. A., Chamberlain, J. K., Simon, W., &amp; Santillo, P. A. (1978). Parasinusoidal location of megakaryocytes in marrow: A determinant of platelet release. American Journal of Hematology, 4(4), 303–312.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ling, L., Zhang, J., Li, Y., Liu, C., Du, L., &amp; Zhou, J. (2023). Platelets play a dual role in the pathophysiology of transfusion‐related acute lung injury. Respiratory Physiology &amp; Neurobiology, 309, 104004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loffredo, L., Di Castelnuovo, A., Chiariello, G. A., Pignatelli, P., &amp; Violi, F. (2022). Full versus prophylactic‐intermediate doses of anticoagulants in COVID‐19: A meta‐analysis. Haematologica, 107(8), 1933–1939.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Majno, G., &amp; Palade, G. E. (1961). Studies on inflammation. 1. The effect of histamine and serotonin on vascular permeability: an electron microscopic study. The Journal of Biophysical and Biochemical Cytology, 11(3), 571–605.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mandal, R. V., Mark, E. J., &amp; Kradin, R. L. (2007). Megakaryocytes and platelet homeostasis in diffuse alveolar damage. Experimental and Molecular Pathology, 83(3), 327–331.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manne, B. K., Denorme, F., Middleton, E. A., Portier, I., Rowley, J. W., Stubben, C., Petrey, A. C., Tolley, N. D., Guo, L., Cody, M., Weyrich, A. S., Yost, C. C., Rondina, M. T., &amp; Campbell, R. A. (2020). Platelet gene expression and function in patients with COVID‐19. Blood, 136(11), 1317–1329.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marcos‐Jubilar, M., Lecumberri, R., &amp; Paramo, J. A. (2023). Immunothrombosis: Molecular aspects and new therapeutic perspectives. Journal of Clinical Medicine, 12(4), 1399.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martinod, K., &amp; Deppermann, C. (2021). Immunothrombosis and thromboinflammation in host defense and disease. Platelets, 32(3), 314–324.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McDonald, B., Davis, R. P., Kim, S. J., Tse, M., Esmon, C. T., Kolaczkowska, E., &amp; Jenne, C. N. (2017). Platelets and neutrophil extracellular traps collaborate to promote intravascular coagulation during sepsis in mice. Blood, 129(10), 1357–1367.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Medford, A. R., &amp; Millar, A. B. (2006). Vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) in acute lung injury (ALI) and acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS): Paradox or paradigm? Thorax, 61(7), 621–626.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Middleton, E., &amp; Rondina, M. T. (2016). Platelets in infectious disease. Hematology‐American Society of Hematology‐Education Program, 2016(1), 256–261.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Middleton, E. A., He, X. Y., Denorme, F., Campbell, R. A., Ng, D., Salvatore, S. P., Mostyka, M., Baxter‐Stoltzfus, A., Borczuk, A. C., Loda, M., Cody, M. J., Manne, B. K., Portier, I., Harris, E. S., Petrey, A. C., Beswick, E. J., Caulin, A. F., Iovino, A., Abegglen, L. M., … Yost, C. C. (2020). Neutrophil extracellular traps contribute to immunothrombosis in COVID‐19 acute respiratory distress syndrome. Blood, 136(10), 1169–1179.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Middleton, E. A., Rondina, M. T., Schwertz, H., &amp; Zimmerman, G. A. (2018). Amicus or adversary revisited: Platelets in acute lung injury and acute respiratory distress syndrome. American Journal of Respiratory Cell and Molecular Biology, 59(1), 18–35.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Middleton, E. A., Rowley, J. W., Campbell, R. A., Grissom, C. K., Brown, S. M., Beesley, S. J., Schwertz, H., Kosaka, Y., Manne, B. K., Krauel, K., Tolley, N. D., Eustes, A. S., Guo, L., Paine, R., 3rd, Harris, E. S., Zimmerman, G. A., Weyrich, A. S., &amp; Rondina, M. T. (2019). Sepsis alters the transcriptional and translational landscape of human and murine platelets. Blood, 134(12), 911–923.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Middleton, E. A., Weyrich, A. S., &amp; Zimmerman, G. A. (2016). Platelets in pulmonary immune responses and inflammatory lung diseases. Physiological Reviews, 96(4), 1211–1259.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nagasawa, A., Matsuno, K., Tamura, S., Hayasaka, K., Shimizu, C., &amp; Moriyama, T. (2013). The basis examination of leukocyte‐platelet aggregates with CD45 gating as a novel platelet activation marker. International Journal of Laboratory Hematology, 35(5), 534–541.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nicolai, L., Leunig, A., Brambs, S., Kaiser, R., Joppich, M., Hoffknecht, M. L., Gold, C., Engel, A., Polewka, V., Muenchhoff, M., Hellmuth, J. C., Ruhle, A., Ledderose, S., Weinberger, T., Schulz, H., Scherer, C., Rudelius, M., Zoller, M., Keppler, O. T., … Stark, K. (2021). Vascular neutrophilic inflammation and immunothrombosis distinguish severe COVID‐19 from influenza pneumonia. Journal of Thrombosis and Haemostasis, 19(2), 574–581.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nicolai, L., Schiefelbein, K., Lipsky, S., Leunig, A., Hoffknecht, M., Pekayvaz, K., Raude, B., Marx, C., Ehrlich, A., Pircher, J., Zhang, Z., Saleh, I., Marel, A. K., Lof, A., Petzold, T., Lorenz, M., Stark, K., Pick, R., Rosenberger, G., … Gaertner, F. (2020). Vascular surveillance by haptotactic blood platelets in inflammation and infection. Nature Communications, 11(1), 5778.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nicolai, L., Schiefelbein, K., Lipsky, S., Leunig, A., Hoffknecht, M., Pekayvaz, K., Raude, B., Marx, C., Ehrlich, A., Pircher, J., Zhang, Z., Saleh, I., Marel, A. K., Lof, A., Petzold, T., Lorenz, M., Stark, K., Pick, R., Rosenberger, G., … Gaertner, F. (2022). Author correction: Vascular surveillance by haptotactic blood platelets in inflammation and infection. Nature Communications, 13(1), 4645.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palankar, R., &amp; Greinacher, A. (2019). Challenging the concept of immunothrombosis. Blood, 133(6), 508–509.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paletta, A., Di Diego Garcia, F., Varese, A., Erra Diaz, F., Garcia, J., Cisneros, J. C., Luduena, G., Mazzitelli, I., Pisarevsky, A., Cabrerizo, G., Lopez Malizia, A., Rodriguez, A. G., Lista, N., Longueira, Y., Sabatte, J., Geffner, J., Remes Lenicov, F., &amp; Ceballos A. (2022). Platelets modulate CD4(+) T‐cell function in COVID‐19 through a PD‐L1 dependent mechanism. British Journal of Haematology, 197(3), 283–292.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pariser, D. N., Hilt, Z. T., Ture, S. K., Blick‐Nitko, S. K., Looney, M. R., Cleary, S. J., Roman‐Pagan, E., Saunders, J., 2nd, Georas, S. N., Veazey, J., Madere, F., Santos, L. T., Arne, A., Huynh, N. P., Livada, A. C., Guerrero‐Martin, S. M., Lyons, C., Metcalf‐Pate, K. A., McGrath, K. E., … Morrell, C. N. (2021). Lung megakaryocytes are immune modulatory cells. Journal of Clinical Investigation, 131(1), e137377.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patel, S. R., Hartwig, J. H., &amp; Italiano, J. E., Jr(2005). The biogenesis of platelets from megakaryocyte proplatelets. Journal of Clinical Investigation, 115(12), 3348–3354.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ponomarev, E. D. (2018). Fresh evidence for platelets as neuronal and innate immune cells: Their role in the activation, differentiation, and deactivation of Th1, Th17, and tregs during tissue inflammation. Frontiers in Immunology, 9, 406.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pons, S., Fodil, S., Azoulay, E., &amp; Zafrani, L. (2020). The vascular endothelium: The cornerstone of organ dysfunction in severe SARS‐CoV‐2 infection. Critical Care (London, England), 24(1), 353.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Popescu, N. I., Lupu, C., &amp; Lupu, F. (2022). Disseminated intravascular coagulation and its immune mechanisms. Blood, 139(13), 1973–1986.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Portier, I., &amp; Campbell, R. A. (2021). Role of platelets in detection and regulation of infection. Arteriosclerosis, Thrombosis, and Vascular Biology, 41(1), 70–78.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pronk, C. J., Rossi, D. J., Mansson, R., Attema, J. L., Norddahl, G. L., Chan, C. K., Sigvardsson, M., Weissman, I. L., &amp; Bryder, D. (2007). Elucidation of the phenotypic, functional, and molecular topography of a myeloerythroid progenitor cell hierarchy. Cell Stem Cell, 1(4), 428–442.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rafii, S., Cao, Z., Lis, R., Siempos, I. I., Chavez, D., Shido, K., Rabbany, S. Y., &amp; Ding, B. S. (2015). Platelet‐derived SDF‐1 primes the pulmonary capillary vascular niche to drive lung alveolar regeneration. Nature Cell Biology, 17(2), 123–136.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reis, S., Popp, M., Schiesser, S., Metzendorf, M. I., Kranke, P., Meybohm, P., &amp; Weibel, S. (2022). Anticoagulation in COVID‐19 patients – An updated systematic review and meta‐analysis. Thrombosis Research, 219, 40–48.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rinder, H. M., Bonan, J. L., Rinder, C. S., Ault, K. A., &amp; Smith, B. R. (1991). Dynamics of leukocyte‐platelet adhesion in whole blood. Blood, 78(7), 1730–1737.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodriguez‐Fraticelli, A. E., Wolock, S. L., Weinreb, C. S., Panero, R., Patel, S. H., Jankovic, M., Sun, J., Calogero, R. A., Klein, A. M., &amp; Camargo, F. D. (2018). Clonal analysis of lineage fate in native haematopoiesis. Nature, 553(7687), 212–216.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rondina, M. T., Carlisle, M., Fraughton, T., Brown, S. M., Miller, R. R., 3rd, Harris, E. S., Weyrich, A. S., Zimmerman, G. A., Supiano, M. A., &amp; Grissom, C. K. (2015). Platelet‐monocyte aggregate formation and mortality risk in older patients with severe sepsis and septic shock. Journals of Gerontology‐Series A, Biological Sciences and Medical Sciences, 70(2), 225–231.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rowley, J. W., Oler, A. J., Tolley, N. D., Hunter, B. N., Low, E. N., Nix, D. A., Yost, C. C., Zimmerman, G. A., &amp; Weyrich, A. S. (2011). Genome‐wide RNA‐seq analysis of human and mouse platelet transcriptomes. Blood, 118(14), e101–e111.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rydenfelt, K., Kjosen, G., Horneland, R., Ludviksen, J. K., Jenssen, T. G., Line, P. D., Tonnessen, T. I., Mollnes, T. E., Haugaa, H., &amp; Pischke, S. E. (2023). Thromboinflammatory response is increased in pancreas transplant alone versus simultaneous pancreas‐kidney transplantation and early pancreas graft thrombosis is associated with complement activation. Frontiers in Immunology, 14, 1044444.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanjuan‐Pla, A., Macaulay, I. C., Jensen, C. T., Woll, P. S., Luis, T. C., Mead, A., Moore, S., Carella, C., Matsuoka, S., Bouriez Jones, T., Chowdhury, O., Stenson, L., Lutteropp, M., Green, J. C., Facchini, R., Boukarabila, H., Grover, A., Gambardella, A., Thongjuea, S., … Jacobsen, S. E. (2013). Platelet‐biased stem cells reside at the apex of the haematopoietic stem‐cell hierarchy. Nature, 502(7470), 232–236.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schneider, C., Lee, J., Koga, S., Ricardo‐Gonzalez, R. R., Nussbaum, J. C., Smith, L. K., Villeda, S. A., Liang, H. E., &amp; Locksley, R. M. (2019). Tissue‐resident group 2 innate lymphoid cells differentiate by layered ontogeny and in situ perinatal priming. Immunity, 50(6), 1425–1438.e5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scurfield, G., &amp; Radley, J. M. (1981). Aspects of platelet formation and release. American Journal of Hematology, 10(3), 285–296.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seifert, U., &amp; Greinacher, A. (2021). Platelets modulate T‐cell activity. Blood, 138(5), 358–360.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shannon, O. (2021). The role of platelets in sepsis. Research and Practice in Thrombosis and Haemostasis, 5(1), 27–37.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh, M. V., Davidson, D. C., Kiebala, M., &amp; Maggirwar, S. B. (2012). Detection of circulating platelet‐monocyte complexes in persons infected with human immunodeficiency virus type‐1. Journal of Virological Methods, 181(2), 170–176.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Slayton, W. B., Georgelas, A., Pierce, L. J., Elenitoba‐Johnson, K. S., Perry, S. S., Marx, M., &amp; Spangrude, G. J. (2002). The spleen is a major site of megakaryopoiesis following transplantation of murine hematopoietic stem cells. Blood, 100(12), 3975–3982.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Su, M., Chen, C., Li, S., Li, M., Zeng, Z., Zhang, Y., Xia, L., Li, X., Zheng, D., Lin, Q., Fan, X., Wen, Y., Liu, Y., Chen, F., Luo, W., Bu, Y., Qin, J., Guo, M., Qiu, M., … Tang, W. H. (2022). Gasdermin D‐dependent platelet pyroptosis exacerbates NET formation and inflammation in severe sepsis. Nature Cardiovascular Research, 1(8), 732–747.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Su, Y., Zhang, T., &amp; Qiao, R. (2023). Pyroptosis in platelets: Thrombocytopenia and inflammation. Journal of Clinical Laboratory Analysis, 37(4), e24852.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun, J., &amp; Li, Y. (2022). Pyroptosis and respiratory diseases: A review of current knowledge. Frontiers in Immunology, 13, 920464.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suzuki‐Inoue, K., &amp; Tsukiji, N. (2020). Platelet CLEC‐2 and lung development. Research and Practice in Thrombosis and Haemostasis, 4(4), 481–490.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tavassoli, M., &amp; Aoki, M. (1989). Localization of megakaryocytes in the bone marrow. Blood Cells, 15(1), 3–14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thompson, B. T., Chambers, R. C., &amp; Liu, K. D. (2017). Acute respiratory distress syndrome. New England Journal of Medicine, 377(6), 562–572.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thon, J. N., Montalvo, A., Patel‐Hett, S., Devine, M. T., Richardson, J. L., Ehrlicher, A., Larson, M. K., Hoffmeister, K., Hartwig, J. H., &amp; Italiano, J. E., Jr. (2010). Cytoskeletal mechanics of proplatelet maturation and platelet release. Journal of Cell Biology, 191(4), 861–874.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valet, C., Magnen, M., Qiu, L., Cleary, S. J., Wang, K. M., Ranucci, S., Grockowiak, E., Boudra, R., Conrad, C., Seo, Y., Calabrese, D. R., Greenland, J. R., Leavitt, A. D., Passegue, E., Mendez‐Ferrer, S., Swirski, F. K., &amp; Looney, M. R. (2022). Sepsis promotes splenic production of a protective platelet pool with high CD40 ligand expression. Journal of Clinical Investigation, 132(7), e153920.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vardon Bounes, F., Memier, V., Marcaud, M., Jacquemin, A., Hamzeh‐Cognasse, H., Garcia, C., Series, J., Sie, P., Minville, V., Gratacap, M. P., &amp; Payrastre, B. (2018). Platelet activation and prothrombotic properties in a mouse model of peritoneal sepsis. Scientific Reports, 8(1), 13536.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vardon‐Bounes, F., Garcia, C., Piton, A., Series, J., Gratacap, M. P., Poette, M., Seguin, T., Crognier, L., Ruiz, S., Silva, S., Conil, J. M., Minville, V., &amp; Payrastre, B. (2022). Evolution of platelet activation parameters during septic shock in intensive care unit. Platelets, 33(6), 918–925.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaughn, V. M., Yost, M., Abshire, C., Flanders, S. A., Paje, D., Grant, P., Kaatz, S., Kim, T., &amp; Barnes, G. D. (2021). Trends in Venous Thromboembolism Anticoagulation in Patients Hospitalized With COVID‐19. Journal of the American Medical Association Network Open, 4(6), e2111788.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ware, L. B., &amp; Matthay, M. A. (2000). The acute respiratory distress syndrome. New England Journal of Medicine, 342(18), 1334–1349.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wartiovaara, U., Salven, P., Mikkola, H., Lassila, R., Kaukonen, J., Joukov, V., Orpana, A., Ristimaki, A., Heikinheimo, M., Joensuu, H., Alitalo, K., &amp; Palotie, A. (1998). Peripheral blood platelets express VEGF‐C and VEGF which are released during platelet activation. Thrombosis and Haemostasis, 80(1), 171–175.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Washington, A. V., Esponda, O., &amp; Gibson, A. (2020). Platelet biology of the rapidly failing lung. British Journal of Haematology, 188(5), 641–651.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weyrich, A. S. (2014). Platelets: More than a sack of glue. Hematology‐American Society of Hematology‐Education Program, 2014(1), 400–403.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weyrich, A. S., Schwertz, H., Kraiss, L. W., &amp; Zimmerman, G. A. (2009). Protein synthesis by platelets: Historical and new perspectives. Journal of Thrombosis and Haemostasis, 7(2), 241–246.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weyrich, A. S., &amp; Zimmerman, G. A. (2013). Platelets in lung biology. Annual Review of Physiology, 75, 569–591.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, W., Fan, Z., Yao, C., Wu, J., &amp; Tao, S. (2020). Platelet maximum aggregation rate serves as a marker in diagnosis and prognosis in patients with sepsis. Annals of Palliative Medicine, 9(3), 847–857.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wurtzel, J. G. T., Lazar, S., Askari, S., Zhao, X., Severa, J., Ayombil, F., Michael, J. V., Camire, R. M., McKenzie, S. E., Stalker, T. J., Ma, P., &amp; Goldfinger, L. E. (2024). Plasma growth factors maintain constitutive translation in platelets to regulate reactivity and thrombotic potential. Blood Advances, 8(6), 1550–1566.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yaguchi, A., Lobo, F. L., Vincent, J. L., &amp; Pradier, O. (2004). Platelet function in sepsis. Journal of Thrombosis and Haemostasis, 2(12), 2096–2102.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zamora, C., Toniolo, E., Diaz‐Torne, C., Canto, E., Magallares, B., Ortiz, M. A., Perea, L., Corominas, H., &amp; Vidal, S. (2019). Association of Platelet Binding to Lymphocytes with B Cell Abnormalities and Clinical Manifestations in Systemic Lupus Erythematosus. Mediators of Inflammation, 2019, 2473164.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zarbock, A., Singbartl, K., &amp; Ley, K. (2006). Complete reversal of acid‐induced acute lung injury by blocking of platelet–neutrophil aggregation. Journal of Clinical Investigation, 116(12), 3211–3219.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhan, H., &amp; Kaushansky, K. (2022). Megakaryocytes as the regulator of the hematopoietic vascular niche. Frontiers in Oncology, 12, 912060.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhi, H., Rauova, L., Hayes, V., Gao, C., Boylan, B., Newman, D. K., McKenzie, S. E., Cooley, B. C., Poncz, M., &amp; Newman, P. J. (2013). Cooperative integrin/ITAM signaling in platelets enhances thrombus formation in vitro and in vivo. Blood, 121(10), 1858–1867.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zimmerman, G. A., &amp; Weyrich, A. S. (2008). Signal‐dependent protein synthesis by activated platelets: New pathways to altered phenotype and function. Arteriosclerosis, Thrombosis, and Vascular Biology, 28(3), s17–s24.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zucker‐Franklin, D., &amp; Philipp, C. S. (2000). Platelet production in the pulmonary capillary bed: New ultrastructural evidence for an old concept. American Journal of Pathology, 157(1), 69–74.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>