<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39425626</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1744-9987</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>19</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Therapeutic apheresis and dialysis : official peer-reviewed journal of the International Society for Apheresis, the Japanese Society for Apheresis, the Japanese Society for Dialysis Therapy</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Ther Apher Dial</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Ineffectiveness of therapeutic plasma exchange as a last resort in severe COVID-19 cases: Experience from a tertiary intensive care unit.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1744-9987.14219</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="AIM" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">Several studies have suggested that cytokine release syndrome (CRS) can be controlled by therapeutic plasma exchange (TPE) treatment. In this study, it was aimed to evaluate the efficacy of TPE treatment in patients who developed life-threatening respiratory failure syndrome (SARS) due to COVID-19 infection.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">In this retrospective, case-control study, patients, who developed SARS, were infected with the COVID-19 virus, and required intensive care unit (ICU) admission were included. Patients included in the study were divided into groups according to whether TPE experience or not and if so, how many sessions were applied. Mortality rates of patients in the ICU and 30-day mortality ratios were evaluated.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">A total of 110 patients, 71.8% of whom were male, with a mean age of 59.7 ± 13.3 years, were included in our study. It was observed that 70% of the patients died within a month and 80% of them died during the ICU follow-up period. The 30-day mortality rates of patients who underwent TPE at least once and those who never underwent TPE were 72.2% and 67.9%, respectively (p: 0.617). CRP, D-dimer, fibrinogen and platelet levels showed to have a decreasing trend after plasmapheresis and fluctuated thereafter. It was observed that procalcitonin and IL-6 levels were increased in the group that underwent plasmapheresis but decreased in those who did not receive plasmapheresis.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Patients severely infected with SARS-CoV-2 showed fluctuations in inflammatory parameters despite TPE treatment; CRS was not suppressed by TPE; and this treatment did not confer survival benefit in this patient group.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 International Society for Apheresis and Japanese Society for Apheresis.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ayer</LastName><ForeName>Mesut</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Haematology, Başakşehir Çam and Sakura City Hospital, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Özgür</LastName><ForeName>Yasemin</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7112-4575</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Haematology, Başakşehir Çam and Sakura City Hospital, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Turan</LastName><ForeName>Güldem</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Anesthesiology, Intensive Care Unit, Başakşehir Çam and Sakura City Hospital, Intensive Care Unit, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yurttaş</LastName><ForeName>Nurgül Özgür</ForeName><Initials>NÖ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Haematology, Başakşehir Çam and Sakura City Hospital, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ulusoy</LastName><ForeName>Yusuf</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Haematology, Başakşehir Çam and Sakura City Hospital, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ekmen</LastName><ForeName>Şevket Ali</ForeName><Initials>ŞA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Başakşehir Çam and Sakura City Hospital, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hanoğlu</LastName><ForeName>Didem</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Emergency Medicine, Başakşehir Çam and Sakura City Hospital, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Eker</LastName><ForeName>Edibe Sevde</ForeName><Initials>ES</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Haematology, Başakşehir Çam and Sakura City Hospital, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Öngören</LastName><ForeName>Şeniz</ForeName><Initials>Ş</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Haematology, Başakşehir Çam and Sakura City Hospital, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Australia</Country><MedlineTA>Ther Apher Dial</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101181252</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1744-9979</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS‐CoV‐2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">intensive care unit</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mortality</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">plasmapheresis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">therapeutic plasma exchange</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>12</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39425626</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1744-9987.14219</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Cucinotta D, Vanelli M. WHO declares COVID‐19 a pandemic. Acta Biomed. 2020;91(1):157–160.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. COVID‐19 weekly epidemiological update. World Heal Organ. 2022;124(58):1–23.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ye Q, Wang B, Mao J. The pathogenesis and treatment of the ‘Cytokine Storm’ in COVID‐19. J Infect. 2020;80(6):607–613. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jinf.2020.03.037</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gilmutdinova IR, Yakovlev MY, Eremin PS, Fesun AD. Prospects of plasmapheresis for patients with severe COVID‐19. Eur J Transl Myol. 2020;30(3):1–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knaup H, Stahl K, Schmidt BMW, Idowu TO, Busch M, Wiesner O, et al. Early therapeutic plasma exchange in septic shock: a prospective open‐label nonrandomized pilot study focusing on safety, hemodynamics, vascular barrier function, and biologic markers. Crit Care. 2018; 22(1):285.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cron RQ. COVID‐19 cytokine storm: targeting the appropriate cytokine. Lancet Rheumatol. 2021;3(4):e236–e237.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turgutkaya A, Yavasoglu I. The application of plasmapheresis for COVID‐19 patients. Ther Apher Dial. 2021; 25(2):248–249.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balagholi S, Dabbaghi R, Eshghi P, Mousavi SA, Heshmati F, Mohammadi S. Potential of therapeutic plasmapheresis in treatment of COVID‐19 patients: immunopathogenesis and coagulopathy. Transfus Apher Sci. 2020;59:102993.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tabibi S, Tabibi T, Conic RRZ, Banisaeed N, Streiff MB. Therapeutic plasma exchange: a potential management strategy for critically ill COVID‐19 patients. J Intensive Care Med. 2020;35:827–835.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhuplatov SB, Zhuplatov IS. Removal of endotoxins and cytokines by plasmapheresis filtration with plasma exchange therapy (TPE) could benefit patients with COVID‐19 in critical condition. J Anest &amp; Inten Care Med. 2020;10:85–89.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen C, Wang Z, Zhao F, Yang Y, Li J, Yuan J, et al. Treatment of 5 critically ill patients with COVID‐19 with convalescent plasma. J Am Med Assoc. 2020;323(16):1582–1589.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khamis F, Al‐Zakwani I, Al Hashmi S, Al Dowaiki S, Al Bahrani M, Pandak N, et al. Therapeutic plasma exchange in adults with severe COVID‐19 infection. Int J Infect Dis. 2020;1(99):214–218.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernandez J, Gratacos‐Ginès J, Olivas P, Costa M, Nieto S, Mateo D, et al. Plasma exchange: an effective rescue therapy in critically ILL patients with coronavirus disease 2019 infection. 2020;48, Crit Care Med:E1350–E1355.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang L, Zhai H, Ma S, Chen J, Gao Y. Efficacy of therapeutic plasma exchange in severe COVID‐19 patients. Br J Haematol. 2020;190:e181–e183.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beraud M, Al HS, Lozano M, Bah A, Keith P. Role of therapeutic plasma exchange in the management of COVID‐19‐induced cytokine storm syndrome. Transfus Apher Sci. 2022;61:103433.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>NCT04374149 @ www.clinicaltrials.gov [Internet]. Available from: https://www.clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/results/NCT04374149?cond=covid+plasma+exchange&amp;draw=3&amp;rank=11</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sedokani A, Feizollahzadeh S. Plasmapheresis, anti‐ACE2 and anti‐FcγRII monoclonal antibodies: a possible treatment for severe cases of COVID‐19. Drug des Devel Ther. 2020;14:2607–2611.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Truong AD, Auld SC, Barker NA, Friend S, Wynn AT, Cobb J, et al. Therapeutic plasma exchange for COVID‐19‐associated hyperviscosity. Transfusion. 2021;61(4):1029–1034.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang SF, Tseng SP, Yen CH, Yang JY, Tsao CH, Shen CW, et al. Antibody‐dependent SARS coronavirus infection is mediated by antibodies against spike proteins. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 2014;451(2):208–214.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu W, Kelley W, Fang DC, Joshi S, Kim Y, Paroder M, et al. The use of therapeutic plasma exchange as adjunctive therapy in the treatment of coronavirus disease 2019: a critical appraisal of the current evidence. J Clin Apher. 2021;36(3):483–491.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu X, Zhang Y, Xu X, Du W, Su K, Zhu C, et al. Evaluation of plasma exchange and continuous veno‐venous hemofiltration for the treatment of severe avian influenza a (H7N9): a cohort study. Ther Apher Dial. 2015;19(2):178–184.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kawashima H, Togashi T, Yamanaka G, Nakajima M, Nagai M, Aritaki K, et al. Efficacy of plasma exchange and methylprednisolone pulse therapy on influenza‐associated encephalopathy. J Infect. 2005;51(2):4–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oh WS, Heo ST, Kim SH, Choi WJ, Han MG, Kim JY. Plasma exchange and ribavirin for rapidly progressive severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome. Int J Infect Dis. 2014;18(1):84–86. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijid.2013.08.011</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Novacescu A, Duma G, Buzzi B, Baditoiu L, Bedreag O, Papurica M, et al. Therapeutic plasma exchange followed by convalescent plasma transfusion in severe and critically ill COVID‐19 patients: a single centre non‐randomized controlled trial. Exp Ther Med. 2021;23(1):76.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cegolon L, Einollahi B, Panahi Y, Imanizadeh S, Rezapour M, Javanbakht M, et al. On therapeutic plasma exchange against severe COVID‐19‐associated pneumonia: an observational clinical study. Front Nutr. 2022;22:9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamran SM, Mirza Z‐E‐H, Naseem A, Liaqat J, Fazal I, Alamgir W, et al. Therapeutic plasma exchange for coronavirus disease‐2019 triggered cytokine release syndrome; a retrospective propensity matched control study. PLoS One. 2021;16(1):1–13. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0244853</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gucyetmez B, Atalan HK, Sertdemir I, Cakir U, Telci L, COVID‐19 Study Group. Therapeutic plasma exchange in patients with COVID‐19 pneumonia in intensive care unit: a retrospective study. Crit Care. 2020;24(1):492. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13054-020-03215-8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kesici S, Yavuz S, Bayrakci B. Get rid of the bad first: therapeutic plasma exchange with convalescent plasma for severe COVID‐19. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2020;117(23):12526–12527.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>