<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39429445</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">0891-8929</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>42</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Season>Fall</Season></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Clinical diabetes : a publication of the American Diabetes Association</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Clin Diabetes</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Depression Rates in Youth With Type 1 Diabetes During the COVID-19 Pandemic: Data From the T1D Exchange Quality Improvement Collaborative.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>532</StartPage><EndPage>539</EndPage><MedlinePgn>532-539</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.2337/cd24-0004</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>This study used data from the T1D Exchange Quality Improvement Collaborative to compare depression rates in youth with type 1 diabetes before and during the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic and identify characteristics of individuals with moderate-to-severe depressive symptoms. Rates of moderate-to-severe depressive symptoms remained stable before and during the pandemic, at 9.6-10.7%. During the pandemic, youth who screened positive for depression were more likely to be female and on public insurance, to have a higher A1C, and to have a history of diabetic ketoacidosis or severe hypoglycemia. They were less likely to identify as non-Hispanic White and more likely to identify as Hispanic.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 by the American Diabetes Association.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Roberts</LastName><ForeName>Alissa</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0221-6273</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Washington, Department of Pediatrics, Seattle, WA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Corathers</LastName><ForeName>Sarah</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7019-278X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cincinnati Children's Hospital Medical Center, University of Cincinnati College of Medicine, Cincinnati, OH.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rapaport</LastName><ForeName>Robert</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Icahn School of Medicine, New York, NY.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rompicherla</LastName><ForeName>Saketh</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>T1D Exchange, Boston, MA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Majidi</LastName><ForeName>Shideh</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4899-3040</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Children's National Health System, Washington, DC.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rioles</LastName><ForeName>Nicole</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3355-0565</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>T1D Exchange, Boston, MA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ebekozien</LastName><ForeName>Osagie</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8473-249X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>T1D Exchange, Boston, MA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Mississippi School of Population Health, Jackson, MS.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Malik</LastName><ForeName>Faisal S</ForeName><Initials>FS</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2543-4214</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Washington, Department of Pediatrics, Seattle, WA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><DataBankList CompleteYN="Y"><DataBank><DataBankName>figshare</DataBankName><AccessionNumberList><AccessionNumber>10.2337/figshare.26221400</AccessionNumber></AccessionNumberList></DataBank></DataBankList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Clin Diabetes</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8406985</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0891-8929</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement>No potential conflicts of interest relevant to this article were reported.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39429445</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11486847</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/cd24-0004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">CD240004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Bernstein CM, Stockwell MS, Gallagher MP, Rosenthal SL, Soren K.. Mental health issues in adolescents and young adults with type 1 diabetes: prevalence and impact on glycemic control. Clin Pediatr (Phila) 2013;52:10–15</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22988007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stahl-Pehe A, Lange K, Bächle C, Castillo K, Holl RW, Rosenbauer J.. Mental health problems among adolescents with early-onset and long-duration type 1 diabetes and their association with quality of life: a population-based survey. PLoS One 2014;9:e92473.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3956941</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24637957</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buchberger B, Huppertz H, Krabbe L, Lux B, Mattivi JT, Siafarikas A.. Symptoms of depression and anxiety in youth with type 1 diabetes: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Psychoneuroendocrinology 2016;70:70–84</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27179232</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McGrady ME, Hood KK.. Depressive symptoms in adolescents with type 1 diabetes: associations with longitudinal outcomes. Diabetes Res Clin Pract 2010;88:e35–e37</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2916945</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20451278</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garey CJ, Clements MA, McAuliffe-Fogarty AH, et al. . The association between depression symptom endorsement and glycemic outcomes in adolescents with type 1 diabetes. Pediatr Diabetes 2022;23:248–257</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34779100</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maahs DM, Hermann JM, Holman N, et al. .; National Paediatric Diabetes Audit and the Royal College of Paediatrics and Child Health, the DPV Initiative, and the T1D Exchange Clinic Network . Rates of diabetic ketoacidosis: international comparison with 49,859 pediatric patients with type 1 diabetes from England, Wales, the U.S., Austria, and Germany. Diabetes Care 2015;38:1876–1882</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26283737</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Z, McGoogan JM.. Characteristics of and important lessons from the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) outbreak in China: summary of a report of 72314 cases from the Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention. JAMA 2020;323:1239–1242</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32091533</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Viner R, Russell S, Saulle R, et al. . School closures during social lockdown and mental health, health behaviors, and well-being among children and adolescents during the first COVID-19 wave: a systematic review. JAMA Pediatr 2022;176:400–409</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35040870</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Widnall E, Adams EA, Plackett R, et al. . Adolescent experiences of the COVID-19 pandemic and school closures and implications for mental health, peer relationships and learning: a qualitative study in south-west England. Int J Environ Res Public Health 2022;19:7163.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9222495</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35742408</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bolt J, Patel F, Stone L, Pandian D, Manuel MM, Gaines N.. Impact of COVID-19 on pediatric mental and behavioral health visits to the emergency department. Pediatr Emerg Care 2022;38:409–415</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9351515</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35766893</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hussong J, Möhler E, Kühn A, et al. . Mental health and health-related quality of life in German adolescents after the third wave of the COVID-19 pandemic. Children (Basel) 2022;9:780.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9221692</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35740717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hossain MM, Nesa F, Das J, et al. . Global burden of mental health problems among children and adolescents during COVID-19 pandemic: an umbrella review. Psychiatry Res 2022;317:114814.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9420079</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36055064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wade C, Burton ET, Akinseye L, Nelson G, Smith-Young J, Kim A.. Increased anxiety symptoms in pediatric type 1 diabetes during the acute phase of COVID-19 lockdown. J Pediatr Endocrinol Metab 2022;35:627–630</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35344643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neo EY, Sharma H, Mason L, Liu A, Poulton A, Bhurawala H.. The psychosocial impact of type 1 diabetes mellitus in children and adolescents during the COVID-19 pandemic. J Paediatr Child Health 2022;58:1786–1791</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9796503</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35770822</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cusinato M, Martino M, Sartori A, et al. . Anxiety, depression, and glycemic control during Covid-19 pandemic in youths with type 1 diabetes. J Pediatr Endocrinol Metab 2021;34:1089–1093</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34171940</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Young-Hyman D, de Groot M, Hill-Briggs F, Gonzalez JS, Hood K, Peyrot M.. Psychosocial care for people with diabetes: a position statement of the American Diabetes Association. Diabetes Care 2016;39:2126–2140</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5127231</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27879358</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delamater AM, de Wit M, McDarby V, et al. . ISPAD clinical practice consensus guidelines 2018: psychological care of children and adolescents with type 1 diabetes. Pediatr Diabetes 2018;19(Suppl. 27):237–249</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30058247</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Magesh S, John D, Li WT, et al. . Disparities in COVID-19 outcomes by race, ethnicity, and socioeconomic status: a systematic-review and meta-analysis. JAMA Netw Open 2021;4:e2134147.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8586903</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34762110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Malley G, Ebekozien O, Desimone M, et al. . COVID-19 hospitalization in adults with type 1 diabetes: results from the T1D Exchange Multicenter Surveillance Study. J Clin Endocrinol Metab 2021;106:e936–e942</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7717244</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33165563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ebekozien O, Agarwal S, Noor N, et al. . Inequities in diabetic ketoacidosis among patients with type 1 diabetes and COVID-19: data from 52 US clinical centers. J Clin Endocrinol Metab 2021;106:e1755–e1762</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7928931</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33410917</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alonso GT, Corathers S, Shah A, et al. . Establishment of the T1D Exchange Quality Improvement Collaborative (T1DX-QI). Clin Diabetes 2020;38:141–151</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7164986</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32327886</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richardson LP, McCauley E, Grossman DC, et al. . Evaluation of the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 item for detecting major depression among adolescents. Pediatrics 2010;126:1117–1123</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3217785</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21041282</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marker AM, Patton SR, Clements MA, Egan AE, McDonough RJ.. Adjusted cutoff scores increase sensitivity of depression screening measures in adolescents with type 1 diabetes. Diabetes Care 2022;45:2501–2508</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35984419</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vacaru SV, Beijers R, de Weerth C.. Internalizing symptoms and family functioning predict adolescent depressive symptoms during COVID-19: a longitudinal study in a community sample. PLoS One 2022;17:e0264962.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8932580</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35303003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mayne SL, Hannan C, Davis M, et al. . COVID-19 and adolescent depression and suicide risk screening outcomes. Pediatrics 2021;148:e2021051507.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34140393</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bitsko RH, Claussen AH, Lichstein J, et al. . Mental health surveillance among children: United States, 2013–2019. MMWR Suppl 2022;71:1–42</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8890771</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35202359</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harrington KR, Shapira A, Volkening LK, et al. . Associations of diabetes self-management characteristics, HbA1c, and psychosocial outcomes with depressive symptoms in a contemporary sample of adolescents with type 1 diabetes. J Diabetes Complications 2021;35:107838.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7870579</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33431226</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee JM, Carlson E, Albanese-O’Neill A, et al. . Adoption of telemedicine for type 1 diabetes care during the COVID-19 pandemic. Diabetes Technol Ther 2021;23:642–651</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8501471</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33851873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>