<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39425759</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1573-2959</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>196</Volume><Issue>11</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>19</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Environmental monitoring and assessment</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Environ Monit Assess</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Quantifying the impact of COVID-19 restrictions on air pollution in Ahvaz: a comparative dual-approach assessment of observed against baseline and forecasted criteria air pollutants.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1079</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1079</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s10661-024-13231-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>In response to the COVID-19 pandemic, the Iranian government swiftly implemented immediate and decisive measures to control the spread of the infection. This study aims to demonstrate the impact of restriction measure on air pollution, also to highlight the potential variability in results that can arias from different methodological approach. A comprehensive dual-approach assessment was conducted to evaluate the effect of the lockdown measures on criteria air pollutants. Firstly, a traditional approach compared air quality during the pandemic period with baseline conditions from 2013 to 2019. Secondly, observed air pollution values during different periods with varying restrictions in 2020 were compared with expected values. This comprehensive analysis allows for a robust comparison and quantification of the impact of different lockdown measures in Ahvaz. The study revealed significant changes in air pollutant concentrations in Ahvaz during 2020, with variations observed across different pollutants. Notable reductions were observed in O3 levels, particularly in November (-54.44% compared to the baseline) and December (-63.58% compared to expected values). Decreases in CO levels were observed in multiple months, while substantial reductions in PM10 and PM2.5 were observed during various periods. Inconsistencies in the magnitudes and directions of changes were found when comparing baseline and forecasted values. The overall stringency index showed an inverse association with changes in O3, NO2, and CO, with international travel controls and restrictions on internal movement having significant impacts. This study provides valuable insights into the impact of COVID-19 lockdown measures on air pollution in Ahvaz, Iran, using a comprehensive dual-approach assessment. The findings highlight the effectiveness of these measures in reducing specific criteria air pollutants and emphasize the importance of implementing appropriate strategies for air quality management during similar public health emergencies.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer Nature Switzerland AG.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kaydi</LastName><ForeName>Neda</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Environmental Technologies Research Center, Medical Basic Sciences Research Institute, Ahvaz Jundishapur University of Medical Sciences, Ahvaz, Khuzestan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Student Research Committee, Ahvaz Jundishapur University of Medical Sciences, Ahvaz, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Maraghi</LastName><ForeName>Elham</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biostatistics and Epidemiology, School of Public Health, Ahvaz Jundishapur University of Medical Sciences, Ahvaz, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bahrami</LastName><ForeName>Zeinab</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Graduate School of Engineering, Department of Environmental Engineering, Kyoto University, Kyoto, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shenavar</LastName><ForeName>Bamshad</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Khuzestan Department of Environment, Environmental Assessment, Air Pollution and Climate Change Office, Ahvaz, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rostami</LastName><ForeName>Soghra</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Khuzestan Department of Environment, Environmental Assessment, Air Pollution and Climate Change Office, Ahvaz, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Azarian</LastName><ForeName>Alireza</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Khuzestan Department of Environment, Laboratory Office, Ahvaz, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mojadam</LastName><ForeName>Mehdi</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health, School of Health, Abadan University of Medical Sciences, Abadan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jahedi</LastName><ForeName>Faezeh</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Environmental Health Engineering, School of Public Health, Ahvaz Jundishapur University of Medical Sciences, Ahvaz, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jaafarzadeh</LastName><ForeName>Neemat</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Environmental Technologies Research Center, Medical Basic Sciences Research Institute, Ahvaz Jundishapur University of Medical Sciences, Ahvaz, Khuzestan, Iran. n.jaafarzade@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khafaie</LastName><ForeName>Morteza Abdullatif</ForeName><Initials>MA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Environmental Technologies Research Center, Medical Basic Sciences Research Institute, Ahvaz Jundishapur University of Medical Sciences, Ahvaz, Khuzestan, Iran. m.khafaie@live.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>330102348</GrantID><Agency>Student Research Committee, Ahvaz Jundishapur University of Medical Sciences, Ahvaz, Iran</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Environ Monit Assess</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8508350</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0167-6369</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000393">Air Pollutants</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D052638">Particulate Matter</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>66H7ZZK23N</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D010126">Ozone</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000397" MajorTopicYN="Y">Air Pollution</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007492" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Iran</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000393" MajorTopicYN="Y">Air Pollutants</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004784" MajorTopicYN="Y">Environmental Monitoring</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D052638" MajorTopicYN="Y">Particulate Matter</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010126" MajorTopicYN="N">Ozone</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ARMA modeling</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Ahvaz</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Air pollution</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19 pandemic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Environmental health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Public health</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39425759</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10661-024-13231-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s10661-024-13231-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Barbieri, D. M., Lou, B., Passavanti, M., Hui, C., Lessa, D. A., Maharaj, B., Banerjee, A., Wang, F., Chang, K., Naik, B., Yu, L., Liu, Z., Sikka, G., Tucker, A., Mirhosseini, A. F., Naseri, S., Qiao, Y., Gupta, A., Abbas, M., … Adomako, S. (2020). Survey data regarding perceived air quality in Australia, Brazil, China, Ghana, India, Iran, Italy, Norway, South Africa, United States before and during Covid-19 restrictions. Data in Brief, 32, 106169.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.dib.2020.106169</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bherwani, H., Kumar, S., Musugu, K., Nair, M., Gautam, S., Gupta, A., Ho, C. H., Anshul, A., &amp; Kumar, R. (2021). Assessment and valuation of health impacts of fine particulate matter during COVID-19 lockdown: A comprehensive study of tropical and sub tropical countries. Environmental Science and Pollution Research International, 28, 44522–44537.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-021-13813-w</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Box, G. E. P., Jenkins, G. M., Reinsel, G. C., &amp; Ljung, G. M. (2015). Time Series Analysis: Forecasting and Control. Wiley.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Broomandi, P., Karaca, F., Nikfal, A., Jahanbakhshi, A., Tamjidi, M., &amp; Kim, J. R. (2020). Impact of COVID-19 event on the air quality in Iran. Aerosol and Air Quality Research, 20, 1793–1804.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4209/aaqr.2020.05.0205</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, K., Wang, M., Huang, C., Kinney, P. L., &amp; Anastas, P. T. (2020). Air pollution reduction and mortality benefit during the COVID-19 outbreak in China. Lancet Planet Health, 4, e210–e212.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2542-5196(20)30107-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, X., Zhang, F., Zhang, D., Xu, L., Liu, R., Teng, X., Zhang, X., Wang, S., &amp; Li, W. (2023). Variations of air pollutant response to COVID-19 lockdown in cities of the Tibetan Plateau. Environmental Science: Atmospheres, 3, 708–716.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chereches, I. A., Arion, I. D., Muresan, I. C., &amp; Gaspar, F. (2023). Study of the effects of the COVID-19 pandemic on air quality: A case study in Cluj-Napoca, Romania. Sustainability, 15, 2549.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/su15032549</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fei, S., Wagan, R. A., Hasnain, A., Hussain, A., Bhatti, U. A., &amp; Elahi, E. (2022). Spatiotemporal impact of the COVID-19 pandemic lockdown on air quality pattern in Nanjing, China. Frontiers in Environmental Science, 10, 952310.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fenvs.2022.952310</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Filippini, T., Rothman, K. J., Goffi, A., Ferrari, F., Maffeis, G., Orsini, N., &amp; Vinceti, M. (2020). Satellite-detected tropospheric nitrogen dioxide and spread of SARS-CoV-2 infection in Northern Italy. Science of the Total Environment, 739, 140278.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.140278</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gu, B., &amp; Liu, J. (2023). COVID-19 pandemic, port congestion, and air quality: Evidence from China. Ocean &amp; Coastal Management, 235, 106497.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ocecoaman.2023.106497</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo, Q., He, Z., &amp; Wang, Z. (2023). Change in air quality during 2014–2021 in Jinan City in China and its influencing factors. Toxics, 11, 210.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/toxics11030210</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo, Q., He, Z., &amp; Wang, Z. (2024). The characteristics of air quality changes in Hohhot City in China and their relationship with meteorological and socio-economic factors. Aerosol and Air Quality Research, 24, 230274.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4209/aaqr.230274</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hale, T., Angrist, N., Goldszmidt, R., Kira, B., Petherick, A., Phillips, T., Webster, S., Cameron-Blake, E., Hallas, L., Majumdar, S., &amp; Tatlow, H. (2021). A global panel database of pandemic policies (Oxford COVID-19 Government Response Tracker). Nature Human Behaviour, 5, 529–538.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41562-021-01079-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hasnain, A., Sheng, Y., Hashmi, M. Z., Bhatti, U. A., Ahmed, Z., &amp; Zha, Y. (2023). Assessing the ambient air quality patterns associated to the COVID-19 outbreak in the Yangtze River Delta: A random forest approach. Chemosphere, 314, 137638.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2022.137638</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaydi, N., Maraghi, E., Shenavar, B., Bahrami, Z., Azarian, A., Rostami, S., Ashrafi, M. J., Karimi, S., Haghighifard, N. J. &amp; Khafaie, M. A. (2024). Air pollution history and projection in Ahvaz: Insights from one of the most polluted cities in the world. Environmental Engineering and Management Journal. Forthcoming.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, K., Ni, R., Jiang, T., Tian, Y., Zhang, X., Li, C., &amp; Xie, C. (2022). The regional impact of the COVID-19 lockdown on the air quality in Ji’nan, China. Scientific Reports, 12, 12099.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-16105-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mazlan, N. A., Zaki, N. A. M., Narashid, R. H., Talib, N., Manokaran, J., Arshad, F. C., Fauzi, S. S. M., Dom, N. C., Valipour, M., &amp; Dambul, R. (2023). COVID-19 restriction movement control order (MCO) impacted emissions of peninsular Malaysia using Sentinel-2a and Sentinel-5p satellite. Earth Systems and Environment, 7, 347–358.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s41748-022-00329-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma, P., Ghosh, A., &amp; Patra, P. (2023). Statistical assessment of COVID-19 lockdowns on ambient air quality, Himachal Pradesh and learnings for implementing clean technologies: Insight from industrial town, India. Management of Environmental Quality: An International Journal, 34, 386–407.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1108/MEQ-12-2021-0290</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sicard, P., de Marco, A., Agathokleous, E., Feng, Z., Xu, X., Paoletti, E., Rodriguez, J. J. D., &amp; Calatayud, V. (2020). Amplified ozone pollution in cities during the COVID-19 lockdown. Science of the Total Environment, 735, 139542.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.139542</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tobías, A., Carnerero, C., Reche, C., Massagué, J., Via, M., Minguillón, M. C., Alastuey, A., &amp; Querol, X. (2020). Changes in air quality during the lockdown in Barcelona (Spain) one month into the SARS-CoV-2 epidemic. Science of the Total Environment, 726, 138540.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.138540</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venter, Z. S., Aunan, K., Chowdhury, S., &amp; Lelieveld, J. (2020). COVID-19 lockdowns cause global air pollution declines. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 117, 18984–18990.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.2006853117</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Volke, M. I., Abarca-Del-rio, R., &amp; Ulloa-Tesser, C. (2023). Impact of mobility restrictions on NO2 concentrations in key Latin American cities during the first wave of the COVID-19 pandemic. Urban Climate, 48, 101412.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.uclim.2023.101412</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>