<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39423220</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1932-6203</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>19</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>PloS one</Title><ISOAbbreviation>PLoS One</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Medical students' perception of mobile learning during COVID-19 in Iran: A national study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e0308248</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e0308248</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e0308248</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1371/journal.pone.0308248</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Mobile learning has gained significant attention in medical education in recent years. The COVID-19 crisis has further accelerated its adoption. A lack of research on student perceptions of mobile learning during pandemics limits strategies for maintaining education during these times. This study examines the perceptions of medical students in Iran regarding the mobile learning during COVID-19. It is imperative that these perceptions are understood to optimize mobile learning effectiveness in medical education during disruptions.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHOD" NlmCategory="METHODS">A cross-sectional study was done in 2022 among 785 medical students in Iran who spent summer semester. Convenience sampling was used to select the sample. We used Biswas et al.'s scale for measuring medical students' perceptions of mobile learning during pandemics. Face and content validity was determined by qualitative methods. Internal consistency was measured with Cronbach's Alpha (0.79). Data was collected through an online questionnaire. To analyze the data, descriptive and analytical statistics were conducted with SPSS software at a significance level of p&lt;0.05.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">In total, 1,200 medical students were asked to complete the survey, and 785 responded, resulting in a 65.4% response rate. Mobile learning has been embraced by majority of medical students, with Android devices being used the most frequently. They also have frequent access to the internet, and they rely on a wide range of apps and platforms for academic purposes. Students perceive mobile devices to be highly advantageous for improving subject knowledge (Mean = 4.71±0.58), accessing study materials (Mean = 4.44±0.75), and providing flexible learning opportunities (Mean = 4.40±0.79). Despite this, participants were less confident about the ability of mobile devices to assist with specific study problems (Mean = 3.12 ± 1.28), facilitate class discussions (Mean = 3.33 ± 1.38), and overcome screen size limitations (Mean = 3.32 ± 1.38).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Medical students in Iran have widely adopted mobile learning and perceive it as beneficial for acquiring knowledge, accessing material, and being flexible during COVID-19. M-learning's effectiveness in specific learning activities must be investigated in further research, and concerns regarding problem-solving, discussion facilitation, and screen size limitations should be addressed.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: © 2024 Ahmady et al. This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ahmady</LastName><ForeName>Soleiman</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Professor of Medical Education, School of Medical Education and Learning Technology, Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of LIME, Research Affiliated Faculty, Karolinska Institute, Solna, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khajeali</LastName><ForeName>Nasrin</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medical Education Department, Ahvaz Jundishapur University of Medical Sciences, Ahvaz, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kohan</LastName><ForeName>Noushin</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8163-742X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Education, Smart University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zarei</LastName><ForeName>Afagh</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Educational Development Center, Birjand University of Medical Sciences, Birjand, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Biswas</LastName><ForeName>Bikram</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Educational Administration, Noakhali Science and Technology, Noakhali, Bangladesh.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Barzegar</LastName><ForeName>Mohammad</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of English Language, School of Health Management and Information Sciences Iran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Moghaddam</LastName><ForeName>Azadeh Kordestani</ForeName><Initials>AK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Social Welfare and Rehabilitation Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>PLoS One</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101285081</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1932-6203</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013337" MajorTopicYN="Y">Students, Medical</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007492" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Iran</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003430" MajorTopicYN="N">Cross-Sectional Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011795" MajorTopicYN="N">Surveys and Questionnaires</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D063731" MajorTopicYN="Y">Mobile Applications</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D020375" MajorTopicYN="N">Education, Distance</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055815" MajorTopicYN="N">Young Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007858" MajorTopicYN="N">Learning</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004501" MajorTopicYN="N">Education, Medical</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010465" MajorTopicYN="N">Perception</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>34</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39423220</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11488732</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0308248</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">PONE-D-23-12547</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Humphreys H, Baxter R, Gilroy J, Cavalleri GL, O’Connor T, Kerrigan SW, et al.. All hands on deck during the COVID-19 pandemic. Maintaining face-to-face medical education and clinical placements. PloS one. 2024;19(7):e0306129. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0306129</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0306129</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11216567</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38950018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ortiz Riofrio AG, Valdivieso-Andrade EJ, Acosta Masaquiza NM, Aguirre AS, Almeida Villavicencio NA, Calderón Pilla CS, et al.. COVID-19: Medical education from the point of view of medical students using the participatory Delphi method. PloS one. 2024;19(7):e0297602. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0297602</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0297602</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11226019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38968213</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu X, Shao X. Modern mobile learning technologies in online piano education: Online educational course design and impact on learning. Interactive Learning Environments. 2024;32(4):1279–90.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chandran VP, Balakrishnan A, Rashid M, Pai Kulyadi G, Khan S, Devi ES, et al.. Mobile applications in medical education: A systematic review and meta-analysis. PLoS One. 2022;17(3):e0265927. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0265927</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0265927</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8947018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35324994</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee SS, Tay SM, Balakrishnan A, Yeo SP, Samarasekera DD. Mobile learning in clinical settings: unveiling the paradox. Korean Journal of Medical Education. 2021;33(4):349. doi: 10.3946/kjme.2021.204</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3946/kjme.2021.204</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8655354</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34875152</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sawarkar G, Sawarkar P. Critical appraisal of e-learning through mobile devices in medical education. Indian Journal of Forensic Medicine &amp; Toxicology. 2020;14(4):6732–6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akour I, Alshurideh M, Al Kurdi B, Al Ali A, Salloum S. Using machine learning algorithms to predict people’s intention to use mobile learning platforms during the COVID-19 pandemic: Machine learning approach. JMIR Medical Education. 2021;7(1):e24032. doi: 10.2196/24032</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/24032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8081278</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33444154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baghcheghi N, Koohestani HR, Karimy M, Alizadeh S. Factors affecting mobile learning adoption in healthcare professional students based on technology acceptance model. Acta facultatis medicae Naissensis. 2020;37(2):191–200.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azizi SM, Khatony A. Investigating factors affecting on medical sciences students’ intention to adopt mobile learning. BMC medical education. 2019;19:1–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6802341</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31638977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alizadeh DI. Medical students’ perception of using electronic learning tools in an ESP program. International Journal of Research in English Education. 2018;3(1):11–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suner A, Yilmaz Y, Pişkin B. Mobile learning in dentistry: usage habits, attitudes and perceptions of undergraduate students. PeerJ. 2019;7:e7391. doi: 10.7717/peerj.7391</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7717/peerj.7391</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6673424</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31392099</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tlili A, Padilla-Zea N, Garzón J, Wang Y, Kinshuk K, Burgos D. The changing landscape of mobile learning pedagogy: A systematic literature review. Interactive Learning Environments. 2023;31(10):6462–79.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saikat S, Dhillon JS, Wan Ahmad WF, Jamaluddin RAd. A systematic review of the benefits and challenges of mobile learning during the COVID-19 pandemic. Education Sciences. 2021;11(9):459.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alhumaid K. Developing an educational framework for using mobile learning during the era of COVID-19. International Journal of Data and Network Science. 2021;5(3):215.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cochrane TD, Narayan V, Aiello S, Alizadeh M, Birt J, Bone E, et al.. Analysing mobile learning designs: A framework for transforming learning post-COVID. Australasian Journal of Educational Technology. 2022;38(4):1–21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joko J, Santoso AB, Muslim S, Harimurti R, editors. Effectiveness of mobile learning implementation in increasing student competence and preventing the spread and impact of COVID-19. 2020 Third International Conference on Vocational Education and Electrical Engineering (ICVEE); 2020: IEEE.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pimmer C, Linxen S, Gröhbiel U, Jha AK, Burg G. Mobile learning in resource-constrained environments: a case study of medical education. Medical teacher. 2013;35(5):e1157–e65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23137244</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kucuk S, Baydas Onlu O, Kapakin S. A model for medical students’ behavioral intention to use mobile learning. Journal of Medical Education and Curricular Development. 2020;7:2382120520973222.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7716062</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33313399</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Basu S, Marimuthu Y, Sharma N, Sharma P, Gangadharan N, Santra S. Attitude towards mobile learning among resident doctors involved in undergraduate medical education at a government medical college in Delhi, India. Journal of education and health promotion. 2020;9(1):321.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7774636</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33426125</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han H, Hurtubise L, Plantegenest G, Vitek CRR, Patwari R, Foshee C, et al.. Mobile learning literature review in medical education. The digital era of learning: Novel educational strategies and challenges for teaching students in the 21st Century. 2020:41–77.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang C-Y, Hwang G-J. Trends of mobile technology-enhanced medical education: a review of journal publications from 1998 to 2016. International Journal of Mobile Learning and Organisation. 2018;12(4):373–93.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koohestani HR, Arabshahi SKS, Fata L, Ahmadi F. The educational effects of mobile learning on students of medical sciences: A systematic review in experimental studies. Journal of advances in medical education &amp; professionalism. 2018;6(2):58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5856906</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29607333</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mosallami Aghili SM, Mohammadhoseini M, Samadi S, Shahi A. Mobile Learning Use Rate and Effective Factors with Possible Obstacles to its Use in Medical Education among Medical Students of Tehran University of Medical Sciences. Educational Development of Judishapur. 2021;11(4):840–51.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fesharakinia A, Zare Bidaki M, Khazaii T, Hanafi FR, Darafshy R. The Effect of Mobile Learning in Clinical Learning in Birjand University of Medical Sciences. Future of Medical Education Journal. 2016;6(1).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ShahAli S, Shahabi S, Kohan N, Ebrahimi Takamjani I, Ebrahimi R. Using e-learning methods for physiotherapy students learning–a systematic review and meta-analysis of the impact on knowledge, skills, satisfaction and attitudes. European Journal of Physiotherapy. 2023;25(5):252–64.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patil RN, Almale BD, Patil M, Gujrathi A, Dhakne-Palwe S, Patil AR, et al.. Attitudes and perceptions of medical undergraduates towards mobile learning (M-learning). Journal of clinical and diagnostic research: JCDR. 2016;10(10):JC06. doi: 10.7860/JCDR/2016/20214.8682</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7860/JCDR/2016/20214.8682</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5121694</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27891356</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gavali MY, Khismatrao DS, Gavali YV, Patil K. Smartphone, the new learning aid amongst medical students. Journal of clinical and diagnostic research: JCDR. 2017;11(5):JC05. doi: 10.7860/JCDR/2017/20948.9826</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7860/JCDR/2017/20948.9826</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5483706</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28658804</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh K, Sarkar S, Gaur U, Gupta S, Adams O, Sa B, et al.. Smartphones and educational apps use among medical students of a smart university campus. Frontiers in Communication. 2021;6:649102.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rohilla J, Rohilla R, Rohilla A, Singh K. Academic use and attitude of the 1st year medical students toward smartphones in a North Indian city. Digital Medicine. 2016;2(1):13–6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sridhar V, Padhyegurjar SB, Padhyegurjar MS. A Study among Medical Students on Efficient Use of Smartphones for Academic Purposes and the Distractions Caused by Social Networking Sites in a Rural Medical College in South India. Journal of Research in Medical Education &amp; Ethics. 2018;8(3):179–84.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ayatollahi A, Ayatollahi J, Ayatollahi F, Ayatollahi R, Shahcheraghi SH. Computer and internet use among undergraduate medical students in Iran. Pakistan journal of medical sciences. 2014;30(5):1054. doi: 10.12669/pjms.305.5355</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.12669/pjms.305.5355</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4163231</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25225525</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dias L, Victor A. Teaching and learning with mobile devices in the 21st century digital world: Benefits and challenges. European Journal of Multidisciplinary Studies. 2022;7(1):26–34.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Milheim KL, Fraenza C, Palermo-Kielb K. Supporting Student-Initiated Mobile Device Use in Online Learning. Online Learning. 2021;25(3):267–88.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan H, Malik A. Academic use of smartphones among medical students in Pakistan. Information Development. 2022;38(2):299–309.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bagheri-Nesami M, Ahmady S, Kohan N. Relationship between information and communications technology engagement with online self-regulated learning in nursing students of Mazandaran University of medical sciences. Journal of Nursing and Midwifery Sciences. 2021;8(4):253–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biswas B, Roy SK, Roy F. Students perception of mobile learning during COVID-19 in Bangladesh: University student perspective. 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siddiqi N, Jahan F, Moin F, Al-Shehhi F, Al-Balushi F. Excessive use of mobile phones by medical students: should precautions be taken? Biomedical and Pharmacology Journal. 2017;10(4):1631–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>AlHajri R, Al-Sharhan S, Al-Hunaiyyan A. Students’ perceptions of mobile learning: Case study of Kuwait. International Journal of Educational and Pedagogical Sciences. 2017;11(2):371–4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soon MKS, Martinengo L, Lu J, Car LT, Chia CLK. The use of telegram in surgical education: Exploratory study. JMIR medical education. 2022;8(3):e35983. doi: 10.2196/35983</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/35983</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9518707</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36099020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan SY, Md Yunus M. Sustaining English language education with social networking sites (SNSs): a systematic review. Sustainability. 2023;15(7):5710.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hossain ME, Ahmed SZ. Academic use of smartphones by university students: a developing country perspective. The Electronic Library. 2016;34(4):651–65.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahman A. The awareness and usage of mobile phone among students of Dhaka University in Bangladesh. Journal of Business Studies. 2014;35(3):17–30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wallace S, Clark M, White J. ‘It’s on my iPhone’: attitudes to the use of mobile computing devices in medical education, a mixed-methods study. BMJ open. 2012;2(4):e001099. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2012-001099</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2012-001099</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3432838</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22923627</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahmoodi F, Habibi Ramiani E, Babazadeh R. Effective factors on the acceptance of mobile learning among students of Tabriz University and Tabriz University of Medical Sciences. Education Strategies in Medical Sciences. 2017;10(6):438–46.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang YS, Wu MC, Wang HY. Investigating the determinants and age and gender differences in the acceptance of mobile learning. British journal of educational technology. 2009;40(1):92–118.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ariffin S, Glahn C, Anshar M, Daud F, Kiong T, Noordin N, et al.. Early investigation of the impact of mobile learning ethics student-generated activities for STEM subjects in a local Malaysian university context. 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uzunboylu H, Ozdamli F. Teacher perception for m‐learning: scale development and teachers’ perceptions. Journal of Computer assisted learning. 2011;27(6):544–56.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>