<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39426524</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1527-3296</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>17</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>American journal of infection control</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Am J Infect Control</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Efficiency and Simulation of Thailand's Chiang Mai University Model for COVID-19 Mass Vaccination Hub (CMU-MVH Model).</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0196-6553(24)00758-2</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.ajic.2024.10.005</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Mass vaccination is crucial for achieving herd immunity and controlling pandemics. Simulation models predict vaccination outcomes. This study evaluates efficiency and designs a tailored vaccination plan for Thailand.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Data was derived from a COVID-19 Mass Vaccination Hub (MVH) in Chiang Mai, Thailand. It was taken between June 2021 and December 2021. The discreet event simulation model is developed in Arena Simulation Enterprise Suite version 14.0.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The operational efficiency of Chiang Mai University Mass Vaccination Hub (CMU-MVH) was 1,073 vaccinations per 8 hours with 38 service staff. The average processing times (APT) were 2.5 minutes for the registration station, 12.2 minutes for the assessment station, 8.3 minutes for vaccination, and 28.2 minutes for observation. With 100% staff availability and staff utilization ranging from 0.5 to 0.7, the CMU-MVH could handle 180 to 230 vaccinees per hour or 1,227 to 1,527 vaccinees per day. Reduced staff availability leads to an increase in average processing time, especially when staff availability is lower or equal to 60%.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The CMU-MVH could handle approximately a thousand vaccinations within 8 working hours. This capability could assist policymakers in developing more effective strategies and planning for future mass vaccinations.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DATA AVAILABILITY STATEMENT" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The data that support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author, upon reasonable request.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kitro</LastName><ForeName>Amornphat</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, Chiang Mai University, Chiang Mai 50200, Thailand; Environmental and Occupational Medicine Excellence Center, Faculty of Medicine, Chiang Mai University, Chiang Mai 50200, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tippong</LastName><ForeName>Danuphon</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Management Sciences, Prince of Songkla University, Songkla 90110, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sirikul</LastName><ForeName>Wachiranun</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, Chiang Mai University, Chiang Mai 50200, Thailand; Environmental and Occupational Medicine Excellence Center, Faculty of Medicine, Chiang Mai University, Chiang Mai 50200, Thailand; Center of Data Analytics and Knowledge Synthesis for Health Care, Chiang Mai University, Chiang Mai 50200, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Isaradech</LastName><ForeName>Natthanaphop</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, Chiang Mai University, Chiang Mai 50200, Thailand; Center of Data Analytics and Knowledge Synthesis for Health Care, Chiang Mai University, Chiang Mai 50200, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kosai</LastName><ForeName>Apiradee</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Health Promotion Unit, Maharaj Nakorn Chiang Mai, Faculty of Medicine, Chiang Mai University, Chiang Mai 50200, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Saengoa</LastName><ForeName>Pimprapas</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Health Promotion Unit, Maharaj Nakorn Chiang Mai, Faculty of Medicine, Chiang Mai University, Chiang Mai 50200, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Thammasarot</LastName><ForeName>Jiraporn</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Health Promotion Unit, Maharaj Nakorn Chiang Mai, Faculty of Medicine, Chiang Mai University, Chiang Mai 50200, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Siviroj</LastName><ForeName>Penprapa</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, Chiang Mai University, Chiang Mai 50200, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rungsiyakull</LastName><ForeName>Chaiy</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Mechanical Engineering, Faculty of Engineering, Chiang Mai University Chiang Mai, 50200, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Srithanaviboonchai</LastName><ForeName>Kriengkrai</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, Chiang Mai University, Chiang Mai 50200, Thailand; Research Institute for Health Sciences, Chiang Mai University, Chiang Mai 50200, Thailand. Electronic address: kriengkrai.s@cmu.ac.th.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Am J Infect Control</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8004854</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0196-6553</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mass vaccination hub</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Simulation model</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Thailand</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vaccination</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of Competing Interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper: [Amornphat Kitro (first author) reports financial support and administrative support were provided by Chiang Mai University Faculty of Medicine. Amornphat Kitro (first author) reports a relationship with Chiang Mai University Faculty of Medicine that includes: employment]. Conflicts of Interest We declare no conflicts of interest. The views and opinions expressed in this article are those of the authors only and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated institutions. The authors declare no conflicts of interest. Conflicts of Interest The authors declare no conflicts of interest. The views and opinions expressed in this article are those of the authors only and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated institutions.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39426524</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ajic.2024.10.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0196-6553(24)00758-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>