<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39423970</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1879-0003</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>282</Volume><Issue>Pt 1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>18</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>International journal of biological macromolecules</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Int J Biol Macromol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Investigating TCR-pMHC interactions for TCRs without identified epitopes by constructing a computational pipeline.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>136502</StartPage><MedlinePgn>136502</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2024.136502</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0141-8130(24)07311-2</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The molecular mechanisms underlying epitope recognition by T cell receptors (TCRs) are critical for activating T cell immune responses and rationally designing TCR-based therapeutics. Single-cell sequencing techniques vastly boost the accumulation of TCR sequences, while the limitation of available TCR-pMHC structures hampers further investigations. In this study, we proposed a computational pipeline that incorporates structural information and single-cell sequencing data to investigate the epitope-recognition mechanisms for TCRs without identified epitopes. By antigen specificity clustering, we mapped the epitope sequences between epitope-known and epitope-unknown TCRs from COVID-19 patients. One reported SARS-CoV-2 epitope, NQKLIANQF (S<sub>919</sub><sub>-</sub><sub>927</sub>), was identified for a TCR expressed by 614 T cells (TCR-614). Epitope screening also identified a potential cross-reactive epitope, KLKTLVATA (NSP3<sub>1790</sub><sub>-</sub><sub>1798</sub>), for a TCR expressed by 204 T cells (TCR-204). By molecular dynamics (MD) simulations, we revealed the detailed epitope-recognition mechanisms for both TCRs. The structural motifs responsible for epitope recognition revealed by the MD simulations are consistent with the sequential features recognized by the sequence-based clustering method. We hope that this strategy could facilitate the discovery and optimization of TCR-based therapeutics.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Song</LastName><ForeName>Kaiyuan</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Systems Biomedicine (Ministry of Education), Shanghai Center for Systems Biomedicine, Shanghai Jiao Tong University, Shanghai 200240, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Honglin</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Pharmacy, Shanghai Jiao Tong University, Shanghai 200240, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shi</LastName><ForeName>Yi</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bio-X Institutes, Key Laboratory for the Genetics of Developmental and Neuropsychiatric Disorders, Shanghai Jiao Tong University, 1954 Huashan Road, Shanghai 200030, China; Shanghai Key Laboratory of Psychotic Disorders, Brain Science and Technology Research Center, Shanghai Jiao Tong University, 1954 Huashan Road, Shanghai 200030, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zou</LastName><ForeName>Xin</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Digital Diagnosis and Treatment Innovation Center for Cancer, Institute of Translational Medicine, Shanghai Jiao Tong University, Shanghai 200240, China; Ninth People's Hospital, Shanghai Key Laboratory of Stomatology and Shanghai Research Institute of Stomatology, National Clinical Research Center of Stomatology, Shanghai Jiao Tong University, School of Medicine, Shanghai 200011, China. Electronic address: albumxin@qq.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Da</LastName><ForeName>Lin-Tai</ForeName><Initials>LT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of Systems Biomedicine (Ministry of Education), Shanghai Center for Systems Biomedicine, Shanghai Jiao Tong University, Shanghai 200240, China. Electronic address: darlt@sjtu.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hao</LastName><ForeName>Jie</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Clinical Science, Zhongshan Hospital, Fudan University, Shanghai 200032, China. Electronic address: jhao@fudan.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Int J Biol Macromol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7909578</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0141-8130</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Epitope prediction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Molecular dynamics simulation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Single-cell sequencing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">TCR-pMHC</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39423970</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2024.136502</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0141-8130(24)07311-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>