<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39429020</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1537-2995</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>21</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Transfusion</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Transfusion</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Adherence to COVID-19 vaccination recommendations and vaccine hesitancy in US blood donors.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/trf.18051</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">General vaccination rates have been falling globally despite unequivocal health benefits. Noncompliance can result from access barriers and/or hesitant attitudes. Few studies have investigated the prevalence and determinants of noncompliance with COVID-19 vaccination in blood donors.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">We surveyed blood donors on COVID-19 infection and vaccination history, barriers and motivations for COVID-19 vaccination, and comorbidities. We estimate the prevalence of noncompliance, the prevalence of hesitancy toward COVID-19 vaccines, and investigate associated factors using multivariable models.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">From December 2021 to December 2022, 33,610 survey respondents were included. Of these, 24% had not been vaccinated for COVID-19 or had missing vaccination information, and 99% of those who reported reasons for being unvaccinated declared at least one of three hesitant attitudes presented in the survey (safety concerns; personal/cultural/religious beliefs; being young and not worrying about being vaccinated). Among noncompliant donors, &lt;2% reported access barriers. In the multivariable model addressing factors associated with vaccine noncompliance, younger age, male gender, White/Caucasian race, absence of comorbidities, residency in a State with less restrictive COVID-19 policies, and living in micropolitan or rural areas were identified as significant predictors. Younger age and White/Caucasian race were independently associated with vaccine hesitancy among noncompliant donors.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">We found high rates of noncompliance with COVID-19 vaccination in blood donors, mostly driven by vaccine hesitancy. Understanding vaccine adherence among blood donors-a relatively highly educated and healthy population, with good healthcare access and usually motivated by altruism-could provide key information on determinants of vaccine noncompliance that may be harder to overcome.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 AABB.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Avelino-Silva</LastName><ForeName>Vivian I</ForeName><Initials>VI</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0007-4887-8807</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Vitalant Research Institute, San Francisco, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, University of California San Francisco, San Francisco, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bruhn</LastName><ForeName>Roberta</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5898-8168</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Vitalant Research Institute, San Francisco, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Laboratory Medicine, University of California San Francisco, San Francisco, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zurita</LastName><ForeName>Karla G</ForeName><Initials>KG</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Vitalant Research Institute, San Francisco, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Laboratory Medicine, University of California San Francisco, San Francisco, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Grebe</LastName><ForeName>Eduard</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7046-7245</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Vitalant Research Institute, San Francisco, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Laboratory Medicine, University of California San Francisco, San Francisco, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>South African Centre for Epidemiological Modeling and Analysis (SACEMA), Stellenbosch University, Stellenbosch, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Stone</LastName><ForeName>Mars</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Vitalant Research Institute, San Francisco, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Laboratory Medicine, University of California San Francisco, San Francisco, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Busch</LastName><ForeName>Michael P</ForeName><Initials>MP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Vitalant Research Institute, San Francisco, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Laboratory Medicine, University of California San Francisco, San Francisco, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Custer</LastName><ForeName>Brian</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6251-366X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Vitalant Research Institute, San Francisco, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Laboratory Medicine, University of California San Francisco, San Francisco, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>75D30120C08170</GrantID><Acronym>CC</Acronym><Agency>CDC HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Transfusion</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0417360</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0041-1132</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS‐CoV‐2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">blood donors</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vaccine hesitancy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vaccines</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39429020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/trf.18051</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. The Global Health Observatory. Immunization and vaccine‐preventable communicable diseases. [cited 2024 may 6]. Available from: https://www.who.int/data/gho/data/themes/immunization</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cunniff L, Alyanak E, Fix A, Novak M, Peterson M, Mevis K, et al. The impact of the COVID‐19 pandemic on vaccination uptake in the United States and strategies to recover and improve vaccination rates: a review. Hum Vaccin Immunother. 2023;19(2):2246502.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mathis AD, Raines K, Masters NB, Filardo TD, Kim G, Crooke SN, et al. Measles—United States, January 1, 2020–march 28, 2024. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2024;73(14):295–300.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Global measles outbreaks. [cited 2024 May 6]. Available from: https://www.cdc.gov/globalhealth/measles/data/global-measles-outbreaks.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kishore N, Krow‐Lucal E, Diop OM, Jorba J, Avagnan T, Grabovac V, et al. Surveillance to track Progress toward polio eradication—worldwide, 2022–2023. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2024;73(13):278–285.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lopez Cavestany R, Eisenhawer M, Diop OM, Verma H, Quddus A, Mach O. The last mile in polio eradication: program challenges and perseverance. Pathogens. 2024;13(4):323.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tauil MDC, Sato APS, Waldman EA. Factors associated with incomplete or delayed vaccination across countries: a systematic review. Vaccine. 2016;34(24):2635–2643.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dubé E, Laberge C, Guay M, Bramadat P, Roy R, Bettinger JA. Vaccine hesitancy: an overview. Hum Vaccin Immunother. 2013;9(8):1763–1773.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larson HJ, Gakidou E, Murray CJL. The vaccine‐hesitant moment. Longo DL, editor. N Engl J Med. 2022;387(1):58–65.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Our World in Data. Coronavirus (COVID‐19) vaccinations. [cited 2024 may 6]. Available from: https://ourworldindata.org/covid-vaccinations</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cascini F, Pantovic A, Al‐Ajlouni Y, Failla G, Ricciardi W. Attitudes, acceptance and hesitancy among the general population worldwide to receive the COVID‐19 vaccines and their contributing factors: a systematic review. EClinicalMedicine. 2021;40:101113.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khairat S, Zou B, Adler‐Milstein J. Factors and reasons associated with low COVID‐19 vaccine uptake among highly hesitant communities in the US. Am J Infect Control. 2022;50(3):262–267.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehta JM, Chakrabarti C, de Leon J, Homan P, Skipton T, Sparkman R. Assessing the role of collectivism and individualism on COVID‐19 beliefs and behaviors in the southeastern United States. Moretti A, editor. PLoS One. 2023;18(1):e0278929.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Howard‐Williams M, Soelaeman RH, Fischer LS, McCord R, Davison R, Dunphy C. Association between state‐issued COVID‐19 vaccine mandates and vaccine administration rates in 12 US states and the District of Columbia. JAMA Health Forum. 2022;3(10):e223810.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Altman JD, Miner DS, Lee AA, Asay AE, Nielson BU, Rose AM, et al. Factors affecting vaccine attitudes influenced by the COVID‐19 pandemic. Vaccine. 2023;11(3):516.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agley J, Xiao Y, Thompson EE, Golzarri‐Arroyo L. Factors associated with reported likelihood to get vaccinated for COVID‐19 in a nationally representative US survey. Public Health. 2021;196:91–94.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fischinger JM, Stephan B, Wasserscheid K, Eichler H, Gärtner BC. A cost–benefit analysis of blood donor vaccination as an alternative to additional DNA testing for reducing transfusion transmission of hepatitis B virus. Vaccine. 2010;28(49):7797–7802.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Politis C, Hatzitaki M, Richardson C, Damaskos P, Bollas G, Grouzi E, et al. Perceptions and attitudes of blood donors in Greece towards vaccination against COVID‐19. Vox Sang. 2022;117(S1):119–120.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patel EU, Bloch EM, Grabowski MK, Goel R, Lokhandwala PM, Brunker PAR, et al. Sociodemographic and behavioral characteristics associated with blood donation in the United States: a population‐based study. Transfusion. 2019;59(9):2899–2907.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wittock N, Hustinx L, Bracke P, Buffel V. Who donates? Cross‐country and periodical variation in blood donor demographics in Europe between 1994 and 2014. Transfusion. 2017;57(11):2619–2628.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steele WR, Schreiber GB, Guiltinan A, Nass C, Glynn SA, Wright DJ, et al. The role of altruistic behavior, empathetic concern, and social responsibility motivation in blood donation behavior. Transfusion. 2008;48(1):43–54.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jones JM, Stone M, Sulaeman H, Fink RV, Dave H, Levy ME, et al. Estimated US infection‐ and vaccine‐induced SARS‐CoV‐2 seroprevalence based on blood donations, July 2020–May 2021. JAMA. 2021;326(14):1400–1409.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jones JM, Opsomer JD, Stone M, Benoit T, Ferg RA, Stramer SL, et al. Updated US infection‐ and vaccine‐induced SARS‐CoV‐2 seroprevalence estimates based on blood donations, July 2020–December 2021. JAMA. 2022;328(3):298–301.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raifman J, Nocka K, Jones D, Bor J, Lipson S, Jay J, et al. COVID‐19 US state policy database. [cited 2024 may 6]. Available from: www.tinyurl.com/statepolicies</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orenstein WA, Ahmed R. Simply put: vaccination saves lives. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2017;114(16):4031–4033.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodrigues CMC, Plotkin SA. Impact of vaccines; health, economic and social perspectives. Front Microbiol. 2020;11:1526.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phadke VK, Bednarczyk RA, Salmon DA, Omer SB. Association between vaccine refusal and vaccine‐preventable diseases in the United States: a review of measles and pertussis. JAMA. 2016;315(11):1149–1158.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nuwarda RF, Ramzan I, Weekes L, Kayser V. Vaccine hesitancy: contemporary issues and historical background. Vaccine. 2022;10(10):1595.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eagan RL, Larson HJ, de Figueiredo A. Recent trends in vaccine coverage and confidence: a cause for concern. Hum Vaccin Immunother. 2023;19(2):2237374.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilson SL, Wiysonge C. Social media and vaccine hesitancy. BMJ Glob Health. 2020;5(10):e004206.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnson NF, Velásquez N, Restrepo NJ, Leahy R, Gabriel N, El Oud S, et al. The online competition between pro‐ and anti‐vaccination views. Nature. 2020;582(7811):230–233.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Geoghegan S, O'Callaghan KP, Offit PA. Vaccine safety: myths and misinformation. Front Microbiol. 2020;11:372.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dubé E, Gagnon D, MacDonald N, Bocquier A, Peretti‐Watel P, Verger P. Underlying factors impacting vaccine hesitancy in high income countries: a review of qualitative studies. Expert Rev Vaccines. 2018;17(11):989–1004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cole WM, Schofer E, Velasco K. Individual empowerment, institutional confidence, and vaccination rates in cross‐National Perspective, 1995 to 2018. Am Sociol Rev. 2023;88(3):379–417.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dong E, Nixon K, Gardner LM. A population level study on the determinants of COVID‐19 vaccination rates at the U.S. county level. Sci Rep. 2024;14(1):4277.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alemi F, Lee KH. Impact of political leaning on COVID‐19 vaccine hesitancy: a network‐based multiple mediation analysis. Cureus. 2023;15(8):e43232. [cited 2024 May 6]; Available from: https://www.cureus.com/articles/166493-impact-of-political-leaning-on-covid-19-vaccine-hesitancy-a-network-based-multiple-mediation-analysis</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seara‐Morais GJ, Avelino‐Silva TJ, Couto M, Avelino‐Silva VI. The pervasive association between political ideology and COVID‐19 vaccine uptake in Brazil: an ecologic study. BMC Public Health. 2023;23(1):1606.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siani A, Tranter A. Is vaccine confidence an unexpected victim of the COVID‐19 pandemic? Vaccine. 2022;40(50):7262–7269.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. COVID data tracker. [cited 2024 may 6]. Available from: https://covid.cdc.gov/covid-data-tracker/#datatracker-home</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kriss JL, Hung MC, Srivastav A, Black CL, Lindley MC, Lee JT, et al. COVID‐19 vaccination coverage, by race and ethnicity—National Immunization Survey Adult COVID module, United States, December 2020–November 2021. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2022;71(23):757–763.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bajema KL, Rowneki M, Berry K, Bohnert A, Bowling CB, Boyko EJ, et al. Rates of and factors associated with primary and booster COVID‐19 vaccine receipt by US veterans, December 2020 to June 2022. JAMA Netw Open. 2023;6(2):e2254387.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bruxvoort KJ, Sy LS, Hong V, Lewin B, Qian L, Huang X, et al. Factors associated with uptake of bivalent mRNA COVID‐19 vaccines in a large US health care system. Vaccine. 2023;41(49):7460–7468.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aw J, Seng JJB, Seah SSY, Low LL. COVID‐19 vaccine hesitancy—a scoping review of literature in high‐income countries. Vaccine. 2021;9(8):900.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang XY, Gong RN, Sassine S, Morsa M, Tchogna AS, Drouin O, et al. Risk perception of COVID‐19 infection and adherence to preventive measures among adolescents and young adults. Children. 2020;7(12):311.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hilverda F, Vollmann M. The role of risk perception in Students' COVID‐19 vaccine uptake: a longitudinal study. Vaccine. 2021;10(1):22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ochieng C, Anand S, Mutwiri G, Szafron M, Alphonsus K. Factors associated with COVID‐19 vaccine hesitancy among visible minority groups from a global context: a scoping review. Vaccine. 2021;9(12):1445.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hussain B, Latif A, Timmons S, Nkhoma K, Nellums LB. Overcoming COVID‐19 vaccine hesitancy among ethnic minorities: a systematic review of UK studies. Vaccine. 2022;40(25):3413–3432.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kricorian K, Turner K. COVID‐19 vaccine acceptance and beliefs among Black and Hispanic Americans. Camacho‐Rivera M, editor. PLoS One. 2021;16(8):e0256122.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu P, Tatar O, Griffin‐Mathieu G, Perez S, Haward B, Zimet G, et al. The efficacy of a brief, altruism‐eliciting video intervention in enhancing COVID‐19 vaccination intentions among a population‐based sample of younger adults: randomized controlled trial. JMIR Public Health Surveill. 2022;8(5):e37328.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cucciniello M, Pin P, Imre B, Porumbescu GA, Melegaro A. Altruism and vaccination intentions: evidence from behavioral experiments. Soc Sci Med. 2022;292:114195.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shim E, Chapman GB, Townsend JP, Galvani AP. The influence of altruism on influenza vaccination decisions. J R Soc Interface. 2012;9(74):2234–2243.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Avelino‐Silva VI, Ferreira‐Silva SN, Soares MEM, Vasconcelos R, Fujita L, Medeiros T, et al. Say it right: measuring the impact of different communication strategies on the decision to get vaccinated. BMC Public Health. 2023;23(1):1162.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Penţa MA, Băban A. Message framing in vaccine communication: a systematic review of published literature. Health Commun. 2018;33(3):299–314.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>