<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39423630</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1532-2831</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>30</Volume><Issue>6</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>17</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Radiography (London, England : 1995)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Radiography (Lond)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Radiomics reproducibility in computed tomography through changes of ROI size, resolution, and hounsfield unit: A phantom study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1629</StartPage><EndPage>1636</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1629-1636</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.radi.2024.10.003</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S1078-8174(24)00300-6</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Although radiomics has revealed an intriguing perspective for quantitative radiology, the impact of scanning parameters on its outcomes must be considered. In this study, the effects of changes in the region of interest (ROI) sizes, Hounsfield Unit (HU), and resolution of computed tomography (CT) on feature reproducibility have been investigated.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">The GAMMEX 464 phantom was used to evaluate the reproducibility of radiomics features across different ROI sizes, HU, and resolution. Data were acquired using a consistent system setup, with the phantom repositioned for each scan. The first acquisition series examined the effects of different ROI sizes and resolutions (1, 3, and 5 mm) on feature reproducibility. The second series assessed the impact of different HU and resolution. Segmentation and feature extraction were performed using LIFEx 7.1.0 software, focusing on textural radiomics features. Statistical analysis involved calculating the coefficient of variation (COV) to categorize feature variability. COV &lt;5 % was considered highly stable.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Out of the 32 textural features studied, the analysis of changes in ROI size with a resolution of 1 mm, 3 mm, and 5 mm revealed that 16, 17, and 18 features had high reproducibility, with a COV&lt;5 %. Polyethylene, acrylic, and water also demonstrated stable textural features across changes in scan parameters and image resolutions, with 4 reproducible features in all resolutions. The grey-level run length matrix (GLRLM) and grey-level zone length matrix (GLZLM) radiomics groups were highly stable in the context of variations in scan parameters and different materials.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The results of this study highlight the importance of standardizing radiomics studies to reduce the influence of pre-analysis steps on feature values. This standardization is crucial for guaranteeing the consistency of radiomics features under various imaging conditions. Additional research is required to enhance these results.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="IMPLICATIONS FOR PRACTICE" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">To ensure the reproducibility and reliability of radiomics features, it is imperative to standardize scanning parameters and pre-analysis protocols. This standardization will enhance the consistency of radiomics applications in both clinical and research environments.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 The College of Radiographers. Published by Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Soleymani</LastName><ForeName>Y</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neuroscience and Addiction Studies, School of Advanced Technologies in Medicine, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran. Electronic address: soleymani.yunus@yahoo.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Valibeiglou</LastName><ForeName>Z</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Physics, School of Medicine, Tabriz University of Medical Sciences, Tabriz, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fazel Ghaziani</LastName><ForeName>M</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, Faculty of Allied Medical Sciences, Tabriz University of Medical Science, Tabriz, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jahanshahi</LastName><ForeName>A</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, Faculty of Medicine, Tabriz University of Medical Sciences, Tabriz, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khezerloo</LastName><ForeName>D</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, Faculty of Allied Medical Sciences, Tabriz University of Medical Science, Tabriz, Iran. Electronic address: khezerlood@tbzmed.ac.ir.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Radiography (Lond)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9604102</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1078-8174</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Computed tomography</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Quantitative image analysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Radiomics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Reproducibility</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Resolution</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflicts of interest The authors have no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39423630</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.radi.2024.10.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S1078-8174(24)00300-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>