<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39425192</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1472-6963</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>24</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>18</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC health services research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Health Serv Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Spatiotemporal evolution and development path of healthcare services supply in China.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1258</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1258</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1258</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12913-024-11545-4</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECT" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">Promoting the accessibility and equity of healthcare services, as well as enhancing service capacity, are crucial for building a sound healthcare system. Particularly in the past two years of the normalized COVID-19 situation, this issue has garnered widespread attention in the academic community. This study aims to investigate and analyze the characteristics and trends of the spatial-temporal evolution of healthcare service supply levels in China. It also seeks to explore the influencing factors and pathways for development, with the goal of optimizing the allocation of healthcare resources.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">This article uses the entropy weight TOPSIS method combined with Dagum Gini coefficient and Kernel density to evaluate the supply level of healthcare services in 31 provinces and cities in China from 2012 to 2020, and explores its development and spatial pattern characteristics. Then, through Moran index, panel regression model and spatial econometric testing, the spatial correlation problem and its influencing factors are further analyzed, and targeted policy recommendations are proposed based on it, laying the foundation for further promoting the balanced development of healthcare service supply capacity.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">(1) Healthcare services supply levels in various provinces and cities in China have significantly increased, with a shift in spatial distribution from 'higher in the east and lower in the west' to 'convergence between east and west, with lower levels in the central regions.' (2) Relative differences among regions are narrowing annually, primarily due to interactions between the four regions rather than within each region, with expanding impact of overlapping regions. (3) Absolute differences among regions are also decreasing, moving towards uniformity with a contraction of extension and a restraint on the trend towards multipolarization. (4) Spatial correlation between adjacent regions is weakening, eventually becoming non-significant, with fading spatial effects. (5) The correlation between local economic development, population factors, institutional arrangements, and the current state of supply is significant, and the research design and conclusions remain robust even after thorough consideration of spatial effects. The study explores the development pathways based on the objective existence of regional development and the controllable government actions.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The overall level of healthcare service supply in China has improved, but regional differences still exist. The objective level of regional development and the subjective behavior of local governments have a significant impact on the supply of healthcare services. Therefore, it is recommended that each region adapt to local conditions, identify its own strengths and weaknesses, coordinate resource supply and demand, consider the impact of key factors, and optimize the allocation of healthcare development resources.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Xiang-Min</ForeName><Initials>XM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Finance and Public Administration, Yunnan University of Finance and Economics, Kunming, 650221, People's Republic of China. lixmchn@163.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>2024Y505</GrantID><Agency>Yunnan Provincial Department of Education Science Research Fund Project</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2023YUFEYC027</GrantID><Agency>Yunnan University of Finance and Economics Graduate Innovation Fund</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Health Serv Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101088677</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1472-6963</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002681" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">China</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D062211" MajorTopicYN="Y">Spatio-Temporal Analysis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006296" MajorTopicYN="N">Health Services</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000600" MajorTopicYN="N">supply &amp; distribution</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006297" MajorTopicYN="N">Health Services Accessibility</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003695" MajorTopicYN="N">Delivery of Health Care</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000458" MajorTopicYN="N">organization &amp; administration</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Dagum Gini coefficient</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Dynamic evolution</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Healthcare services</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Kernel density estimation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Moran’s I</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Panel regression model</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Spatial econometric testing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Spatial pattern</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Supply level</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39425192</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11487962</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12913-024-11545-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12913-024-11545-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>The General Office of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of China and the General Office of the State Council. Opinions on Further Improving the Healthcare Service System [https://www.gov.cn/zhengce/2023-03/23/content_5748063.htm] Accessed on 23 Mar 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Ja, Liang S, Shi P. China’s opening up and trade. In: The Geography of Contemporary China edn.: Springer; 2022. p. 337–376. https://www.springer.com/series/13179</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen Y, Sun Z. Estimating the spatial correlation and convergence of China’s healthcare resources allocation: evidence from the Yangtze River Delta Region. Archives Public Health. 2022;80(1):207. 10.1186/s13690-022-00958-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9471039</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36104735</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sidel VW. he right to health care: an international perspective. Bioethics and Human Rights: A Reader for Health Professionals. 1978. p. 347.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weinstein M, Stason W. Allocating resources: the case of hypertension. Hastings Cent Rep. 1977;7(5). 10.2307/3560720.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">410753</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mechanic D. Rationing Health Care: Public Policy and the Medical Marketplace. Hastings Center Rep. 1976;6(1):34–7. 10.2307/3560360.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1254457</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mechanic D. Ethics, Justice, and Medical Care systems. Annals Am Acad Political Social Sci. 1978;437:74–85. http://www.jstor.org/stable/1042494.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Institute of Medicine (US) Committee on Assuring the Health of the Public in the 21st Century. The Future of the Public’s Health in the 21st Century. Washington (DC): National Academies Press (US). 2002. https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK221239/10.17226/10548.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25057638</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tiebout CM. A pure theory of local expenditures. J Polit Econ. 1956;64:416–24. 10.1086/257839.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fairman S. Commentary: Collaborative Governance for Innovation in the National Health Service: early reflections on the Development of Academic Health Science Networks. Public Adm Rev. 2013;73:831–2. 10.1111/puar.12149.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matteo LD. The determinants of the public-private mix in Canadian health care expenditures: 1975–1996. Health Policy. 2000;52:87–112. 10.1016/S0168-8510(00)00071-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10794839</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Z. The convergence of health care expenditure in the US states. Health Econ. 2009;18(1):55–70. 10.1007/s11205-016-1357-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18273915</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Costa-Font J, Pons-Novell J. Public health expenditure and spatial interactions in a decentralized national health system. Health Econ. 2007;16(3):291–306. 10.1002/hec.1154.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16981194</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Signorelli C, Odone A, Bianco D, Di Vivo N, Bevere F. La Spesa per la prevenzione in Italia (2006–2013): analisi descrittiva, trend regionali e confronti internazionali [Health expenditure for prevention in Italy (2006–2013): descriptive analysis, regional trends and international comparisons]. Epidemiol Prev. 2016;40(5):374–80. 10.19191/EP16.5.AD01.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27764919</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Behera DK, Mohanty RK, Dash U. Cyclicality of public health expenditure in India: role of fiscal transfer and domestic revenue mobilization. Int Rev Econ. 2020;67:87–110. 10.1007/s12232-019-00333-w.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alexander A, Madsen GL, Miller RW, Wakefield EL, Wise DS, K. K., Alexander RL. The state of nursing home Information Technology Sophistication in Rural and Nonrural US markets. JRural Health. 2017;33(3):266–74. 10.1111/jrh.12188.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27333002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mayaud JR, Tran M, Nuttall R. An urban data framework for assessing equity in cities: comparing accessibility to healthcare facilities in Cascadia. Comput Environ Urban Syst. 2019;78. 10.1016/j.compenvurbsys.2019.101401.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Young JC, Garro LY. Variation in the choice of treatment in two Mexican communities. Soc Sci Med. 1982;16(16):1453–65. 10.1016/0277-9536(82)90060-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7135019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pu L. Fairness of the distribution of Public Healthcare resources. Front Public Health. 2021;9:768728. 10.3389/fpubh.2021.768728.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8631734</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34858935</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin X, Wu J, Bashir AK, Yang W, Singh A, AlZubi AA. FairHealth: Long-Term Proportional Fairness-Driven 5G Edge Healthcare in Internet of Medical things. IEEE Trans Industr Inf. 2022;18(12):8905–15. 10.1109/TII.2022.3183000.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yao R, Zhang W, Evans R, Cao G, Rui T, Shen L. Inequities in Health Care services caused by the Adoption of Digital Health Technologies: scoping review. J Med Internet Res. 2022;24(3):e34144. 10.2196/34144.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8981004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35311682</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen B, Jin F. Spatial distribution, regional differences, and dynamic evolution of the healthcare services supply in China. Front Public Health. 2022;10:1020402. 10.3389/fpubh.2022.1020402.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9540227</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36211684</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Z, He H, Liu X, Wei H, Feng Q, Wei B. Health resource allocation in Western China from 2014 to 2018. Archives Public Health = Archives belges de sante Publique. 2023;81(1):30. 10.1186/s13690-023-01046-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9946701</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36814309</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Su W, Du L, Fan Y, Wang P. Equity and efficiency of public hospitals’ health resource allocation in Guangdong Province, China. Int J Equity Health. 2022;21(1):138. 10.1186/s12939-022-01741-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9493174</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36138478</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xia Y, Chen H, Zuo C, Zhang N. The Impact of Traffic on Equality of Urban Healthcare Service accessibility: a Case Study in Wuhan, China. Sustainable Cities Soc. 2022. 10.1016/j.scs.2022.104130.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zare H, Tavana M, Mardani A, Masoudian S, Kamali Saraji M. A hybrid data envelopment analysis and game theory model for performance measurement in healthcare. Health Care Manag Sci. 2019;22(3):475–88. 10.1007/s10729-018-9456-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30225622</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun J, Luo H. Evaluation on equality and efficiency of health resources allocation and health services utilization in China. Int J Equity Health. 2017;16(1):127. 10.1186/s12939-017-0614-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5513103</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28709422</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu Y, Li Y, Wu M, Fu H. How do Chinese people perceive their healthcare system? Trends and determinants of public satisfaction and perceived fairness, 2006–2019. BMC Health Serv Res. 2022;22(1):22. 10.1186/s12913-021-07413-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8725557</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34983522</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meesala A, Paul J. Service quality, consumer satisfaction and loyalty in hospitals: thinking for the future. J Retailing Consumer Serv. 2018;40:261–9. 10.1016/j.jretconser.2016.10.011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang L, Sun L, Wen L, Zhang H, Li C, Hanson K, Fang H. Financing strategies to improve essential public health equalization and its effects in China. Int J Equity Health. 2016;15(1):194. 10.1186/s12939-016-0482-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5134004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27905941</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding J, Hu X, Zhang X, Shang L, Yu M, Chen H. Equity and efficiency of healthcare service systems at the provincial level of China’s mainland: a comparative study from 2009 to 2014. BMC Public Health. 2018;18(1):214. 10.1186/s12889-018-5084-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5799902</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29402260</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>OECD. Developing Composite indicators for assessing Health System Efficiency, in measuring up: improving Health System performance in OECD Countries. Paris: OECD Publishing; 2003. 10.1787/9789264195950-16-en.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waters H. R. Measuring equity in access to health care. Soc Sci Med. 2000;51(4):599–612. 10.1016/s0277-9536(00)00003-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10868673</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Şahin TK, Ocak S, Top M. Analytic hierarchy process for hospital site selection. Health Policy Technol. 2019. 10.1016/j.hlpt.2019.02.005.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Z. The convergence of health care expenditure in the US states. Health Econ. 2009;18(1):55–70. 10.1002/hec.1343.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18273915</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dagum C. A new approach to the decomposition of the Gini income inequality ratio. Empirical Economics. 1997;22:515–31. 10.1007/BF01205777.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ge X, Xu J, Xie Y, Guo X, Yang D. Evaluation and dynamic evolution of Eco-efficiency of Resource-Based Cities—A case study of typical resource-based cities in China. Sustainability. 2021 10.3390/su13126802.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y. An analytical process of spatial autocorrelation functions based on Moran’s index. PLoS ONE. 2021;16(4):e0249589. 10.1371/journal.pone.0249589.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8046215</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33852621</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anselin L. Spatial econometrics: methods and models. Volume 4. Springer Science &amp; Business Media; 2013.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>