<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39428773</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1998-4022</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>72</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Neurology India</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Neurol India</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>MR Imaging in Covid-19-Associated Invasive Fungal Sinusitis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1009</StartPage><EndPage>1015</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1009-1015</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4103/neurol-india.ni_1225_21</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND AND AIM" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">We witnessed a sharp peak in the incidence of invasive fungal sinusitis, particularly mucormycosis, in patients with history of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) infection in India. Rhino-orbito-cerebral mucormycosis (ROCM) is a fulminant rapidly progressive disease. Early diagnosis significantly improves patient survival and outcomes. Hence, neuroimaging plays a very important role. We studied the magnetic resonance (MR) imaging manifestations of invasive fungal sinusitis and established an imaging protocol, which helps in early diagnosis of the disease per se as well as its complications. We evaluated the differences between COVID-19-associated and non-COVID-19-associated ROCM.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIALS AND METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">We retrospectively analyzed the MR imaging manifestations of 91 histopathologically proven cases of post-COVID-19-invasive fungal sinusitis.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">We observed stage I disease limited to sinuses in 25.2%, stage II disease with intraorbital spread in 23%, and stage III disease with intracranial spread in 51.6% of our patients. Dural involvement was the commonest and earliest sign of stage III disease. Direct parenchymal invasion from the adjacent paranasal sinuses was the commonest pattern of cerebral involvement, involving basifrontal lobe (14.2%) followed by anteromedial temporal lobe (5.4%). We observed orbital and intracranial complications including subperiosteal orbital abscess (1%), cavernous sinus involvement (29.6%), angioinvasion (15.3%), perineural spread (9.8%), and osteomyelitis of skull base and craniofacial bones (45%). Contrary to non-COVID-19-associated ROCM, we did not observe any case with superior ophthalmic vein/dural venous sinus thrombosis or basilar artery angioinvasion in our study.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">In our study, stage III disease was most commonly due to direct parenchymal invasion into frontal and temporal lobes from the adjacent frontal and sphenoid sinuses, respectively. The commonest vascular complications in our study were cavernous sinus involvement followed by angioinvasion into the cavernous ICA leading to watershed infarcts.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Copyright: © 2024 Neurology India, Neurological Society of India.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pabbisetti</LastName><ForeName>Divya</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, Krishna Institute of Medical Sciences, Secunderabad, Telangana, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gudipati</LastName><ForeName>Anantaram</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kaul</LastName><ForeName>Subhash</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nalla</LastName><ForeName>Sahithi</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>India</Country><MedlineTA>Neurol India</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0042005</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0028-3886</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000000981" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnostic imaging</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008279" MajorTopicYN="Y">Magnetic Resonance Imaging</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012189" MajorTopicYN="N">Retrospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012852" MajorTopicYN="Y">Sinusitis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000000981" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnostic imaging</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009091" MajorTopicYN="N">Mucormycosis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000000981" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnostic imaging</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055815" MajorTopicYN="N">Young Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000368" MajorTopicYN="N">Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007194" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">India</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000293" MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescent</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2022</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39428773</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/neurol-india.ni_1225_21</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">02223311-202409000-00014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Ravani S, Agrawal G, Leuva P, Modi P, Amin K. Rise of the phoenix: Mucormycosis in COVID-19 times. Indian J Ophthalmol 2021;69:1563–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rao R, Shetty A, Nagesh C. Orbital infarction syndrome secondary to rhino-orbital mucormycosis in a case of COVID-19: Clinico-radiological features. Indian J Ophthalmol 2021;69:1627–30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Skiada A, Pavleas I, Drogari-Apiranthitou M. Epidemiology and diagnosis of mucormycosis: An update. J Fungi (Basel) 2020;6:265.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chikley A, Ben-Ami R, Kontoyiannis DP. Mucormycosis of the central nervous system. J Fungi (Basel) 2019;5:59.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Honavar SG. Code mucor: Guidelines for the diagnosis, staging and management of rhino-orbito-cerebral mucormycosis in the setting of COVID-19. Indian J Ophthalmol 2021;69:1361–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Therakathu J, Prabhu S, Irodi A, Sudhakar SV, Yadav VK, Rupa V. Imaging features of rhinocerebral mucormycosis: A study of 43 patients. Egypt J Radiol Nucl Med 2018;49:447–52.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thajeb P, Thajeb T, Dai D. Fatal strokes in patients with rhino-orbito-cerebral mucormycosis and associated vasculopathy. Scand J Infect Dis 2004;36:643–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turunc T, Demiroglu YZ, Aliskan H, Colakoglu S, Arslan H. Eleven cases of mucormycosis with atypical clinical manifestations in diabetic patients. Diabetes Res Clin Pract 2008;82:203–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herrera D, Dublin A, Ormsby E, Aminpour S, Howell L. Imaging findings of rhinocerebral mucormycosis. Skull Base 2009;19:117–25.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takahashi S, Horiguchi T, Mikami S, Kitamura Y, Kawase T. Subcortical intracerebral hemorrhage caused by mucormycosis in a patient with a history of bone-marrow transplantation. J Stroke Cerebrovasc Dis 2009;18:405–6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dubey S, Mukherjee D, Sarkar P, Mukhopadhyay P, Barman D, Bandopadhyay M, et al. COVID-19 associated rhino-orbital-cerebral mucormycosis: An observational study from Eastern India, with special emphasis on neurological spectrum. Diabetes Metab Syndr 2021;15:102267.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Kholy NA, El-Fattah AMA, Khafagy YW. invasive fungal sinusitis in post COVID-19 patients: A new clinical entity. Laryngoscope 2021;131:2652–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhattacharyya A, Sarma P, Sharma DJ, Das KK, Kaur H, Prajapat M, et al. COVID- 19-associated rhino-orbital-cerebral mucromycosis: A systematic review, meta-analysis, meta-regression analysis. Indian J Pharmacol 2021;53:499–510.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nehara HR, Puri I, Singhal V, Ih S, Bishnoi BR, Sirohi P. Rhinocerebral mucormycosis in COVID-19 patient with diabetes a deadly trio: Case series from the north-western part of India. Indian J Med Microbiol 2021;39:380–3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fouad YA, Abdelaziz TT, Askoura A, Saleh MI, Mahmoud MS, Ashour DM, et al. Spike in rhino-orbital-cerebral mucormycosis cases presenting to a tertiary care center during the COVID-19 pandemic. Front Med (Lausanne) 2021;8:645270.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joshi AR, Muthe MM, Patankar SH, Athawale A, Achhapalia Y. CT and MRI findings of invasive mucormycosis in the setting of COVID-19: Experience from a single center in India. AJR Am J Roentgenol 2021;217:1431–2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mazzai L, Anglani M, Giraudo C, Martucci M, Cester G, Causin F. Imaging features of rhinocerebral mucormycosis: From onset to vascular complications. Acta Radiol 2021;20:0284185120988828.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan L-L, Singh S, Jones D, Diaz EM Jr, Ginsberg LE. Imaging of mucormycosis skull base osteomyelitis. Am J Neuroradiol 2000;21:828–31.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>