<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39426125</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2211-0356</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>92</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>11</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Multiple sclerosis and related disorders</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Mult Scler Relat Disord</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The correlation between rituximab dose reduction and acute relapses of neuromyelitis optica spectrum disorder, lessons from COVID-19 epidemic.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>105940</StartPage><MedlinePgn>105940</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.msard.2024.105940</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S2211-0348(24)00516-9</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">COVID-19 was a viral infection that led to a global pandemic in March 2020. At the beginning of the pandemic, clinicians encountered the challenge of how immunosuppressive treatments would affect the course of COVID-19 infection in people with autoimmune diseases. Neuromyelitis optica spectrum disorder is an autoimmune astrocytopathy that is caused by an inflammation in the CNS. Major treatments to prevent acute relapses include immunosuppressive drugs. Rituximab is a well-established immunosuppressive agent in NMOSD maintenance therapy. Some reports suggested that treatment with Rituximab might increase the risk of COVID-19 infection and its mortality in NMOSD. On the other hand, dose reduction or extended interval treatment might lead to acute relapses of NMOSD and permanent disability.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">In this study, we evaluated the correlation between the dose of rituximab and the relapse rate of NMOSD during an epidemic. This was an observational study on 171 patients among whom 55 cases were seropositive. Some patients received full dose rituximab routinely (1000 mg/dose, every 6 months), but others were treated with half dose (500 mg/dose) during the epidemic. Also, some doses were prescribed with a delay, based on the level of CD19 and CD20.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The Pearson correlation coefficient (r) showed a negative and significant relation (r: - 0.19, p: 0.022) between the amount of drug and the number of relapses in the seropositive group, so low dosage of the drug was related to more acute relapses. In seronegative cases, there was not any valuable relationship. (p: 0.367).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Lower dose of rituximab, especially in seropositive NMOSD patients, can potentially lead to acute relapses. So, the more frequent evaluation of the CD19, CD20, and, CD27 levels, and the general clinical condition of the patients should be considered.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ashtari</LastName><ForeName>Fereshteh</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Neurology Department, Isfahan Neuroscience Research Center, Isfahan University of Medical Science(,) Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mehdipour</LastName><ForeName>Roshanak</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Isfahan Neuroscience Research Center, Isfahan University of Medical Science, Iran. Electronic address: roshym13@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Asgari</LastName><ForeName>Mina</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Isfahan University of Medical Sciences, Isfahan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ghalamkari</LastName><ForeName>Arshia</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Isfahan University of Medical Sciences, Isfahan, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Mult Scler Relat Disord</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101580247</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2211-0348</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Demyelinating disease</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Neuromyelitis optica</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Rituximab</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest On behalf of all authors, the corresponding author states that: The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper. Any of theauthor is an Editorial Board Member/Editor-in-Chief/Associate Editor/Guest Editor for Multiple Sclerosis and Related Disorders journal and was not involved in the editorial review or the decision to publish this article.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39426125</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.msard.2024.105940</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2211-0348(24)00516-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>