<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39428555</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1976-9148</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>21</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Biomolecules &amp; therapeutics</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Biomol Ther (Seoul)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Is There such a Thing as Post-Viral Depression?: Implications for Precision Medicine.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4062/biomolther.2024.170</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Viral infections are increasingly recognized as triggers for depressive disorders, particularly following the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic and the rise of long COVID. Viruses such as Herpes Simplex Virus (HSV), Epstein-Barr Virus (EBV), Cytomegalovirus (CMV), and Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) are linked to depression through complex neurobiological mechanisms. These include immune system dysregulation, chronic inflammation, and neurotransmitter imbalances that affect brain function and mood regulation. Viral activation of the immune system leads to the release of pro-inflammatory cytokines, resulting in neuroinflammation and associated depressive symptoms. Furthermore, specific viruses can disrupt neurotransmitter systems, including serotonin, dopamine, and glutamate, all of which are essential for mood stabilization. The unique interactions of different viruses with these systems underscore the need for virus-specific therapeutic approaches. Current broad-spectrum treatments often overlook the precise neurobiological pathways involved in post-viral depression, reducing their efficacy. This review emphasizes the need to understand these virus-specific interactions to create tailored interventions that directly address the neurobiological effects induced by each type of virus. These interventions may include immunomodulatory treatments that target persistent inflammation, antiviral therapies to reduce the viral load, or neuroprotective strategies that restore neurotransmitter balance. Precision medicine offers promising avenues for the effective management of virus-induced depression, providing patient-specific approaches that address the specific biological mechanisms involved. By focusing on the development of these targeted treatments, this review aims to pave the way for a new era in psychiatric care that fully addresses the root causes of depression induced by viral infections.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Park</LastName><ForeName>Eun-Sook</ForeName><Initials>ES</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Biomedical Science and Technology, School of Medicine, Konkuk University, Seoul 05029, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shin</LastName><ForeName>Chan Young</ForeName><Initials>CY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Medicine and Center for Neuroscience Research, Konkuk University, Seoul 05029, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacology and Department of Advanced Translational Medicine, School of Medicine, Konkuk University, Seoul 05029, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Biomedical Sciences &amp; Technology, Konkuk University, Seoul 05029, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jeon</LastName><ForeName>Se Jin</ForeName><Initials>SJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacology, College of Medicine, Hallym University, Chuncheon 24252, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ham</LastName><ForeName>Byung-Joo</ForeName><Initials>BJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, Korea University Anam Hospital, Korea University College of Medicine, Seoul 02841, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Korea (South)</Country><MedlineTA>Biomol Ther (Seoul)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101472832</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1976-9148</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Depression</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Epigenetics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mitochondria</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Neurotransmitter imbalance</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Precision medicine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Viral infection</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>48</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>48</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39428555</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4062/biomolther.2024.170</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">biomolther.2024.170</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>