<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39428551</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1099-1654</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>34</Volume><Issue>6</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Reviews in medical virology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Rev Med Virol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Next-Generation Sequencing Methods for Near-Real-Time Molecular Epidemiology of HIV and HCV.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70001</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70001</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/rmv.70001</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The World Health Organisation has set targets of reducing the transmission of new hepatitis C (HCV) infections by 90%, and ending human immunodeficiency virus-1 (HIV) as a public health threat, by 2030. To achieve this, efficient and timely viral surveillance, and effective public health interventions, are required. Traditional epidemiological methods are largely dependent on the recognition of incident cases with symptomatic illness; acute HIV and HCV infections are commonly asymptomatic, which may lead to delays in the recognition of such new infections. Instead, for these viruses, molecular epidemiology may improve the detection of, and response to, clusters of viral transmission. Molecular epidemiology using historical datasets has highlighted key populations that may have benefitted from a timely intervention. Similar analyses performed on contemporary samples are needed to underpin the 2030 targets, but this requires the generation of a cohesive dataset of viral genome sequences in near-real-time. To generate such data, methodologies harnessing next-generation sequencing (NGS) should be utilised. Here we discuss the opportunity presented by NGS for public health surveillance of HIV and HCV, and discuss three methods that can generate sequences for such analysis. These include full-length genome amplification, utilised for analysis of HCV in the research space; tiling PCR, which was the method of choice for many diagnostic laboratories in the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic; and bait-capture hybridisation, which has been utilised in local HIV outbreaks. These techniques could be applied for near-real-time HIV and HCV surveillance, informing public health strategies that will be key to achieving 2030 targets.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Reviews in Medical Virology published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Horsburgh</LastName><ForeName>Bethany A</ForeName><Initials>BA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4263-2351</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine, The Kirby Institute, University of New South Wales, Sydney, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Walker</LastName><ForeName>Gregory J</ForeName><Initials>GJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Virology Research Laboratory, Serology and Virology Division (SAViD), Prince of Wales Hospital, Randwick, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine, School of Biomedical Sciences, University of New South Wales, Sydney, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kelleher</LastName><ForeName>Anthony</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine, The Kirby Institute, University of New South Wales, Sydney, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lloyd</LastName><ForeName>Andrew R</ForeName><Initials>AR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine, The Kirby Institute, University of New South Wales, Sydney, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bull</LastName><ForeName>Rowena A</ForeName><Initials>RA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9844-3744</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine, The Kirby Institute, University of New South Wales, Sydney, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine, School of Biomedical Sciences, University of New South Wales, Sydney, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Giallonardo</LastName><ForeName>Francesca Di</ForeName><Initials>FD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine, The Kirby Institute, University of New South Wales, Sydney, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Australian Government</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Rev Med Virol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9112448</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1052-9276</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006526" MajorTopicYN="Y">Hepatitis C</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D059014" MajorTopicYN="Y">High-Throughput Nucleotide Sequencing</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015658" MajorTopicYN="Y">HIV Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000635" MajorTopicYN="N">transmission</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017720" MajorTopicYN="Y">Molecular Epidemiology</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016174" MajorTopicYN="Y">Hepacivirus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000145" MajorTopicYN="N">classification</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="N">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016679" MajorTopicYN="N">Genome, Viral</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015497" MajorTopicYN="N">HIV-1</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">HCV</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">HIV</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">assays</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">next‐generation‐sequencing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">surveillance</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">transmission</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>49</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>48</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39428551</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/rmv.70001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization, Global Progress Report on HIV, Viral Hepatitis and Sexually Transmitted Infections (O WH, 2021), https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240027077.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Barré‐Sinoussi, S. S. Abdool Karim, J. Albert, et al., “Expert Consensus Statement on the Science of HIV in the Context of Criminal Law,” Journal of the International AIDS Society 21, no. 7 (2018): e25161, https://doi.org/10.1002/jia2.25161.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Boyd, D. Cooper, E. A. Crock, et al., “Sexual Transmission of HIV and the Law: An Australian Medical Consensus Statement,” Medical Journal of Australia 205, no. 9 (2016): 409–412, https://doi.org/10.5694/mja16.00934.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. M. Volz, J. S. Koopman, M. J. Ward, A. L. Brown, and S. D. W. Frost, “Simple Epidemiological Dynamics Explain Phylogenetic Clustering of HIV From Patients With Recent Infection,” PLoS Computational Biology 8, no. 6 (2012): e1002552, https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002552.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. M. Mansky and H. M. Temin, “Lower In Vivo Mutation Rate of Human Immunodeficiency Virus Type 1 Than That Predicted From the Fidelity of Purified Reverse Transcriptase,” Journal of Virology 69, no. 8 (1995): 5087–5094, https://doi.org/10.1128/jvi.69.8.5087‐5094.1995.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Bartenschlager and V. Lohmann, “Replication of Hepatitis C Virus,” Journal of General Virology 81, no. pt. 7 (2000): 1631–1648, https://doi.org/10.1099/0022‐1317‐81‐7‐1631.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. M. Oster, J. O. Wertheim, A. L. Hernandez, M. C. B. Ocfemia, N. Saduvala, and H. I. Hall, “Using Molecular HIV Surveillance Data to Understand Transmission Between Subpopulations in the United States,” Journal of Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndromes 70, no. 4 (2015): 444–451, https://doi.org/10.1097/QAI.0000000000000809.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. D. Rice, J. Elford, Z. Yin, and V. C. Delpech, “A New Method to Assign Country of HIV Infection Among Heterosexuals Born Abroad and Diagnosed With HIV,” AIDS 26, no. 15 (2012): 1961–1966, https://doi.org/10.1097/qad.0b013e3283578b80.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. B. Cunningham, B. Jacka, K. DeBeck, et al., “Methamphetamine Injecting Is Associated With Phylogenetic Clustering of Hepatitis C Virus Infection Among Street‐Involved Youth in Vancouver, Canada,” Drug and Alcohol Dependence 152 (2015): 272–276, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2015.04.005.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. O. Wertheim, C. Chato, and A. F. Y. Poon, “Comparative Analysis of HIV Sequences in Real Time for Public Health,” Current Opinion in HIV and AIDS 14, no. 3 (2019): 213–220, https://doi.org/10.1097/coh.0000000000000539.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Verbeeck, M. J. Stanley, J. Shieh, et al., “Evaluation of Versant Hepatitis C Virus Genotype Assay (LiPA) 2.0,” Journal of Clinical Microbiology 46, no. 6 (2008): 1901–1906, https://doi.org/10.1128/jcm.02390‐07.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization, Hepatitis C Drug Resistance Webinar: Awareness of Hepatitis C Drug Resistance as Access to Hepatitis C Diagnosis and Treatment Expands (2023), https://www.who.int/news‐room/events/detail/2023/11/22/default‐calendar/hepatitis‐c‐drug‐resistance‐webinar‐awareness‐of‐hcv‐drug‐resistance.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Heard, F. Zolala, and L. Maher, Australian Needle Syringe Program Survey National Data Report 2018‐2022: Prevalence of HIV, HCV and Injecting and Sexual Behaviour Among NSP Attendees. Kirby Institute (UNSW, 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Grebely, C. Markus, L. M. Causer, et al., “A National Programme to Scale‐Up Decentralised Hepatitis C Point‐Of‐Care Testing and Treatment in Australia,” Lancet Gastroenterology Hepatology 8, no. 3 (2023): 204–207, https://doi.org/10.1016/S2468‐1253(22)00355‐7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Department of Health and Aged Care, Sixth National Hepatitis C Strategy 2023–2030 (Australian Government, 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. M. Johannesson, R. H. Fridriksdottir, T. J. Löve, et al., “High Rate of Hepatitis C Virus Reinfection Among Recently Injecting Drug Users: Results From the TraP Hep C Program‐A Prospective Nationwide, Population‐Based Study,” Clinical Infectious Diseases 75, no. 10 (2022): 1732–1739, https://doi.org/10.1093/cid/ciac272.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. F. Manso, D. F. Bibby, K. Lythgow, et al., “Technical Validation of a Hepatitis C Virus Whole Genome Sequencing Assay for Detection of Genotype and Antiviral Resistance in the Clinical Pathway,” Frontiers in Microbiology 11 (2020), https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2020.576572.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thomson E., C. L. C. Ip, A. Badhan, et al., “Comparison of Next‐Generation Sequencing Technologies for Comprehensive Assessment of Full‐Length Hepatitis C Viral Genomes,” Journal of Clinical Microbiology 54, no. 10 (2016): 2470–2484, https://doi.org/10.1128/JCM.00330‐16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. F. Poon, R. Gustafson, P. Daly, et al., “Near Real‐Time Monitoring of HIV Transmission Hotspots From Routine HIV Genotyping: An Implementation Case Study,” Lancet HIV 3, no. 5 (2016): e231–e238, https://doi.org/10.1016/s2352‐3018(16)00046‐1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. M. Oster, S. B. Lyss, R. P. McClung, et al., “HIV Cluster and Outbreak Detection and Response: The Science and Experience,” American Journal of Preventive Medicine 61, no. 5 (2021): S130–S142, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.amepre.2021.05.029.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. M. Oster, A. M. France, R. P. McClung, et al., “The CDC HIV Outbreak Coordination Unit: Developing a Standardized, Collaborative Approach to HIV Outbreak Assessment and Response,” Public Health Reports 137, no. 4 (2022): 643–648, https://doi.org/10.1177/00333549211018678.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Molldrem and A. K. J. Smith, “Reassessing the Ethics of Molecular HIV Surveillance in the Era of Cluster Detection and Response: Toward HIV Data Justice,” American Journal of Bioethics 20, no. 10 (2020): 10–23, https://doi.org/10.1080/15265161.2020.1806373.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. McClelland, A. Guta, and M. Gagnon, “The Rise of Molecular HIV Surveillance: Implications on Consent and Criminalization,” Critical Public Health 30, no. 4 (2020): 487–493, https://doi.org/10.1080/09581596.2019.1582755.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. P. McClung, A. D. Atkins, M. Kilkenny, et al., “Response to a Large HIV Outbreak, Cabell County, West Virginia, 2018,” American Journal of Preventive Medicine 61, no. 5 (2021): S143–S150, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.amepre.2021.05.039.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. Novitsky, S. Moyo, Q. Lei, V. DeGruttola, and M. Essex, “Importance of Viral Sequence Length and Number of Variable and Informative Sites in Analysis of HIV Clustering,” AIDS Research and Human Retroviruses 31, no. 5 (2015): 531–542, https://doi.org/10.1089/aid.2014.0211.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Yebra, E. B. Hodcroft, M. L. Ragonnet‐Cronin, et al., “Using Nearly Full‐Genome HIV Sequence Data Improves Phylogeny Reconstruction in a Simulated Epidemic,” Scientific Reports 6, no. 1 (2016): 39489, https://doi.org/10.1038/srep39489.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. K. Alidjinou, J. Deldalle, C. Hallaert, et al., “RNA and DNA Sanger Sequencing Versus Next‐Generation Sequencing for HIV‐1 Drug Resistance Testing in Treatment‐Naive Patients,” Journal of Antimicrobial Chemotherapy 72, no. 10 (2017): 2823–2830, https://doi.org/10.1093/jac/dkx232.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Casadellà and R. Paredes, “Deep Sequencing for HIV‐1 Clinical Management,” Virus Research 239 (2017): 69–81, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.virusres.2016.10.019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U. M. Parikh, K. McCormick, G. van Zyl, and J. W. Mellors, “Future Technologies for Monitoring HIV Drug Resistance and Cure,” Current Opinion in HIV and AIDS 12, no. 2 (2017): 182–189, https://doi.org/10.1097/COH.0000000000000344.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Ji, E. Enns, C. J. Brumme, et al., “Bioinformatic Data Processing Pipelines in Support of Next‐Generation Sequencing‐Based HIV Drug Resistance Testing: The Winnipeg Consensus,” Journal of the International AIDS Society 21, no. 10 (2018): e25193, https://doi.org/10.1002/jia2.25193.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Ji, P. Sandstrom, R. Paredes, et al., “Are We Ready for NGS HIV Drug Resistance Testing? The Second ‘Winnipeg Consensus’ Symposium,” Viruses 12, no. 6 (2020): 586, https://doi.org/10.3390/v12060586.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. A. Bull, T. N. Adikari, J. M. Ferguson, et al., “Analytical Validity of Nanopore Sequencing for Rapid SARS‐CoV‐2 Genome Analysis,” Nature Communications 11, no. 1 (2020): 6272, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467‐020‐20075‐6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Ni, X. Liu, Z. M. Simeneh, M. Yang, and R. Li, “Benchmarking of Nanopore R10.4 and R9.4.1 Flow Cells in Single‐Cell Whole‐Genome Amplification and Whole‐Genome Shotgun Sequencing,” Computational and Structural Biotechnology Journal 21 (2023): 2352–2364, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.csbj.2023.03.038.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Arslan, F. J. Garcia, M. Guo, et al., “Sequencing by Avidity Enables High Accuracy With Low Reagent Consumption,” Nature Biotechnology 42, no. 1 (2024): 132–138, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41587‐023‐01750‐7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Metrichor, Oxford Nanopore Technologies (EPI2ME, 2024), https://labs.epi2me.io/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. L. Kalantar, T. Carvalho, C. F. A. de Bourcy, et al., “IDseq—An Open Source Cloud‐Based Pipeline and Analysis Service for Metagenomic Pathogen Detection and Monitoring,” GigaScience 9, no. 10 (2020), https://doi.org/10.1093/gigascience/giaa111.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Thenin‐Houssier and S. T. Valente, “HIV‐1 Capsid Inhibitors as Antiretroviral Agents,” Current HIV Research 14, no. 3 (2016): 270–282, https://doi.org/10.2174/1570162x14999160224103555.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Temereanca and S. Ruta, “Strategies to Overcome HIV Drug Resistance‐Current and Future Perspectives,” Frontiers in Microbiology 14 (2023): 1133407, https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2023.1133407.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Jin, D. Li, M. H. Lin, L. Li, and D. Harrich, “Tat‐Based Therapies as an Adjuvant for an HIV‐1 Functional Cure,” Viruses 12, no. 4 (2020): 415, https://doi.org/10.3390/v12040415.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. A. Bull, A. A. Eltahla, C. Rodrigo, et al., “A Method for Near Full‐Length Amplification and Sequencing for Six Hepatitis C Virus Genotypes,” BMC Genomics 17, no. 1 (2016): 247, https://doi.org/10.1186/s12864‐016‐2575‐8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Riaz, P. Leung, K. Barton, et al., “Adaptation of Oxford Nanopore Technology for Hepatitis C Whole Genome Sequencing and Identification of Within‐Host Viral Variants,” BMC Genomics 22, no. 1 (2021): 148, https://doi.org/10.1186/s12864‐021‐07460‐1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. R. Lapointe, W. Dong, W. W. Y. Dong, et al., “Validation of a Genotype‐independent Hepatitis C Virus Near‐Whole Genome Sequencing Assay,” Viruses 13, no. 9 (2021): 1721, https://doi.org/10.3390/v13091721.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. A. Eltahla, P. Leung, M. R. Pirozyan, et al., “Dynamic Evolution of Hepatitis C Virus Resistance‐Associated Substitutions in the Absence of Antiviral Treatment,” Scientific Reports 7, no. 1 (2017): 41719, https://doi.org/10.1038/srep41719.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Rodrigo, A. A. Eltahla, R. A. Bull, et al., “Phylogenetic Analysis of Full‐Length, Early Infection, Hepatitis C Virus Genomes Among People With Intravenous Drug Use: The InC(3) Study,” Journal of Viral Hepatitis 24, no. 1 (2017): 43–52, https://doi.org/10.1111/jvh.12616.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Koopsen, G. Matthews, J. Rockstroh, et al., “Hepatitis C Virus Transmission Between Eight High‐Income Countries Among Men Who Have Sex With Men: A Whole‐Genome Analysis,” Lancet Microbe 4, no. 8 (2023): e622–e631, https://doi.org/10.1016/S2666‐5247(23)00108‐8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Quick, N. D. Grubaugh, S. T. Pullan, et al., “Multiplex PCR Method for MinION and Illumina Sequencing of Zika and Other Virus Genomes Directly From Clinical Samples,” Nature Protocols 12, no. 6 (2017): 1261–1276, https://doi.org/10.1038/nprot.2017.066.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Quick, N. J. Loman, S. Duraffour, et al., “Real‐Time, Portable Genome Sequencing for Ebola Surveillance,” Nature 530, no. 7589 (2016): 228–232, https://doi.org/10.1038/nature16996.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. R. Tyson, P. James, D. Stoddart, et al., “Improvements to the ARTIC Multiplex PCR Method for SARS‐CoV‐2 Genome Sequencing Using Nanopore,” bioRxiv (2020), https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.09.04.283077.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. E. Freed, M. Vlková, M. B. Faisal, and O. K. Silander, “Rapid and Inexpensive Whole‐Genome Sequencing of SARS‐CoV‐2 Using 1200 Bp Tiled Amplicons and Oxford Nanopore Rapid Barcoding,” Biology Methods Protocol 5, no. 1 (2020): bpaa014, https://doi.org/10.1093/biomethods/bpaa014.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Plitnick J., Griesemer S., Lasek‐Nesselquist E., et al., “Whole‐Genome Sequencing of SARS‐CoV‐2: Assessment of the Ion Torrent AmpliSeq Panel and Comparison With the Illumina MiSeq ARTIC Protocol,” Journal of Clinical Microbiology59, no. 1 (2021): e721, https://doi.org/10.1128/JCM.00649‐21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. S. Gonzalez‐Reiche, M. M. Hernandez, M. J. Sullivan, et al., “Introductions and Early Spread of SARS‐CoV‐2 in the New York City Area,” Science 369, no. 6501 (2020): 297–301, https://doi.org/10.1126/science.abc1917.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. T. Maurano, S. Ramaswami, P. Zappile, et al., “Sequencing Identifies Multiple Early Introductions of SARS‐CoV‐2 to the New York City Region,” Genome Research 30, no. 12 (2020): 1781–1788, https://doi.org/10.1101/gr.266676.120.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Lu, L. du Plessis, Z. Liu, et al., “Genomic Epidemiology of SARS‐CoV‐2 in Guangdong Province, China,” Cell 181, no. 5 (2020): 997–1003, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2020.04.023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. W. Meredith, W. L. Hamilton, B. Warne, et al., “Rapid Implementation of SARS‐CoV‐2 Sequencing to Investigate Cases of Health‐Care Associated COVID‐19: A Prospective Genomic Surveillance Study,” Lancet Infectious Diseases 20, no. 11 (2020): 1263–1271, https://doi.org/10.1016/S1473‐3099(20)30562‐4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. S. Eden, R. Rockett, I. Carter, et al., “An Emergent Clade of SARS‐CoV‐2 Linked to Returned Travellers From Iran,” Virus Evol 6, no. 1 (2020): veaa027, https://doi.org/10.1093/ve/veaa027.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. J. Rockett, A. Arnott, C. Lam, et al., “Revealing COVID‐19 Transmission in Australia by SARS‐CoV‐2 Genome Sequencing and Agent‐Based Modeling,” Nature Medicine 26, no. 9 (2020): 1398–1404, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41591‐020‐1000‐7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Seemann, C. R. Lane, N. L. Sherry, et al., “Tracking the COVID‐19 Pandemic in Australia Using Genomics,” Nature Communications 11, no. 1 (2020): 4376, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467‐020‐18314‐x.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. R. Lane, N. L. Sherry, A. F. Porter, et al., “Genomics‐Informed Responses in the Elimination of COVID‐19 in Victoria, Australia: An Observational, Genomic Epidemiological Study,” Lancet Public Health 6, no. 8 (2021): e547–e556, https://doi.org/10.1016/S2468‐2667(21)00133‐X.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. S. Kuchinski, J. Nguyen, T. D. Lee, et al., “Mutations in Emerging Variant of Concern Lineages Disrupt Genomic Sequencing of SARS‐CoV‐2 Clinical Specimens,” International Journal of Infectious Diseases 114 (2022): 51–54, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijid.2021.10.050.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davis J. J., Long S. W., Christensen P. A., et al., “Analysis of the ARTIC Version 3 and Version 4 SARS‐CoV‐2 Primers and Their Impact on the Detection of the G142D Amino Acid Substitution in the Spike Protein,” Microbiology Spectrum 9, no. 3 (2021): e01803‐e01821, https://doi.org/10.1128/Spectrum.01803‐21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Yakovleva, G. Kovalenko, M. Redlinger, et al., “Hepatitis C Virus in People With Experience of Injection Drug Use Following Their Displacement to Southern Ukraine before 2020,” BMC Infectious Diseases 23, no. 1 (2023): 446, https://doi.org/10.1186/s12879‐023‐08423‐5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. J. Williams, H. Tutil, S. Roy, et al., “Utilization of Agilent SureSelect Target Enrichment for Whole Genome Sequencing of Viruses and Bacteria,” Agilent in Application Note, (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agilent, “Bridging the Efficiency and Throughput Gap With Magnis Automated NGS Library Preparation Solution,” Agilent in White Paper, (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. M. Fogel, D. Bonsall, V. Cummings, et al., “Performance of a High‐Throughput Next‐Generation Sequencing Method for Analysis of HIV Drug Resistance and Viral Load,” Journal of Antimicrobial Chemotherapy 75, no. 12 (2020): 3510–3516, https://doi.org/10.1093/jac/dkaa352.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Bonsall, T. Golubchik, M. de Cesare, et al., “A Comprehensive Genomics Solution for HIV Surveillance and Clinical Monitoring in Low‐Income Settings,” Journal of Clinical Microbiology 58, no. 10 (2020): e420, https://doi.org/10.1128/JCM.00382‐20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wymant C., Bezemer D., Blanquart F., et al., “A Highly Virulent Variant of HIV‐1 Circulating in the Netherlands,” Science 375, no. 6580 (2020): 540‐545, https://doi.org/10.1126/science.abk1688.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Monod, A. Brizzi, R. M. Galiwango, et al., “Longitudinal Population‐Level HIV Epidemiologic and Genomic Surveillance Highlights Growing Gender Disparity of HIV Transmission in Uganda,” Nature Microbiology 9, no. 1 (2024): 35–54, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41564‐023‐01530‐8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Abdullahi, I. M. Kida, U. A. Maina, et al., “Limited Emergence of Resistance to Integrase Strand Transfer Inhibitors (INSTIs) in ART‐Experienced Participants Failing Dolutegravir‐Based Antiretroviral Therapy: A Cross‐Sectional Analysis of a Northeast Nigerian Cohort,” Journal of Antimicrobial Chemotherapy 78, no. 8 (2023): 2000–2007, https://doi.org/10.1093/jac/dkad195.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Beerenwinkel and O. Zagordi, “Ultra‐Deep Sequencing for the Analysis of Viral Populations,” Current Opinion Virology 1, no. 5 (2011): 413–418, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.coviro.2011.07.008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. R. Head, H. K. Komori, S. A. LaMere, et al., “Library Construction for Next‐Generation Sequencing: Overviews and Challenges,” Biotechniques 56, no. 2 (2014): 61–77, https://doi.org/10.2144/000114133.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Van Laethem, K. Theys, and A. M. Vandamme, “HIV‐1 Genotypic Drug Resistance Testing: Digging Deep, Reaching Wide?,” Current Opinion Virology 14 (2015): 16–23, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.coviro.2015.06.001.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. J. Metzner, “Technologies for HIV‐1 Drug Resistance Testing: Inventory and Needs,” Current Opinion in HIV and AIDS 17, no. 4 (2022): 222–228, https://doi.org/10.1097/coh.0000000000000737.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Jenkins, T. Le, R. Farhat, et al., “Validation of an HIV Whole Genome Sequencing Method for HIV Drug Resistance Testing in an Australian Clinical Microbiology Laboratory,” Journal of Medical Virology 95, no. 12 (2023): e29273, https://doi.org/10.1002/jmv.29273.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>HIVREsnet, WHO HIVResNet HIV Drug Resistance Laboratory Operational Framework. Second (WHO, 2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Zhou, X. L. Yang, X. G. Wang, et al., “A Pneumonia Outbreak Associated With a New Coronavirus of Probable Bat Origin,” Nature 579, no. 7798 (2020): 270–273, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586‐020‐2012‐7.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>