<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39439046</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1440-1630</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>22</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Australian occupational therapy journal</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Aust Occup Ther J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Investigating patient satisfaction with a hand therapy telehealth service during COVID-19.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1440-1630.13003</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Throughout the COVID-19 pandemic, outpatient hand therapy services were restricted. The use of telehealth was adopted to continue to provide care to patients with hand injuries. This survey aims to investigate patient satisfaction with hand therapy delivered via telehealth in a NSW public tertiary referral metropolitan setting and explore whether this differs for specific hand injury/conditions and treatments offered.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Patients using hand therapy services via telehealth between 28 June 2021 and 27 May 2022 responded to a bespoke electronic survey. Participants were grouped depending on their particular injury/condition and treatment received. Analysis was conducted using MS Excel, and correlations were determined by using Fisher's exact test.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="COMMUNITY AND CONSUMER INVOLVEMENT" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">No consumers were involved in the study design or analysis.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Sixty-eight of 262 patients responded to the survey (26% response rate). Overall results showed high patient satisfaction (n = 55, 81%) with hand therapy delivered via telehealth with most patients agreeing that telehealth should be offered going forward (n = 59, 87%). Benefits reported by patients included convenience, reduced travel time and parking issues, and time saving. Patients receiving therapy for 'finger thumb bony injury with K wires' demonstrated a statistically significant association of lower satisfaction with telehealth (n = 3, 43%, P = 0.02). Patients receiving wound care over telehealth were just as satisfied with their experience (n = 15, 82%) as overall results (n = 55, 81%).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The survey suggests that patients are satisfied with their experience of telehealth for hand therapy. Patients with finger thumb bony injuries with k wires may be less suitable for telehealth. Wound care appears to be well received over telehealth in a hand therapy population.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="PLAIN LANGUAGE SUMMARY" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">There is little evidence to guide hand therapists in which conditions or injuries patients find can be managed well with telehealth. Patients who answered a survey about their experience with telehealth for their hand therapy management overall reported satisfaction with the experience. Some patients had undergone surgery for broken fingers and thumbs using wires to hold the bone together while it healed. These patients were less likely to find telehealth satisfactory for their hand therapy care. Most patients requiring wound care over telehealth found this satisfactory.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Occupational Therapy Australia.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Graham</LastName><ForeName>Elise M</ForeName><Initials>EM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0000-2488-0215</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physiotherapy, Royal Prince Alfred Hospital SLHD, Sydney, New South Wales, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ahern</LastName><ForeName>Elspeth</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Occupational Therapy, Royal Prince Alfred Hospital SLHD, Sydney, New South Wales, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Australia</Country><MedlineTA>Aust Occup Ther J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>15420200R</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0045-0766</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">domains of practice: hand function</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">domains of practice: upper limb function</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">populations/conditions: trauma</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">practice area: musculoskeletal/hand therapy</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39439046</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1440-1630.13003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Australian Commission on Safety and Quality in Healthcare. (2018). Australian Hospital Patient Experience Question Set. https://www.safetyandquality.gov.au/our-work/indicators-measurement-and-reporting/australian-hospital-patient-experience-question-set</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bradford, N., Caffery, L., &amp; Smith, A. (2016). Telehealth services in rural and remote Australia: A systematic review of models of care and factors influencing success and sustainability. Rural and Remote Health, 16, 3808. https://doi.org/10.22605/RRH3808</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bureau of Health Information. (2021). Patients' experiences of virtual care from NSW public hospitals, results from the 2020 outpatient survey. https://www.bhi.nsw.gov.au/BHI_reports/patient_survey_results/virtual_care_survey_2020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ceprnja, D., Clark, D., Young, J., Lee, R., Flynn, K., &amp; Maka, K. (2022). Evaluating experiences, usability and patient satisfaction with telehealth for tertiary outpatient physiotherapy services during COVID‐19: A mixed‐methods study. Physiotherapy Theory and Practice, 39(9), 1929–1937. https://doi.org/10.1080/09593985.2022.2059423</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cottrell, M. A., &amp; Russell, T. G. (2020). Telehealth for musculoskeletal physiotherapy. Musculoskeletal Science and Practice, 48, 102193. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.msksp.2020.102193</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harkey, L. C., Jung, S. M., Newton, E., &amp; Patterson, A. (2020). Patient satisfaction with telehealth in rural settings: A systematic review. International Journal of Telerehabilitation, 12, 53–64. https://doi.org/10.5195/ijt.2020.6303</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harper, K., Fitzgerald, S., Xiyin, P., Kuzich, J., Leow, S., Jacques, A., Biostat, M., &amp; Harris, C. (2022). Does the integration of telehealth into occupational therapy practice impact clinical outcomes for hand and upper limb rehabilitation? A matched case control study. International Journal of Telerehabilitation, 14(2), e6505. https://doi.org/10.5195/ijt.2022.6505</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hirth, M. J., Hahn, J., &amp; Jamwal, R. J. (2022). Exploring the patient experience of telehealth hand therapy services during the COVID‐19 pandemic. Journal of Hand Therapy, 36(3), 606–615. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jht.2022.07.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Macdermid, J. C., Turgeon, T., Richards, R. S., Beadle, M., &amp; Roth, J. H. (1998). Patient rating of wrist pain and disability: a reliable and valid measurement tool. Journal of Orthopaedic Trauma, 12(8), 577–586. https://doi.org/10.1097/00005131-199811000-00009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>MacKenzie, A., Papadopolous, E., Lisandrelli, G., Abutalib, Z., &amp; Fritz Eannucci, E. (2023). Patient satisfaction with telehealth vs in‐person hand therapy: A retrospective review of results of an online satisfaction survey. Journal of Hand Therapy, 36, 974–981. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jht.2022.11.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Monaghesh, E., &amp; Hajizadeh, A. (2020). The role of telehealth during COVID‐19 outbreak: A systematic review based on current evidence. BMC Public Health, 20(1), 1193. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889-020-09301-4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parmanto, B., Lewis, A. N. Jr., Graham, K. M., &amp; Bertolet, M. H. (2016). Development of the telehealth usability questionnaire (TUQ). International Journal of Telerehabilitation, 8(1), 3–10. https://doi.org/10.5195/ijt.2016.6196 Priganc</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rouder, J., Saucier, O., Kinder, R., &amp; Jans, M. (2021). What to do with all those open‐ended responses? Data visualization techniques for survey researchers. Survey Practice. https://doi.org/10.29115/SP-2021-0008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sloane, E., Dowling, C., Ebert, K., Papadopoulos, E., &amp; Weinstock‐Zlotnick, G. (2021). Expected and unexpected: Preconceptions of telehealth for hand therapy patients. Musculoskeletal Journal of Hospital for Special Surgery, 17, 94–98. https://doi.org/10.1177/1556331620972072</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sutherland, K., Chessman, J., Zhao, J., Sara, G., Shetty, A., Smith, S., Went, A., Dyson, S., &amp; Levesque, J. F. (2020). Impact of COVID‐19 on healthcare activity in NSW, Australia. Public Health Research and Practice, 30(4), e3042030. https://doi.org/10.17061/phrp3042030</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tenforde, A., Borgstrom, H., Polich, G., Steere, H., Davis, I., Cotton, K., O'Donnell, M., &amp; Silver, J. (2020). Outpatient physical, occupational, and speech therapy synchronous telemedicine: A survey study of patient satisfaction with virtual visits during the COVID‐19 pandemic. American Journal of Physical Medicine &amp; Rehabilitation, 99(11), 977–981. https://doi.org/10.1097/PHM.0000000000001571</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Timon, C., O'Ceallaigh, B., Siney, E., &amp; McInerney, N. (2021). Rapid implementation of virtual hand therapy clinics during COVID‐19; opportunities for the future. Journal of Plastic, Reconstructive and Aesthetic Surgery, 30, 29–32. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpra.2021.06.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Worboys, T., Brassington, M., Ward, E. C., &amp; Cornwell, P. L. (2018). Delivering occupational therapy hand assessment and treatment sessions via telehealth. Journal of Telemedicine and Telecare, 24, 185–192. https://doi.org/10.1177/1357633X17691861</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organisation. (n.d.) Coronavirus disease (COVID‐19) pandemic. https://www.who.int/europe/emergencies/situations/covid-19</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>