<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39434583</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1746-1561</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>94</Volume><Issue>11</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Journal of school health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Sch Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Planning for Long-Term Recovery: The Impact of COVID-19 on Educators Working With Children From Seasonal and Migrant Farmworker Families.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1049</StartPage><EndPage>1057</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1049-1057</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/josh.13514</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Education faced challenges during the COVID-19 pandemic. Although the United States has declared an end to the public health emergency, schools continue to be impacted. While considerable research has focused on the impact of the pandemic on students, fewer studies have focused on educators, and even less on educators who specialize in working with marginalized student populations.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">This study measured the impact of the pandemic impact on educators working with students from seasonal and migrant farmworker families to understand what supports educators need as schools plan for long-term recovery. A total of 1024 educators including early childhood education and K-12 teachers, as well as administrators, completed a COVID-19 questionnaire between October 2020 and January 2021, measuring their experiences as well as personal and work-related stressors during the pandemic.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Educators underwent difficult COVID-19 experiences and faced several factors contributing to personal and work-related stress. Personal stress factors included concerns about they themselves, or family members, becoming ill, concerns about the emotional/mental health of their family, and fear of loss/reduction in employment. Work-related stress factors included concerns about the emotional and mental health of co-workers.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Educators working with migrant children need additional supports-including support from administrators, psychological services, and opportunities to give/receive colleague/peer support.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 American School Health Association.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rosado</LastName><ForeName>Javier I</ForeName><Initials>JI</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0210-2743</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Florida State University College of Medicine, Isabel Collier Read Medical Campus, Immokalee, FL.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Torres-Aponte</LastName><ForeName>Lisandra</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0000-5019-9351</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Florida State University College of Medicine, Isabel Collier Read Medical Campus, Immokalee, FL.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Yuxia</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Florida State University College of Medicine, Tallahassee, FL.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Sch Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0376370</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-4391</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014171" MajorTopicYN="Y">Transients and Migrants</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000070777" MajorTopicYN="Y">School Teachers</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000067565" MajorTopicYN="Y">Farmers</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014481" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">United States</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013334" MajorTopicYN="N">Students</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011795" MajorTopicYN="N">Surveys and Questionnaires</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">educator wellbeing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">migrant education</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>28</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>28</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39434583</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/josh.13514</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Atiles JT, Almodóvar M, Chavarría Vargas A, Dias MJA, Zúñiga León IM. International responses to COVID‐19: challenges faced by early childhood professionals. Eur Early Child Educ Res J. 2021;29(1):66‐78. https://doi.org/10.1080/1350293x.2021.1872674.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brainard J. “COVID‐ization” of research levels off. Science. 2022;376(6595):782‐783. https://doi.org/10.1126/science.add0532.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pokhrel S, Chhetri R. A literature review on impact of COVID‐19 pandemic on teaching and learning. High Educ Future. 2021;8(1):133‐141. https://doi.org/10.1177/2347631120983481.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quandt SA, LaMonto NJ, Mora DC, Talton JW, Laurienti PJ, Arcury TA. COVID‐19 pandemic among immigrant Latinx farmworker and non‐farmworker families: a rural‐urban comparison of economic, educational, healthcare, and immigration concerns. New Solut. 2021;31(1):30‐47. https://doi.org/10.1177/1048291121992468.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Habib RR, El Khayat M, Ghanawi J, Katrib RS, Hneiny L, Halwani DA. Child labor and associated risk factors in the wake of the COVID‐19 pandemic: a scoping review. Front Public Health. 2024;11:1240988. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpubh.2023.1240988.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daumiller M, Rinas R, Schoon I, Lüftenegger M. How did COVID‐19 affect education and what can Be learned moving forward? Z Psychol. 2023;231(3):177‐191. https://doi.org/10.1027/2151‐2604/a000527.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oducado RM, Rabacal J, Moralista R, Tamdang K. Perceived stress due COVID‐19 pandemic among employed professional teachers. Int J Educ Res Innov. 2020;15(15):305‐316. https://doi.org/10.46661/ijeri.5284.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klapproth F, Federkeil L, Heinschke F, Jungmann T. Teachers experiences of stress and their coping strategies during COVID ‐ 19 induced distance teaching. J Pedagogic Res. 2020;4(4):444‐452. https://doi.org/10.33902/jpr.2020062805.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Natale R, Davidson B, Woody M, et al. A model of care for delivering supports to childcare providers during the COVID‐19 pandemic. Res Sq. 2020:1:1. https://doi.org/10.21203/rs.3.rs‐39115/v1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosado J, Torres Aponte L, Velazques J, Wang Y. COVID‐19 Impact on Migrant Education Teachers &amp; Staff. Presented at: Poster presentation at the American Psychological Association Annual Convention, American Psychological Association, Virtual (National); 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chitra A. Study on impact of occupational stress on job satisfaction of teachers during Covid‐19 pandemic period. Glob Develop Rev. 2020;4(2):52‐62.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Košir K, Dugonik Š, Huskić A, Gračner J, Kokol Z, Krajnc Ž. Predictors of perceived teachers' and school counsellors' work stress in the transition period of online education in schools during the COVID‐19 pandemic. Educ Stud. 2022;48(6):844‐848. https://doi.org/10.1080/03055698.2020.1833840.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>MacDonald M, Hill C. The educational impact of the Covid‐19 rapid response on teachers, students, and families: insights from British Columbia, Canada. Prospects. 2021;51:627‐641. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11125‐020‐09527‐5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mulvihill T, Martin L. Voices in education: the social–emotional impact on teachers in a COVID‐19 world: how can teacher education lend a hand? Teach Educ. 2022;57(3):239‐248. https://doi.org/10.1080/08878730.2022.2076389.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Regional Terrorism and Disaster Coalitions for Child and Family Resilience. COVID‐19 Survey for Pre‐k to 12 Teachers and School Staff. Montclaire, NJ: Montclair State University; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grasso DJ, Briggs‐Gowan MJ, Carter AS, Goldstein BL, Ford JD. Profiling COVID‐related experiences in the United States with the epidemic‐pandemic impacts inventory: linkages to psychosocial functioning. Brain Behav. 2021;11(8):e02197. https://doi.org/10.1002/brb3.2197.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Montiel Ishino FA, McNab P, Villalobos K, Cohen JH, Nápoles AM, Williams F. Hispanic/Latino acculturation profiles and telomere length: latent class analysis on a nationally representative sample. Front Public Health. 2021;9:640226.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Susilaningsih F, Komariah M, Mediawati A, Lumbantobing V. Quality of work‐life among lecturers during online learning in COVID‐19 pandemic period: a scoping review. Malaysian J Med Health Sci. 2021;17(Suppl 4):2636‐9346.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bottiani JH, Duran CAK, Pas ET, Bradshaw CP. Teacher stress and burnout in urban middle schools: associations with job demands, resources, and effective classroom practices. J Sch Psychol. 2019;77:36‐51. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jsp.2019.10.002.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Skaalvik EM, Skaalvik S. Job demands and job resources as predictors of teacher motivation and well‐being. Soc Psychol Educ. 2018;21(5):1251‐1275. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11218‐018‐9464‐8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walsh C. Developing Teacher Capacity and Resilience to Support Vulnerable High School Learners. The Organizational Improvement Plan at Western University. London, Canada: Western University; 2022:271. https://ir.lib.uwo.ca/oip/271/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ortega L, Thompson I, Daniels H. School staff advice‐seeking patterns regarding support for vulnerable students. J Educ Adm. 2019;58(2):151‐170. https://doi.org/10.1108/jea‐12‐2018‐0236.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Madrid JE. Title I's migrant education program: the challenges of addressing migrant students' educational needs in the 21st century. Georgetown J Law Modern Critical Race Perspect. 2019;11(1):67‐98.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng M, Asif M, Tufail MS, et al. COVID academic pandemic: techno stress faced by teaching staff for online academic activities. Front Psychol. 2022;13:895371. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2022.895371.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daumiller M, Rinas R, Hein J, Janke S, Dickhäuser O, Dresel M. Shifting from face‐to‐face to online teaching during COVID‐19: the role of university faculty achievement goals for attitudes towards this sudden change, and their relevance for burnout/engagement and student evaluations of teaching quality. Comput Hum Behav. 2021;118:1‐20. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chb.2020.106677.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kakepotoa I, Talpur Q, Memon IA, Halepoto IA, Jalbani KB. Pedagogical shift: faculty insights about E‐teaching barriers during COVID pandemic. Int J Innov Creativity Change. 2024;15(6):1147‐1160.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robinson LE, Valido A, Drescher A, et al. Teachers, stress, and the COVID‐19 pandemic: a qualitative analysis. Sch Ment Heal. 2023;15:78‐89. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12310‐022‐09533‐2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Health and Human Services. COVID‐19 Public Health Emergency (PHE); 2023. https://www.hhs.gov/coronavirus/covid‐19‐public‐health‐emergency/index.html. Accessed May 8, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mucci GA, Collins E, Pearce E, et al. The lost years: an integrative review of the mental health, educational, and social impact of the pandemic on children and adolescents from 2019 to 2022. J Pediatr Neuropsychol. 2024;10:49‐90. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40817‐024‐00160‐0.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zimmerman KO, Benjamin DK. Lessons learned from the COVID‐19 pandemic in K‐12 education. Pediatrics. 2023;152(Supp 1):e2023060352O.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Betthäuser BA, Bach‐Mortensen AM, Engzell P. A systematic review and meta‐analysis of the evidence on learning during the COVID‐19 pandemic. Nat Hum Behav. 2023;7(3):375‐385. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562‐022‐01506‐4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Namkung JM, Goodrich JM, Hebert M, Koziol N. Impacts of the COVID‐19 pandemic on student learning and opportunity gaps across the 2020–2021 school year: a National Survey of teachers. Front Educ. 2022;7:921497. https://doi.org/10.3389/feduc.2022.921497.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hesham Abdou Ahmed G. Special education teachers' mental health after reopening schools during Covid‐19. PLoS One. 2023;18(5):E0284870. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0284870.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith P, Oudyk J, Cedillo L, Inouye K, Potter G, Mustard C. The psychosocial work environment among educators during the COVID‐19 pandemic. Occup Med (Lond). 2022;72(7):439‐445. https://doi.org/10.1093/occmed/kqac050.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buskila Y, Chen‐Levi T. The role of authentic school leaders in promoting teachers' well‐being: perceptions of Israeli teachers. Athens J Educ. 2021;8(2):161‐180. https://doi.org/10.30958/aje.8‐2‐3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dosil Santamaría M, Idoiaga Mondragon N, Berasategi Santxo N, Ozamiz‐Etxebarria N. Teacher stress, anxiety and depression at the beginning of the academic year during the COVID‐19 pandemic. Glob Mental Health (Camb). 2021;8(14):1‐8. https://doi.org/10.1017/gmh.2021.14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan X. Study on stress management of college teachers based on employee assistance program. J Educ. 2023;203(4):812‐817. https://doi.org/10.1177/0022057421996255.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim LE, Oxley L, Asbury K. “My brain feels like a browser with 100 tabs open”: a longitudinal study of teachers' mental health and well‐being during the COVID‐19 pandemic. Br J Educ Psychol. 2022;92(1):299‐318. https://doi.org/10.1111/bjep.12450.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nawaz K, Saeed H, Sajeel T. Covid‐19 and the state of research from the perspective of psychology. Int J Bus Psychol. 2020;2:35‐44.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Codding RS, Collier‐Meek M, Jimerson S, Klingbeil DA, Mayer MJ, Miller F. School psychology reflections on COVID‐19, antiracism, and gender and racial disparities in publishing. Sch Psychol. 2020;35(4):227‐232. https://doi.org/10.1037/spq0000399.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>