<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39438985</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2524-3489</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>6</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>22</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Neurological research and practice</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Neurol Res Pract</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Cognitive recovery of post critical care patients with and without COVID-19: differences and similarities, an observational study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>50</StartPage><MedlinePgn>50</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">50</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s42466-024-00349-w</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) patients treated in an intensive care unit (ICU) are at high risk of developing cognitive impairments of a "post-intensive care syndrome" (PICS). We explored whether critically ill COVID-19 and non-COVID-19 survivors differ in their post-ICU recovery course in terms of severity and affected cognitive domains.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">An observational prospective study was conducted in a German post-acute neurological early rehabilitation clinic. Critically ill patients with or without SARS-CoV-2 infection (at least mechanically ventilated for one week) underwent repeated standardized assessments during their subsequent inpatient rehabilitation stay. Cognitive functions (information processing speed, learning, recognition, short-term and working-memory, word fluency, flexibility) assigned to different domains (attention, memory, executive functions) were assessed as primary outcome. Secondary outcomes included mental (depression, anxiety) and physical (Barthel index, modified ranking scale) state.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Out of 92 eligible patients (screened between June 2021 and August 2023), 34 were examined, and 30 were available for analysis (15 per group). Both groups were ventilated for a similar period (COVID-19 vs. Non-COVID-19: median: 48 vs. 53 days). Patients of COVID-19 group spend on average 10 days longer at ICU and developed slightly more complications, but subsequent inpatient rehabilitation was of comparable duration (median: 36.5 vs. 37 days). On the group-level both groups showed similar cognitive dysfunctions with striking impairments (normative T-scores &lt; 41) in information processing speed, word fluency, flexibility, and recognition memory on admission. Significant gains until discharge were only revealed for information processing speed in both groups (main effect visit, mean difference [95%CI] - 7.5 [- 13.1, - 2.0]). Physical and mental state were also similarly affected in both groups on admission, but improved over time, indicating that overall recovery for higher-order cognitive functions is slowest. Interestingly, majority of patients stated correctly being still physically disabled, while a discrepancy was found between subjective and objective evaluation of cognitive health.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Results suggest a substantial overlap of cognitive, mental and physical dysfunction in post-acute recovery of ICU survivors independent of SARS-CoV-2 infection which warrants further monitoring to reduce the risk of long-term burden and enable a return to previous functionality.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="TRIAL REGISTRATION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Retrospectively registered at https://drks.de/search/de/trial/DRKS00025523 , 21.06.2021.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gorsler</LastName><ForeName>Anna</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinic for Neurological Rehabilitation, Fachklinik Für Neurologische Frührehabilitation, Kliniken Beelitz GmbH, Paracelsusring 6a, Beelitz-Heilstätten, 14547, Brandenburg, Germany. gorsler@kliniken-beelitz.de.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Health Sciences Brandenburg, Brandenburg Medical School Theodor Fontane, Brandenburg, Germany. gorsler@kliniken-beelitz.de.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Franke</LastName><ForeName>Christiana</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurology and Experimental Neurology, Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin, Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Quitschau</LastName><ForeName>Anneke</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurology and Experimental Neurology, Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin, Berlin, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Külzow</LastName><ForeName>Nadine</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4549-8343</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinic for Neurological Rehabilitation, Fachklinik Für Neurologische Frührehabilitation, Kliniken Beelitz GmbH, Paracelsusring 6a, Beelitz-Heilstätten, 14547, Brandenburg, Germany. kuelzow@kliniken-beelitz.de.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Neurol Res Pract</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101767802</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2524-3489</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Cognitive impairment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Intensive care unit</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">PICS</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Recovery</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Rehabilitation</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors report there are no competing interests to declare.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>56</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>55</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39438985</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11495021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s42466-024-00349-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s42466-024-00349-w</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Varatharaj, A., Thomas, N., Ellul, M. A., Davies, N. W. S., Pollak, T. A., Tenorio, E. L., &amp; Plant, G. (2020). Neurological and neuropsychiatric complications of COVID-19 in 153 patients: A UK-wide surveillance study. The Lancet Psychiatry,7(10), 875–882. 10.1016/S2215-0366(20)30287-X</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7316461</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32593341</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morin, L., Savale, L., Pham, T., Colle, R., Figueiredo, S., Harrois, A., &amp; Monnet, X. (2021). Four-month clinical status of a cohort of patients after hospitalization for COVID-19. JAMA Journal of the American Medical Association,325(15), 1525–1534. 10.1001/jama.2021.3331</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7970386</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33729425</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heesakkers, H., Van Der Hoeven, J. G., Corsten, S., Janssen, I., Ewalds, E., Simons, K. S., &amp; Zegers, M. (2022). Clinical outcomes among patients with 1-year survival following intensive care unit treatment for COVID-19. JAMA Journal of the American Medical Association,327(6), 559–565. 10.1001/jama.2022.0040</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8787680</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35072716</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vrettou, C. S., Mantziou, V., Vassiliou, A. G., Dimopoulou, I., Orfanos, S. E., &amp; Kotanidou, A. (2022). Post-intensive care syndrome in survivors from Critical Illness including COVID-19 patients: A narrative review. Life. 10.3390/life12010107</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8778667</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35054500</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Needham, D. M., Davidson, J., Cohen, H., Hopkins, R. O., Weinert, C., Wunsch, H., Harvey, M. A. et al. (2012). Improving long-term outcomes after discharge from intensive care unit: Report from a stakeholders’ conference*. Critical Care Medicine, 40(2). Retrieved from https://journals.lww.com/ccmjournal/fulltext/2012/02000/improving_long_term_outcomes_after_discharge_from.20.aspx</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21946660</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sasannejad, C., Ely, E. W., &amp; Lahiri, S. (2019). Long-term cognitive impairment after acute respiratory distress syndrome: A review of clinical impact and pathophysiological mechanisms. Critical Care,23(1), 1–12. 10.1186/s13054-019-2626-z</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6852966</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31718695</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fröhlich, M., Haubner, S., &amp; Bucher, M. (2019). Vorbeugung gegen die Langzeitfolgen eines Intensivaufenthalts. Intensiv,27(04), 176–182.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rousseau, A.-F., Colson, C., Minguet, P., Kellens, I., Collard, M., Vancraybex, C., &amp; Misset, B. (2023). Characteristics of mid-term post-intensive care syndrome in patients attending a follow-up clinic: A prospective comparison between COVID-19 and non-COVID-19 survivors. Critical Care Explorations,5(1), e0850. 10.1097/CCE.0000000000000850</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9851681</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36699242</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weidman, K., LaFond, E., Hoffman, K. L., Goyal, P., Parkhurst, C. N., Derry-Vick, H., &amp; Lief, L. (2022). Post-intensive care unit syndrome in a cohort of COVID-19 survivors in New York City. Annals of the American Thoracic Society,19(7), 1158–1168. 10.1513/AnnalsATS.202104-520OC</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9278639</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34936536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nasreddine, Z. S., Phillips, N. A., Bédirian, V., Charbonneau, S., Whitehead, V., Collin, I., &amp; Chertkow, H. (2005). The montreal cognitive assessment, MoCA: A brief screening tool for mild cognitive impairment. Journal of the American Geriatrics Society,53(4), 695–699. 10.1111/j.1532-5415.2005.53221.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15817019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laux, L., Hock, M., Bergner-Köther, R., Hodapp, V., Renner, K.-H., &amp; Merzbacher, G. (2013). STADI. Das State-trait-Angst-depressions-inventar. Hogrefe.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Swieten, J. C., Koudstaal, P. J., Visser, M. C., Schouten, H. J., &amp; van Gijn, J. (1988). Interobserver agreement for the assessment of handicap in stroke patients. Stroke,19(5), 604–607. 10.1161/01.str.19.5.604</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3363593</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahoney, F. I. (1965). Functional evaluation: The Barthel index. Maryland state medical journal,14(2), 61–65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14258950</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hatakeyama, J., Inoue, S., Liu, K., Yamakawa, K., Nishida, T., Ohshimo, S., &amp; Nakamura, K. (2022). Prevalence and risk factor analysis of post-intensive care syndrome in patients with COVID-19 requiring Mechanical ventilation: A multicenter prospective observational study. Journal of Clinical Medicine. 10.3390/jcm11195758</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9571505</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36233627</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schönle, P. W. (1995). The early rehabilitation Barthel Index-an early rehabilitation-oriented extension of the Barthel Index. Die Rehabilitation,34(2), 69–73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7624593</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prosiegel, M., Böttger, S., Schenk, T., König, N., Marolf, M., Vaney, C., &amp; Yassouridis, A. (1996). Der erweiterte Barthel-Index (EBI)–Eine neue Skala zur Erfassung von Fähigkeitsstörungen bei neurologischen Patienten. Neurol Rehabil,1, 7–13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herdman, M., Gudex, C., Lloyd, A., Janssen, M., Kind, P., Parkin, D., &amp; Badia, X. (2011). Development and preliminary testing of the new five-level version of EQ-5D (EQ-5D-5L). Quality of Life Research,20(10), 1727–1736. 10.1007/s11136-011-9903-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3220807</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21479777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marten, O., &amp; Greiner, W. (2021). EQ-5D-5L reference values for the German general elderly population. Health and Quality of Life Outcomes,19(1), 1–11. 10.1186/s12955-021-01719-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7937199</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33676523</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reitan, R. (1979). Trail-Making Test. Arizona: Reitan Neuropyschology Laboratory.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aschenbrenner, S., Tucha, O., &amp; Lange, C. W. (2000). RWT Regensburger Wortflüssigkeitstest: Handanweisung. Hogrefe.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Härting, C., Markowitsch, H.-J., Neufeld, H., Calabrese, P., Deisinger, K., &amp; Kessler, J. (2000). Wechsler memory scale—Revised edition, German edition, Manual. Huber.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oswald, W. D., &amp; Fleischmann, U. M. (1995). NAI—Nürnberger Altersinventar (3 überarb). Hogrefe.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morris, J. C., Heyman, A., Mohs, R. C., Hughes, J. P., van Belle, G., Fillenbaum, G., &amp; Clark, C. (1989). The consortium to establish a registry for Alzheimer’s disease (CERAD). Part I. Clinical and neuropsychological assessment of Alzheimer’s disease. Neurology,39(9), 1159–1165. 10.1212/wnl.39.9.1159</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2771064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Helmstaedter, C., &amp; Lendt, M. (2001). VLMT—Verbaler Lern—und Merkfähigkeitstest. Beltz.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1690447</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lenhard, W., &amp; Lenhard, A. (2014). Norm Scale Calculator. 10.13140/RG.2.1.4592.5363</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harris, P. A., Taylor, R., Minor, B. L., Elliott, V., Fernandez, M., O’Neal, L., &amp; Duda, S. N. (2019). The REDCap consortium: Building an international community of software platform partners. Journal of biomedical informatics,95, 103208. 10.1016/j.jbi.2019.103208</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7254481</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31078660</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lindsey, H. M. (2015). Effects of neuroplasticity-based cognitive rehabilitation training on neuropsychological functioning and white matter tract integrity in traumatic brain injury running head: Neuroplasticity-based cognitive rehabilitation effects of neuroplasticity-based C. Retrieved from https://www.researchgate.net/publication/277006377</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cahn-Weiner, D. A., Boyle, P. A., &amp; Malloy, P. F. (2002). Tests of executive function predict instrumental activities of daily living in community-dwelling older individuals. Applied Neuropsychology,9(3), 187–191. 10.1207/S15324826AN0903_8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12584085</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daste, C., Ficarra, S., Dumitrache, A., Cariou, A., Lefèbvre, A., Pène, F., &amp; Lefèvre-Colau, M. M. (2021). Post-intensive care syndrome in patients surviving COVID-19. Annals of Physical and Rehabilitation Medicine,64(6), 18–20. 10.1016/j.rehab.2021.101549</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8233854</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34182168</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hodgson, C. L., Higgins, A. M., Bailey, M. J., Mather, A. M., Beach, L., Bellomo, R., &amp; Neto, A. S. (2022). Comparison of 6-month outcomes of survivors of COVID-19 versus Non–COVID-19 critical illness. American Journal of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine,205(10), 1159–1168. 10.1164/rccm.202110-2335OC</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9872799</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35258437</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Awan, H. A., Najmuddin Diwan, M., Aamir, A., Ali, M., Di Giannantonio, M., Ullah, I., &amp; De Berardis, D. (2021). SARS-CoV-2 and the brain: What do we know about the causality of ‘Cognitive COVID? Journal of Clinical Medicine,10(15), 3441. 10.3390/jcm10153441</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8347421</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34362224</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Inoue, S., Hatakeyama, J., Kondo, Y., Hifumi, T., Sakuramoto, H., Kawaski, T., &amp; Nishida, O. (2019). Post-intensive care syndrome: Its pathophysiology, prevention, and furture directions. Acute Medicine &amp; Surgery,6, 233–246.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6603316</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31304024</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo, P., Ballesteros, A. B., Yeung, S. P., Liu, R., Saha, A., Curtis, L., &amp; Cheke, L. G. (2021). COVCOG 2: Cognitive and memory deficits in long COVID: A second publication from the COVID and cognition study. Frontiers in aging neuroscience. 10.1101/2021.10.27.21265563</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8967943</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35370620</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calsavara, A. J. C., Costa, P. A., Nobre, V., &amp; Teixeira, A. L. (2018). Factors associated with short and long term cognitive changes in patients with sepsis. Scientific Reports,8(1), 1–10. 10.1038/s41598-018-22754-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5852240</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29540719</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bland, A. R., Barraclough, M., Trender, W. R., Mehta, M. A., Hellyer, P. J., Hampshire, A., &amp; Harenwall, S. (2024). Profiles of objective and subjective cognitive function in Post-COVID Syndrome, COVID-19 recovered, and COVID-19 naïve individuals. Scientific Reports,14(1), 1–12. 10.1038/s41598-024-62050-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11166972</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38862569</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Latronico, N., &amp; Bolton, C. F. (2011). Critical illness polyneuropathy and myopathy: A major cause of muscle weakness and paralysis. The Lancet Neurology,10(10), 931–941. 10.1016/S1474-4422(11)70178-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21939902</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>