<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39431229</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2717-011X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>23</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Jan</Month><Day>05</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Current journal of neurology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Curr J Neurol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>New diagnosis of multiple sclerosis in the setting of recent Sinopharm COVID-19 vaccine (BBIBP-CorV) exposure: A series of clinical cases and updated review of the literature.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>21</StartPage><EndPage>38</EndPage><MedlinePgn>21-38</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.18502/cjn.v23i1.16430</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText><b>Background:</b> Multiple sclerosis (MS) is the most common cause of non-traumatic disability in young individuals. There are limited reports of developing demyelinating events following the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) vaccination. <b>Methods:</b> We reported all individuals (n = 8) with new MS diagnoses with recent exposure (≤ 6 weeks) to the Sinopharm (BBIBP-CorV) vaccine between September 2021 and June 2022. We also reviewed the related literature published as of September 2023. <b>Results:</b> Of 338 newly diagnosed patients with MS who attended our tertiary referral MS center during the study period, 8 (2.36%) had their first demyelinating attack with a median interval of 2 [2.0, 4.0] weeks following the Sinopharm vaccine (sex ratio 1:1, median age: 20.5 [18.0, 27.0] years). No personal or family history of autoimmune/neurological disorders was documented, except for one patient's history of a previous potential demyelinating event and another's family history of immune thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP). All patients had demyelinating brain MRI lesions, and 4 had cervical spinal cord involvement. The brain areas most commonly affected were the periventricular and subcortical regions. Positive oligoclonal bands (OCBs) in all patients supported the MS diagnosis. All patients were diagnosed with relapsing-remitting MS and received intravenous methylprednisolone (IVMP) alone or in combination with plasma exchange (3/8). Rituximab was the most frequently used disease-modifying treatment (3/8). <b>Conclusion:</b> This study provides preliminary evidence of a potential association between the Sinopharm vaccine and the initial manifestations of MS. However, further larger-scale studies with control groups and long-term follow-ups are needed to confirm this association and determine the underlying mechanisms.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Iranian Neurological Association, and Tehran University of Medical Sciences Published by Tehran University of Medical Sciences.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Paybast</LastName><ForeName>Sepideh</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Iranian Center of Neurological Research, Neuroscience Institute, Imam Khomeini Hospital Complex, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jameie</LastName><ForeName>Melika</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Iranian Center of Neurological Research, Neuroscience Institute, Imam Khomeini Hospital Complex, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shahbazi</LastName><ForeName>Mojtaba</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Iranian Center of Neurological Research, Neuroscience Institute, Imam Khomeini Hospital Complex, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Habibi</LastName><ForeName>Mohammad Amin</ForeName><Initials>MA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Student Research Committee, School of Medicine, Qom University of Medical Sciences, Qom, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mohammadianinejad</LastName><ForeName>Seyed Ehsan</ForeName><Initials>SE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Iranian Center of Neurological Research, Neuroscience Institute, Imam Khomeini Hospital Complex, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Harirchian</LastName><ForeName>Mohammad Hossein</ForeName><Initials>MH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Iranian Center of Neurological Research, Neuroscience Institute, Imam Khomeini Hospital Complex, Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Iran</Country><MedlineTA>Curr J Neurol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101769679</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2717-011X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">CNS Demyelinating Autoimmune Diseases</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19 Vaccines</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Demyelinating Diseases</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Multiple Sclerosis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Safety</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflict of interest in this study.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>11</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39431229</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11489623</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18502/cjn.v23i1.16430</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">CJN-23-21</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Hu B, Guo H, Zhou P, Shi ZL. Characteristics of SARS-CoV-2 and COVID-19. Nat Rev Microbiol. 2021;19(3):141–54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7537588</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33024307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cucinotta D, Vanelli M. WHO declares COVID-19 a pandemic. Acta Biomed. 2020;91(1):157–60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7569573</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32191675</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. WHO Coronavirus (COVID-19) Dashboard [Online]  [cited 2022 Feb 28].  Available from: URL: https://covid19.who.int/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zali A, Khodadoost M, Gholamzadeh S, Janbazi S, Piri H, Taraghikhah N, et al. Mortality among hospitalized COVID-19 patients during surges of SARS-CoV-2 alpha (B.1.1.7) and delta (B.1.617.2) variants. Sci Rep. 2022;12(1):18918.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9640720</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36344540</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jameie M, Safarian NM, Mansouri P, Jalali A, Aghajani F, Lotfi-Tokaldany M, et al. The impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on hospitalization rates due to prosthetic valve thrombosis. J Tehran Heart Cent. 2023;18(2):136–41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10459344</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37637285</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soheili A, Khani S, Montazeri S, Shayegh A, Miragha M, Jameie M, et al. COVID-19 and acute kidney injury presentation; stages and prognosis. J Prev Epidemiol. 2021;6(1):e15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Majidi F, Mohagheghi Dare RA, Jameie M, Jameie M, Mansouri P, Varpaei HA, et al. The relationship between cardiological parameters and PCR in patients with coronavirus infection: A cross-sectional study. Medicine (Baltimore) 2022;101(50):e31935.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9771227</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36550863</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang C, Tee M, Roy AE, Fardin MA, Srichokchatchawan W, Habib HA, et al. The impact of COVID-19 pandemic on physical and mental health of Asians: A study of seven middle-income countries in Asia. PLoS One. 2021;16(2):e0246824.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7877638</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33571297</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duden GS, Reiter J, Paswerg A, Weibelzahl S. Mental health of healthcare professionals during the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic: A comparative investigation from the first and second pandemic years. BMJ Open. 2023;13(3):e067244.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10039975</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36948559</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borhany H, Golbabaei S, Jameie M, Borhani K. Moral decision-making in healthcare and medical professions during the COVID-19 pandemic. Trends in Psychol. 2023;31(1):210–30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen X, Laurent S, Onur OA, Kleineberg NN, Fink GR, Schweitzer F, et al. A systematic review of neurological symptoms and complications of COVID-19. J Neurol. 2021;268(2):392–402.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7370630</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32691236</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Coronavirus Disease (COVID-19): Vaccines [Online]  [cited 2022 Mar 1].  Available from: URL: https://www.who.int/news-room/questions-and-answers/item/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-vaccines?gclid=CjwKCAiAgvKQBhBbEiwAaPQw3GLluFkuSSoT_AIhcXDldrPzXpnUkkciDrC70HeFHja3PHifQkQ5MxoC AoIQAvD_BwE&amp;amp;topicsurvey=v8kj13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walton C, King R, Rechtman L, Kaye W, Leray E, Marrie RA, et al. Rising prevalence of multiple sclerosis worldwide: Insights from the Atlas of MS, third edition. Mult Scler. 2020;26(14):1816–21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7720355</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33174475</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vandebergh M, Degryse N, Dubois B, Goris A. Environmental risk factors in multiple sclerosis: Bridging Mendelian randomization and observational studies. J Neurol. 2022;269(8):4565–74.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35366084</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abrahamyan S, Eberspacher B, Hoshi MM, Aly L, Luessi F, Groppa S, et al. Complete Epstein-Barr virus seropositivity in a large cohort of patients with early multiple sclerosis. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry. 2020;91(7):681–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7361012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32371533</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Najafi S, Ghane M, Poortahmasebi V, Jazayeri SM, Yousefzadeh-Chabok S. Prevalence of cytomegalovirus in patients with multiple sclerosis: A case-control study in northern Iran. Jundishapur J Microbiol. 2016;9(7):e36582.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5035392</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27679707</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rice EM, Thakolwiboon S, Avila M. Geographic heterogeneity in the association of varicella-zoster virus seropositivity and multiple sclerosis: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Mult Scler Relat Disord. 2021;53:103024.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34148006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kazmierski R, Wender M, Guzik P, Zielonka D. Association of influenza incidence with multiple sclerosis onset. Folia Neuropathol. 2004;42(1):19–23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15119741</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan F, Sharma P, Pandey S, Sharma D, Vijayavarman V, Kumar N, et al. COVID-19-associated Guillain-Barre syndrome: Postinfectious alone or neuroinvasive too? J Med Virol. 2021;93(10):6045–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8426929</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34170552</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahapure KS, Prabhune AS, Chouvhan AV. COVID-19-associated acute disseminated encephalomyelitis: A systematic review. Asian J Neurosurg. 2021;16(3):457–69.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8477843</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34660355</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valiuddin H, Skwirsk B, Paz-Arabo P. Acute transverse myelitis associated with SARS-CoV-2: A case-report. Brain Behav Immun Health. 2020;5:100091.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7275168</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32835294</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toljan K, Amin M, Kunchok A, Ontaneda D. New diagnosis of multiple sclerosis in the setting of mRNA COVID-19 vaccine exposure. J Neuroimmunol. 2022;362:577785.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8656147</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34922126</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khayat-Khoei M, Bhattacharyya S, Katz J, Harrison D, Tauhid S, Bruso P, et al. COVID-19 mRNA vaccination leading to CNS inflammation: A case series. J Neurol. 2022;269(3):1093–106.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8417681</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34480607</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Havla J, Schultz Y, Zimmermann H, Hohlfeld R, Danek A, Kumpfel T. First manifestation of multiple sclerosis after immunization with the Pfizer-BioNTech COVID-19 vaccine. J Neurol. 2022;269(1):55–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8193159</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34115170</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fujimori J, Miyazawa K, Nakashima I. Initial clinical manifestation of multiple sclerosis after immunization with the Pfizer-BioNTech COVID-19 vaccine. J Neuroimmunol. 2021;361:577755.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8527738</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34700047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goss AL, Samudralwar RD, Das RR, Nath A. ANA investigates: Neurological complications of COVID-19 vaccines. Ann Neurol. 2021;89(5):856–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8250888</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33710649</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patone M, Handunnetthi L, Saatci D, Pan J, Katikireddi SV, Razvi S, et al. Neurological complications after first dose of COVID-19 vaccines and SARS-CoV-2 infection. Nat Med. 2021;27(12):2144–53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8629105</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34697502</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ismail II, Salama S. A systematic review of cases of CNS demyelination following COVID-19 vaccination. J Neuroimmunol. 2022;362:577765.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8577051</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34839149</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alroughani R, Al-Hashel J, Abokalawa F, AlMojel M, Farouk AS. COVID-19 vaccination in people with multiple sclerosis, real-life experience. Clin Neurol Neurosurg. 2022;220:107374.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9293951</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35961255</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watad A, De Marco G, Mahajna H, Druyan A, Eltity M, Hijazi N, et al. Immune-mediated disease flares or new-onset disease in 27 subjects following mRNA/DNA SARS-CoV-2 vaccination. Vaccines (Basel) 2021;9(5):435.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8146571</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33946748</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farez MF, Correale J. Immunizations and risk of multiple sclerosis: Systematic review and meta-analysis. J Neurol. 2011;258(7):1197–206.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21431896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Langer-Gould A, Qian L, Tartof SY, Brara SM, Jacobsen SJ, Beaber BE, et al. Vaccines and the risk of multiple sclerosis and other central nervous system demyelinating diseases. JAMA Neurol. 2014;71(12):1506–13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25329096</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scheller NM, Svanstrom H, Pasternak B, Arnheim-Dahlstrom L, Sundstrom K, Fink K, et al. Quadrivalent HPV vaccination and risk of multiple sclerosis and other demyelinating diseases of the central nervous system. JAMA. 2015;313(1):54–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25562266</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mailand MT, Frederiksen JL. Vaccines and multiple sclerosis: A systematic review. J Neurol. 2017;264(6):1035–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27604618</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hapfelmeier A, Gasperi C, Donnachie E, Hemmer B. A large case-control study on vaccination as risk factor for multiple sclerosis. Neurology. 2019;93(9):e908–e916.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31363057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huttner A, Eperon G, Lascano AM, Roth S, Schwob JM, Siegrist CA, et al. Risk of MS relapse after yellow fever vaccination: A self-controlled case series. Neurol Neuroimmunol Neuroinflamm. 2020;7(4):e726.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7217657</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32358223</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jameie M, Togha M, Looha MA, Hemmati N, Jafari E, Nasergivehchi S, et al. Clinical characteristics and factors associated with headaches following COVID-19 vaccination: A cross-sectional cohort study (P14-12.003) Neurology. 2023;100(17_Suppl_2):4105.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10433229</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37602254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garcia-Grimshaw M, Ceballos-Liceaga SE, Hernandez-Vanegas LE, Nunez I, Hernandez-Valdivia N, Carrillo-Garcia DA, et al. Neurologic adverse events among 704,003 first-dose recipients of the BNT162b2 mRNA COVID-19 vaccine in Mexico: A nationwide descriptive study. Clin Immunol. 2021;229:108786.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8213977</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34147649</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>VAERS Team. Vaccine Adverse Event Reporting System (VAERS) Standard Operating Procedures for COVID-19 (as of 29 January 2021) [Online]  [cited 2023 Sep 4].  Available from: URL: https://www.cdc.gov/vaccinesafety/pdf/VAERS-v2-SOP.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tagliaferri AR, Horani G, Stephens K, Michael P. A rare presentation of undiagnosed multiple sclerosis after the COVID-19 vaccine. J Community Hosp Intern Med Perspect. 2021;11(6):772–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8604537</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34804388</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mathew T, John SK. COVID‐19 vaccine (ChAdOx1 nCoV‐19 Corona virus vaccine (Recombinant) – COVISHIELD related MS relapse. Neuroimmunology Reports. 2021;1:100006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim KH, Kim SH, Park NY, Hyun JW, Kim HJ. Onset of various CNS inflammatory demyelination diseases following COVID-19 vaccinations. Mult Scler Relat Disord. 2022;68:104141.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9392895</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36037757</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nistri R, Barbuti E, Rinaldi V, Tufano L, Pozzilli V, Ianniello A, et al. Case report: Multiple sclerosis relapses after vaccination against SARS-CoV2: A series of clinical cases. Front Neurol. 2021;12:765954.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8569136</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34744992</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nabizadeh F, Ramezannezhad E, Kazemzadeh K, Khalili E, Ghaffary EM, Mirmosayyeb O. Multiple sclerosis relapse after COVID-19 vaccination: A case report-based systematic review. J Clin Neurosci. 2022;104:118–25.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9388441</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36029752</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Etemadifar M, Abhari AP, Nouri H, Sigari AA, Piran Daliyeh SM, Maracy MR, et al. Self-reported safety of the BBIBP-CorV (Sinopharm) COVID-19 vaccine among Iranian people with multiple sclerosis. Hum Vaccin Immunother. 2022;18(1):2041945.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9009900</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35201963</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ebrahimi N, Mazdak M, Shaygannejad V, Mirmosayyeb O. CNS demyelinating disease following inactivated or viral vector SARS-CoV-2 vaccines: A case series. Vaccine. 2023;41(5):1003–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9816077</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36635139</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gagnier JJ, Kienle G, Altman DG, Moher D, Sox H, Riley D. The CARE guidelines: Consensus-based clinical case reporting guideline development. J Med Case Rep. 2013;7:223.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3844611</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24228906</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Medical Association. World Medical Association Declaration of Helsinki: Ethical principles for medical research involving human subjects. JAMA. 2013;310(20):2191–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24141714</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thompson AJ, Banwell BL, Barkhof F, Carroll WM, Coetzee T, Comi G, et al. Diagnosis of multiple sclerosis: 2017 revisions of the McDonald criteria. Lancet Neurol. 2018;17(2):162–73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29275977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Butler M, Tamborska A, Wood GK, Ellul M, Thomas RH, Galea I, et al. Considerations for causality assessment of neurological and neuropsychiatric complications of SARS-CoV-2 vaccines: From cerebral venous sinus thrombosis to functional neurological disorder. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry. 2021;92(11):1144–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7614639</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34362855</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramo-Tello C, Blanco Y, Brieva L, Casanova B, Martinez-Caceres E, Ontaneda D, et al. Recommendations for the diagnosis and treatment of multiple sclerosis relapses. J Pers Med. 2021;12(1):6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8780774</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35055321</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mallapaty S. Iran hopes to defeat COVID with home-grown crop of vaccines. Nature. 2021;596(7873):475.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34404947</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. The Sinopharm COVID-19 vaccine: What you need to know [Online]  [cited 2022 Mar 1].  Available from: URL: https://www.who.int/news-room/feature-stories/detail/the-sinopharm-covid-19-vaccine-what-you-need-to-know.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Annexes to the interim recommendations for use of the inactivated COVID-19 vaccine BIBP developed by China National Biotec Group (CNBG), Sinopharm, 7 May 2021 [Online]  [cited 2021 May 7].  Available from: URL: https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/WHO-2019-nCoV-vaccines-SAGE_recommendation-BIBP-annexes-2021.1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pormohammad A, Zarei M, Ghorbani S, Mohammadi M, Razizadeh MH, Turner DL, et al. Efficacy and safety of COVID-19 vaccines: A systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized clinical trials. Vaccines (Basel) 2021;9(5):467.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8148145</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34066475</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gee J, Marquez P, Su J, Calvert GM, Liu R, Myers T, et al. First month of COVID-19 vaccine safety monitoring - United States, December 14, 2020-January 13, 2021. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2021;70(8):283–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8344985</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33630816</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Voysey M, Clemens SAC, Madhi SA, Weckx LY, Folegatti PM, Aley PK, et al. Safety and efficacy of the ChAdOx1 nCoV-19 vaccine (AZD1222) against SARS-CoV-2: An interim analysis of four randomised controlled trials in Brazil, South Africa, and the UK. Lancet. 2021;397(10269):99–111.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7723445</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33306989</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. People with Certain Medical Conditions [Online]  [cited 2022 Feb 28].  Available from: URL: https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/need-extra-precautions/people-with-medical-conditions.html?CDC_AA_refVal=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.cdc.gov%2Fcoronavirus%2F2019-ncov%2Fvaccines%2Frecommendations%2Funderlying-conditions.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jameie M, Togha M, Azizmohammad LM, Jafari E, Yazdan PM, Hemmati N, et al. Characteristics of headaches attributed to SARS-CoV-2 vaccination and factors associated with its frequency and prolongation: A cross-sectional cohort study. Front Neurol. 2023;14:1214501.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10433229</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37602254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abara WE, Gee J, Marquez P, Woo J, Myers TR, DeSantis A, et al. Reports of Guillain-Barre syndrome after COVID-19 vaccination in the United States. JAMA Netw Open. 2023;6(2):e2253845.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9892957</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36723942</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rafati A, Pasebani Y, Jameie M, Yang Y, Jameie M, Ilkhani S, et al. Association of SARS-CoV-2 vaccination or infection with bell palsy: A systematic review and meta-analysis. JAMA Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg. 2023;149(6):493–504.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10141297</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37103913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eslait-Olaciregui S, Llinas-Caballero K, Patino-Manjarres D, Urbina-Ariza T, Cediel-Becerra JF, Dominguez-Dominguez CA. Serious neurological adverse events following immunization against SARS-CoV-2: A narrative review of the literature. Ther Adv Drug Saf. 2023;14:20420986231165674.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10201278</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37223456</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mirmosayyeb O, Ghaffary EM, Vaheb S, Pourkazemi R, Shaygannejad V. Multiple sclerosis (MS) and neuromyelitis optica spectrum disorder (NMOSD) following COVID-19 vaccines: A systematic review. Rev Neurol (Paris) 2023;179(4):265–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9844421</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36658048</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amanollahi M, Jameie M, Heidari A, Rezaei N. The dialogue between neuroinflammation and adult neurogenesis: Mechanisms involved and alterations in neurological diseases. Mol Neurobiol. 2023;60(2):923–59.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36383328</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amanollahi M, Jameie M, Rezaei N. Neuroinflammation as a potential therapeutic target in neuroimmunological diseases. In: Rezaei N, Yazdanpanah N, editors. Translational Neuroimmunology. 1st ed. . Volume 7. Cambridge, MA: Academic Press; 2023. pp. 475–504.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salemi S, D'Amelio R. Could autoimmunity be induced by vaccination? Int Rev Immunol. 2010;29(3):247–69.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20521925</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wraith DC, Goldman M, Lambert PH. Vaccination and autoimmune disease: What is the evidence? Lancet. 2003;362(9396):1659–66.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14630450</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garcia-Grimshaw M, Ceballos-Liceaga SE, Hernandez-Vanegas LE, Nunez I, Hernandez-Valdivia N, Carrillo-Garcia DA, et al. Systemic and neurologic adverse events among 704,003 first-dose recipients of the Pfizer-Biontech (BNT162b2) mRNA COVID-19 vaccine in Mexico [Online] [cited 2021]. Available from: URL:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2139/ssrn.3816489</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8213977</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34147649</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Causality assessment of an adverse event following immunization (AEFI): User manual for the revised WHO classification. Geneva, Switzerland: WHO; 2018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shimonovich M, Pearce A, Thomson H, Keyes K, Katikireddi SV. Assessing causality in epidemiology: Revisiting Bradford Hill to incorporate developments in causal thinking. Eur J Epidemiol. 2021;36(9):873–87.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8206235</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33324996</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>