<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39438156</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1532-8449</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>21</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of pediatric nursing</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Pediatr Nurs</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Attitudes of healthcare professionals regarding vaccines and influencing factors: A cross-sectional study.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0882-5963(24)00374-9</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.pedn.2024.10.013</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="AIMS" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">This study aims to examine the attitudes of healthcare professionals toward vaccines and identify factors influencing these attitudes.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">The study, which employed a descriptive and cross-sectional methodology, included doctors, nurses, and midwives employed at a public hospital between March 2022 and February 2023. Data were collected through face-to-face interviews using structured questionnaires, including the "Attitudes Towards Vaccination Scale."</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Healthcare workers generally had positive attitudes toward vaccination, with nearly all receiving the COVID-19 vaccine. Participants with children reported high childhood vaccination rates, and factors such as gender and occupation significantly influenced vaccination attitudes (p &lt; 0.001). While 87.1 % of the participants expressed concerns about the potential adverse effects of vaccines, those who believed vaccines had no side effects exhibited more favorable attitudes toward vaccination. Furthermore, the study revealed a considerable degree of endorsement for mandatory childhood vaccinations, with 75.1 % of participants expressing support for implementing legal obligations.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The findings of this study show healthcare workers' generally positive attitudes and confidence toward vaccines. However, more research should be conducted on the reasons for hesitancy toward COVID-19 vaccination. Increasing education and information activities is essential to overcome hesitations against new vaccines. Since the attitudes of healthcare workers toward vaccines can affect society's general vaccine acceptance and vaccination rates, studies in this field are of great importance.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="IMPLICATIONS TO PRACTICE" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The study underscores the crucial role of healthcare professionals as advocates for vaccination, emphasizing the need for tailored communication strategies to effectively address vaccine hesitancy, particularly regarding safety concerns.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Duran</LastName><ForeName>Rüveyda</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nurse, Gölcük Necati Çelik Devlet Hospital, Çiftlik, Kocaeli, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Çalbayram</LastName><ForeName>Nazan</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Canakkale Onsekiz Mart University, Faculty of Health Sciences, Department of Nursing, Terzioğlu Yerleşkesi, Canakkale, Turkey. Electronic address: nazancalbayram@comu.edu.tr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Pediatr Nurs</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8607529</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0882-5963</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Attitude</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Health personnel</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Vaccine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Vaccine hesitancy</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>21</Hour><Minute>56</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39438156</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pedn.2024.10.013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0882-5963(24)00374-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>