<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39434057</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1472-6955</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>23</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>21</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC nursing</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Nurs</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on the professional commitment of male nursing students in China: a descriptive comparative study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>771</StartPage><MedlinePgn>771</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">771</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12912-024-02410-0</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The social culture, gender stereotypes, and social status of nursing in China impact the professional commitment of male nursing students. Increasing the professional commitment of male nursing students is critical for alleviating the shortage of nurses and addressing the gender gap. The outbreak of the COVID-19 pandemic has caused widespread public concern about the nursing profession and may have changed people's perception of the profession, which in turn may have a positive impact on the professional commitment of male nursing students in China.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">This research aimed to assess how the COVID-19 pandemic affected the professional commitment of male nursing students in China and to analyze the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on potential factors that might affect their professional commitment.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A descriptive comparative study was conducted. This study involved total 368 male nursing students from five 4-year universities in Henan Province, China. 190 male nursing students were included before the COVID-19 pandemic (October to November 2019) and 178 were included after the COVID-19 pandemic (April to May 2023). The data, such as the sociodemographic characteristics and professional commitment of the two samples, were collected using a paper-and-pencil questionnaire. The research instruments used included the Professional Commitment Scale, the Multidimensional Scale of Perceived Social Support and the General Self-efficacy Scale. The data analysis employed χ<sup>2</sup>-tests, t-tests and hierarchical regression models.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The proportion of Chinese male nursing students who are interested in nursing and do not intend to leave the major has increased after the pandemic (65.17% vs. 29.47%, 61.80% vs. 39.47%, respectively). Male nursing students exhibited greater professional commitment (3.30 ± 0.63) after the pandemic compared to before the pandemic (2.77 ± 0.43). The various factors, such as grade, intend to leave the major, interest in nursing, social support, and general self-efficacy, were linked to professional commitment of male nursing students in China.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Male nursing students in China exhibited greater professional commitment after the pandemic. This phenomenon may be attributed to the public's increased recognition of the significance of nursing work during the pandemic, and the social status and image of nursing profession have been improved. Given the changes brought about by the COVID-19, strategies should be considered by nursing decision makers and schools to strengthen the professional commitment of male nursing students and increase the number of male nurses in the post-pandemic era.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Huijie</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Nursing and Health, School of Nursing and Health, Henan University, Jin Ming Avenue, Kaifeng, 475004, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cheng</LastName><ForeName>Shuyuan</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Nursing and Health, School of Nursing and Health, Henan University, Jin Ming Avenue, Kaifeng, 475004, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Peixuan</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Nursing and Health, School of Nursing and Health, Henan University, Jin Ming Avenue, Kaifeng, 475004, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Feng</LastName><ForeName>Zhifen</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Nursing and Health, School of Nursing and Health, Henan University, Jin Ming Avenue, Kaifeng, 475004, China. fzf0315@126.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Guozeng</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Nursing and Health, School of Nursing and Health, Henan University, Jin Ming Avenue, Kaifeng, 475004, China. zhanggz@henu.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Nurs</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101088683</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1472-6955</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Male nursing students</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Professional commitment</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39434057</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11492640</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12912-024-02410-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12912-024-02410-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Burmeister EA, Kalisch BJ, Xie B, Doumit MAA, Lee E, Ferraresion A, Terzioglu F, Bragadóttir H. Determinants of nurse absenteeism and intent to leave: an international study. J Nurs Manag. 2019;27(1):143–53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30209880</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Urgent need for investment in nursing. https://www.who.int/westernpacific/news/item/07-04-2020-urgent-need-for-investment-in-nursing (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hollup O. The impact of gender, culture, and sexuality on Mauritian nursing: nursing as a non-gendered occupational identity or masculine field? Qualitative study. Int J Nurs Stud. 2014;51(5):752–60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24144275</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Health Commission of the People’s Republic of China. Transcript of the press conference of the National Health Commission on May 11, 2022. http://www.nhc.gov.cn/xcs/s3574/202205/521fc41948544e00a9ffe886eaac1496.shtml (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evans J. Men in nursing: issues of gender segregation and hidden advantage. J Adv Nurs. 1997;26(2):226–31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9292354</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evans J. Men nurses: a historical and feminist perspective. J Adv Nurs. 2004;47(3):321–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15238127</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abushaikha L, Mahadeen A, AbdelKader R, Nabolsi M. Academic challenges and positive aspects: perceptions of male nursing students. Int Nurs Rev. 2014;61(2):263–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24666351</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith BW, Rojo J, Everett B, Montayre J, Sierra J, Salamonson Y. Professional success of men in the nursing workforce: an integrative review. J Nurs Manag. 2021;29(8):2470–88.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34350663</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu C, Fu MM, Cheng SZ, Lin YW, Yan JR, Wu J, Zhang XY, Cao BH, Du J, Lang HJ. Career identity and career success among Chinese male nurses: the mediating role of work engagement. J Nurs Manag. 2022;30(7):3350–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10087454</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36056581</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu K-Y, Lin P-L, Wu C-M, Hsieh Y-L, Chang Y-Y. The relationships among turnover intentions, professional commitment, and job satisfaction of hospital nurses. J Prof Nurs. 2002;18(4):214–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12244540</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>García-Moyano L, Altisent R, Pellicer-García B, Guerrero-Portillo S, Arrazola-Alberdi O, Delgado-Marroquín MT. A concept analysis of professional commitment in nursing. Nurs Ethics. 2019;26(3):778–97.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28812947</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li J, Huang C, Yang Y, Liu J, Lin X, Pan J. How nursing students’ risk perception affected their professional commitment during the COVID-19 pandemic: the mediating effects of negative emotions and moderating effects of psychological capital. Humanit Soc Sci Commun. 2023;10(1):195.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10156579</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37192948</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Masood M, Afsar B. Transformational leadership and innovative work behavior among nursing staff. Nurs Inq. 2017; 24(4).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28150910</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galletta M, Vandenberghe C, Portoghese I, Allegrini E, Saiani L, Battistelli A. A cross-lagged analysis of the relationships among workgroup commitment, motivation and proactive work behaviour in nurses. J Nurs Manage. 2019;27(6):1148–58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31066948</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ying W, Mingxuan L, Qian Z, Shuxian Z, Yufang G, Kefang W. The mediating role of professional commitment between the clinical learning environment and learning engagement of nursing students in clinical practice: a cross-sectional study. Nurs Educ Today. 2023;121:105677.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36473329</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao L, Su Y, Jiang N, Zhou F, Liao L, Liu Y. Changes in professional commitment of undergraduate nurse students before and after internship: a longitudinal study. Bmc Med Educ. 2022;22(1):282.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9011945</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35422035</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang J, Ren X, Lai F, Chen J, Shan S, Tian L. Professional commitment and related factors among nursing undergraduates: a latent profile analysis. Nurs Educ Today. 2023;131:105958.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37690440</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bandura A. Self-efficacy: toward a unifying theory of behavioral change. Psychol Rev. 1977;84(2):191–215.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">847061</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zou L, Xie Z, Tan M, Ou Q, Liao M. The effect of professional identity on nursing academic achievement: the chain mediating effect of general self-efficacy and learning engagement. Bmc Med Educ. 2024;24(1):1014–1014.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11406816</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39285393</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gonzalez A, Conde A, Diaz P, Garcia M, Ricoy C. Instructors’ teaching styles: relation with competences, self-efficacy, and commitment in pre-service teachers. High Educ. 2018;75(4):625–42.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng L, Chen Q, Zhang F. Mediating effects of meaning in life on the relationship between general self-efficacy and nursing professional commitment in nursing students: a structural equation modeling approach. Med (Baltim). 2021;100(29):e26754.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8294931</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34398054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin N, Dean A, Ensel WM. Social support scales: a methodological note. Schizophrenia Bull. 1981;7(1):73–89.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7233114</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang H-Y, Chu T-L, Liao Y-N, Chang Y-T, Teng C-I. How do career barriers and supports impact nurse professional commitment and professional turnover intention? J Nurs Manage. 2019;27(2):347–56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30203506</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hua W, Fang Q, Lin W, Liu Z, Lu W, Zhu D, Wu Y. The level and influencing factors of graduating nursing students’ professional commitment from the perspective of Ecological systems Theory: a cross-sectional study. Nurse Educ Today. 2022;119:105567.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9482089</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36152589</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y, Zhang Y, Jin R. Professional Identity of male nursing students in 3-Year Colleges and Junior Male nurses in China. Am J Mens Health. 2020;14(4):1557988320936583.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7383711</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32703068</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y. Nurses’ work role in the context of gender and Chinese culture: an online forum study. J Nurs Res. 2010;18(2):117–25.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20592657</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang H. COVID-19 and Chinese nurses’ mental health. Lancet. 2023;402(10407):1039–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37741673</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turale S. COVID-19: looking to the future of nursing: innovations &amp; policy recommendations. Int Nurs Rev. 2021;68(2):139–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8207033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34053075</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Z, Fu W, Tian C, Zhang F, Zhao B, Mao J, Saligan LN. Professional identity of Chinese nursing students during the COVID-19 pandemic outbreak: a nation-wide cross-sectional study. Nurse Educ Pract. 2021;52:103040.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9760126</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33813343</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faul F, Erdfelder E, Lang AG, Buchner A. G*Power 3: a flexible statistical power analysis program for the social, behavioral, and biomedical sciences. Behav Res Methods. 2007;39(2):175–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17695343</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zimet GD, Powell SS, Farley GK, Werkman S, assessment, KABJJop. Psychometric characteristics of the Multidimensional Scale of Perceived Social Support. J Pers Assess. 1990; 55(3–4):610–617.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2280326</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y, Fu C. The mediating effect of school belonging between perceived social support and mental resilience in nursing undergraduates. Chin J Nurs Educ. 2024;21(1):47–52.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schwarzer R, Bäßler J, Kwiatek P, Schröder K, Zhang JX. The Assessment of optimistic Self-beliefs: comparison of the German, Spanish, and Chinese versions of the General Self‐efficacy scale. Appl Psychol. 1997;46(1):69–88.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Z, Geng L, Zeng L, Lv Y. Relationships among health education ability,self-directed learning ability and self-efficacy in nursing students during clinical practice. J Nurs Sci. 2020;35(19):79–8090.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu KY, Chang LC, Wu HL. Relationships between professional commitment, job satisfaction, and work stress in public health nurses in Taiwan. J Prof Nurs. 2007;23(2):110–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17383604</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao Y, Cheng S, Madani C, Zhang G. Educational experience of male students in a baccalaureate nursing program in China. Nurse Educ Pract. 2019;35:124–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30785064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang R, Pei J, Wang Y, Wang L, Yeerjiang Y, Gao H, Xu W. COVID-19 outbreak improves attractiveness of medical careers in Chinese senior high school students. Bmc Med Educ. 2022;22(1):241.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8978502</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35379234</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu J, Grypma S, Cao Y, Bu L, Shen L, Davidson PM. Historically-informed nursing: a transnational case study in China. Nurs Inq. 2018; 25(1).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28631346</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nie S, Sun C, Wang L, Wang X. The Professional identity of nursing students and their intention to leave the nursing Profession during the Coronavirus Disease (COVID-19) pandemic. J Nurs Res. 2021;29(2):e139.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33534354</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kong L, Qin F, Zhou A, Ding S, Qu H. Relationship between Self-Acceptance and Intention to stay at Work among Clinical nurses in China: a cross-sectional online survey. Front Psychiatry. 2022;13:897157.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9314741</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35903629</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng D, Su S, Yang Y, Xia J, Su Y. Job satisfaction mediates subjective social status and turnover intention among Chinese nurses. Nurs Health Sci. 2017;19(3):388–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28636135</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steinlage AJ, Steinlage CB, Curell AM. Lessons from COVID-19 for the Next War: Crisis standards of Care in the role 3 Intensive Care Unit. Mil Med. 2023;188(5–6):132–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36695501</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crismon D, Mansfield KJ, Hiatt SO, Christensen SS, Cloyes KG. COVID-19 pandemic impact on experiences and perceptions of nurse graduates. J Prof Nurs. 2021;37(5):857–65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9767315</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34742515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Twidwell J, Dial D, Fehr C. Gender, career choice confidence, and perceived faculty support in baccalaureate nursing students. J Prof Nurs. 2022;39:96–100.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35272837</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhong Y, Zhao H, Wang X, Ji J. Using the theory of planned behaviour to explain junior nurses’ and final-year student nurses’ intention to care for COVID-19 patients in China: a multisite cross-sectional study. J Nurs Manag. 2022;30(7):2259–67.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9115239</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35434870</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reverté-Villarroya S, Ortega L, Lavedán A, Masot O, Burjalés-Martí MD, Ballester-Ferrando D, Fuentes-Pumarola C, Botigué T. The influence of COVID-19 on the mental health of final-year nursing students: comparing the situation before and during the pandemic. Int J Ment Health Nurs. 2021;30(3):694–702.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33393201</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ten Hoeve Y, Castelein S, Jansen WS, Jansen GJ, Roodbol PF. Nursing students’ changing orientation and attitudes towards nursing during education: a two year longitudinal study. Nurse Educ Today. 2017;48:19–24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27697678</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neumbe IM, Ssenyonga L, Soita DJ, Iramiot JS, Nekaka R. Attitudes and perceptions of undergraduate nursing students towards the nursing profession. PLoS ONE. 2023;18(7):e0280700.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10368257</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37490484</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Younas A, Sundus A, Zeb H, Sommer J. A mixed methods review of male nursing students’ challenges during nursing education and strategies to Tackle these challenges. J Prof Nurs. 2019;35(4):260–76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31345506</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leyva-Moral JM, Aguayo-González M, San Rafael Gutiérrez S, Jiménez Pera M, Mestres-Soler O. Understanding the expectations of nursing students following the first clinical internship: a qualitative study. Nurs Health Sci. 2022;24(1):93–100.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34747098</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>