<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39434075</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1472-6823</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>24</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>21</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC endocrine disorders</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Endocr Disord</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Type 2 diabetes and susceptibility to COVID-19: a machine learning analysis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>221</StartPage><MedlinePgn>221</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">221</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12902-024-01758-3</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) was one of the most prevalent comorbidities among patients with coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19). Interactions between different metabolic parameters contribute to the susceptibility to the virus; thereby, this study aimed to rank the importance of clinical and laboratory variables as risk factors for COVID-19 or as protective factors against it by applying machine learning methods.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHOD" NlmCategory="METHODS">This study is a retrospective cohort conducted at a single center, focusing on a population with T2DM. The patients attended the Yazd Diabetes Research Center in Yazd, Iran, from February 20, 2020, to October 21, 2020. Clinical and laboratory data were collected within three months before the onset of the COVID-19 pandemic in Iran. 59 patients were infected with COVID-19, while 59 were not. The dataset was split into 70% training and 30% test sets. Principal Component Analysis (PCA) was applied to the data. The most important components were selected using a 'sequential feature selector' and scored by a Linear Discriminant Analysis model. PCA loadings were then multiplied by the PCs' scores to determine the importance of the original variables in contracting COVID-19.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">HDL-C, followed by eGFR, showed a strong negative correlation with the risk of contracting the virus. Higher levels of HDL-C and eGFR offer protection against COVID-19 in the T2DM population. But, the ratio of BUN to creatinine did not show any correlation. Conversely, the AIP, TyG index and TG showed the most positive correlation with susceptibility to COVID-19 in such a way that higher levels of these factors increase the risk of contracting the virus. The positive correlation of diastolic BP, TyG-BMI index, MAP, BMI, weight, TC, FPG, HbA1C, Cr, systolic BP, BUN, and LDL-C with the risk of COVID-19 decreased, respectively.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The atherogenic index of plasma, triglyceride glucose index, and triglyceride levels are the most significant risk factors for COVID-19 contracting in individuals with T2DM. Meanwhile, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol is the most protective factor.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shabestari</LastName><ForeName>Motahare</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medical School, Shahid Sadoughi University of Medical Sciences, Yazd, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Azizi</LastName><ForeName>Reyhaneh</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Diabetes Research Center, Shahid Sadoughi University of Medical Sciences, Yazd, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ghadiri-Anari</LastName><ForeName>Akram</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Diabetes Research Center, Shahid Sadoughi University of Medical Sciences, Yazd, Iran. ghadiriam@yahoo.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Endocr Disord</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101088676</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1472-6823</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D008076">Cholesterol, HDL</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003924" MajorTopicYN="Y">Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000069550" MajorTopicYN="Y">Machine Learning</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012189" MajorTopicYN="N">Retrospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007492" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Iran</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012307" MajorTopicYN="N">Risk Factors</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="Y">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000368" MajorTopicYN="N">Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008076" MajorTopicYN="N">Cholesterol, HDL</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000097" MajorTopicYN="N">blood</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004198" MajorTopicYN="N">Disease Susceptibility</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005919" MajorTopicYN="N">Glomerular Filtration Rate</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Atherogenic dyslipidemia</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Insulin resistance</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Machine learning (ML)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM)</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>48</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39434075</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11492751</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12902-024-01758-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12902-024-01758-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Stoian AP, Banerjee Y, Rizvi AA, Rizzo M. Diabetes and the COVID-19 pandemic: how insights from recent experience might Guide Future Management. Metab Syndr Relat Disord. 2020;18(4):173–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7196360</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32271125</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leahy JL. Pathogenesis of type 2 diabetes mellitus. Arch Med Res. 2005;36(3):197–209.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15925010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ormazabal V, Nair S, Elfeky O, Aguayo C, Salomon C, Zuñiga FA. Association between insulin resistance and the development of cardiovascular disease. Cardiovasc Diabetol. 2018;17(1):122.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6119242</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30170598</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah BR, Hux JE. Quantifying the risk of infectious diseases for people with diabetes. Diabetes Care. 2003;26(2):510–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12547890</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farmer JA. Diabetic dyslipidemia and atherosclerosis: evidence from clinical trials. Curr Diab Rep. 2008;8(1):71–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18367002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taskinen MR, Borén J. New insights into the pathophysiology of dyslipidemia in type 2 diabetes. Atherosclerosis. 2015;239(2):483–95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25706066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saltiel AR, Olefsky JM. Inflammatory mechanisms linking obesity and metabolic disease. J Clin Invest. 2017;127(1):1–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5199709</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28045402</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bellia A, Andreadi A, Giudice L, De Taddeo S, Maiorino A, D’Ippolito I, et al. Atherogenic dyslipidemia on admission is Associated with poorer outcome in people with and without diabetes hospitalized for COVID-19. Diabetes Care. 2021;44(9):2149–57.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34253561</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alicic RZ, Rooney MT, Tuttle KR. Diabetic kidney disease: challenges, Progress, and possibilities. Clin J Am Soc Nephrol. 2017;12(12):2032–45.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5718284</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28522654</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Syed-Ahmed M, Narayanan M. Immune Dysfunction and risk of infection in chronic kidney disease. Adv Chronic Kidney Dis. 2019;26(1):8–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30876622</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carlson N, Nelveg-Kristensen KE, Freese Ballegaard E, Feldt-Rasmussen B, Hornum M, Kamper AL, et al. Increased vulnerability to COVID-19 in chronic kidney disease. J Intern Med. 2021;290(1):166–78.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8014284</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33452733</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li R, Chen Y, Ritchie MD, Moore JH. Electronic health records and polygenic risk scores for predicting disease risk. Nat Rev Genet. 2020;21(8):493–502.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32235907</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deo RC. Machine learning in Medicine. Circulation. 2015;132(20):1920–30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5831252</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26572668</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levey AS, Stevens LA, Schmid CH, Zhang YL, Castro AF 3rd, Feldman HI, et al. A new equation to estimate glomerular filtration rate. Ann Intern Med. 2009;150(9):604–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2763564</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19414839</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guerrero-Romero F, Simental-Mendía LE, González-Ortiz M, Martínez-Abundis E, Ramos-Zavala MG, Hernández-González SO, et al. The product of triglycerides and glucose, a simple measure of insulin sensitivity. Comparison with the euglycemic-hyperinsulinemic clamp. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2010;95(7):3347–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20484475</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niroumand S, Khajedaluee M, Khadem-Rezaiyan M, Abrishami M, Juya M, Khodaee G, Dadgarmoghaddam M. Atherogenic Index of Plasma (AIP): a marker of cardiovascular disease. Med J Islam Repub Iran. 2015;29:240.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4715400</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26793631</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cabello-Solorzano K, Ortigosa de Araujo I, Peña M, Correia L, Tallón-Ballesteros J A, editors. The impact of data normalization on the accuracy of machine learning algorithms: a comparative analysis. International Conference on Soft Computing Models in Industrial and Environmental Applications; 2023: Springer.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shlens J. A tutorial on principal component analysis. arXiv Preprint arXiv:14041100. 2014.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kotsiantis S. Feature selection for machine learning classification problems: a recent overview. Artif Intell Rev. 2011;42(1):157–76.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fawcett T. An introduction to ROC analysis. Pattern Recognit Lett. 2006;27(8):861–74.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao H, Lai Z, Leung H, Zhang X, Zhao H, Lai Z et al. Linear discriminant analysis. Feature Learn Understanding: Algorithms Appl. 2020:71–85.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Houwelingen J, Le Cessie S. Logistic regression, a review. Stat Neerl. 1988;42(4):215–32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burges CJ. A tutorial on support vector machines for pattern recognition. Data Min Knowl Disc. 1998;2(2):121–67.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peterson LE. K-nearest neighbor. Scholarpedia. 2009;4(2):1883.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Breiman L. Random forests. Mach Learn. 2001;45:5–32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen T, Guestrin C, editors. Xgboost: A scalable tree boosting system. Proceedings of the 22nd acm sigkdd international conference on knowledge discovery and data mining; 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tibshirani R. Regression shrinkage and selection via the lasso. J Royal Stat Soc Ser B: Stat Methodol. 1996;58(1):267–88.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rajula HSR, Verlato G, Manchia M, Antonucci N, Fanos V. Comparison of Conventional Statistical methods with Machine Learning in Medicine: diagnosis, Drug Development, and treatment. Med (Kaunas). 2020;56(9).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7560135</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32911665</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Catapano AL, Pirillo A, Bonacina F, Norata GD. HDL in innate and adaptive immunity. Cardiovasc Res. 2014;103(3):372–83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24935428</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Claxton AJ, Jacobs DR Jr., Iribarren C, Welles SL, Sidney S, Feingold KR. Association between serum total cholesterol and HIV infection in a high-risk cohort of young men. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr Hum Retrovirol. 1998;17(1):51–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9436759</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Madsen CM, Varbo A, Tybjærg-Hansen A, Frikke-Schmidt R, Nordestgaard BG. U-shaped relationship of HDL and risk of infectious disease: two prospective population-based cohort studies. Eur Heart J. 2018;39(14):1181–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29228167</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aung N, Khanji MY, Munroe PB, Petersen SE. Causal Inference for Genetic Obesity, Cardiometabolic Profile and COVID-19 susceptibility: a mendelian randomization study. Front Genet. 2020;11:586308.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7686798</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33262790</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chidambaram V, Kumar A, Majella MG, Seth B, Sivakumar RK, Voruganti D, et al. HDL cholesterol levels and susceptibility to COVID-19. EBioMedicine. 2022;82:104166.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9284176</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35843172</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hilser JR, Han Y, Biswas S, Gukasyan J, Cai Z, Zhu R, et al. Association of serum HDL-cholesterol and apolipoprotein A1 levels with risk of severe SARS-CoV-2 infection. J Lipid Res. 2021;62:100061.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7923911</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33667465</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei C, Wan L, Yan Q, Wang X, Zhang J, Yang X, et al. HDL-scavenger receptor B type 1 facilitates SARS-CoV-2 entry. Nat Metab. 2020;2(12):1391–400.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33244168</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cho KH, Kim JR, Lee IC, Kwon HJ. Native high-density lipoproteins (HDL) with higher paraoxonase exerts a potent antiviral effect against SARS-CoV-2 (COVID-19), while glycated HDL lost the antiviral activity. Antioxid (Basel). 2021;10(2).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7912765</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33535459</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oliveira C, Fournier C, Descamps V, Morel V, Scipione CA, Romagnuolo R, et al. Apolipoprotein(a) inhibits hepatitis C virus entry through interaction with infectious particles. Hepatology. 2017;65(6):1851–64.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5488163</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28152568</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trinder M, Walley KR, Boyd JH, Brunham LR. Causal inference for genetically determined levels of high-density lipoprotein cholesterol and risk of Infectious Disease. Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol. 2020;40(1):267–78.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6946100</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31694394</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trinder M, Wang Y, Madsen CM, Ponomarev T, Bohunek L, Daisely BA, et al. Inhibition of Cholesteryl Ester Transfer Protein Preserves High-Density Lipoprotein Cholesterol and improves survival in Sepsis. Circulation. 2021;143(9):921–34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33228395</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lim Y, Lee MH, Lee SK, Jeong S, Han HW. Increased estimated GFR is negatively Associated with the risk of SARS-CoV-2 infection and severe COVID-19 within normal to mildly decreased levels: nested case-control study. J Korean Med Sci. 2023;38(49):e415.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10727919</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38111284</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mirijello A, Piscitelli P, de Matthaeis A, Inglese M, D’Errico MM, Massa V et al. Low eGFR is a strong predictor of worse outcome in hospitalized COVID-19 patients. J Clin Med. 2021;10(22).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8619033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34830506</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Q, Lin M, Deng Y, Huang H. The causal relationship between COVID-19 and estimated glomerular filtration rate: a bidirectional mendelian randomization study. BMC Nephrol. 2024;25(1):21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10790484</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38225574</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kurts C, Panzer U, Anders HJ, Rees AJ. The immune system and kidney disease: basic concepts and clinical implications. Nat Rev Immunol. 2013;13(10):738–53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24037418</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muniyappa R, Montagnani M, Koh KK, Quon MJ. Cardiovascular actions of insulin. Endocr Rev. 2007;28(5):463–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17525361</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Govender N, Khaliq OP, Moodley J, Naicker T. Insulin resistance in COVID-19 and diabetes. Prim Care Diabetes. 2021;15(4):629–34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8031259</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33849817</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh B, Saxena A. Surrogate markers of insulin resistance: a review. World J Diabetes. 2010;1(2):36–47.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3083884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21537426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Er LK, Wu S, Chou HH, Hsu LA, Teng MS, Sun YC, Ko YL. Triglyceride glucose-body Mass Index is a simple and clinically useful surrogate marker for insulin resistance in nondiabetic individuals. PLoS ONE. 2016;11(3):e0149731.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4773118</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26930652</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lioy B, Webb RJ, Amirabdollahian F. The Association between the Atherogenic Index of Plasma and Cardiometabolic Risk Factors: A Review. Healthcare (Basel). 2023;11(7).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10094587</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37046893</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rohani-Rasaf M, Mirjalili K, Vatannejad A, Teimouri M. Are lipid ratios and triglyceride-glucose index associated with critical care outcomes in COVID-19 patients? PLoS ONE. 2022;17(8):e0272000.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9342722</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35913952</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ren H, Yang Y, Wang F, Yan Y, Shi X, Dong K, et al. Association of the insulin resistance marker TyG index with the severity and mortality of COVID-19. Cardiovasc Diabetol. 2020;19(1):58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7213552</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32393351</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turgay Yıldırım Ö, Kaya Ş. The atherogenic index of plasma as a predictor of mortality in patients with COVID-19. Heart Lung. 2021;50(2):329–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7837614</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33524862</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alshammari S, AlMasoudi AS, AlBuhayri AH, AlAtwi HM, AlHwiti SS, Alaidi HM, et al. Effect of COVID-19 on glycemic control, Insulin Resistance, and pH in Elderly patients with type 2 diabetes. Cureus. 2023;15(2):e35390.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9954760</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36846644</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manoria PC, Chopra HK, Parashar SK, Dutta AL, Pinto B, Mullasari A, Prajapati S. The nuances of atherogenic dyslipidemia in diabetes: focus on triglycerides and current management strategies. Indian Heart J. 2013;65(6):683–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3905264</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24407538</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boden G. Obesity, insulin resistance and free fatty acids. Curr Opin Endocrinol Diabetes Obes. 2011;18(2):139–43.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3169796</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21297467</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boden G, She P, Mozzoli M, Cheung P, Gumireddy K, Reddy P, et al. Free fatty acids produce insulin resistance and activate the proinflammatory nuclear factor-kappab pathway in rat liver. Diabetes. 2005;54(12):3458–65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16306362</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Itani SI, Ruderman NB, Schmieder F, Boden G. Lipid-induced insulin resistance in human muscle is associated with changes in diacylglycerol, protein kinase C, and IkappaB-alpha. Diabetes. 2002;51(7):2005–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12086926</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weisberg SP, McCann D, Desai M, Rosenbaum M, Leibel RL, Ferrante AW. Jr. Obesity is associated with macrophage accumulation in adipose tissue. J Clin Invest. 2003;112(12):1796–808.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC296995</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14679176</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Masana L, Correig E, Ibarretxe D, Anoro E, Arroyo JA, Jericó C, et al. Low HDL and high triglycerides predict COVID-19 severity. Sci Rep. 2021;11(1):7217.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8010012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33785815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhong P, Wang Z, Du Z. Serum triglyceride levels and related factors as prognostic indicators in COVID-19 patients: a retrospective study. Immun Inflamm Dis. 2021;9(3):1055–60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8342209</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34236141</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reynolds HR, Adhikari S, Pulgarin C, Troxel AB, Iturrate E, Johnson SB, et al. Renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system inhibitors and risk of Covid-19. N Engl J Med. 2020;382(25):2441–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7206932</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32356628</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vincent JL, Taccone FS. Understanding pathways to death in patients with COVID-19. Lancet Respir Med. 2020;8(5):430–2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7270480</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32272081</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guzik TJ, Hoch NE, Brown KA, McCann LA, Rahman A, Dikalov S, et al. Role of the T cell in the genesis of angiotensin II induced hypertension and vascular dysfunction. J Exp Med. 2007;204(10):2449–60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2118469</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17875676</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Norlander AE, Madhur MS, Harrison DG. The immunology of hypertension. J Exp Med. 2018;215(1):21–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5748862</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29247045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patrick DM, Van Beusecum JP, Kirabo A. The role of inflammation in hypertension: novel concepts. Curr Opin Physiol. 2021;19:92–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7552986</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33073072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Touyz RM, Rios FJ, Alves-Lopes R, Neves KB, Camargo LL, Montezano AC. Oxidative stress: a unifying paradigm in hypertension. Can J Cardiol. 2020;36(5):659–70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7225748</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32389339</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siedlinski M, Jozefczuk E, Xu X, Teumer A, Evangelou E, Schnabel RB, et al. White Blood cells and blood pressure: a mendelian randomization study. Circulation. 2020;141(16):1307–17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7176352</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32148083</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Youn JC, Yu HT, Lim BJ, Koh MJ, Lee J, Chang DY, et al. Immunosenescent CD8 + T cells and C-X-C chemokine receptor type 3 chemokines are increased in human hypertension. Hypertension. 2013;62(1):126–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23716586</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodilla E, López-Carmona MD, Cortes X, Cobos-Palacios L, Canales S, Sáez MC, et al. Impact of arterial stiffness on all-cause mortality in patients hospitalized with COVID-19 in Spain. Hypertension. 2021;77(3):856–67.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7884247</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33377393</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Safar ME, Asmar R, Benetos A, Blacher J, Boutouyrie P, Lacolley P, et al. Interaction between Hypertension and arterial stiffness. Hypertension. 2018;72(4):796–805.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30354723</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>