<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39437129</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1538-943X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>ASAIO journal (American Society for Artificial Internal Organs : 1992)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>ASAIO J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation for COVID-19 During the Delta and Omicron Waves in North America.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/MAT.0000000000002334</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Clinical outcomes for patients with severe acute respiratory failure caused by different variants of the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) supported with extracorporeal membrane oxygenation (ECMO) are incompletely understood. Clinical characteristics, pre-ECMO management, and hospital mortality at 90 days for adults with COVID-19 who received venovenous ECMO (VV-ECMO) at North American centers during waves predominated by Delta (August 16 to December 12, 2021) and Omicron (January 31 to May 31, 2022) severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) variants were compared in a competing risks framework. One thousand seven hundred and sixty-six patients (1,580 Delta, 186 Omicron) received VV-ECMO for COVID-19 during the Delta- and Omicron-predominant waves in North American centers. In the unadjusted competing risks model, no significant difference was observed in risk of hospital mortality at 90 days between patients during the Delta- versus Omicron-predominant wave (subhazard ratio [sHR], 0.94; 95% confidence interval [CI], 0.74-1.19), but patients supported with VV-ECMO during the Omicron-predominant wave had a significantly lower adjusted risk of hospital mortality at 90 days (subhazard ratio, 0.71; 95% CI, 0.51-0.99). Patients receiving VV-ECMO during the Omicron-predominant wave had a similar unadjusted risk of hospital mortality at 90 days, but a significantly lower adjusted risk of hospital mortality at 90 days than those receiving VV-ECMO during the Delta-predominant wave.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © ASAIO 2024.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hickey</LastName><ForeName>Andrew J</ForeName><Initials>AJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Division of Pulmonology and Sleep Medicine, Department of Medicine, Atrium Health Pulmonology and Sleep Medicine, Atrium Health, Charlotte, North Carolina.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Greendyk</LastName><ForeName>Richard</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5846-1382</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Pulmonary, Allergy, and Critical Care Medicine, Columbia University Irving Medical Center, New York, New York.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cummings</LastName><ForeName>Matthew J</ForeName><Initials>MJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Pulmonary, Allergy, and Critical Care Medicine, Columbia University Irving Medical Center, New York, New York.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abrams</LastName><ForeName>Darryl</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Pulmonary, Allergy, and Critical Care Medicine, Columbia University Irving Medical Center, New York, New York.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>O'Donnell</LastName><ForeName>Max R</ForeName><Initials>MR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Pulmonary, Allergy, and Critical Care Medicine, Columbia University Irving Medical Center, New York, New York.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, Columbia University Mailman School of Public Health, New York, New York.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rackley</LastName><ForeName>Craig R</ForeName><Initials>CR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Pulmonary, Allergy, and Critical Care Medicine, Duke University Medical Center, Durham, North Carolina.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Barbaro</LastName><ForeName>Ryan P</ForeName><Initials>RP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Pediatric Critical Care Medicine, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Brodie</LastName><ForeName>Daniel</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, School of Medicine, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Maryland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Agerstrand</LastName><ForeName>Cara</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9676-2709</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Pulmonary, Allergy, and Critical Care Medicine, Columbia University Irving Medical Center, New York, New York.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>ASAIO J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9204109</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1058-2916</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CoiStatement>Disclosure: D.B. receives research support from and consults for LivaNova. He has been on the medical advisory boards for Abiomed, Xenios, Medtronic, Inspira, and Cellenkos. He is the President-elect of the Extracorporeal Life Support Organization (ELSO) and the Chair of the Executive Committee of the International ECMO Network (ECMONet), and he writes for UpToDate. D.A. and C.A. write for UpToDate. The other authors have no conflicts of interest to report.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39437129</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MAT.0000000000002334</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00002480-990000000-00585</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Barbaro RP, MacLaren G, Boonstra PS, et al.; Extracorporeal Life Support Organization: Extracorporeal membrane oxygenation support in COVID-19: An international cohort study of the Extracorporeal Life Support Organization registry. Lancet 396: 1071–1078, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Combes A, Hajage D, Capellier G, et al.; EOLIA Trial Group, REVA, and ECMONet: Extracorporeal membrane oxygenation for severe acute respiratory distress syndrome. N Engl J Med 378: 1965–1975, 2018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peek GJ, Mugford M, Tiruvoipati R, et al.; CESAR trial collaboration: Efficacy and economic assessment of conventional ventilatory support versus extracorporeal membrane oxygenation for severe adult respiratory failure (CESAR): A multicentre randomised controlled trial. Lancet 374: 1351–1363, 2009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Australia and New Zealand Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation (ANZ ECMO) Influenza Investigators: Extracorporeal membrane oxygenation for 2009 influenza A(H1N1) acute respiratory distress syndrome. JAMA 302: 1888–1895, 2009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noah MA, Peek GJ, Finney SJ, et al.; Referral to an extracorporeal membrane oxygenation center and mortality among patients with severe 2009 influenza A(H1N1). JAMA 306: 1659–1668, 2011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pham T, Combes A, Rozé H, et al.; REVA Research Network: Extracorporeal membrane oxygenation for pandemic influenza A(H1N1)-induced acute respiratory distress syndrome: A cohort study and propensity-matched analysis. Am J Respir Crit Care Med 187: 276–285, 2013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barbaro RP, MacLaren G, Boonstra PS, et al.; Extracorporeal Life Support Organization: Extracorporeal membrane oxygenation for COVID-19: Evolving outcomes from the international Extracorporeal Life Support Organization Registry. Lancet 398: 1230–1238, 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ling RR, Ramanathan K, Sim JJL, et al.: Evolving outcomes of extracorporeal membrane oxygenation during the first 2 years of the COVID-19 pandemic: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Crit Care 26: 147, 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The RECOVERY Collaborative Group: Dexamethasone in hospitalized patients with COVID-19. N Engl J Med 384: 693–704, 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beigel JH, Tomashek KM, Dodd LE, et al.; ACTT-1 Study Group Members: Remdesivir for the treatment of COVID-19—final report. N Engl J Med 383: 1813–1826, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davies NG, Abbott S, Barnard RC, et al.: Estimated transmissibility and impact of SARS-CoV-2 lineage B.1.1.7 in England. Science 372: 1–9, 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paul P, France AM, Aoki Y, et al.: Genomic surveillance for SARS-CoV-2 variants circulating in the United States, December 2020–May 2021. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 70: 846–850, 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walensky RP, Walke HT, Fauci AS: SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern in the United States—challenges and opportunities. JAMA 325: 1037–1038, 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>del Rio C, Malani PN, Omer SB: Confronting the Delta variant of SARS-CoV-2, summer 2021. JAMA 326: 1001–1002, 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fiolet T, Kherabi Y, MacDonald CJ, Ghosn J, Peiffer-Smadja N: Comparing COVID-19 vaccines for their characteristics, efficacy and effectiveness against SARS-CoV-2 and variants of concern: A narrative review. Clin Microbiol Infect 28: 202–221, 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fisman DN, Tuite AR: Evaluation of the relative virulence of novel SARS-CoV-2 variants: A retrospective cohort study in Ontario, Canada. CMAJ 193: E1619–E1625, 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmidt M, Hajage D, Landoll M, et al.; ECMO-SURGES Investigators: Comparative outcomes of extracorporeal membrane oxygenation for COVID-19 delivered in experienced European centres during successive SARS-CoV-2 variant outbreaks (ECMO-SURGES): An international, multicentre, retrospective cohort study. Lancet Respir Med 11: 163–175, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iuliano AD, Brunkard JM, Boehmer TK, et al.: Trends in disease severity and health care utilization during the early Omicron variant period compared with previous SARS-CoV-2 high transmission periods—United States, December 2020–January 2022. Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 71: 146–152, 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdullah F, Myers J, Basu D, et al.: Decreased severity of disease during the first global Omicron variant COVID-19 outbreak in a large hospital in Tshwane, South Africa. Int J Infect Dis 116: 38–42, 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hyams C, Challen R, Marlow R, et al.; AvonCAP Research Group: Severity of Omicron (B.1.1.529) and Delta (B.1.617.2) SARS-CoV-2 infection among hospitalised adults: A prospective cohort study in Bristol, United Kingdom. Lancet Reg Health Eur 25: 100556, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Relan P, Motaze NV, Kothari K, et al.: Severity and outcomes of Omicron variant of SARS-CoV-2 compared to Delta variant and severity of Omicron sublineages: A systematic review and metanalysis. BMJ Glob Health. 8: e012328, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wolter N, Jassat W, Walaza S, et al.: Early assessment of the clinical severity of the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant in South Africa: A data linkage study. Lancet 399: 437–446, 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Prost N, Audureau E, Heming N, et al.: Clinical phenotypes and outcomes associated with SARS-CoV-2 variant Omicron in critically ill French patients with COVID-19. Nat Commun 13: 6025, 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Global Initiative on Sharing All Influenza Data (GISAID). Tracking of hCoV-19 variants. https://gisaid.org/hcov19-variants/ . Published 2022. Accessed September 23, 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Resche-Rigon M, Azoulay E, Chevret S: Evaluating mortality in intensive care units: Contribution of competing risks analyses. Crit Care 10: R5, 2006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wolkewitz M, Lambert J, von Cube M, et al.: Statistical analysis of clinical COVID-19 data: A concise overview of lessons learned, common errors and how to avoid them. Clin Epidemiol 12: 925–928, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fine JP, Gray RJ: A proportional hazards model for the subdistribution of a competing risk. J Am Stat Assoc 94: 496–509, 1999.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shih E, DiMaio JM, Squiers JJ, et al.: Extracorporeal membrane oxygenation for respiratory failure in phases of COVID-19 variants. J Card Surg 37: 2972–2979, 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gallaher J, Raff L, Schneider A, et al.: The role of ECMO in COVID-19 acute respiratory failure: Defining risk factors for mortality. Am J Surg 225: 1096–1101, 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Z, Azman AS, Chen X, et al.: Global landscape of SARS-CoV-2 genomic surveillance and data sharing. Nat Genet 54: 499–507, 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chiara M, D’Erchia AM, Gissi C, et al.: Next generation sequencing of SARS-CoV-2 genomes: Challenges, applications and opportunities. Brief Bioinform 22: 616–630, 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brito AF, Semenova E, Dudas G, et al.; Bulgarian SARS-CoV-2 sequencing group: Global disparities in SARS-CoV-2 genomic surveillance. Nat Commun 13: 7003, 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang C, Liu B, Zhang S, et al.: Differences in incidence and fatality of COVID-19 by SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant versus delta variant in relation to vaccine coverage: A world-wide review. J Med Virol 95: e28118, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ulloa AC, Buchan SA, Daneman N, Brown KA: Estimates of SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant severity in Ontario, Canada. JAMA 327: 1286–1288, 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spiezia L, Boscolo A, Poletto F, et al.: COVID-19-related severe hypercoagulability in patients admitted to intensive care unit for acute respiratory failure. Thromb Haemost 120: 998–1000, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grobbelaar LM, Kruger A, Venter C, et al.: Relative hypercoagulopathy of the SARS-CoV-2 beta and delta variants when compared to the less severe Omicron variants is related to TEG parameters, the extent of fibrin amyloid microclots, and the severity of clinical illness. Semin Thromb Hemost 48: 858–868, 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sidebotham D, McGeorge A, McGuinness S, Edwards M, Willcox T, Beca J: Extracorporeal membrane oxygenation for treating severe cardiac and respiratory failure in adults: part 2—technical considerations. J Cardiothorac Vasc Anesth 24: 164–172, 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. COVID data tracker weekly review. https://archive.cdc.gov/www_cdc_gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/covid-data/covidview/past-reports/04222022.html . Published April 2022. Accessed April 28, 2023. Archived June 28, 2023.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>