<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39436325</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1099-0968</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>22</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>European eating disorders review : the journal of the Eating Disorders Association</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Eur Eat Disord Rev</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The collateral effects of the COVID-19 pandemic: A gender-specific systematic review of disordered eating behaviour in the general population.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/erv.3141</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">The COVID-19 pandemic initiated public health measures, impacting mental health and exacerbating disordered eating behaviours (DEB). This study aims to fill gaps in understanding DEB in the general population during the pandemic, emphasising gender dynamics and the experiences of gender and/or sexual minority (SGM) individuals.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHOD" NlmCategory="METHODS">A systematic literature review followed PRISMA guidelines to investigate DEB during the pandemic, focusing on gender-sensitive analyses and SGM populations. Outcomes from the included studies were synthesised to identify patterns and associations related to DEB, particularly considering gender dynamics and SGM experiences.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Significant gender associations with DEB were observed, with women consistently exhibiting higher scores. SGM populations also showed elevated DEB symptoms. Longitudinal studies indicated changes in DEB over time, with some decreases observed among men.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The review underscores significant gender differences in DEB during the pandemic, with women exhibiting higher symptom levels. Lockdown measures had nuanced impacts on DEB, varying across studies. Various factors including pandemic-related stressors influenced DEB. Consideration of these factors can inform tailored interventions for DEB in the general population. Overall, the review enhances our understanding of how gender intersects with the pandemic's impact on DEB, emphasising the need for diverse approaches to address these behaviours.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). European Eating Disorders Review published by Eating Disorders Association and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Laskowski</LastName><ForeName>Nora M</ForeName><Initials>NM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0213-5171</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medical Faculty, University Clinic for Psychosomatic Medicine and Psychotherapy, Campus East-Westphalia, Ruhr-University Bochum, Luebbecke, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Brandt</LastName><ForeName>Gerrit</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4895-1599</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medical Faculty, University Clinic for Psychosomatic Medicine and Psychotherapy, Campus East-Westphalia, Ruhr-University Bochum, Luebbecke, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Reque</LastName><ForeName>Cristina Ballero</ForeName><Initials>CB</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0097-7594</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medical Faculty, University Clinic for Psychosomatic Medicine and Psychotherapy, Campus East-Westphalia, Ruhr-University Bochum, Luebbecke, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sabel</LastName><ForeName>Luisa</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0003-1589-2785</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medical Faculty, University Clinic for Psychosomatic Medicine and Psychotherapy, Campus East-Westphalia, Ruhr-University Bochum, Luebbecke, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pahlenkemper</LastName><ForeName>Marie</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0003-5111-3830</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medical Faculty, University Clinic for Psychosomatic Medicine and Psychotherapy, Campus East-Westphalia, Ruhr-University Bochum, Luebbecke, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zaiser</LastName><ForeName>Christopher</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0002-7643-5425</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medical Faculty, University Clinic for Psychosomatic Medicine and Psychotherapy, Campus East-Westphalia, Ruhr-University Bochum, Luebbecke, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Paslakis</LastName><ForeName>Georgios</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2069-0024</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medical Faculty, University Clinic for Psychosomatic Medicine and Psychotherapy, Campus East-Westphalia, Ruhr-University Bochum, Luebbecke, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>01KX2121</GrantID><Agency>German Federal Ministry of Education and Research (BMBF)</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Eur Eat Disord Rev</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9436977</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1072-4133</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">LGBTQ+</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">eating disorders</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">gender differences</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pandemic</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39436325</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/erv.3141</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Abate, B. B., Kassie, A. M., Kassaw, M. W., Aragie, T. G., &amp; Masresha, S. A. (2020). Sex difference in coronavirus disease (COVID‐19): A systematic review and meta‐analysis. BMJ Open, 10(10), e040129. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen‐2020‐040129</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abouk, R., &amp; Heydari, B. (2021). The immediate effect of COVID‐19 policies on social‐distancing behavior in the United States. Public Health Reports, 136(2), 245–252. https://doi.org/10.1177/0033354920976575</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alon, T., Doepke, M., Olmstead‐Rumsey, J., &amp; Tertilt, M. (2020). The impact of COVID‐19 on gender equality. National Bureau of Economic Research Working Paper Series, University of California. https://doi.org/10.3386/w26947</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anderson, L. N., Yoshida‐Montezuma, Y., Dewart, N., Jalil, E., Khattar, J., De Rubeis, V., Carsley, S., Griffith, L. E., &amp; Mbuagbaw, L. (2023). Obesity and weight change during the COVID‐19 pandemic in children and adults: A systematic review and meta‐analysis. Obesity Reviews, 24(5). https://doi.org/10.1111/obr.13550</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aoun, A., Duarte Garcia, F., Mounzer, C., Hlais, S., Grigioni, S., Honein, K., &amp; Déchelotte, P. (2013). War stress may be another risk factor for eating disorders in civilians: A study in Lebanese university students. General Hospital Psychiatry, 35(4), 393–397. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.genhosppsych.2013.02.007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baceviciene, M., &amp; Jankauskiene, R. (2021). Changes in sociocultural attitudes towards appearance, body image, eating attitudes and behaviours, physical activity, and quality of life in students before and during COVID‐19 lockdown. Appetite, 166, 105452. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.appet.2021.105452</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barakat, S., McLean, S. A., Bryant, E., Le, A., Marks, P., Aouad, P., Barakat, S., Boakes, R., Brennan, L., Bryant, E., Byrne, S., Caldwell, B., Calvert, S., Carroll, B., Castle, D., Caterson, I., Chelius, B., Chiem, L., Clarke, S., …, &amp; Touyz, S. (2023). Risk factors for eating disorders: Findings from a rapid review. Journal of Eating Disorders, 11(1), 8. https://doi.org/10.1186/s40337‐022‐00717‐4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baranauskas, M., Kupčiūnaitė, I., &amp; Stukas, R. (2022). Potential triggers for risking the development of eating disorders in non‐clinical higher‐education students in emerging adulthood. Nutrients, 14(11), 2293. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu14112293</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barcln‐Güzeldere, H. K., &amp; Devrim‐Lanpir, A. (2022). The association between body mass index, emotional eating and perceived stress during COVID‐19 partial quarantine in healthy adults. Public Health Nutrition, 25(1), 43–50. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1368980021002974</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berge, J. M., Larson, N., &amp; Neumark‐Sztainer, D. (2021). Emerging adults and social distancing during COVID‐19: Who was more likely to follow guidelines and what were the correlates with well‐being and weight‐related behaviors? Emerging Adulthood, 9(6), 670–678. https://doi.org/10.1177/21676968211051482</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Birmingham, W. C., Wadsworth, L. L., Lassetter, J. H., Graff, T. C., Lauren, E., &amp; Hung, M. (2023). COVID‐19 lockdown: Impact on college students’ lives. Journal of American College Health, 71(3), 879–893. https://doi.org/10.1080/07448481.2021.1909041</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonfanti, R. C., Sideli, L., Teti, A., Musetti, A., Cella, S., Barberis, N., Borsarini, B., Fortunato, L., Sechi, C., Micali, N., &amp; Lo Coco, G. (2023). The impact of the first and second wave of the COVID‐19 pandemic on eating symptoms and dysfunctional eating behaviours in the general population: A systematic review and meta‐analysis. Nutrients, 15(16), 3607. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu15163607</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bowleg, L., &amp; Landers, S. (2021). The need for COVID‐19 LGBTQ‐specific data. American Journal of Public Health, 111(9), 1604–1605. https://doi.org/10.2105/AJPH.2021.306463</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brandt, G., Halbeisen, G., Braks, K., Huber, T. J., &amp; Paslakis, G. (2023). Gender differences in individuals with obesity and binge eating disorder: A retrospective comparison of phenotypical features and treatment outcomes. European Eating Disorder Review, 31(3), 413–424. https://doi.org/10.1002/erv.2972</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burke, N. L., Schaefer, L. M., Hazzard, V. M., &amp; Rodgers, R. F. (2020). Where identities converge: The importance of intersectionality in eating disorders research. International Journal of Eating Disorders, 53(10), 1605–1609. https://doi.org/10.1002/eat.23371</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carpio‐Arias, T. V., Piedra‐Andrade, J. S., Nicolalde‐Cifuentes, T. M., Padilla‐Samaniego, M. V., Tapia‐Veloz, E. C., &amp; Vinueza‐Veloz, M. F. (2022). Mobility restrictions and mental health among young adults during the COVID‐19 pandemic in Ecuador. Gaceta Sanitaria, 36(6), 512–519. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gaceta.2021.12.008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ciftci, S., &amp; Kızıl, M. (2023). Is there a link between sleep quality and a tendency for eating disorders? Journal of Nutrition and Dietetics, 51(2), 34–44. https://doi.org/10.33076/2023.BDD.1751</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Convertino, A. D., Helm, J. L., Pennesi, J. L., Gonzales, M., &amp; Blashill, A. J. (2021). Integrating minority stress theory and the tripartite influence model: A model of eating disordered behavior in sexual minority young adults. Appetite, 163, 105204. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.appet.2021.105204</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cooper, M., Reilly, E. E., Siegel, J. A., Coniglio, K., Sadeh‐Sharvit, S., Pisetsky, E. M., &amp; Anderson, L. M. (2022). Eating disorders during the COVID‐19 pandemic and quarantine: An overview of risks and recommendations for treatment and early intervention. Eating Disorders, 30(1), 54–76. https://doi.org/10.1080/10640266.2020.1790271</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Costarelli, V., &amp; Patsai, A. (2012). Academic examination stress increases disordered eating symptomatology in female university students. Eating and Weight Disorders ‐ Studies on Anorexia, Bulimia and Obesity, 17(3), e164–e169. https://doi.org/10.1007/BF03325343</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Culbert, K. M., Sisk, C. L., &amp; Klump, K. L. (2021). A narrative review of sex differences in eating disorders: Is there a biological basis? Clinical Therapeutics, 43(1), 95–111. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.clinthera.2020.12.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daly, M., &amp; Costigan, E. (2022). Trends in eating disorder risk among U.S. college students, 2013–2021. Psychiatry Research, 317, 114882. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.psychres.2022.114882</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Danielsen, S., Joensen, A., Andersen, P. K., Madsen, T., &amp; Strandberg‐Larsen, K. (2023). Self‐injury, suicidality and eating disorder symptoms in young adults following COVID‐19 lockdowns in Denmark. Nature Human Behaviour, 7(3), 411–419. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562‐022‐01511‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Pasquale, C., Sciacca, F., Conti, D., Pistorio, M. L., Hichy, Z., Cardullo, R. L., &amp; Di Nuovo, S. (2021). Relations between mood states and eating behavior during COVID‐19 pandemic in a sample of Italian college students. Frontiers in Psychology, 12. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2021.684195</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Devoe, D. J., Han, A., Anderson, A., Katzman, D. K., Patten, S. B., Soumbasis, A., Flanagan, J., Paslakis, G., Vyver, E., Marcoux, G., &amp; Dimitropoulos, G. (2023). The impact of the COVID‐19 pandemic on eating disorders: A systematic review. International Journal of Eating Disorders, 56(1), 5–25. https://doi.org/10.1002/eat.23704</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drabble, L. A., &amp; Eliason, M. J. (2021). Introduction to special issue: Impacts of the COVID‐19 pandemic on LGBTQ+ health and well‐being. Journal of Homosexuality, 68(4), 545–559. https://doi.org/10.1080/00918369.2020.1868182</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duan, W., Ding, Q., Peng, S., Kang, Q., Guo, L., Zhang, L., Wei, Y., Xiao, Z., Fan, J., &amp; Chen, J. (2023). Chinese university students showed less disordered eating during the COVID‐19 campus lockdown. Eating and Weight Disorders, 28(1), 47. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40519‐023‐01569‐w</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elran‐Barak, R., &amp; Goldschmidt, A. B. (2021). Differences in severity of eating disorder symptoms between adults with depression and adults with anxiety. Eating and Weight Disorders, 26(5), 1409–1416. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40519‐020‐00947‐y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ernst, M., Werner, A. M., Tibubos, A. M., Beutel, M. E., de Zwaan, M., &amp; Brähler, E. (2021). Gender‐dependent associations of anxiety and depression symptoms with eating disorder psychopathology in a representative population sample. Frontiers in Psychiatry, 12. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2021.645654</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fairburn, C. G., &amp; Beglin, S. J. (2008). Eating disorder examination questionnaire (EDE‐Q 6.0). In C. G. Fairburn (Ed.), Cognitive behaviour therapy and eating disorders (pp. 309–313). Guilford Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fairburn, C. G., &amp; Cooper, Z. (1993). The eating disorder examination. In C. G. Fairburn &amp; G. T. Wilson (Eds.), Binge eating: Nature, assessment and treatment (pp. 317–360). Guilford Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan, H., Gan, Y., Wang, R., Chen, S., Lipowska, M., Li, J., Li, K., Krokosz, D., Yang, Y., &amp; Lipowski, M. (2021). The relationship between obligatory exercise and eating attitudes, and the mediating role of sociocultural attitudes towards appearance during the COVID‐19 pandemic. Nutrients, 13(12), 4286. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu13124286</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fancourt, D., Steptoe, A., &amp; Bu, F. (2021). Trajectories of anxiety and depressive symptoms during enforced isolation due to COVID‐19 in england: A longitudinal observational study. The Lancet Psychiatry, 8(2), 141–149. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2215‐0366(20)30482‐X</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernández‐Aranda, F., Casas, M., Claes, L., Bryan, D. C., Favaro, A., Granero, R., Gudiol, C., Jiménez‐Murcia, S., Karwautz, A., Le Grange, D., Menchón, J. M., Tchanturia, K., &amp; Treasure, J. (2020). COVID‐19 and implications for eating disorders. European Eating Disorders Review, 28(3), 239–245. https://doi.org/10.1002/erv.2738</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fisher, C. B., Tao, X., &amp; Yip, T. (2023). The effects of COVID‐19 victimization distress and racial bias on mental health among AIAN, Asian, Black, and Latinx young adults. Cultural Diversity and Ethnic Minority Psychology, 29(2), 119–131. https://doi.org/10.1037/cdp0000539</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garaulet, M., Canteras, M., Morales, E., López‐Guimera, G., Sánchez‐Carracedo, D., &amp; Corbalán‐Tutau, M. D. (2012). Validation of a questionnaire on emotional eating for use in cases of obesity: The emotional eater questionnaire (EEQ). Nutricion Hospitalaria, 27(2), 645–651. https://doi.org/10.1590/S0212‐16112012000200043</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garner, D. M. (1991). Eating disorder inventory‐2. Psychological Assessment Resources.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garner, D. M., Olmsted, M. P., Bohr, Y., &amp; Garfinkel, P. E. (1982). The eating attitudes test: Psychometric features and clinical correlates. Psychological Medicine, 12(4), 871–878. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0033291700049163</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gideon, N., Hawkes, N., Mond, J., Saunders, R., Tchanturia, K., &amp; Serpell, L. (2016). Development and psychometric validation of the EDE‐QS, a 12 item short form of the eating disorder examination questionnaire (EDE‐Q). PLoS One, 11(5), e0152744. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0152744</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gilsbach, S., Plana, M. T., Castro‐Fornieles, J., Gatta, M., Karlsson, G. P., Flamarique, I., Raynaud, J. P., Riva, A., Solberg, A. L., van Elburg, A. A., Wentz, E., Nacinovich, R., &amp; Herpertz‐Dahlmann, B. (2022). Increase in admission rates and symptom severity of childhood and adolescent anorexia nervosa in europe during the COVID‐19 pandemic: Data from specialized eating disorder units in different European countries. Child and Adolescent Psychiatry and Mental Health, 16(1), 46. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13034‐022‐00482‐x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gormally, J., Black, S., Daston, S., &amp; Rardin, D. (1982). The assessment of binge eeating severity among obese persons. Addictive Behaviors, 7(1), 47–55. https://doi.org/10.1016/0306‐4603(82)90024‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haddad, C., Zakhour, M., Bou Kheir, M., Haddad, R., Al Hachach, M., Sacre, H., &amp; Salameh, P. (2000). Association between eating behavior and quarantine/confinement stressors during the coronavirus disease 2019 outbreak. Journal of Eating Disorders, 8(1), 40. https://doi.org/10.1186/s40337‐020‐00317‐0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haileamlak, A. (2022). Pandemics will be more frequent. Ethiopian Journal of Health Sciences, 32(2), 228. https://doi.org/10.4314/ejhs.v32i2.1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halbeisen, G., Braks, K., Huber, T. J., &amp; Paslakis, G. (2022). Gender differences in treatment outcomes for eating disorders: A case‐matched, retrospective pre‐post comparison. Nutrients, 14(11), 2240. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu14112240</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halbeisen, G., Brandt, G., &amp; Paslakis, G. (2022). A plea for diversity in eating disorders research. Frontiers in Psychiatry, 13. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2022.820043</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halbeisen, G., Laskowski, N. M., Brandt, G., Waschescio, U., &amp; Paslakis, G. (2024). Eating disorders in men ‐ an underestimated problem, an unseen need. Deutsches Ärzteblatt International. https://doi.org/10.3238/arztebl.m2023.0246</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamidi, R., Ghodsi, P., &amp; Taghiloo, S. (2024). The mediating role of psychological well‐being in explaining the effect of a health‐promoting lifestyle on death anxiety in seniors with COVID‐19 experience. Health Nexus, 2(1), 89–98. https://doi.org/10.61838/kman.hn.2.1.10</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamzaid, N. H., Gumisi, Z. G. R., Ahmad Helme, S. K., Azmi, N., &amp; Shahril, M. R. (2022). Lifestyle and psychological factors affecting eating habits and physical activity among government servants in the states with the highest cumulative cases in Malaysia during the COVID‐19 pandemic. Frontiers in Public Health, 10. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpubh.2022.816530</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hanlon, P., Wightman, H., Politis, M., Kirkpatrick, S., Jones, C., Andrew, M. K., Vetrano, D. L., Dent, E., &amp; Hoogendijk, E. O. (2024). The relationship between frailty and social vulnerability: A systematic review. The Lancet. Healthy Longevity, 5(3), e214–e226. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2666‐7568(23)00263‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hawes, M. T., Szenczy, A. K., Klein, D. N., Hajcak, G., &amp; Nelson, B. D. (2022). Increases in depression and anxiety symptoms in adolescents and young adults during the COVID‐19 pandemic. Psychological Medicine, 52(14), 3222–3230. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0033291720005358</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hazzard, V. M., Loth, K. A., Hooper, L., &amp; Becker, C. B. (2020). Food insecurity and eating disorders: A review of emerging evidence. Current Psychiatry Reports, 22(12), 74. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11920‐020‐01200‐0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hazzard, V. M., Simone, M., Borg, S. L., Borton, K. A., Sonneville, K. R., Calzo, J. P., &amp; Lipson, S. K. (2020). Disparities in eating disorder risk and diagnosis among sexual minority college students: Findings from the national Healthy Minds Study. International Journal of Eating Disorders, 53(9), 1563–1568. https://doi.org/10.1002/eat.23304</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herman, B. K., Deal, L. S., DiBenedetti, D. B., Nelson, L., Fehnel, S. E., &amp; Brown, T. M. (2016). Development of the 7‐item binge‐eating disorder screener (BEDS‐7). The Primary Care Companion for CNS Disorders. https://doi.org/10.4088/PCC.15m01896</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holmes, E. A., O’Connor, R. C., Perry, V. H., Tracey, I., Wessely, S., Arseneault, L., Ballard, C., Christensen, H., Cohen Silver, R., Everall, I., Ford, T., John, A., Kabir, T., King, K., Madan, I., Michie, S., Przybylski, A. K., Shafran, R., Sweeney, A., …, &amp; Bullmore, E. (2020). Multidisciplinary research priorities for the COVID‐19 pandemic: A call for action for mental health science. The Lancet Psychiatry, 7(6), 547–560. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2215‐0366(20)30168‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hunter, L., Gerritsen, S., &amp; Egli, V. (2022). Changes in eating behaviours due to crises, disasters and pandemics: A scoping review. Nutrition &amp; Food Science, 53(2), 358–390. https://doi.org/10.1108/NFS‐12‐2021‐0385</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>IMF. (2024). Internation monetary fund: Datamapper 2024. https://www.imf.org/external/datamapper/NGDPDPC@WEO/OEMDC/ADVEC/WEOWORLD/DNK</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kakaei, H., Nourmoradi, H., Bakhtiyari, S., Jalilian, M., &amp; Mirzaei, A. (2022). Chapter One – Effect of COVID‐19 on food security, hunger, and food crisis. COVID‐19 and the Sustainable Development Goals, 3–29. https://doi.org/10.1016/B978‐0‐323‐91307‐2.00005‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kann, L., Warren, C. W., Harris, W. A., Collins, J. L., Williams, B. I., Ross, J. G., &amp; Kolbe, L. J. (1996). Youth risk behavior surveillance—United States, 1995. Journal of School Health, 66(10), 365–377. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1746‐1561.1996.tb03394.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, R., Olpin, E., Novilla, L. K., &amp; Crandall, A. (2022). The association of COVID‐19 stressors and family health on overeating before and during the COVID‐19 pandemic. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, 19(10), 6174. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph19106174</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kocaay, F., Ayyildiz, P., &amp; Şanlier, N. (2022). Enquiring into experiences of fear, posttraumatic stress and nutritional habits of medical students during the COVID‐19 pandemic. Duzce Medical Journal, 24(3), 307–314. https://doi.org/10.18678/dtfd.1192388</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuijer, R. G., &amp; Boyce, J. A. (2012). Emotional eating and its effect on eating behaviour after a natural disaster. Appetite, 58(3), 936–939. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.appet.2012.02.046</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laskowski, N. M., Brandt, G., &amp; Paslakis, G. (2024). Geschlechtsspezifische Unterschiede und Ungleichheiten der COVID‐19 Pandemie: Eine Synthese systematischer Reviews unter Einbeziehung sexueller und geschlechtlicher Minderheiten. PPmP ‐ Psychotherapie · Psychosomatik · Medizinische Psychologie, 74(02), 57–69. https://doi.org/10.1055/a‐2228‐6244</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laskowski, N. M., Halbeisen, G., Braks, K., Huber, T. J., &amp; Paslakis, G. (2023). Factor structure of the Eating Disorder Examination‐Questionnaire (EDE‐Q) in adult men with eating disorders. Journal of Eating Disorders, 11(1), 34. https://doi.org/10.1186/s40337‐023‐00757‐4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Latner, J. D., Mond, J. M., Kelly, M. C., Haynes, S. N., &amp; Hay, P. J. (2014). The loss of control over eating scale: Development and psychometric evaluation. International Journal of Eating Disorders, 47(6), 647–659. https://doi.org/10.1002/eat.22296</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levine, M. P. (2012). Loneliness and eating disorders. Journal of Psychology, 146(1–2), 243–257. https://doi.org/10.1080/00223980.2011.606435</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ling, J., Duren, P., &amp; Robbins, L. B. (2022). Food insecurity and mental well‐being among low‐income families during covid‐19 pandemic. American Journal of Health Promotion, 36(7), 1123–1132. https://doi.org/10.1177/08901171221089627</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma, L. L., Wang, Y. Y., Yang, Z. H., Huang, D., Weng, H., &amp; Zeng, X. T. (2020). Methodological quality (risk of bias) assessment tools for primary and secondary medical studies: What are they and which is better? Military Medical Research, 7(1), 7. https://doi.org/10.1186/s40779‐020‐00238‐8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahar, B., Warsi, J., &amp; Shah, T. (2021). Eating disorders and eating pattern during covid‐19 pandemic: A short bulletin. Journal of Liaquat University of Medical &amp; Health Sciences, 20(02), 157–162. https://doi.org/10.22442/jlumhs.2021.00776</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McQuaid, R. J., Cox, S. M. L., Ogunlana, A., &amp; Jaworska, N. (2021). The burden of loneliness: Implications of the social determinants of health during COVID‐19. Psychiatry Research, 296, 113648. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.psychres.2020.113648</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mensinger, J. L., Granche, J. L., Cox, S. A., &amp; Henretty, J. R. (2020). Sexual and gender minority individuals report higher rates of abuse and more severe eating disorder symptoms than cisgender heterosexual individuals at admission to eating disorder treatment. International Journal of Eating Disorders, 53(4), 541–554. https://doi.org/10.1002/eat.23257</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meyer, I. H. (2003). Prejudice, social stress, and mental health in lesbian, gay, and bisexual populations: Conceptual issues and research evidence. Psychological Bulletin, 129(5), 674–697. https://doi.org/10.1037/0033‐2909.129.5.674</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miniati, M., Marzetti, F., Palagini, L., Marazziti, D., Orrù, G., Conversano, C., &amp; Gemignani, A. (2021). Eating disorders spectrum during the covid pandemic: A systematic review. Frontiers in Psychology, 12. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2021.663376</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohapatra, S., Mohapatra, M., Kar, S., &amp; Tekkalaki, B. (2021). Perceived stress and emotional overeating during COVID‐19 pandemic. Annals of Indian Psychiatry, 5(2), 132–138. https://doi.org/10.4103/aip.aip_18_21</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moher, D. (2009). Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta‐analyses: The PRISMA statement. Annals of Internal Medicine, 151(4), 264. https://doi.org/10.7326/0003‐4819‐151‐4‐200908180‐00135</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morgan, J. F. (2000). The SCOFF questionnaire: A new screening tool for eating disorders. Western Journal of Medicine, 172(3), 164–165. https://doi.org/10.1136/ewjm.172.3.164</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nashwan, A. J., Villar, R. C., Al‐Qudimat, A. R., Kader, N., Alabdulla, M., Abujaber, A. A., Al‐Jabry, M. M., Harkous, M., Philip, A., Ali, R., Chandra, P., Yassin, M. A., Shraim, M., &amp; Singh, K. (2021). Quality of life, sleep quality, depression, anxiety, stress, eating habits, and social bounds in nurses during the coronavirus disease 2019 pandemic in Qatar (the protector study): A cross‐sectional, comparative study. Journal of Personalized Medicine, 11(9), 918. https://doi.org/10.3390/jpm11090918</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Flynn, J. L., Nowicki, G. P., Laveway, K., Gordon, A. R., &amp; Rodgers, R. F. (2023). Toward inclusivity: A systematic review of the conceptualization of sexual minority status and associated eating disorder outcomes across two decades. International Journal of Eating Disorders, 45(2), 350–365. https://doi.org/10.1002/eat.23830</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Özcan, B. A., &amp; Yeşilkaya, B. (2021). Adverse effect of emotional eating developed during the COVID‐19 pandemic on healthy nutrition, a vicious circle: A cross‐sectional descriptive study. Revista Española de Nutrición Humana y Dietética, 25, e1144. https://doi.org/10.14306/renhyd.25.S2.1144</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pandya, A., &amp; Lodha, P. (2021). Social connectedness, excessive screen time during COVID‐19 and mental health: A review of current evidence. Frontiers in Human Dynamics, 3. https://doi.org/10.3389/fhumd.2021.684137</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parenteau, A. M., Boyer, C. J., Campos, L. J., Carranza, A. F., Deer, L. K., Hartman, D. T., Bidwell, J. T., &amp; Hostinar, C. E. (2023). A review of mental health disparities during COVID‐19: Evidence, mechanisms, and policy recommendations for promoting societal resilience. Development and Psychopathology, 35(4), 1821–1842. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0954579422000499</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parker, L. L., &amp; Harriger, J. A. (2020). Eating disorders and disordered eating behaviors in the LGBT population: A review of the literature. Journal of Eating Disorders, 8(1), 51. https://doi.org/10.1186/s40337‐020‐00327‐y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pensgaard, A. M., Oevreboe, T. H., &amp; Ivarsson, A. (2021). Mental health among elite athletes in Norway during a selected period of the COVID‐19 pandemic. BMJ Open Sport and Exercise Medicine, 7(1), e001025. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjsem‐2020‐001025</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Periasamy, P., Ansar, S., Suganthi, V., Gunasekaran, S., Vaithilingam, K., &amp; Kannan, V. R. (2022). Impact of lockdown on college students sleep quality, physical activity and eating attitudes in South India—A cross‐sectional observational study. International Journal of Life Science and Pharma Research. https://doi.org/10.22376/ijpbs/lpr.2022.12.6.l47‐58</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phillipou, A., Tan, E. J., Toh, W. L., Van Rheenen, T. E., Meyer, D., Neill, E., Sumner, P., &amp; Rossell, S. L. (2021). Mental health of individuals with and without eating disorders across six months and two waves of COVID‐19. Eating Behaviors, 43, 101564. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eatbeh.2021.101564</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pinchuk, I., Solonskyi, A., Yachnik, Y., Kopchak, O., Klasa, K., Sobański, J. A., &amp; Odintsova, T. (2024). Psychological well‐being of Ukrainian students three months after the emerge of full‐scale war. Psychiatria Polska, 58(1), 121–151. https://doi.org/10.12740/PP/177073</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pineda‐García, G., Serrano‐Medina, A., Ochoa‐Ruíz, E., &amp; Martínez, A. L. (2021). Body image, anxiety, and bulimic behavior during confinement due to covid‐19 in Mexico. Healthcare (Switzerland), 9(11), 1435. https://doi.org/10.3390/healthcare9111435</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Puhl, R. M., Lessard, L. M., Larson, N., Eisenberg, M. E., &amp; Neumark‐Stzainer, D. (2020). Weight stigma as a predictor of distress and maladaptive eating behaviors during covid‐19: Longitudinal findings from the eat study. Annals of Behavioral Medicine, 54(10), 738–746. https://doi.org/10.1093/ABM/KAAA077</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qian, J., Wu, Y., Liu, F., Zhu, Y., Jin, H., Zhang, H., Wan, Y., Li, C., &amp; Yu, D. (2022). An update on the prevalence of eating disorders in the general population: A systematic review and meta‐analysis. Eating and Weight Disorders, 27(2), 415–428. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40519‐021‐01162‐z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiu, J., Shen, B., Zhao, M., Wang, Z., Xie, B., &amp; Xu, Y. (2020). A nationwide survey of psychological distress among Chinese people in the COVID‐19 epidemic: Implications and policy recommendations. General Psychiatry, 33(2), e100213. https://doi.org/10.1136/gpsych‐2020‐100213</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramalho, S. M., Trovisqueira, A., de Lourdes, M., Gonçalves, S., Ribeiro, I., Vaz, A. R., Machado, P. P. P., &amp; Conceição, E. (2022). The impact of COVID‐19 lockdown on disordered eating behaviors: The mediation role of psychological distress. Eating and Weight Disorders, 27(1), 179–188. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40519‐021‐01128‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rassolnia, A., &amp; Nobari, H. (2024). The impact of socio‐economic status and physical activity on psychological well‐being and sleep quality among college students during the COVID‐19 pandemic. International Journal of Sport Studies for Health, 7(2), 1–12. https://doi.org/10.61838/kman.intjssh.7.2.1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richardson, C., Patton, M., Phillips, S., &amp; Paslakis, G. (2020). The impact of the COVID‐19 pandemic on help‐seeking behaviors in individuals suffering from eating disorders and their caregivers. General Hospital Psychiatry, 67, 136–140. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.genhosppsych.2020.10.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richardson, C., Phillips, S., &amp; Paslakis, G. (2021). One year in: The impact of the COVID‐19 pandemic on help‐seeking behaviors among youth experiencing eating disorders and their caregivers. Psychiatry Research, 306, 114263. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.psychres.2021.114263</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robinson, E., Boyland, E., Chisholm, A., Harrold, J., Maloney, N., Marty, L., Mead, B., Noonan, R., &amp; Hardman, C. (2020). Obesity, eating behavior and physical activity during COVID‐19 lockdown: A study of UK adults. Appetite, 156, 104853. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.appet.2020.104853</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodgers, R. F., Lombardo, C., Cerolini, S., Franko, D. L., Omori, M., Fuller‐Tyszkiewicz, M., Linardon, J., Courtet, P., &amp; Guillaume, S. (2020). The impact of the COVID‐19 pandemic on eating disorder risk and symptoms. International Journal of Eating Disorders, 53(7), 1166–1170. https://doi.org/10.1002/eat.23318</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Romano, K. A., Lipson, S. K., Beccia, A. L., Quatromoni, P. A., &amp; Murgueitio, J. (2023). Disparities in eating disorder symptoms and mental healthcare engagement prior to and following the onset of the COVID‐19 pandemic: Findings from a national study of US college students. International Journal of Eating Disorders, 56(1), 203–215. https://doi.org/10.1002/eat.23869</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sagaribay, R., Frietze, G., Lerma, M., Gainza Perez, M., Eno Louden, J., &amp; Cooper, T. V. (2022). A prospective analysis of loss of control over eating, sociodemographics, and mental health during COVID‐19 in the United States. Obesity Research &amp; Clinical Practice, 16(1), 87–90. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.orcp.2021.11.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salerno, J. P., Devadas, J., Pease, M., Nketia, B., &amp; Fish, J. N. (2020). Sexual and gender minority stress amid the COVID‐19 pandemic: Implications for LGBTQ young persons’ mental health and well‐being. Public Health Reports, 135(6), 721–727. https://doi.org/10.1177/0033354920954511</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santarossa, S., &amp; Woodruff, S. J. (2017). #Socialmedia: Exploring the relationship of social networking sites on body image, self‐esteem, and eating disorders. Social Media and Society, 3(2). https://doi.org/10.1177/2056305117704407</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schimmenti, A., Billieux, J., &amp; Starcevic, V. (2020). The four horsemen of fear: An integrated model of understanding fear experiences during the COVID‐19 pandemic. Clinical Neuropsychiatry, 17(2), 41–45. https://doi.org/10.36131/CN20200202</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schneider, J., Pegram, G., Gibson, B., Talamonti, D., Tinoco, A., Craddock, N., Matheson, E., &amp; Forshaw, M. (2023). A mixed‐studies systematic review of the experiences of body image, disordered eating, and eating disorders during the COVID‐19 pandemic. International Journal of Eating Disorders, 56(1), 26–67. https://doi.org/10.1002/eat.23706</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schoeps, K., Tamarit, A., De la Barrera, U., Lacomba‐Trejo, L., Montoya‐Castilla, I., Del Rosario, C., Coello, F., Herrera, S., Trujillo, Á., Riveros Munevar, F., &amp; Amador Esparza, N. A. (2023). Social and psychological effects of COVID‐19 pandemic on adolescents' and young adults' mental health: A cross‐cultural mediation study. Psychological Reports, 126(6), 2729–2756. https://doi.org/10.1177/00332941221100451</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharpe, H., Newman, E., Robertson, M. D. A., Opitz, M. C., Peebles, I., &amp; Duffy, F. (2022). An 8‐month longitudinal exploration of body image and disordered eating in the UK during the COVID‐19 pandemic. Eating Behaviors, 46, 101660. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eatbeh.2022.101660</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shisslak, C. M., Renger, R., Sharpe, T., Crago, M., McKnight, K. M., Gray, N., Bryson, S., Estes, L. S., Parnaby, O. G., Killen, J., &amp; Taylor, C. B. (1999). Development and evaluation of the McKnight risk factor survey for assessing potential risk and protective factors for disordered eating in preadolescent and adolescent girls. International Journal of Eating Disorders, 25(2), 195–214. https://doi.org/10.1002/(SICI)1098‐108X(199903)25:2&lt;195::AID‐EAT9&gt;3.0.CO;2‐B</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Solmi, M., Veronese, N., Sergi, G., Luchini, C., Favaro, A., Santonastaso, P., Vancampfort, D., Correll, C. U., Ussher, M., Thapa‐Chhetri, N., Fornaro, M., &amp; Stubbs, B. (2016). The association between smoking prevalence and eating disorders: A systematic review and meta‐analysis. Addiction, 111(11), 1914–1922. https://doi.org/10.1111/add.13457</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Støving, R. K., Andries, A., Brixen, K., Bilenberg, N., &amp; Hørder, K. (2011). Gender differences in outcome of eating disorders: A retrospective cohort study. Psychiatry Research, 186(2–3), 362–366. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.psychres.2010.08.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suarez‐Albor, C. L., Galletta, M., &amp; Gómez‐Bustamante, E. M. (2022). Factors associated with eating disorders in adolescents: A systematic review. Acta BioMedica, 93(3). https://doi.org/10.23750/abm.v93i3.13140</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sumalla‐Cano, S., Forbes‐Hernández, T., Aparicio‐Obregón, S., Crespo, J., Eléxpuru‐Zabaleta, M., Gracia‐Villar, M., Giampieri, F., &amp; Elío, I. (2022). Changes in the lifestyle of the Spanish university population during confinement for COVID‐19. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, 19(4), 2210. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph19042210</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sundgot‐Borgen, J., &amp; Torstveit, M. K. (2004). Prevalence of eating disorders in elite athletes is higher than in the general population. Clinical Journal of Sport Medicine, 14(1), 25–32. https://doi.org/10.1097/00042752‐200401000‐00005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tabler, J., Schmitz, R. M., Charak, R., &amp; Dickinson, E. (2021). Perceived weight gain and eating disorder symptoms among LGBTQ+ adults during the COVID‐19 pandemic: A convergent mixed‐method study. Journal of Eating Disorders, 9(1), 115. https://doi.org/10.1186/s40337‐021‐00470‐0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan, S. T., &amp; Shahril, P. I. A. (2023). Moderate‐to‐severe food insecurity is positively correlated with the risk of eating disorders in the aftermath of the COVID‐19 pandemic. Ethics, Medicine, and Public Health, 27, 100874. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jemep.2023.100874</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tavolacci, M. P., Ladner, J., &amp; Dechelotte, P. (2021). COVID‐19 pandemic and eating disorders among university students. Nutrients, 13(12), 4294. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu13124294</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Termorshuizen, J. D., Watson, H. J., Thornton, L. M., Borg, S., Flatt, R. E., MacDermod, C. M., Harper, L. E., van Furth, E. F., Peat, C. M., &amp; Bulik, C. M. (2020). Early impact of COVID‐19 on individuals with self‐reported eating disorders: A survey of ∼1,000 individuals in the United States and The Netherlands. International Journal of Eating Disorders, 53(11), 1780–1790. https://doi.org/10.1002/eat.23353</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Joanna Briggs Institute. (2017). Critical appraisal checklist for analytical cross sectional studies. Checklist for Analytical Cross Sectional Studies. Retrieved from https://jbi.global/critical‐appraisal‐tools</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thompson, J. K., Van Den Berg, P., Roehrig, M., Guarda, A. S., &amp; Heinberg, L. J. (2004). The sociocultural attitudes towards appearance scale‐3 (SATAQ‐3): Development and validation. International Journal of Eating Disorders, 35(3), 293–304. https://doi.org/10.1002/eat.10257</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Traut, P., Halbeisen, G., Braks, K., Huber, T. J., &amp; Paslakis, G. (2023). Sociodemographic and clinical features of men and women with eating disorders: A diagnosis‐matched, retrospective comparison among inpatients. Frontiers in Psychiatry, 14, 1192693. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2023.1192693</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Udo, T., &amp; Grilo, C. M. (2018). Prevalence and correlates of DSM‐5–defined eating disorders in a nationally representative sample of U.S. Adults. Biological Psychiatry, 84(5), 345–354. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biopsych.2018.03.014</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Veritas Health Innovation. (2024). covidence.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. (2024). WHO COVID‐19 dashboard. Retrieved from https://data.who.int/dashboards/covid19/cases?n=c</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yanovski, S. Z., Marcus, M. D., Wadden, T. A., &amp; Walsh, B. T. (2015). The Questionnaire on Eating and Weight Patterns‐5: An updated screening instrument for binge eating disorder. International Journal of Eating Disorders, 48(3), 259–261. https://doi.org/10.1002/eat.22372</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>