<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39432633</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1536-5964</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>103</Volume><Issue>42</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>18</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Medicine (Baltimore)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Exploring the mechanism of comorbidity in patients with T1DM and COVID-19: Integrating bioinformatics and Mendelian randomization methods.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e40128</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e40128</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e40128</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/MD.0000000000040128</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>During the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic, the incidence of type 1 diabetes mellitus (T1DM) has increased. Additionally, evidence suggests that individuals with diabetes mellitus may have increased susceptibility to severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 infection. However, the specific causal relationships and interaction mechanisms between T1DM and COVID-19 remain unclear. This study aims to investigate the causal relationship between T1DM and COVID-19, utilizing differential gene expression and Mendelian randomization analyses. Differentially expressed gene sets from datasets GSE156035 and GSE171110 were intersected to identify shared genes, analyzed for functional enrichment. Mendelian randomization models were employed to assess causal effects, revealing no direct causal link between T1DM and COVID-19 in the European population (P &gt; .05). Notably, DNA replication and sister chromatid cohesion 1 (DSCC1) showed negative causal associations with both diseases (T1DM: OR = 0.943, 95% CI: 0.898-0.991, P = .020; COVID-19: OR = 0.919, 95% CI: 0.882-0.958, P &lt; .001), suggesting a protective effect against their comorbidity. This genetic evidence highlights DSCC1 as a potential target for monitoring and managing the co-occurrence of T1DM and COVID-19.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Tingliang</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Endocrinology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Guangxi Medical University, Nanning, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Yun</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wu</LastName><ForeName>Chunjiao</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huang</LastName><ForeName>Zhenxing</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liang</LastName><ForeName>Xinghuan</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Luo</LastName><ForeName>Zuojie</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2969-8329</Identifier></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Medicine (Baltimore)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>2985248R</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0025-7974</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D057182" MajorTopicYN="Y">Mendelian Randomization Analysis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019295" MajorTopicYN="Y">Computational Biology</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015897" MajorTopicYN="Y">Comorbidity</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003922" MajorTopicYN="Y">Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>57</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39432633</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11495797</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000040128</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00005792-202410180-00049</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Rahmati M, Yon DK, Lee SW, et al. . New-onset type 1 diabetes in children and adolescents as postacute sequelae of SARS-CoV-2 infection: a systematic review and meta-analysis of cohort studies. J Med Virol. 2023;95:e28833.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37264687</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh AK, Khunti K. COVID-19 and diabetes. Annu Rev Med. 2022;73:129–47.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34379444</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barranco C. Increased T1DM risk in children infected with SARS-CoV-2. Nat Metab. 2022;4:1431.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36400928</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kashfi K, Anbardar N, Asadipooya A, Asadipooya K. Type 1 diabetes and COVID-19: a literature review and possible management. Int J Endocrinol Metab. 2023;21:e139768.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11041820</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38666042</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Metwally AA, Mehta P, Johnson BS, Nagarjuna A, Snyder MP. COVID-19-induced new-onset diabetes: trends and technologies. Diabetes. 2021;70:2733–44.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8660988</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34686519</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lima-Martínez MM, Carrera Boada C, Madera-Silva MD, Marín W, Contreras M. COVID-19 and diabetes: a bidirectional relationship. Clin Investig Arterioscler. 2021;33:151–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7598432</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33303218</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Markin L, Fartushok T, Fartushok N, Soyka L, Fedevych Y. Diabetes Mellitus and covid-19: today’s challenges. Georgian Med News. 2023;43:50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37354672</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shang L, Shao M, Guo Q, et al. . Diabetes Mellitus is associated with severe infection and mortality in patients with COVID-19: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Arch Med Res. 2020;51:700–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7413048</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32811670</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Li K, Mo S, et al. . Identification of common genes and pathways between type 2 diabetes and COVID-19. Front Genet. 2024;15:1249501.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11063347</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38699234</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao T, Ding J, Liang Z, et al. . When type II diabetes mellitus meets COVID-19-Identification of the shared gene signatures and biological mechanism between the two diseases. Eur J Clin Invest. 2023;53:e13955.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36656083</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cecelja M, Lewis CM, Shah AM, Chowienczyk P. Cardiovascular health and risk of hospitalization with COVID-19: a mendelian randomization study. JRSM Cardiovasc Dis. 2021;10:20480040211059374.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8619738</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34840730</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoshikawa M, Asaba K, Nakayama T. Estimating causal effects of genetically predicted type 2 diabetes on COVID-19 in the East Asian population. Front Endocrinol (Lausanne). 2022;13:1014882.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9767950</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36568068</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Yi B, Wang S, Chen X, Wen Z. Effect of hyperglycemia on the immune function of COVID-19 patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus: a retrospective study. PeerJ. 2022;10:e14570.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10286731</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37359706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hayden MR. An immediate and long-term complication of COVID-19 May Be Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus: the central role of β-Cell dysfunction, apoptosis and exploration of possible mechanisms. Cells. 2020;9:2475.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7697826</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33202960</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang P, Zheng CB, Liu XY, Zhang X, Huang L, Zeng X. Lymphocytes regulate expression of the SARS-CoV-2 cell entry factor ACE2 in the pancreas of T2DM patients. Diabet Med. 2023;40:e15106.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37014274</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han M, Ma K, Wang X, et al. . Immunological characteristics in type 2 diabetes mellitus among COVID-19 patients. Front Endocrinol (Lausanne). 2021;12:596518.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7992040</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33776910</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shao S, Yang Q, Pan R, Yu X, Chen Y. Interaction of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 and diabetes. Front Endocrinol (Lausanne). 2021;12:731974.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8527093</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34690930</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rey-Reñones C, Martinez-Torres S, Martín-Luján FM, et al. . Type 2 diabetes mellitus and COVID-19: a narrative review. Biomedicines. 2022;10:2089.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9495673</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36140191</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Z, Zhang L, Tang F, et al. . Transcriptome analysis of peripheral blood mononuclear cells in patients with type 1 diabetes mellitus. Endocrine. 2022;78:270–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35976509</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu S, Long J, Liang T, et al. . Bioinformatics analysis based on high-throughput sequencing data to identify hub genes related to different clinical types of COVID-19. Funct Integr Genomics. 2023;23:71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9975444</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36856850</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kanehisa M, Furumichi M, Sato Y, Ishiguro-Watanabe M, Tanabe M. KEGG: integrating viruses and cellular organisms. Nucleic Acids Res. 2021;49:D545–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7779016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33125081</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeremiah SS, Moin ASM, Butler AE. Virus-induced diabetes mellitus: revisiting infection etiology in light of SARS-CoV-2. Metabolism. 2024;156:155917.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38642828</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Demirci I, Haymana C, Tasci I, et al. . Higher rate of COVID-19 mortality in patients with type 1 than type 2 diabetes: a nationwide study. Endokrynol Pol. 2022;73:87–95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35119089</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kempegowda P, Melson E, Johnson A, et al. . Effect of COVID-19 on the clinical course of diabetic ketoacidosis (DKA) in people with type 1 and type 2 diabetes. Endocr Connect. 2021;10:371–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8133369</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33666571</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Guo H, Wang G, Zhai J, Du B. COVID-19 as a trigger for type 1 diabetes. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2023;108:2176–83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36950864</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zareini B, Sørensen KK, Eiken PA, et al. . Association of COVID-19 and development of type 1 diabetes: a Danish Nationwide Register Study. Diabetes Care. 2023;46:1477–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37276529</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rao S, Lau A, So HC. Exploring diseases/traits and blood proteins causally related to expression of ACE2, the Putative Receptor of SARS-CoV-2: a mendelian randomization analysis highlights tentative relevance of diabetes-related traits. Diabetes Care. 2020;43:1416–26.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32430459</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Kell AL, Wasserfall C, Guingab-Cagmat J, Webb-Roberston BM, Atkinson MA, Garrett TJ. Targeted metabolomic analysis identifies increased serum levels of GABA and branched chain amino acids in canine diabetes. Metabolomics. 2021;17:100.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8693811</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34775536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vigers T, Vinovskis C, Li LP, et al. . Plasma levels of carboxylic acids are markers of early kidney dysfunction in young people with type 1 diabetes. Pediatr Nephrol. 2023;38:193–202.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10182875</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35507146</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luporini RL, Pott-Junior H, Di Medeiros Leal MCB, et al. . Phenylalanine and COVID-19: tracking disease severity markers. Int Immunopharmacol. 2021;101:108313.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8559801</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34741868</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Satarker S, Nampoothiri M. Structural proteins in severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus-2. Arch Med Res. 2020;51:482–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7247499</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32493627</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding H, Wang F, Shi X, et al. . LncRNA MALAT1 induces the dysfunction of β cells via reducing the histone acetylation of the PDX-1 promoter in type 1 diabetes. Exp Mol Pathol. 2020;114:104432.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32243891</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hatakeyama D, Masuda T, Miki R, Ohtsuki S, Kuzuhara T. In-vitro acetylation of SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2 nucleocapsid proteins by human PCAF and GCN5. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 2021;557:273–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8030717</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33894414</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blagov AV, Summerhill VI, Sukhorukov VN, Popov MA, Grechko AV, Orekhov AN. Type 1 diabetes mellitus: inflammation, mitophagy, and mitochondrial function. Mitochondrion. 2023;72:11–21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37453498</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prasada Kabekkodu S, Chakrabarty S, Jayaram P, et al. . Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronaviruses contributing to mitochondrial dysfunction: Implications for post-COVID complications. Mitochondrion. 2023;69:43–56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9854144</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36690315</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pérez-Torres I, Soto ME, Guarner-Lans V, Manzano-Pech L, Soria-Castro E. The possible role of glucose-6-Phosphate Dehydrogenase in the SARS-CoV-2 Infection. Cells. 2022;11:1982.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9265820</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35805067</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oliva M, Tosat-Bitrián C, Barrado-Gil L, et al. . Effect of clinically used microtubule targeting drugs on viral infection and transport function. Int J Mol Sci. 2022;23:3448.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8998746</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35408808</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muralidharan C, Conteh AM, Marasco MR, et al. . Pancreatic beta cell autophagy is impaired in type 1 diabetes. Diabetologia. 2021;64:865–77.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7940272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33515072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang SC, Liao JY. Epidemiologic implication of the association between herpes simplex virus infection and the risk of type 1 Diabetes Mellitus: a nationwide case-control study in Taiwan. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19:7832.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9265894</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35805493</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farid H, Khan M, Jamal S, Ghafoor R. Oral manifestations of Covid-19-A literature review. Rev Med Virol. 2022;32:e2248.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8209937</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34028129</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Schie JJ, de Lint K, Pai GM, Rooimans MA, Wolthuis RM, de Lange J. MMS22L-TONSL functions in sister chromatid cohesion in a pathway parallel to DSCC1-RFC. Life Sci Alliance. 2023;6:e202201596.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9733570</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36622344</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamaguchi K, Yamaguchi R, Takahashi N, et al. . Overexpression of cohesion establishment factor DSCC1 through E2F in colorectal cancer. PLoS One. 2014;9:e85750.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3894995</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24465681</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yavuz O, Dincel GC, Yildirim S, El-Ashram S, Al-Olayan E. Impact of apoptosis and oxidative stress on pancreatic beta cell pathophysiology in streptozotocin-induced Type 1 diabetes mellitus. Tissue Cell. 2024;91:102552.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39255742</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li X, Zhang Z, Wang Z, Gutiérrez-Castrellón P, Shi H. Cell deaths: Involvement in the pathogenesis and intervention therapy of COVID-19. Signal Transduct Target Ther. 2022;7:186.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9189267</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35697684</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Primorac D, Vrdoljak K, Brlek P, et al. . Adaptive immune responses and immunity to SARS-CoV-2. Front Immunol. 2022;13:848582.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9114812</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35603211</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ilonen J, Lempainen J, Veijola R. The heterogeneous pathogenesis of type 1 diabetes mellitus. Nat Rev Endocrinol. 2019;15:635–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31534209</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zou X, Wang S, Zhang Y, Wang X, Yang W. The role of follicular T helper cells in the onset and treatment of type 1 diabetes. Int Immunopharmacol. 2020;84:106499.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32298964</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feldman J, Bals J, Altomare CG, et al. . Naive human B cells engage the receptor binding domain of SARS-CoV-2, variants of concern, and related sarbecoviruses. Sci Immunol. 2021;6:eabl5842.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8720485</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34648356</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J, Gilani SF, Noor N, et al. . Decoding the DSCC1 gene as a pan-cancer biomarker in human cancers via comprehensive multi-omics analyses. Am J Transl Res. 2024;16:738–54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10994803</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38586115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun L, Xi S, He G, et al. . Two to Tango: dialogue between adaptive and innate immunity in type 1 Diabetes. J Diabetes Res. 2020;2020:4106518.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7415089</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32802890</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith MJ, Simmons KM, Cambier JC. B cells in type 1 diabetes mellitus and diabetic kidney disease. Nat Rev Nephrol. 2017;13:712–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6733025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29038537</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin G, Wang W, Cheng P, Tian Y, Zhang L, Niu HU. DNA replication and sister chromatid cohesion 1 promotes breast carcinoma progression by modulating the Wnt/β-catenin signaling and p53 protein. J Biosci. 2020;45:127.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33184243</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horwitz E, Krogvold L, Zhitomirsky S, et al. . β-Cell DNA Damage Response Promotes Islet Inflammation in Type 1 Diabetes. Diabetes. 2018;67:2305–18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6198335</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30150306</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carroll KR, Elfers EE, Stevens JJ, et al. . Extending Remission and Reversing New-Onset Type 1 diabetes by targeted ablation of autoreactive T Cells. Diabetes. 2018;67:2319–28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6198341</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30104248</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Major J, Crotta S, Llorian M, et al. . Type I and III interferons disrupt lung epithelial repair during recovery from viral infection. Science. 2020;369:712–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7292500</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32527928</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shati AA, Alfaifi MY. Salidroside protects against diabetes mellitus-induced kidney injury and renal fibrosis by attenuating TGF-β1 and Wnt1/3a/β-catenin signalling. Clin Exp Pharmacol Physiol. 2020;47:1692–704.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32472701</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu B, Wu Y, Huang S, et al. . Uncoupling of macrophage inflammation from self-renewal modulates host recovery from respiratory viral infection. Immunity. 2021;54:1200–18.e9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8192557</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33951416</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>