<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39439636</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Role of Carcinoembryonic Antigen in Severity Assessment and Mortality Prediction in COVID-19 Patients.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e69894</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e69894</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e69894</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.69894</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Background Early risk stratification of COVID-19 may yield a better prognosis by tailoring effective treatment strategies. Recent studies have identified that elevated carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA) has prognostic value in terms of disease severity and mortality in patients with pneumonia. This study aims to explore the potential of CEA as a marker for both severity assessment and mortality prediction in COVID-19 patients. Methods From August 2020 to October 2021, we conducted this observational study in which patients who tested positive for COVID-19 by reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) or had high-resolution computed tomography (HRCT) chest suggestive of COVID-19 were included on day 0 of their admission to the COVID unit. Patients were classified into mild, moderate, severe, and critical according to the World Health Organization (WHO) guidelines. Blood samples were collected for complete blood count (CBC), C-reactive protein (CRP), ferritin, and CEA on days 0, 3, 7, and 14 of admission. The patient's profile was used to obtain lactate dehydrogenase (LDH), D-dimer, and HRCT scores [based on COVID-19 reporting and data system (CO-RADS) grade]. We used receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves with Youden's index to find the initial (day 0) critical values of CEA for each of mild, moderate, severe, and critical COVID-19. The Kaplan-Meier survival curve was used to predict mortality with the best initial (day 0) cut-off value of CEA. Results Among 75 patients in this study, 15, 20, 19, and 21 were in the mild, moderate, severe, and critical groups, respectively; most were male (68%), and mortality was 18 (24%). Spearman's rank correlation test demonstrates a strong correlation between COVID-19 severity and changes in CEA. In the ROC curves, the area under the curve (AUC) value of CEA was higher among markers in all classifications except for mild to moderate disease. The AUC and critical values of CEA were as follows: for mild to moderate (0.948), 2.5 ng/ml; moderate to severe (1.000), 6.02 ng/ml; and severe to critical (0.769), 11.75 ng/ml. The survival curve shows the best initial cut-off values for mortality outcomes: CEA ≥7.15, CRP ≥81.52, ferritin ≥680.68, lymphocyte percentage ≤7.5, and neutrophil lymphocyte ratio ≥12.7. Conclusions The initial levels of CEA can serve as markers for severity assessment and mortality outcome prediction of COVID-19.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Anjan et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Anjan</LastName><ForeName>Md Ashraful Hassan</ForeName><Initials>MAH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, Bangabandhu Sheikh Mujib Medical University, Dhaka, BGD.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ahmed</LastName><ForeName>Quazi Mamtaz U</ForeName><Initials>QMU</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, Bangabandhu Sheikh Mujib Medical University, Dhaka, BGD.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Masum</LastName><ForeName>Abdullah Al</ForeName><Initials>AA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, Bangabandhu Sheikh Mujib Medical University, Dhaka, BGD.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sami</LastName><ForeName>Chowdhury Adnan</ForeName><Initials>CA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, Bangabandhu Sheikh Mujib Medical University, Dhaka, BGD.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Matin</LastName><ForeName>Md Abdul</ForeName><Initials>MA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, Nilphamari Sadar Hospital, Nilphamari, BGD.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Islam</LastName><ForeName>Mohammad Syedul</ForeName><Initials>MS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, Bangabandhu Sheikh Mujib Medical University, Dhaka, BGD.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chowdhury</LastName><ForeName>Fazle R</ForeName><Initials>FR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, Bangabandhu Sheikh Mujib Medical University, Dhaka, BGD.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Arafat</LastName><ForeName>Shohael Mahmud</ForeName><Initials>SM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, Bangabandhu Sheikh Mujib Medical University, Dhaka, BGD.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rahman</LastName><ForeName>Mahbubur</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, Bangabandhu Sheikh Mujib Medical University, Dhaka, BGD.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hasan</LastName><ForeName>Md Nazmul</ForeName><Initials>MN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, Bangabandhu Sheikh Mujib Medical University, Dhaka, BGD.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">biomarker comparison</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">carcinoembryonic antigen</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">carcinoembryonic antigen (cea)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">covid-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mortality prediction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">severity categorization</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Institutional Review Board of Bangabandhu Shiekh Mujib Medical University issued approval BSMMU/2020/11106. Animal subjects: All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: This study was partly funded by the University Grant Commission of Bangabandhu Sheikh Mujib Medical University. Financial relationships: Md. Ashraful Hassan Anjan declare(s) a grant from University Grant Commission of Bangabandhu Sheikh Mujib Medical University. Funders play no role in study design, monitoring, result, or outcome. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>56</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>55</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39439636</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11494406</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.69894</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>A pneumonia outbreak associated with a new coronavirus of probable bat origin. Zhou P, Yang XL, Wang XG, et al. Nature. 2020;579:270–273.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7095418</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32015507</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cytokine storm in COVID-19: pathogenesis and overview of anti-inflammatory agents used in treatment. Soy M, Keser G, Atagündüz P, Tabak F, Atagündüz I, Kayhan S. Clin Rheumatol. 2020;39:2085–2094.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7260446</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32474885</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clinical characteristics of coronavirus disease 2019 in China. Guan WJ, Ni ZY, Hu Y, et al. N Engl J Med. 2020;382:1708–1720.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7092819</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32109013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ISTH interim guidance on recognition and management of coagulopathy in COVID-19. Thachil J, Tang N, Gando S, et al. J Thromb Haemost. 2020;18:1023–1026.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9906133</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32338827</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Signaling by epithelial members of the CEACAM family - mucosal docking sites for pathogenic bacteria. Tchoupa AK, Schuhmacher T, Hauck CR. Cell Commun Signal. 2014;12:27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4057559</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24735478</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elevated level of serum carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA) and search for a malignancy: a case report. Asad-Ur-Rahman F, Saif MW. Cureus. 2016;8:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4954749</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27446768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA) levels in benign gastrointestinal disease states. M.S. Loewenstein, N. Zamcheck. Cancer. 1978:1412–1418.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">361200</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Immunohistochemical detection of carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA) in non-neoplastic lung disease. Abbona GC, Papotti M, Gugliotta P, Pecchio F, Rapellino M. Int J Biol Markers. 1993;8:240–243.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8138663</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Serum carcinoembryonic antigen: a prognostic marker in HIV-related Pneumocystis carinii pneumonia. Bédos JP, Hignette C, Lucet JC, et al. Scand J Infect Dis. 1992;24:309–315.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1509235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carcinoembryonic antigen-related cell adhesion molecule 5 is an important surface attachment factor that facilitates entry of middle east respiratory syndrome coronavirus. Chan CM, Chu H, Wang Y, et al. J Virol. 2016;90:9114–9127.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5044831</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27489282</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pulmonary and cardiac pathology in African American patients with COVID-19: an autopsy series from New Orleans. Fox SE, Akmatbekov A, Harbert JL, Li G, Quincy Brown J, Vander Heide RS. Lancet Respir Med. 2020;8:681–686.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7255143</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32473124</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Factors associated with prolonged viral RNA shedding in patients with coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) Xu K, Chen Y, Yuan J, et al. Clin Infect Dis. 2020;71:799–806.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7184421</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32271376</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pulmonary pathology of early-phase 2019 novel coronavirus (COVID-19) pneumonia in two patients with lung cancer. Tian S, Hu W, Niu L, Liu H, Xu H, Xiao SY. J Thorac Oncol. 2020;15:700–704.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7128866</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32114094</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Type 2 alveolar cells are stem cells in adult lung. Barkauskas CE, Cronce MJ, Rackley CR, et al. J Clin Invest. 2013;123:3025–3036.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3696553</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23921127</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prognostic value of carcinoembryonic antigen on outcome in patients with coronavirus disease 2019. Yu J, Yang Z, Zhou X, et al. J Infect. 2020;81:0–2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7290182</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32540459</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clinical Spectrum of SARS-CoV-2 Infection.  [
Oct;
2022 
]. 2022. https://www.covid19treatmentguidelines.nih.gov/overview/clinical-spectrum/ https://www.covid19treatmentguidelines.nih.gov/overview/clinical-spectrum/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elevations of serum cancer biomarkers correlate with severity of COVID-19. Wei X, Su J, Yang K, et al. J Med Virol. 2020;92:2036–2041.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7267262</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32347972</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Association between serum carcinoembryonic antigen and cardiometabolic risks: Implication for cardiometabolic prevention. Chang CH, Weng HH, Lin YC, Lin CN, Huang TJ, Chen MY. Front Endocrinol (Lausanne) 2023;14:1113178.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9995979</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36909325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carcinoembryonic antigen: a potential biomarker to evaluate the severity and prognosis of COVID-19. Chen Q, Kong H, Qi X, et al. Front Med (Lausanne) 2020;7:579543.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7573292</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33123542</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferritin as a marker of severity in COVID-19 patients: a fatal correlation. Dahan S, Segal G, Katz I, et al.  https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/33236582/ Isr Med Assoc J. 2020;22:494–500.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33236582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferritin in the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19): a systematic review and meta-analysis. Cheng L, Li H, Li L, Liu C, Yan S, Chen H, Li Y. J Clin Lab Anal. 2020;34:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7595919</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33078400</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>D-dimer as a biomarker for disease severity and mortality in COVID-19 patients: a case control study. Yao Y, Cao J, Wang Q, et al. J Intensive Care. 2020;8:49.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7348129</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32665858</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prognostic value of a clinical biochemistry-based nomogram for coronavirus disease 2019. Yu J, Nie L, Wu D, et al. Front Med (Lausanne) 2020;7:597791.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7848223</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33537326</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The performance of chest CT in evaluating the clinical severity of COVID-19 pneumonia: identifying critical cases based on CT characteristics. Lyu P, Liu X, Zhang R, Shi L, Gao J. Invest Radiol. 2020;55:412–421.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7173027</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32304402</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elevated carcinoembryonic antigen in patients with COVID-19 pneumonia. Yang C, Wang J, Liu J, Huang S, Xiong B. J Cancer Res Clin Oncol. 2020;146:3385–3388.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7453671</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32857179</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>