<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39435212</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Exploring the Intersection of E-commerce and Healthcare: A Visual Analysis of Research Trends.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e69865</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e69865</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e69865</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.69865</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The role of e-commerce in healthcare is one of the key research areas emerging from the broader digital transformation of health services and consumer interactions. This study presents the bibliometric analysis of literature on e-commerce in healthcare based on publications from 1993 to 2024 in Scopus. In particular, this analysis shows trends in the publication record that have been constantly growing, with prominent increases during the COVID-19 pandemic, now hardwiring the fact that digital technologies are key in promoting global health. The study surveys the thematic evolution of key technologies such as artificial intelligence (AI), which is transforming predictive healthcare analytics; blockchain, which is enhancing security in health data transactions; and telemedicine, which is revolutionizing remote patient care, alongside other emerging technologies that are reshaping global healthcare systems. The research also showcases global collaboration patterns, underlining the international dimensions of scholarly contributions to the area under review. These insights provide a foundation for understanding the current state of e-commerce in healthcare and suggest future directions for research and policy development in this fast-evolving field.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Zacharia et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zacharia</LastName><ForeName>Alan</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Economics, St. Thomas College, Thrissur, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Thomas</LastName><ForeName>Ambili Catherine</ForeName><Initials>AC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Commerce, St. Stephen's College, Uzhavoor, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mathew</LastName><ForeName>Prageesh C</ForeName><Initials>PC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Commerce, Newman College, Thodupuzha, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cleetus</LastName><ForeName>Regina Sibi</ForeName><Initials>RS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Commerce, Mar Ivanios College, Thiruvananthapuram, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>John</LastName><ForeName>Sherin Elizabeth</ForeName><Initials>SE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Commerce, St. George's College, Aruvithura, Kottayam, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Joseph</LastName><ForeName>Jeena</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Computer Applications, Marian College Kuttikkanam (Autonomous), Kuttikkanam, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">bibliometric analysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">biblioshiny</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">e-commerce</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vosviewer</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>29</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>28</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39435212</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11493379</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.69865</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Factors affecting the acceptance of e-commerce in hospitals: a narrative review. Ardalan SA, Mirzaei A. Ann Mil Health Sci Res. 2022;20</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E-healthcare services - actual usage and intention to use among Indian consumers. Aishwarya A, Kavitha T, Nayak S. Int J Innov Technol Explor Eng. 2019;8:2735–2740.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Exploring healthcare/health-product ecommerce satisfaction: a text mining and machine learning application. Chatterjee S, Goyal D, Prakash A, Sharma JP. J Bus Res. 2021;131:815–825.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Interactive development of cross-border e-commerce and new Internet economy in digital health sector. Song C. J Commer Biotechnol. 2022;27</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Digitisation of healthcare products and the democratization continuum of the healthcare system in China: a systematic review. Antwi HA, Paixao TL, Antwi MO. Int J Sci Res Sci Eng Technol. 2021;8:266–283.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prioritizing big data applications in e-commerce considering sustainable development indicators. Fozooni A, Nazari S, Jamalpur A. J Future Sustain. 2024;4:169–178.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The rise of electronic commerce in healthcare: the need to ensure consumer safety. Attjioui H, Cheikh A, Tebaa A, Zerhouni MW, Aliat Z, Mefetah H, Bouatia M. https://ijrps.com/home/article/view/2354 Int J Pharm Sci Res. 2020;11</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>New perspectives in bibliometric indicators: moving from citations to citing authors. Cappelletti-Montano B, Columbu S, Montaldo S, Musio M. J Informetr. 2021;15</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Understanding the structure, characteristics, and future of collective intelligence using local and global bibliometric analyses. Calof J, Søilen KS, Klavans R, Abdulkader B, Moudni IE. Technol Forecast Soc Change. 2022;178</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A scientometric review of emerging trends and new developments in recommendation systems. Kim MC, Chen C. Scientometrics. 2015;104:239–263.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mapping of diseases from clinical medicine research - a visualization study. Chen Y, Dong Y, Zeng Y, et al. Scientometrics. 2020;125:171–185.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The impact of Jürgen Habermas's scientific production: a scientometric review. do Carmo G, Felizardo LF, de Castro Alcântara V, da Silva CA, do Prado JW. Scientometrics. 2023;128:1853–1875.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9803888</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36618818</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Research hotspots, trends and opportunities on the metaverse in health education: a bibliometric analysis. Agac G, Sevim F, Celik O, Bostan S, Erdem R, Yalcin YI. Libr Hi Tech. 2023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Artificial intelligence adoption in the physical sciences, natural sciences, life sciences, social sciences and the arts and humanities: a bibliometric analysis of research publications from 1960-2021. Hajkowicz S, Sanderson C, Karimi S, Bratanova A, Naughtin C. Technol Soc. 2023;74</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Correction to: a bibliometric mapping of shadow education research: achievements, limitations, and the future. Hajar A, Karakus M. Asia Pacific Educ Rev. 2023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19, consumer behavior, technology, and society: a literature review and bibliometric analysis. Cruz-Cárdenas J, Zabelina E, Guadalupe-Lanas J, Palacio-Fierro A, Ramos-Galarza C. Technol Forecast Soc Change. 2021;173</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8418327</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34511647</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>How to conduct a bibliometric analysis: an overview and guidelines. Donthu N, Kumar S, Mukherjee D, Pandey N, Lim WM. J Bus Res. 2021;133:285–296.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quality of higher education: a bibliometric review study. Brika SK, Algamdi A, Chergui K, Musa AA, Zouaghi R. Front Educ. 2021;6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8929398</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35308075</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A bibliometric analysis on job stress using visualizing network. Sidhu AK, Singh H, Virdi SS, Kumar R. https://www.amity.edu/gwalior/jccc/pdf/dec_04.pdf J Content Community Commun. 2020;12:21–29.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bibliometric analysis of publications on the omicron variant from 2020 to 2022 in the Scopus database using R and VOSviewer. Ejaz H, Zeeshan HM, Ahmad F, et al. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9566376</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36231710</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A bibliometric analysis: a tutorial for the bibliometrix package in R using IRT literature. Büyükkıdık S. J Meas Eval Educ Psychol. 2022;13:164–193.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Two decades of M-commerce consumer research: a bibliometric analysis using R biblioshiny. Thangavel P, Chandra B. https://ideas.repec.org/a/gam/jsusta/v15y2023i15p11835-d1208343.html Sustainability. 2023;15</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>RStudio: a platform-independent IDE for R and Sweave. Racine J. https://www.researchgate.net/publication/241769137_RStudio_a_platform-independent_IDE_for_R_and_Sweave J Appl Econom. 2012;27</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Explorative bibliometric study of medical image analysis: unveiling trends and advancements. Thomas B, Joseph J, Jose J. https://sv-journal.org/2023-5/04/ Sci Vis. 2023;15:35–49.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A review study on big data analysis using R Studio. Savita Savita, Verma N. Int J Eng Tech Mgmt Res. 2020;6:129–136.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scientific production and thematic breakthroughs in smart learning environments: a bibliometric analysis. Agbo FJ, Oyelere SS, Suhonen J, Tukiainen M. Smart Learn Environ. 2021;8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Software survey: VOSviewer, a computer program for bibliometric mapping. van Eck NJ, Waltman L. Scientometrics. 2010;84:523–538.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2883932</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20585380</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bibliometric analysis of ecopreneurship using VOSviewer and RStudio Bibliometrix, 1989-2019. Guleria D, Kaur G. Libr Hi Tech. 2021;39:1001–1024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Institution of Sociology Teaching in instrumenting multicultural constructs in schools: bibliometric analysis with VOSviewer and RStudio Biblishiny. Rizaldy M, Adriany V, Nurbayani S. DIA Jurnal Ilmiah Administrasi Publik. 2024;22:322–341.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>VOSviewer and Bibliometrix. Arruda H, Silva ER, Lessa M, Proença D Jr, Bartholo R. J Med Libr Assoc. 2022;110:392–395.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9782747</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36589296</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>VOSviewer. Wong D. Tech Serv Q. 2018;35:219–220.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 impact on e-commerce usage: an empirical evidence from the Malaysian healthcare industry. Shahzad A, Hassan R, Abdullah N, Hussain A, Fareed M. Humanit Soc Sci Rev. 2020;8:599–609.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>