<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39439659</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Comparison of the Efficacy and Safety of Low Molecular Weight Heparins and Fondaparinux in Patients With COVID-19: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e69904</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e69904</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e69904</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.69904</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Individuals diagnosed with COVID-19 are at a higher risk of arterial and venous thrombosis, mostly pulmonary microvascular thrombosis, which may significantly impair treatment and result in morbidity. This is a systematic review and meta-analysis of research papers that aim to evaluate the risk of bleeding and thrombosis among patients treated with low molecular weight heparin or fondaparinux (LMWH/F). Additionally, we measured the overall death events. This study was conducted in compliance with the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) criteria. A search was conducted in the Clinicaltrials.gov, PubMed, Scopus, and Web of Science databases to identify observational cohort studies and randomized-controlled clinical trials (RCTs) that compared LMWH/F in proven COVID-19 patients. A total of 220 people from two studies were included. Patients who were treated with fondaparinux had a lower risk of developing venous thromboembolism (VTE) (odds ratio (OR) 0.39; 95% confidence interval (CI) (0.14, 1.096); p = 0.168); pulmonary embolism (OR 0.169, 95% CI (0.021, 1.356), p = 0.094); and deep vein thrombosis compared to patients who received LMWH therapy. The data show a lower mortality rate in the LMWH groups (OR 1.135, 95% CI (0.463, 2.785), p = 0.781) and a lower frequency of bleeding (OR 1.657, 95% CI (0.456, 5.908), p = 0.436). Both drugs have shown anti-thrombotic properties in COVID-19 patients. Fondaparinux was somewhat more effective in reducing thrombosis episodes. This research demonstrates the safe use of LMWH for VTE prophylaxis in hospitalized COVID-19 patients based on bleeding and mortality outcomes.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Shareef et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shareef</LastName><ForeName>Laith G</ForeName><Initials>LG</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Therapeutics, Al-Rasheed University College, Baghdad, IRQ.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Noori</LastName><ForeName>Mustafa M</ForeName><Initials>MM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pharmacology, Al-Rasheed University College, Baghdad, IRQ.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shareef</LastName><ForeName>Aumnia G</ForeName><Initials>AG</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pharmacology, Saad Al-Witry Neuroscience Hospital, Baghdad, IRQ.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mustafa</LastName><ForeName>Ali H</ForeName><Initials>AH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pharmacology, Medical City, Baghdad, IRQ.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">bleeding</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">covid-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">meta-analysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mortality</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sars-cov-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">venous thromboembolism</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>56</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>55</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39439659</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11494850</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.69904</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 clinical characteristics and outcomes in 60 hospitalized Iraqi patients — case series. Bonyan FA, Shareef LG, Al-waily A, et al.  http://www.discoveryjournals.org/medicalscience/current_issue/v24/n104/A61.pdf Med Sci. 2020;24:2251–2258.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Major coagulation disorders and parameters in COVID-19 patients. Teimury A, Khameneh MT, Khaledi EM. Eur J Med Res. 2022;27:25.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8845229</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35168674</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>D-dimer, fibrinogen, and IL-6 in COVID-19 patients with suspected venous thromboembolism: a narrative review. Eljilany I, Elzouki AN. Vasc Health Risk Manag. 2020;16:455–462.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7672709</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33223833</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19-related laboratory coagulation findings. Devreese KM. Int J Lab Hematol. 2021;43:36–42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8444785</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34288440</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thromboembolic prevention and anticoagulant therapy during the COVID-19 pandemic: updated clinical guidance from the anticoagulation forum. Barnes GD, Burnett A, Allen A, et al. J Thromb Thrombolysis. 2022;54:197–210.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9111941</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35579732</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>American Society of Hematology living guidelines on the use of anticoagulation for thromboprophylaxis in patients with COVID-19: January 2022 update on the use of therapeutic-intensity anticoagulation in acutely ill patients. Cuker A, Tseng EK, Nieuwlaat R, et al. Blood Adv. 2022;6:4915–4923.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9068240</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35503027</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 vaccination hesitancy among Iraqi general population between beliefs and barriers: an observational study. Shareef LG, Fawzi Al-Hussainy A, Majeed Hameed S. F1000Res. 2022;11:334.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9046899</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35529280</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Efficacy and safety of fondaparinux versus unfractionated heparin in patients hospitalised with severe COVID-19 pneumonia and coagulopathy: a randomised, open-label clinical trial. Adrian LH, Hutomo SA, Negari AD. Eur Heart J. 2022;43:0.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Good practice statements for antithrombotic therapy in the management of COVID-19: guidance from the SSC of the ISTH. Spyropoulos AC, Connors JM, Douketis JD, et al. J Thromb Haemost. 2022;20:2226–2236.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9349985</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35906715</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The PRISMA 2020 statement: an updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews. Page MJ, McKenzie JE, Bossuyt PM, et al. BMJ. 2021;372:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8008539</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33781348</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antithrombotic and anti-inflammatory effects of fondaparinux and enoxaparin in hospitalized COVID-19 patients: the FONDENOXAVID study. Cardillo G, Viggiano GV, Russo V, et al. J Blood Med. 2021;12:69–75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7886238</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33603528</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thromboprofilaxys with fondaparinux vs. enoxaparin in hospitalized COVID-19 patients: a multicenter Italian observational study. Russo V, Cardillo G, Viggiano GV, et al. Front Med (Lausanne) 2020;7:569567.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7729125</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33330530</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trends in venous thromboembolism anticoagulation in patients hospitalized with COVID-19. Vaughn VM, Yost M, Abshire C, et al. JAMA Netw Open. 2021;4:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8196344</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34115129</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Characterization of heparin and severe acute respiratory syndrome-related coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) spike glycoprotein binding interactions. Kim SY, Jin W, Sood A, et al. Antiviral Res. 2020;181:104873.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7347485</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32653452</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trends in covid-19 therapeutic modalities: a narrative literature. Shareef LG, Abdulwahab SM. https://www.researchgate.net/publication/341540646_TRENDS_IN_COVID-19_THERAPEUTIC_MODALITIES_A_NARRATIVE_LITERATURE_REVIEW_ARTICLE#fullTextFileContent Eur J Pharm Med Res. 2020;7:757–767.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anticoagulation outcomes in hospitalized Covid-19 patients: a systematic review and meta-analysis of case-control and cohort studies. Kamel AM, Sobhy M, Magdy N, Sabry N, Farid S. Rev Med Virol. 2021;31:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7646049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33022834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The use of therapeutic-dose anticoagulation and its effect on mortality in patients with COVID-19: a systematic review. Wijaya I, Andhika R, Huang I. Clin Appl Thromb Hemost. 2020;26</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7791436</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33079569</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Different anticoagulant regimens, mortality, and bleeding in hospitalized patients with COVID-19: a systematic review and an updated meta-analysis. Parisi R, Costanzo S, Di Castelnuovo A, de Gaetano G, Donati MB, Iacoviello L. Semin Thromb Hemost. 2021;47:372–391.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33851386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>