<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39435699</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1467-7652</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>22</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Plant biotechnology journal</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Plant Biotechnol J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>CuBe: a geminivirus-based copper-regulated expression system suitable for post-harvest activation.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/pbi.14485</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The growing demand for sustainable platforms for biomolecule manufacturing has fuelled the development of plant-based production systems. Agroinfiltration, the current industry standard, offers several advantages but faces limitations for large-scale production due to high operational costs and batch-to-batch variability. Alternatively, here, we describe the CuBe system, a novel bean yellow dwarf virus (BeYDV)-derived conditional replicative expression platform stably transformed in Nicotiana benthamiana and activated by copper sulphate (CuSO<sub>4</sub>), an inexpensive and widely used agricultural input. The CuBe system utilizes a synthetic circuit of four genetic modules integrated into the plant genome: (i) a replicative vector harbouring the gene of interest (GOI) flanked by cis-acting elements for geminiviral replication and novelly arranged to enable transgene transcription exclusively upon formation of the circular replicon, (ii) copper-inducible Rep/RepA proteins essential for replicon formation, (iii) the yeast-derived CUP2-Gal4 copper-responsive transcriptional activator for Rep/RepA expression, and (iv) a copper-inducible Flp recombinase to minimize basal Rep/RepA expression. CuSO<sub>4</sub> application triggers the activation of the system, leading to the formation of extrachromosomal replicons, expression of the GOI, and accumulation of the desired recombinant protein. We demonstrate the functionality of the CuBe system in N. benthamiana plants expressing high levels of eGFP and an anti-SARS-CoV-2 antibody upon copper treatment. Notably, the system is functional in post-harvest applications, a strategy with high potential impact for large-scale biomanufacturing. This work presents the CuBe system as a promising alternative to agroinfiltration for cost-effective and scalable production of recombinant proteins in plants.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Plant Biotechnology Journal published by Society for Experimental Biology and The Association of Applied Biologists and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Garcia-Perez</LastName><ForeName>Elena</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2502-0975</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Instituto de Biología Molecular y Celular de Plantas, CSIC-UPV, Valencia, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vazquez-Vilar</LastName><ForeName>Marta</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7175-7818</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Instituto de Biología Molecular y Celular de Plantas, CSIC-UPV, Valencia, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lozano-Duran</LastName><ForeName>Rosa</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Plant Biochemistry, Centre for Plant Molecular Biology (ZMBP), Eberhard Karls University, Tübingen, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Orzaez</LastName><ForeName>Diego</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1662-5403</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Instituto de Biología Molecular y Celular de Plantas, CSIC-UPV, Valencia, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>PID2022-141438OB-I00</GrantID><Agency>Ministerio de Ciencia e Innovación</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>TED2021-131171B-I00</GrantID><Agency>Ministerio de Ciencia e Innovación</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>German Federal and State Governments</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>ACIF2020</GrantID><Agency>Generalitat Valenciana</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Plant Biotechnol J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101201889</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1467-7644</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Nicotiana benthamiana</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">copper switch</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">geminivirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">inducible expression</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">molecular farming</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">plant synthetic biology</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39435699</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/pbi.14485</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>Ahlquist, P., Schwartz, M., Chen, J., Kushner, D., Hao, L. and Dye, B.T. (2005) Viral and host determinants of RNA virus vector replication and expression. Vaccine 23, 1784–1787.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhattacharjee, B. and Hallan, V. (2022) Geminivirus‐derived vectors as tools for functional genomics. Front. Microbiol. 13, 799345.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buchman, C., Skroch, P., Welch, J., Fogel, S. and Karin, M. (1989) The CUP2 gene product, regulator of yeast metallothionein expression, is a copper‐activated DNA‐binding protein. Mol. Cell. Biol. 9, 4091–4095.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buyel, J.F. and Fischer, R. (2012) Predictive models for transient protein expression in tobacco (Nicotiana tabacum L.) can optimize process time, yield, and downstream costs. Biotechnol. Bioeng. 109, 2575–2588.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caddick, M.X., Greenland, A.J., Krause, K.‐P., Qu, N., Riddell, K.V., Salter, M.G., Schuch, W. et al. (1998) An ethanol inducible gene switch for plants used to manipulate carbon metabolism. Nat. Biotechnol. 16, 177–180.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castro, C., Arnold, J.J. and Cameron, C.E. (2005) Incorporation fidelity of the viral RNA‐dependent RNA polymerase: a kinetic, thermodynamic and structural perspective. Virus Res. 107, 141–149.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, Q., He, J., Phoolcharoen, W. and Mason, H.S. (2011) Geminiviral vectors based on bean yellow dwarf virus for production of vaccine antigens and monoclonal antibodies in plants. Hum. Vaccin. 7, 331–338.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chung, Y.H., Church, D., Koellhoffer, E.C., Osota, E., Shukla, S., Rybicki, E.P., Pokorski, J.K. et al. (2022) Integrating plant molecular farming and materials research for next‐generation vaccines. Nature Reviews Materials 7, 372–388.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diamos, A.G. and Mason, H.S. (2019) Modifying the replication of geminiviral vectors reduces cell death and enhances expression of biopharmaceutical proteins in Nicotiana benthamiana leaves. Front. Plant Sci. 9, 1974.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diego‐Martin, B., González, B., Vazquez‐Vilar, M., Selma, S., Mateos‐Fernández, R., Gianoglio, S., Fernández‐Del‐Carmen, A. et al. (2020) Pilot production of SARS‐CoV‐2 related proteins in plants: a proof of concept for rapid repurposing of indoor farms into biomanufacturing facilities. Front. Plant Sci. 11, 612781.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dugdale, B., Mortimer, C.L., Kato, M., James, T.A., Harding, R.M. and Dale, J.L. (2013) In plant activation: an inducible, hyperexpression platform for recombinant protein production in plants. Plant Cell 25, 2429–2443.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dusek, J., Plchova, H., Cerovska, N., Poborilova, Z., Navratil, O., Kratochvilova, K., Gunter, C. et al. (2020) Extended set of GoldenBraid compatible vectors for fast assembly of multigenic constructs and their use to create geminiviral expression vectors. Front. Plant Sci. 11, 522059.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eidenberger, L., Kogelmann, B. and Steinkellner, H. (2023) Plant‐based biopharmaceutical engineering. Nat. Rev. Bioeng. 1, 426–439.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Engler, C., Youles, M., Gruetzner, R., Ehnert, T.‐M., Werner, S., Jones, J.D.G., Patron, N.J. et al. (2014) A golden gate modular cloning toolbox for plants. ACS Synth. Biol. 3, 843.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fischer, R., Schillberg, S., Hellwig, S., Twyman, R.M. and Drossard, J. (2012) GMP issues for recombinant plant‐derived pharmaceutical proteins. Biotechnol. Adv. 30, 434–439.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Folimonova, S.Y., Robertson, C.J., Shilts, T., Folimonov, A.S., Hilf, M.E., Garnsey, S.M. and Dawson, W.O. (2010) Infection with strains of Citrus tristeza virus does not exclude superinfection by other strains of the virus. J. Virol. 84, 1314–1325.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garcia‐Perez, E., Diego‐Martin, B., Quijano‐Rubio, A., Moreno‐Giménez, E., Selma, S., Orzaez, D. and Vazquez‐Vilar, M. (2022) A copper switch for inducing CRISPR/Cas9‐based transcriptional activation tightly regulates gene expression in Nicotiana benthamiana. BMC Biotechnol. 22, 12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gleba, Y., Klimyuk, V. and Marillonnet, S. (2007) Viral vectors for the expression of proteins in plants. Curr. Opin. Biotechnol. 18, 134–141.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gleba, Y.Y., Tusé, D. and Giritch, A. (2013) Plant viral vectors for delivery by agrobacterium. In Plant Viral Vectors, Vol. 375 (Palmer, K. and Gleba, Y., eds), pp. 155–192. Berlin Heidelberg: Springer Berlin Heidelberg.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guiziou, S., Maranas, C.J., Chu, J.C. and Nemhauser, J.L. (2023) An integrase toolbox to record gene‐expression during plant development. Nat. Commun. 14, 1844.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Julve, J.M., Gandía, A., Fernández‐del‐Carmen, A., Sarrion‐Perdigones, A., Castelijns, B., Granell, A. and Orzaez, D. (2013) A coat‐independent superinfection exclusion rapidly imposed in Nicotiana benthamiana cells by tobacco mosaic virus is not prevented by depletion of the movement protein. Plant Mol. Biol. 81, 553–564.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Küpper, H. and Andresen, E. (2016) Mechanisms of metal toxicity in plants. Metallomics 8, 269–285.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lamichhane, J.R., Osdaghi, E., Behlau, F., Köhl, J., Jones, J.B. and Aubertot, J.‐N. (2018) Thirteen decades of antimicrobial copper compounds applied in agriculture. A review. Agron. Sustain. Dev. 38, 28.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lindbo, J.A. (2007) TRBO: a high‐efficiency tobacco mosaic virus RNA‐based overexpression vector. Plant Physiol. 145, 1232–1240.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, L., Davies, J.W. and Stanley, J. (1998) Mutational analysis of bean yellow dwarf virus, a geminivirus of the genus Mastrevirus that is adapted to dicotyledonous plants. J. Gen. Virol. 79, 2265–2274.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, R., Long, Q., Zou, X., Wang, Y. and Pei, Y. (2021) DNA methylation occurring in Cre‐expressing cells inhibits loxP recombination and silences loxP‐sandwiched genes. New Phytol. 231, 210–224.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lloyd, J.P.B., Ly, F., Gong, P., Pflueger, J., Swain, T., Pflueger, C., Fourie, E. et al. (2022) Synthetic memory circuits for stable cell reprogramming in plants. Nat. Biotechnol. 40, 1862–1872.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma, Y., Wang, X.R., Li, T., Zhang, J., Gao, J. and Sun, Z.Y. (2021) Hydrogen and ethanol: production, storage, and transportation. Int. J. Hydrog. Energy 46, 27330–27348.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marillonnet, S., Thoeringer, C., Kandzia, R., Klimyuk, V. and Gleba, Y. (2005) Systemic Agrobacterium tumefaciens–mediated transfection of viral replicons for efficient transient expression in plants. Nat. Biotechnol. 23, 718–723.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mason, M., Sweeney, B., Cain, K., Stephens, P. and Sharfstein, S.T. (2012) Identifying bottlenecks in transient and stable production of recombinant monoclonal‐antibody sequence variants in Chinese hamster ovary cells. Biotechnol. Prog. 28, 846–855.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mor, T.S., Moon, Y., Palmer, K.E. and Mason, H.S. (2003) Geminivirus vectors for high‐level expression of foreign proteins in plant cells. Biotechnol. Bioeng. 81, 430–437.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mortimer, C.L., Dugdale, B. and Dale, J.L. (2015) Updates in inducible transgene expression using viral vectors: from transient to stable expression. Curr. Opin. Biotechnol. 32, 85–92.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pasin, F., Bedoya, L.C., Bernabé‐Orts, J.M., Gallo, A., Simón‐Mateo, C., Orzaez, D. and García, J.A. (2017) Multiple T‐DNA delivery to plants using novel mini binary vectors with compatible replication origins. ACS Synth. Biol. 6, 1962–1968.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pérez‐González, A. and Caro, E. (2019) Benefits of using genomic insulators flanking transgenes to increase expression and avoid positional effects. Sci. Rep. 9, 8474.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rattanapisit, K., Bulaon, C.J.I., Strasser, R., Sun, H. and Phoolcharoen, W. (2023) In vitro and in vivo studies of plant‐produced Atezolizumab as a potential immunotherapeutic antibody. Sci. Rep. 13, 14146.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Regnard, G.L., Halley‐Stott, R.P., Tanzer, F.L., Hitzeroth, I.I. and Rybicki, E.P. (2010) High level protein expression in plants through the use of a novel autonomously replicating geminivirus shuttle vector. Plant Biotechnol. J. 8, 38–46.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sainsbury, F. and Lomonossoff, G.P. (2008) Extremely high‐level and rapid transient protein production in plants without the use of viral replication. Plant Physiol. 148, 1212–1218.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarrion‐Perdigones, A., Vazquez‐Vilar, M., Palací, J., Castelijns, B., Forment, J., Ziarsolo, P., Blanca, J. et al. (2013) GoldenBraid 2.0: a comprehensive DNA assembly framework for plant synthetic biology. Plant Physiol. 162, 1618–1631.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schillberg, S., Raven, N., Spiegel, H., Rasche, S. and Buntru, M. (2019) Critical analysis of the commercial potential of plants for the production of recombinant proteins. Front. Plant Sci. 10, 720. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2019.00720</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shanmugaraj, B., I Bulaon, C.J. and Phoolcharoen, W. (2020) Plant molecular farming: a viable platform for recombinant biopharmaceutical production. Plan. Theory 9, 842.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tamm, L., Thuerig, B., Apostolov, S., Blogg, H., Borgo, E., Corneo, P.E., Fittje, S. et al. (2022) Use of copper‐based fungicides in organic agriculture in twelve European countries. Agronomy 12, 673.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsang, T., Davis, C.I. and Brady, D.C. (2021) Copper biology. Curr. Biol. 31, R421–R427.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vazquez‐Vilar, M., Quijano‐Rubio, A., Fernandez‐Del‐Carmen, A., Sarrion‐Perdigones, A., Ochoa‐Fernandez, R., Ziarsolo, P., Blanca, J. et al. (2017) GB3.0: a platform for plant bio‐design that connects functional DNA elements with associated biological data. Nucleic Acids Res. 45, 2196–2209.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wani, K.I. and Aftab, T. (2022) Limitations, biosafety, ethics, regulatory issues in molecular farming in plants. In Plant Molecular Farming: Applications and New Directions(Wani, K.I. and Aftab, T., eds), pp. 61–74. Cham, Switzerland: Springer International Publishing.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Werner, S., Breus, O., Symonenko, Y., Marillonnet, S. and Gleba, Y. (2011) High‐level recombinant protein expression in transgenic plants by using a double‐inducible viral vector. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 108, 14061–14066.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, X. and Mason, H. (2006) Bean Yellow Dwarf Virus replicons for high‐level transgene expression in transgenic plants and cell cultures. Biotechnol. Bioeng. 93, 271–279.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>