<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39436285</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1538-9774</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>22</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Computers, informatics, nursing : CIN</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Comput Inform Nurs</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Best Practices in Supporting Inpatient Communication With Technology During Visitor Restrictions: An Integrative Review.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/CIN.0000000000001200</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Since the onset of the COVID-19 pandemic, healthcare workers around the world have experimented with technologies to facilitate communication and care for patients and their care partners.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Our team reviewed the literature to examine best practices in utilizing technology to support communication between nurses, patients, and care partners while visitation is limited. We searched four major databases for recent articles on this topic, conducted a systematic screening and review of 1902 articles, and used the Johns Hopkins Nursing Evidence-Based Practice for Nurses and Healthcare Professionals Model &amp; Guidelines to appraise and translate the results of 23 relevant articles.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Our evaluation yielded three main findings from the current literature: (1) Virtual contact by any technological means, especially video visitation, improves satisfaction, reduces anxiety, and is well-received by the target populations. (2) Structured video rounding provides effective communication among healthcare workers, patients, and offsite care partners. (3) Institutional preparation, such as a standardized checklist and dedicating staff to roles focused on facilitating communication, can help healthcare workers create environments conducive to therapeutic virtual communication.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DISCUSSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">In situations that require healthcare facilities to limit visitation between patients and their care partners, the benefits of virtual visitation are evident. There is variance in the types of technologies used to facilitate virtual visits, but across all of them, there are consistent themes demonstrating the benefits of virtual visits and virtual rounding. Healthcare institutions can prepare for future limited-visitation scenarios by reviewing the current evidence and integrating virtual visitation into modern healthcare delivery.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Brown</LastName><ForeName>Stephanie</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5613-9042</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Author Affiliations: The Johns Hopkins Hospital (Ms Brown, Ms Guillergan, Mr Beedle, Mr Gnie, and Ms Wormack) and Department of Nursing, Office of Nursing Professional Practice, The Johns Hopkins Health System, Baltimore, MD (Ms Rosenblum).</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Guillergan</LastName><ForeName>Jamie</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Beedle</LastName><ForeName>Eric</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gnie</LastName><ForeName>Andre</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wilmer</LastName><ForeName>Sterling</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wormack</LastName><ForeName>Kristy</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rosenblum</LastName><ForeName>Nadine</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Comput Inform Nurs</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101141667</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1538-2931</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39436285</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/CIN.0000000000001200</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00024665-990000000-00239</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Maintaining essential health services: operational guidance for the COVID-19 context: interim guidance. Published June 1, 2020. https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/332240.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xyrichis A, Pattison N, Ramsay P, et al. Virtual visiting in intensive care during the COVID-19 pandemic: a qualitative descriptive study with ICU clinicians and non-ICU family team liaison members. BMJ Open. 2022;12(4): e055679. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2021-055679.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2021-055679</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dang D, Dearholt SL, Bissett K, Ascenzi J, Whalen M. Johns Hopkins Evidence-Based Practice for Nurses and Healthcare Professionals. 4th ed. Indianapolis, IN: Sigma Theta Tau International; 2021:295–323.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Page MJ, McKenzie JE, Bossuyt PM, et al. The PRISMA 2020 statement: an updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews. The British Medical Journal. 2021;372: n71. doi:10.1136/bmj.n71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.n71</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shariati E, Dadgari A, Talebi SS, Mahmoodi Shan GR, Ebrahimi H. The effect of the Web-based communication between a nurse and a family member on the perceived stress of the family member of patients with suspected or confirmed COVID-19: a parallel randomized clinical trial. Clinical Nursing Research. 2021;30(7): 1098–1106. doi:10.1177/10547738211017688.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/10547738211017688</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petersson NB, Jørgensen AL, Danbjørg DB, Dieperink KB. Video-consulted rounds with caregivers: the experience of patients with cancer. European Journal of Oncology Nursing. 2020;46: 101763. doi:10.1016/j.ejon.2020.101763.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ejon.2020.101763</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Makwana K, Jain S, Ghugare B, Niraj Rathod NR. Effect of standardised virtual communication on anxiety in relatives of patients with COVID-19 infection in Central Gujarat: a prospective interventional study. Journal of Clinical and Diagnostic Research. 2022;16(6): UC43–UC47. doi:10.7860/JCDR/2022/56802.16499.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7860/JCDR/2022/56802.16499</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vestergaard LV, Østervang C, Danbjørg DB, Dieperink KB. Video-based patient rounds for caregivers of patients with cancer. Oncology Nursing Forum. 2019;46(4): 485–492. doi:10.1188/19.ONF.485-492.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1188/19.ONF.485-492</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haakma T, Tieben R, Sleven B, Buise M, van Mol M. Experiences of nurses with an innovative digital diary intervention in the intensive care unit: a qualitative exploration. Intensive &amp; Critical Care Nursing. 2022;70: 103197. doi:10.1016/j.iccn.2022.103197.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.iccn.2022.103197</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nelson SE, Steuernagle J, Rotello L, Nyquist P, Suarez JI, Ziai W. COVID-19 and telehealth in the intensive care unit setting: a survey. BMC Health Services Research. 2022;22(1): 1–797. doi:10.1186/s12913-022-08197-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12913-022-08197-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Henry J, Leprince T, Garcia Robles S, et al. Qualitative, exploratory, and multidimensional study of telepresence robots for overcoming social isolation of children and adolescents hospitalized in onco-hematology. Journal of Adolescent and Young Adult Oncology. 2020;9(1): 90–95. doi:10.1089/jayao.2019.0059.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/jayao.2019.0059</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Ee SK, McKelvey H, Williams T, et al. Telemedicine intensive care unit (tele-ICU) implementation during COVID-19: a scoping review. Cureus. 2022;14(5): e25133. doi:10.7759/cureus.25133.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.25133</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rose L, Yu L, Casey J, et al. Communication and virtual visiting for families of patients in intensive care during the COVID-19 pandemic: a UK national survey. Annals of the American Thoracic Society. 2021;18(10): 1685–1692. doi:10.1513/AnnalsATS.202012-1500OC.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1513/AnnalsATS.202012-1500OC</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Solt SA, Stolfi D, Ritter VS, Kihlstrom M. An apple iPad a day brings the doctor to you: virtual family-centered rounds in a pediatric intensive care unit. Journal of Pediatric Intensive Care. 2022. doi:10.1055/s-0042-1742673.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1055/s-0042-1742673</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Donnelly S, McDonald F, Goodyer C. Whānau experiences of patients' deaths in Wellington hospital during 2020 COVID-19 pandemic levels 3 &amp; 4. New Zealand Medical Journal. 2022;135(1552): 16–26. https://journal.nzma.org.nz/journal-articles/whanau-experience-of-patients-deaths-in-wellington-hospital-during-2020-COVID-19-pandemic-levels-3-4-open-access.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mignault A, Tchouaket Nguemeleu É, Robins S, Maillet É, Matetsa E, Dupuis S. Automated intraoperative short messaging service updates: quality improvement initiative to relieve caregivers' worries. JMIR Perioperative Medicine. 2022;5(1): e36208. doi:10.2196/36208.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/36208</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sumikawa Y, Yamamoto-Mitani N. Transitional care during COVID-19 pandemic in Japan: calls for new strategies to integrate traditional approaches with information and communication technologies. BioScience Trends. 2021;15(1): 55–57. doi:10.5582/bst.2021.01056.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5582/bst.2021.01056</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bavare AC, Goldman JR, Musick MA, et al. Virtual communication embedded bedside ICU rounds: a hybrid rounds practice adapted to the coronavirus pandemic. Pediatric Critical Care Medicine. 2021;22(8): e427–e436. doi:10.1097/PCC.0000000000002704.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/PCC.0000000000002704</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoo J, Soh JY, Lee WH, Chang DK, Lee SU, Cha WC. Experience of emergency department patients with using the talking pole device: prospective interventional descriptive study. JMIR mHealth and uHealth. 2018;6(11): e191. doi:10.2196/mhealth.9676.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/mhealth.9676</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bettini EA. COVID-19 pandemic restrictions and the use of technology for pediatric palliative care in the acute care setting. Journal of Hospice and Palliative Nursing. 2020;22(6): 432–434. doi:10.1097/NJH.0000000000000694.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/NJH.0000000000000694</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lociciro A, Guillon A, Bodet-Contentin L. A telepresence robot in the room of a COVID-19 patient can provide virtual family presence. Canadian Journal of Anesthesia. 2021;68(11): 1705–1706. doi:10.1007/s12630-021-02039-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12630-021-02039-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doucette E, Sanzone L, Albahouth A, De Luca W, Santella G, Wang K. The role of technology in enhancing a family-centred approach to care: navigating nurse-family communication in the ICU. The Canadian Journal of Critical Care Nursing. 2019;30(3): 29–34. https://cjccn.ca/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/30-3-CJCCNFall2019.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kebapcı A, Türkmen E. The effect of structured virtual patient visits (sVPVs) on COVID-19 patients and relatives' anxiety levels in intensive care unit. Journal of Clinical Nursing. 2022;31(19–20): 2900–2909. doi:10.1111/jocn.16117.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jocn.16117</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krewulak KD, Jaworska N, Spence KL, et al. Impact of restricted visitation policies during the first wave of the COVID-19 pandemic on communication between critically ill patients, families, and clinicians: a qualitative interview study. Annals of the American Thoracic Society. 2022;19(7): 1169–1176. doi:10.1513/AnnalsATS.202107-877OC.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1513/AnnalsATS.202107-877OC</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mistraletti G, Gristina G, Mascarin S, et al. How to communicate with families living in complete isolation. BMJ Supportive &amp; Palliative Care. 2020;bmjspcare-002633. doi:10.1136/bmjspcare-2020-002633.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjspcare-2020-002633</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Otte HR, Østergaard D, Meyhoff CS, Clausen NE, Bendixen G, Linderoth G. Introducing video calls in an intensive care unit during the COVID-19 lockdown: a qualitative study. Danish Medical Journal. 2022;69(6): A09210717. https://ugeskriftet.dk/dmj/introducing-video-calls-intensive-care-unit-during-COVID-19-lockdown-qualitative-study.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>