<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39439579</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1179-1594</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>17</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Risk management and healthcare policy</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Risk Manag Healthc Policy</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Dynamic Insights: Unraveling Public Demand Evolution in Health Emergencies Through Integrated Language Models and Spatial-Temporal Analysis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>2443</StartPage><EndPage>2455</EndPage><MedlinePgn>2443-2455</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.2147/RMHP.S472247</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND AND PURPOSE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">In public health emergencies, rapid perception and analysis of public demands are essential prerequisites for effective crisis communication. Public demands serve as the most instinctive response to the current state of a public health crisis. Therefore, the government must promptly grasp and leverage public demands information to enhance the effectiveness and efficiency of health emergency management, that is planned to better deal with the outbreak and meet the medical demands of the public.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This study employs dynamic topic mining and knowledge graph construction to analyze public demands, presenting a spatial-temporal evolution analysis method for emergencies based on EBU models. EBU models are three large language models, including ERNIE, BERTopic, and UIE.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The data analysis of Shanghai's city closure and control during the COVID-19 epidemic has verified that this method can simplify the labeling and training process, and can use massive social media data to quickly, comprehensively, and accurately analyze public demands from both time and space dimensions. From the visual analysis, geographic information on public demands can be quickly obtained and areas with serious problems can be located. The classification of geographical information can help guide the formulation and implementation of government policies at different levels, and provide a basis for health emergency material dispatch.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This study extends the scope and depth of research on health emergency management, enriching subject categories and research methods in the context of public health emergencies. The use of social media data underscores its potential as a valuable tool for analyzing public demands. The method can provide rapid decision supports for decision-making for public services such as government departments, centers for disease control, medical emergency centers and transport authorities.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Zhang et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Yuan</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Management, Capital Normal University, Beijing, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fu</LastName><ForeName>Lin</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0007-1763-1027</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Management, China Women's University, Beijing, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Guo</LastName><ForeName>Xingyu</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Management, Capital Normal University, Beijing, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Mengkun</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Management, Capital Normal University, Beijing, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Risk Manag Healthc Policy</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101566264</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1179-1594</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">dynamic topic mining</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">health emergency management</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">public demands</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">public health emergencies</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">spatial-temporal evolution</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>56</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>55</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>16</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39439579</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11495202</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/RMHP.S472247</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">472247</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Al-Wathinani AM, AlHokair AA, Almeshari AZ, et al. Ethical Awareness and Practices Among Emergency Department Personnel in Riyadh’s Tertiary Hospitals: a Cross-Sectional Analysis. Risk Manag Healthc Poli. 2024;17:677–688. doi:10.2147/RMHP.S458598</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/RMHP.S458598</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10967605</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38544529</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lyu S, Qian C, McIntyre A, et al. One pandemic, two solutions: comparing the US-China response and health priorities to COVID-19 from the perspective of “Two Types of Control”[C]//Healthcare. MDPI. 2023;11(13):1848.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10341116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37444682</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jamali M, Nejat A, Ghosh S, Jin F, Cao G. Social media data and post-disaster recovery. Int J Inform Manage. 2019;44:25–37. doi:10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2018.09.005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2018.09.005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ru D, Wen H, Zhang Y. A Pre-Generation of Emergency Reference Plan Model of Public Health Emergencies with Case-Based Reasoning. Risk Manag Healthc Poli. 2022;15:2371–2388. doi:10.2147/RMHP.S385967</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/RMHP.S385967</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9762414</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36544507</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiwei W, Nan’axue W. Data Intelligence-Driven Emergency Information Management of Major Emergencies: new Opportunities, New Challenges and New Trends. Library Informat Ser. 2022;66(16):4–12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jie T, Guangwei H, Ting W. Topic Identification and Evolution Path Analysis of Social Appeal Based on Dynamic Semantic Dependency Network. Inform Document Serv. 2022;43(3):20–33.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H LC, Wang D, Lyu S, et al. A digital transformation-enabled framework and strategies for public health risk response and governance: china’s experience. Ind Manage Data Syst. 2023;123(1):133–154. doi:10.1108/IMDS-01-2022-0008</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1108/IMDS-01-2022-0008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malawani AD, Nurmandi A, Purnomo EP, Rahman T. Social media in aid of post disaster management. Transform Govern People Process Policy. 2020;14(2):237–260. doi:10.1108/TG-09-2019-0088</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1108/TG-09-2019-0088</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Z, Nguyen LH, Stuve J, Cao G, Jin F Harvey flooding rescue in social media. In 2017 IEEE International Conference on Big Data (Big Data), IEEE. 2017, 2177–2185.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lai CH, Chib A, Ling R. Digital disparities and vulnerability: mobile phone use, information behaviour, and disaster preparedness in Southeast Asia. Disasters. 2018;42(4):734–760. doi:10.1111/disa.12279</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/disa.12279</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29578613</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qu Y, Huang C, Zhang P, Zhang J Microblogging after a major disaster in China: a case study of the 2010 Yushu earthquake. In Proceedings of the ACM 2011 conference on Computer supported cooperative work. 2011;25–34.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sato S Analysis of tweets hashtagged “# rescue” in the 2017 north Kyushu heavy rain disaster in Japan. In 2018 5th International Conference on Information and Communication Technologies for Disaster Management (ICT-DM). IEEE. 2018. 1–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ragini JR, Anand PR, Bhaskar V. Big data analytics for disaster response and recovery through sentiment analysis. Int J Inform Manage. 2018;42:13–24. doi:10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2018.05.004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2018.05.004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sakaki T, Okazaki M, Matsuo Y. Earthquake shakes twitter users: real-time event detection by social sensors. In Proceedings of the 19th international conference on World wide web. 2010. 851–860).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abd-Alrazaq A, Alhuwail D, Househ M, et al. Top concerns of tweeters during the COVID-19 pandemic: infoveillance study. J Med Int RES. 2020;22(4):e19016. doi:10.2196/19016</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/19016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7175788</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32287039</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahman S, Di L, Esraz-Ul-Zannat M The role of big data in disaster management. In International Conference on Disaster Risk Mitigation. 2017. 1–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blei DM, Ng AY, Jordan MI. Latent Dirichlet allocation. J Mach Learn Res. 2003;2003:993–1022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y, Zhao Q, Lv H, Yu Y A Study of Emergency Web Rumors in Weibo Based on LDA. In 2019 International Conference on Computer Network, Electronic and Automation (ICCNEA). IEEE. 2019. 240–244).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wahid JA, Shi L, Gao Y, et al. Topic2Labels: a framework to annotate and classify the social media data through LDA topics and deep learning models for crisis response. Expert Syst Appl. 2022;195(116562):116562. doi:10.1016/j.eswa.2022.116562</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eswa.2022.116562</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu W, Li J, He Z, et al. Tracking spatio-temporal variation of geo-tagged topics with social media in China: a case study of 2016 hefei rainstorm. Int J Disaster Risk Reduct. 2020;50(101737):101737. doi:10.1016/j.ijdrr.2020.101737</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijdrr.2020.101737</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao J, Xu X, Yin X, Pan B. A risky large group emergency decision-making method based on topic sentiment analysis. Expert Syst Appl. 2022;195:116527. doi:10.1016/j.eswa.2022.116527</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eswa.2022.116527</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grootendorst M. BERTopic: neural topic modeling with a class-based TF-IDF procedure. 2022: arXiv preprint arXiv:2203.05794.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>da Rosa Jr JM, Linhares RS, Ferreira CHG, et al. Uncovering Discussion Groups on claims of Election Fraud from Twitter[C]//International Conference on Social Informatics. Cham: Springer International Publishing; 2022:320–336.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mazzei D, Ramjattan R. Machine Learning for Industry 4.0: a Systematic Review Using Deep Learning-Based Topic Modelling. Sensors. 2022;22(22):8641. doi:10.3390/s22228641</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/s22228641</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9697770</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36433236</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bu W, Shu H, Kang F, Hu Q, Zhao Y. Software Subclassification Based on BERTopic-BERT-BiLSTM Model. Electronics. 2023;12(18):3798. doi:10.3390/electronics12183798</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/electronics12183798</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>An Y, Oh H, Lee J. Marketing insights from reviews using topic modeling with BERTopic and deep clustering network. Appl Sci. 2023;13(16):9443. doi:10.3390/app13169443</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/app13169443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>SUN K, Xudong LUO, Y.l M. Survey of Applications of Pretrained Language Models. Computer Sci. 2023;50(1):176–184.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Information Office of the State Council. White Paper on China’s Actions to Combat the COVID-19 Epidemic [EB/OL]. Available from:
http://www.customs.gov.cn/urumqi_customs/cthyqfk/4088311/index.html. Accessed July
6, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun Y, Wang S, Feng S, et al. (2021). Ernie 3.0: large-scale knowledge enhanced pre-training for language understanding and generation. arXiv preprint arXiv:2107.02137.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Open data from Shanghai Municipal Health Commission, Available from:
https://wsjkw.sh.gov.cn/yqxx/. Accessed October
7, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng WU, Zhang M, Jinlin S. Topic Mining and Hierarchical Diffusion Characteristics Analysis of COVID-19 Policy Based on Spatio-Temporal Big Data Evolution.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venturini L, Di Corso E Analyzing spatial data from twitter during a disaster. In 2017 IEEE International Conference on Big Data (Big Data). IEEE. 2017. 3779–3783.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hobolt SB, Klemmemsen R. Responsive government? Public opinion and government policy preferences in Britain and Denmark. Polit Stud. 2005;53(2):379–402. doi:10.1111/j.1467-9248.2005.00534.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1467-9248.2005.00534.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wlezien C. The public as thermostat: dynamics of preferences for spending. Am J Political Sci. 1995;39(4):981–1000. doi:10.2307/2111666</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2307/2111666</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ZHANG N, ZHENG X. ZHAO Qianxiang.Government Responsiveness: an All-response’Pattern of Daily Governance——An Empirical Study of Local Government Hotline Appeals Using Latent Dirichlet Allocation(LDA). Chin Public Admin. 2023;2023(03):68–78. doi:10.19735/j.issn.1006-0863.2023.03.08</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.19735/j.issn.1006-0863.2023.03.08</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>