<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39432716</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2561-6722</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>7</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>21</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>JMIR pediatrics and parenting</Title><ISOAbbreviation>JMIR Pediatr Parent</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Social Media Exposure and Other Correlates of Increased e-Cigarette Use Among Adolescents During Remote Schooling: Cross-Sectional Study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e49779</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e49779</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e49779</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.2196/49779</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Little is known about the role of exposure to e-cigarette-related digital content, behavioral and mental health factors, and social environment on the change in adolescent e-cigarette use during COVID-19 shelter-in-place orders and remote schooling.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The aim of the study was to examine changes in adolescent e-cigarette use during shelter-in-place and remote schooling in association with exposure to e-cigarette-related digital content and other correlates: stronger e-cigarette dependence, feeling lonely, inability to socialize, e-cigarette use to cope with shelter-in-place, and the number of family members aware of participants' e-cigarette use.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A cross-sectional survey conducted between August 2020 and March 2021 included 85 California adolescents (mean age 16.7, SD 1.2 years; 39/85, 46% identified as female and 37/85, 44% as Hispanic) who reported e-cigarette use in the past 30 days. Multivariable penalized logistic regressions determined associations adjusted for age, race and ethnicity, and mother's education. The outcome of increased e-cigarette use was defined as more frequent use of e-cigarettes of the same or stronger nicotine or tetrahydrocannabinol concentration.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Almost all respondents (83/85, 98%) reported using social media more since shelter-in-place, and 74% (63/85) reported seeing e-cigarette digital content. More than half (46/85, 54%) reported increased e-cigarette use during shelter-in-place. Most individuals who increased use were exposed to e-cigarette digital content (38/46, 83%) compared to those who did not increase e-cigarette use (25/39, 64%), but the association was nonsignificant after adjusting for demographics (adjusted odds ratio [AOR] 2.34, 95% CI 0.71-8.46). Respondents who felt lonely (AOR 3.33, 95% CI 1.27-9.42), used e-cigarettes to cope with shelter-in-place (AOR 4.06, 95% CI 1.39-13.41), or had ≥2 family members aware of participants' e-cigarette use (AOR 6.42, 95% CI 1.29-39.49) were more likely to report increased e-cigarette use.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Almost all participants reported using social media more during shelter-in-place, with many respondents reporting increased e-cigarette use, and significant associations with loneliness and use to cope with shelter-in-place. Future interventions should consider leveraging digital platforms for e-cigarette use prevention and cessation and address the mental health consequences of the COVID-19 pandemic.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© Vira Pravosud, Pamela M Ling, Bonnie Halpern-Felsher, Valerie Gribben. Originally published in JMIR Pediatrics and Parenting (https://pediatrics.jmir.org).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pravosud</LastName><ForeName>Vira</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5762-6632</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Tobacco Control Research and Education, University of California San Francisco, San Francisco, CA, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Data to Discovery and Delivery Innovation, San Francisco VA Health Care System, San Francisco, CA, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Northern California Institute for Research and Education, San Francisco, CA, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ling</LastName><ForeName>Pamela M</ForeName><Initials>PM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6166-9347</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Tobacco Control Research and Education, University of California San Francisco, San Francisco, CA, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Medicine, Department of Medicine, Division of General Internal Medicine, University of California San Francisco, San Francisco, CA, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Halpern-Felsher</LastName><ForeName>Bonnie</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9276-1322</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>REACH Lab, Division of Adolescent Medicine, Department of Pediatrics, Stanford University, Palo Alto, CA, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gribben</LastName><ForeName>Valerie</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0006-3557</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, University of California San Francisco, San Francisco, CA, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Canada</Country><MedlineTA>JMIR Pediatr Parent</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101727244</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2561-6722</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19 shelter-in-place orders</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">adolescents</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">anxiety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">depression</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">e-cigarette implications</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">e-cigarette use</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mental health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">remote schooling</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">smoking</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">social media use</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vape</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper. BH-F is a paid expert scientist in some litigation against the e-cigarette industry and an unpaid scientific advisor and expert regarding some tobacco-related policies. No other authors have any conflicts to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39432716</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/49779</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">v7i1e49779</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11515927</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Cooper M, Park-Lee E, Ren C, Cornelius M, Jamal A, Cullen KA. Notes from the field: e-cigarette use among middle and high school students—United States, 2022. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2022 Oct 7;71(40):1283–1285. doi: 10.15585/mmwr.mm7140a3. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7140a3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9541029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36201370</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gentzke AS, Wang TW, Cornelius M, et al. Tobacco product use and associated factors among middle and high school students—National Youth Tobacco Survey, United States, 2021. MMWR Surveill Summ. 2022 Mar 11;71(5):1–29. doi: 10.15585/mmwr.ss7105a1. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.ss7105a1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8923300</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35271557</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamberger ES, Halpern-Felsher B. Vaping in adolescents: epidemiology and respiratory harm. Curr Opin Pediatr. 2020 Jun;32(3):378–383. doi: 10.1097/MOP.0000000000000896. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MOP.0000000000000896</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7285995</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32332328</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>England LJ, Bunnell RE, Pechacek TF, Tong VT, McAfee TA. Nicotine and the developing human: a neglected element in the electronic cigarette debate. Am J Prev Med. 2015 Aug;49(2):286–293. doi: 10.1016/j.amepre.2015.01.015. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.amepre.2015.01.015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4594223</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25794473</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith RF, McDonald CG, Bergstrom HC, Ehlinger DG, Brielmaier JM. Adolescent nicotine induces persisting changes in development of neural connectivity. Neurosci Biobehav Rev. 2015 Aug;55:432–443. doi: 10.1016/j.neubiorev.2015.05.019. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2015.05.019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26048001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Groner J. Health effects of electronic cigarettes. Curr Probl Pediatr Adolesc Health Care. 2022 Jun;52(6):101202. doi: 10.1016/j.cppeds.2022.101202. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cppeds.2022.101202</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35525788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banks E, Yazidjoglou A, Brown S. Electronic cigarettes and health outcomes: systematic review of global evidence: Report for the Australian Department of Health. National Centre for Epidemiology and Population Health. 2022.  [30-09-2024]. https://www.nhmrc.gov.au/sites/default/files/documents/attachments/ecigarettes/Electronic_cigarettes_and_health_outcomes_%20systematic_review_of_evidence.pdf URL. Accessed.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnston LD, Miech RA, O’Malley PM, Bachman JG, Schulenberg JE, Patrick ME. Monitoring the future: national survey results on drug use 1975-2021: overview, key findings on adolescent drug use. Institute for Social Research, University of Michigan. 2022.  [24-09-2024]. https://deepblue.lib.umich.edu/bitstream/handle/2027.42/171751/mtf-overview2021.pdf?sequence=1&amp;isAllowed=y URL. Accessed.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen N, Barrington-Trimis JL, Urman R, et al. Past 30-day co-use of tobacco and marijuana products among adolescents and young adults in California. Addict Behav. 2019 Nov;98:106053. doi: 10.1016/j.addbeh.2019.106053. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.addbeh.2019.106053</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6708734</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31357072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hublet A, Bendtsen P, de Looze ME, et al. Trends in the co-occurrence of tobacco and cannabis use in 15-year-olds from 2002 to 2010 in 28 countries of Europe and North America. Eur J Public Health. 2015 Apr;25 Suppl 2:73–75. doi: 10.1093/eurpub/ckv032. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/eurpub/ckv032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25805793</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Veliz PT, McCabe SE, Evans-Polce RJ, Boyd CJ. Assessing how the history of e-cigarette and cigarette use are associated with the developmental course of marijuana use in a sample of United States adolescents. Drug Alcohol Depend. 2020 Nov 1;216:108308. doi: 10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2020.108308. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2020.108308</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7606514</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33007703</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramo DE, Liu H, Prochaska JJ. Tobacco and marijuana use among adolescents and young adults: a systematic review of their co-use. Clin Psychol Rev. 2012 Mar;32(2):105–121. doi: 10.1016/j.cpr.2011.12.002. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cpr.2011.12.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3267894</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22245559</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seiler-Ramadas R, Sandner I, Haider S, Grabovac I, Dorner TE. Health effects of electronic cigarette (e‑cigarette) use on organ systems and its implications for public health. Wien Klin Wochenschr. 2021 Oct;133(19-20):1020–1027. doi: 10.1007/s00508-020-01711-z. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00508-020-01711-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8500897</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32691214</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tzortzi A, Kapetanstrataki M, Evangelopoulou V, Beghrakis P. A systematic literature review of e-cigarette-related illness and injury: not just for the respirologist. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020 Mar 27;17(7):2248. doi: 10.3390/ijerph17072248. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph17072248</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7177608</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32230711</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gordon T, Karey E, Rebuli ME, Escobar YN, Jaspers I, Chen LC. e-Cigarette toxicology. Annu Rev Pharmacol Toxicol. 2022 Jan 6;62(1):301–322. doi: 10.1146/annurev-pharmtox-042921-084202. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1146/annurev-pharmtox-042921-084202</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9386787</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34555289</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arseneault L, Cannon M, Witton J, Murray RM. Causal association between cannabis and psychosis: examination of the evidence. Br J Psychiatry. 2004 Feb;184(2):110–117. doi: 10.1192/bjp.184.2.110. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1192/bjp.184.2.110</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14754822</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arseneault L, Cannon M, Poulton R, Murray R, Caspi A, Moffitt TE. Cannabis use in adolescence and risk for adult psychosis: longitudinal prospective study. BMJ. 2002 Nov 23;325(7374):1212–1213. doi: 10.1136/bmj.325.7374.1212. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.325.7374.1212</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC135493</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12446537</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Renard J, Krebs MO, Le Pen G, Jay TM. Long-term consequences of adolescent cannabinoid exposure in adult psychopathology. Front Neurosci. 2014;8:361. doi: 10.3389/fnins.2014.00361. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fnins.2014.00361</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4226229</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25426017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osman A, Kowitt SD, Ranney LM, Heck C, Goldstein AO. Risk factors for multiple tobacco product use among high school youth. Addict Behav. 2019 Dec;99:106068. doi: 10.1016/j.addbeh.2019.106068. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.addbeh.2019.106068</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6791764</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31470239</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith CL, Cooper BR, Miguel A, Hill L, Roll J, McPherson S. Predictors of cannabis and tobacco co-use in youth: exploring the mediating role of age at first use in the population assessment of tobacco health (PATH) study. J Cannabis Res. 2021 Jun 1;3(1):16. doi: 10.1186/s42238-021-00072-2. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s42238-021-00072-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8170934</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34074338</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arrazola RA, Singh T, Corey CG, et al. Tobacco use among middle and high school students—United States, 2011-2014. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2015 Apr 17;64(14):381–385. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5779546</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25879896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang TW, Neff LJ, Park-Lee E, Ren C, Cullen KA, King BA. e-Cigarette use among middle and high school students—United States, 2020. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2020 Sep 18;69(37):1310–1312. doi: 10.15585/mmwr.mm6937e1. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm6937e1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7498174</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32941408</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benowitz NL, Goniewicz ML, Halpern-Felsher B, et al. Tobacco product use and the risks of SARS-CoV-2 infection and COVID-19: current understanding and recommendations for future research. Lancet Respir Med. 2022 Sep;10(9):900–915. doi: 10.1016/S2213-2600(22)00182-5. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(22)00182-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9381032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35985357</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Owotomo O, Walley S. The youth e-cigarette epidemic: updates and review of devices, epidemiology and regulation. Curr Probl Pediatr Adolesc Health Care. 2022 Jun;52(6):101200. doi: 10.1016/j.cppeds.2022.101200. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cppeds.2022.101200</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35577717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park-Lee E, Ren C, Sawdey MD, et al. Notes from the field: e-cigarette use among middle and high school students—National Youth Tobacco Survey, United States, 2021. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2021 Oct 1;70(39):1387–1389. doi: 10.15585/mmwr.mm7039a4. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7039a4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8486384</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34591834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaffee BW, Cheng J, Couch ET, Hoeft KS, Halpern-Felsher B. Adolescents’ substance use and physical activity before and during the COVID-19 pandemic. JAMA Pediatr. 2021 Jul 1;175(7):715–722. doi: 10.1001/jamapediatrics.2021.0541. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamapediatrics.2021.0541</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8094031</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33938922</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaiha SM, Cheng J, Halpern-Felsher B. Association between youth smoking, electronic cigarette use, and COVID-19. J Adolesc Health. 2020 Oct;67(4):519–523. doi: 10.1016/j.jadohealth.2020.07.002. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jadohealth.2020.07.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7417895</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32798097</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaiha SM, Lempert LK, Halpern-Felsher B. Underage youth and young adult e-cigarette use and access before and during the coronavirus disease 2019 pandemic. JAMA Netw Open. 2020 Dec 1;3(12):e2027572. doi: 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.27572. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.27572</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7716191</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33270127</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kreslake JM, Simard BJ, O’Connor KM, Patel M, Vallone DM, Hair EC. e-Cigarette use among youths and young adults during the COVID-19 pandemic: United States, 2020. Am J Public Health. 2021 Jun;111(6):1132–1140. doi: 10.2105/AJPH.2021.306210. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2021.306210</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8101576</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33856888</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Popova L, Henderson K, Kute N, et al. “I’m Bored and I’m Stressed”: a qualitative study of exclusive smokers, ENDS users, and transitioning smokers or ENDS users in the time of COVID-19. Nicotine Tob Res. 2023 Jan 5;25(2):185–192. doi: 10.1093/ntr/ntab199. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ntr/ntab199</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8522380</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34610133</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pandya A, Lodha P. Social connectedness, excessive screen time during COVID-19 and mental health: a review of current evidence. Front Hum Dyn. 2021;3 doi: 10.3389/fhumd.2021.684137. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fhumd.2021.684137</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cho H, Li W, Shen L, Cannon J. Mechanisms of social media effects on attitudes toward e-cigarette use: motivations, mediators, and moderators in a national survey of adolescents. J Med Internet Res. 2019;21(6):e14303. doi: 10.2196/14303. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/14303</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6620891</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31250830</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mantey DS, Cooper MR, Clendennen SL, Pasch KE, Perry CL. e-Cigarette marketing exposure is associated with e-cigarette use among US youth. J Adolesc Health. 2016 Jun;58(6):686–690. doi: 10.1016/j.jadohealth.2016.03.003. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jadohealth.2016.03.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4900536</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27080732</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh T, Agaku IT, Arrazola RA, et al. Exposure to advertisements and electronic cigarette use among US middle and high school students. Pediatrics. 2016 May 1;137(5) doi: 10.1542/peds.2015-4155. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1542/peds.2015-4155</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nicksic NE, Harrell MB, Pérez A, Pasch KE, Perry CL. Recall of e-cigarette advertisements and adolescent e-cigarette use. Tob Regul Sci. 2017 Apr;3(2):210–221. doi: 10.18001/TRS.3.2.9. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18001/TRS.3.2.9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5665569</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29104901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee J, Tan ASL, Porter L, Young-Wolff KC, Carter-Harris L, Salloum RG. Association between social media use and vaping among Florida adolescents, 2019. Prev Chron Dis. 2021 May 13;18:E49. doi: 10.5888/pcd18.200550. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5888/pcd18.200550</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8139446</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33988495</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hansen J, Hanewinkel R, Morgenstern M. Electronic cigarette marketing and smoking behaviour in adolescence: a cross-sectional study. ERJ Open Res. 2018 Oct;4(4):00155-2018. doi: 10.1183/23120541.00155-2018. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1183/23120541.00155-2018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6258091</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30510958</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Camenga D, Gutierrez KM, Kong G, Cavallo D, Simon P, Krishnan-Sarin S. e-Cigarette advertising exposure in e-cigarette naïve adolescents and subsequent e-cigarette use: a longitudinal cohort study. Addict Behav. 2018 Jun;81:78–83. doi: 10.1016/j.addbeh.2018.02.008. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.addbeh.2018.02.008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5845830</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29432916</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pokhrel P, Herzog TA, Fagan P, Unger JB, Stacy AW. e-Cigarette advertising exposure, explicit and implicit harm perceptions, and e-cigarette use susceptibility among nonsmoking young adults. Nicotine Tob Res. 2019 Jan 1;21(1):127–131. doi: 10.1093/ntr/nty030. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ntr/nty030</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6610163</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29444275</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vogel EA, Ramo DE, Rubinstein ML, et al. Effects of social media on adolescents’ willingness and intention to use e-cigarettes: an experimental investigation. Nicotine Tob Res. 2021 Mar 19;23(4):694–701. doi: 10.1093/ntr/ntaa003. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ntr/ntaa003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7976937</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31912147</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Villanti AC, Rath JM, Williams VF, et al. Impact of exposure to electronic cigarette advertising on susceptibility and trial of electronic cigarettes and cigarettes in US young adults: a randomized controlled trial. Nicotine Tob Res. 2016 May;18(5):1331–1339. doi: 10.1093/ntr/ntv235. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ntr/ntv235</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26574551</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farrelly MC, Duke JC, Crankshaw EC, et al. A randomized trial of the effect of e-cigarette TV advertisements on intentions to use e-cigarettes. Am J Prev Med. 2015 Nov;49(5):686–693. doi: 10.1016/j.amepre.2015.05.010. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.amepre.2015.05.010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26163170</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Whitehill JM, Trangenstein PJ, Jenkins MC, Jernigan DH, Moreno MA. Exposure to cannabis marketing in social and traditional media and past-year use among adolescents in states with legal retail cannabis. J Adolesc Health. 2020 Feb;66(2):247–254. doi: 10.1016/j.jadohealth.2019.08.024. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jadohealth.2019.08.024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6980270</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31708374</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun T, Lim CCW, Chung J, et al. Vaping on TikTok: a systematic thematic analysis. Tob Control. 2023 Mar;32(2):251–254. doi: 10.1136/tobaccocontrol-2021-056619. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/tobaccocontrol-2021-056619</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34312317</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chu KH, Matheny SJ, Sidani JE, Allem JP, Unger JB, Cruz TB. Instagram’s #JUUL: who’s posting what. Transl Behav Med. 2021 Feb 11;11(1):257–261. doi: 10.1093/tbm/ibz169. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/tbm/ibz169</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7877305</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31912873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Urman R, McConnell R, Unger JB, et al. Electronic cigarette and cigarette social environments and ever use of each product: a prospective study of young adults in Southern California. Nicotine Tob Res. 2019 Sep 19;21(10):1347–1354. doi: 10.1093/ntr/nty097. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ntr/nty097</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6751522</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29741713</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kwon E, Seo DC, Lin HC, Chen Z. Predictors of youth e-cigarette use susceptibility in a U.S. nationally representative sample. Addict Behav. 2018 Jul;82:79–85. doi: 10.1016/j.addbeh.2018.02.026. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.addbeh.2018.02.026</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29501011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coleman M, Donaldson CD, Crano WD, Pike JR, Stacy AW. Associations between family and peer e-cigarette use with adolescent tobacco and marijuana usage: a longitudinal path analytic approach. Nicotine Tob Res. 2021 May 4;23(5):849–855. doi: 10.1093/ntr/ntaa204. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ntr/ntaa204</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8628870</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33038257</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Riehm KE, Young AS, Feder KA, et al. Mental health problems and initiation of e-cigarette and combustible cigarette use. Pediatrics. 2019 Jul;144(1):e20182935. doi: 10.1542/peds.2018-2935. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1542/peds.2018-2935</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6615573</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31160343</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park SH, Lee L, Shearston JA, Weitzman M. Patterns of electronic cigarette use and level of psychological distress. PLOS ONE. 2017;12(3):e0173625. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0173625. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0173625</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5344459</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28278239</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Becker TD, Arnold MK, Ro V, Martin L, Rice TR. Systematic review of electronic cigarette use (vaping) and mental health comorbidity among adolescents and young adults. Nicotine Tob Res. 2021 Feb 16;23(3):415–425. doi: 10.1093/ntr/ntaa171. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ntr/ntaa171</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32905589</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cambron C. e-Cigarette use is associated with increased psychological distress among youth: a pooled cross-sectional analysis of state-level data from 2019 and 2021. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022 Sep 17;19(18):11726. doi: 10.3390/ijerph191811726. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph191811726</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9516976</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36142001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Executive order N-33-20. Executive Department, State of California. 2020.  [30-03-2023]. https://www.napa.courts.ca.gov/system/files/eo-n-33-20.pdf URL. Accessed.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Executive order N-07-21. Executive Department, State of California. 2021.  [30-03-2023]. https://www.gov.ca.gov/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/6.11.21-EO-N-07-21-signed.pdf?emrc=fd1520 URL. Accessed.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smets J, Baeyens F, Chaumont M, Adriaens K, Van Gucht D. When less is more: vaping low-nicotine vs. high-nicotine e-liquid is compensated by increased wattage and higher liquid consumption. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2019 Feb 28;16(5):723. doi: 10.3390/ijerph16050723. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph16050723</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6427796</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30823395</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morean ME, Krishnan-Sarin S, Sussman S, et al. Psychometric evaluation of the e-cigarette dependence scale. Nicotine Tob Res. 2019 Oct 26;21(11):1556–1564. doi: 10.1093/ntr/ntx271. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ntr/ntx271</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6821314</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29301008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nunnally JC, Bernstein IH. The assessment of reliability. Psych Theory. 1994;3:248–292.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andreassen CS, Torsheim T, Brunborg GS, Pallesen S. Development of a Facebook Addiction Scale. Psychol Rep. 2012 Apr;110(2):501–517. doi: 10.2466/02.09.18.PR0.110.2.501-517. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2466/02.09.18.PR0.110.2.501-517</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22662404</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orosz G, Tóth-Király I, Bőthe B. Four facets of Facebook intensity—the development of the Multidimensional Facebook Intensity Scale. Pers Individ Dif. 2016 Oct;100:95–104. doi: 10.1016/j.paid.2015.11.038. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.paid.2015.11.038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kessler RC, Andrews G, Colpe LJ, et al. Short screening scales to monitor population prevalences and trends in non-specific psychological distress. Psychol Med. 2002 Aug;32(6):959–976. doi: 10.1017/s0033291702006074. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/s0033291702006074</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12214795</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mewton L, Kessler RC, Slade T, et al. The psychometric properties of the Kessler Psychological Distress Scale (K6) in a general population sample of adolescents. Psychol Assess. 2016 Oct;28(10):1232–1242. doi: 10.1037/pas0000239. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/pas0000239</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26619095</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Devika S, Jeyaseelan L, Sebastian G. Analysis of sparse data in logistic regression in medical research: a newer approach. J Postgrad Med. 2016;62(1):26–31. doi: 10.4103/0022-3859.173193. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/0022-3859.173193</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4944325</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26732193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Royston P. Profile likelihood for estimation and confidence intervals. Stata J. 2007 Sep;7(3):376–387. doi: 10.1177/1536867X0700700305. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1536867X0700700305</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simon P, Camenga DR, Kong G, et al. Youth e-cigarette, blunt, and other tobacco use profiles: does SES matter? Tob Regul Sci. 2017 Jan;3(1):115–127. doi: 10.18001/TRS.3.1.12. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18001/TRS.3.1.12</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5654631</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29082301</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rothman KJ. No adjustments are needed for multiple comparisons. Epidemiology. 1990 Jan;1(1):43–46. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2081237</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pienkowski M, Chaiton M, Dubray J, Schwartz R. e-Cigarette dependence in youth. Nicotine Tob Res. 2022 Jun 15;24(7):1089–1094. doi: 10.1093/ntr/ntab268. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ntr/ntab268</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9200078</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34936704</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vogel EA, Cho J, McConnell RS, Barrington-Trimis JL, Leventhal AM. Prevalence of electronic cigarette dependence among youth and its association with future use. JAMA Netw Open. 2020 Feb 5;3(2):e1921513. doi: 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.21513. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.21513</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7780897</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32074292</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu SH, Zhuang Y, Braden K, et al.   Center for Research and Intervention in Tobacco Control (CRITC), University of California, San Diego; 2019. Results of the statewide 2017-18 California Student Tobacco Survey.https://www.cdph.ca.gov/Programs/CCDPHP/DCDIC/CTCB/CDPH%20Document%20Library/ResearchandEvaluation/Reports/2017-18CaliforniaStudentTobaccoSurveyBiennialReport.pdf URL.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barrington-Trimis JL, Berhane K, Unger JB, et al. The e-cigarette social environment, e-cigarette use, and susceptibility to cigarette smoking. J Adolesc Health. 2016 Jul;59(1):75–80. doi: 10.1016/j.jadohealth.2016.03.019. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jadohealth.2016.03.019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4920702</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27161417</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oliver AL, Kossowsky J, Minegishi M, Levy S, Weitzman ER. The association of vaping with social/emotional health and attitudes toward COVID-19 mitigation measures in adolescent and young adult cohorts during the COVID-19 pandemic. Subst Abus. 2023;44(1):73–85. doi: 10.1177/08897077231165860. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/08897077231165860</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10133863</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37226905</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma P, Ebbert JO, Rosedahl JK, Philpot LM. Changes in substance use among young adults during a respiratory disease pandemic. SAGE Open Med. 2020;8:2050312120965321. doi: 10.1177/2050312120965321. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/2050312120965321</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7576913</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33133603</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amin S, Dunn AG, Laranjo L. Exposure to e-cigarette information and advertising in social media and e-cigarette use in Australia: a mixed methods study. Drug Alcohol Depend. 2020 Aug 1;213:108112. doi: 10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2020.108112. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2020.108112</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32574981</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kwon M, Park E. Perceptions and sentiments about electronic cigarettes on social media platforms: systematic review. JMIR Public Health Surveill. 2020 Jan 15;6(1):e13673. doi: 10.2196/13673. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/13673</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6996744</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31939747</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freeman JL, Caldwell PHY, Scott KM. How adolescents trust health information on social media: a systematic review. Acad Pediatr. 2023;23(4):703–719. doi: 10.1016/j.acap.2022.12.011. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.acap.2022.12.011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36581098</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Das JK, Salam RA, Arshad A, Finkelstein Y, Bhutta ZA. Interventions for adolescent substance abuse: an overview of systematic reviews. J Adolesc Health. 2016 Oct;59(4S):S61–S75. doi: 10.1016/j.jadohealth.2016.06.021. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jadohealth.2016.06.021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5026681</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27664597</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berg CJ, Krishnan N, Graham AL, Abroms LC. A synthesis of the literature to inform vaping cessation interventions for young adults. Addict Behav. 2021 Aug;119:106898. doi: 10.1016/j.addbeh.2021.106898. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.addbeh.2021.106898</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8113079</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33894483</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haines-Saah RJ, Kelly MT, Oliffe JL, Bottorff JL. Picture Me Smokefree: a qualitative study using social media and digital photography to engage young adults in tobacco reduction and cessation. J Med Internet Res. 2015 Jan 26;17(1):e27. doi: 10.2196/jmir.4061. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/jmir.4061</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4327185</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25624064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buller DB, Borland R, Woodall WG, et al. Randomized trials on consider this, a tailored, internet-delivered smoking prevention program for adolescents. Health Educ Behav. 2008 Apr;35(2):260–281. doi: 10.1177/1090198106288982. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1090198106288982</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4380290</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17114331</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baskerville NB, Azagba S, Norman C, McKeown K, Brown KS. Effect of a digital social media campaign on young adult smoking cessation. Nicotine Tob Res. 2015 Mar;18(3):351–360. doi: 10.1093/ntr/ntv119. doi.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ntr/ntv119</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26045252</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Graham AL, Amato MS, Cha S, Jacobs MA, Bottcher MM, Papandonatos GD. Effectiveness of a vaping cessation text message program among young adult e-cigarette users: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA Intern Med. 2021 Jul 1;181(7):923–930. doi: 10.1001/jamainternmed.2021.1793. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2021.1793</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8129897</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33999133</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Markey EJ. S.1628 - Children and Teens’ Online Privacy Protection Act. Congress.gov. 2021.  [05-04-2023]. https://www.congress.gov/bill/117th-congress/senate-bill/1628/text URL. Accessed.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reid Chassiakos YL, Radesky J, Christakis D, Moreno MA, Cross C, Council on Communications and Media Children and adolescents and digital media. Pediatrics. 2016 Nov;138(5):e20162593. doi: 10.1542/peds.2016-2593. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1542/peds.2016-2593</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27940795</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Protecting youth mental health: the U.S. Surgeon General’s Advisory. Office of the Surgeon General. 2021.  [21-09-2022]. https://www.hhs.gov/sites/default/files/surgeon-general-youth-mental-health-advisory.pdf URL. Accessed.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chadi N, Ryan NC, Geoffroy MC. COVID-19 and the impacts on youth mental health: emerging evidence from longitudinal studies. Can J Public Health. 2022 Feb;113(1):44–52. doi: 10.17269/s41997-021-00567-8. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.17269/s41997-021-00567-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8796598</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35089589</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Racine N, McArthur BA, Cooke JE, Eirich R, Zhu J, Madigan S. Global prevalence of depressive and anxiety symptoms in children and adolescents during COVID-19: a meta-analysis. JAMA Pediatr. 2021 Nov 1;175(11):1142–1150. doi: 10.1001/jamapediatrics.2021.2482. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamapediatrics.2021.2482</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8353576</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34369987</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yard E, Radhakrishnan L, Ballesteros MF, et al. Emergency department visits for suspected suicide attempts among persons aged 12-25 years before and during the COVID-19 pandemic—United States, January 2019-May 2021. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2021 Jun 18;70(24):888–894. doi: 10.15585/mmwr.mm7024e1. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7024e1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8220953</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34138833</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prochaska JJ, Sung HY, Max W, Shi Y, Ong M. Validity study of the K6 scale as a measure of moderate mental distress based on mental health treatment need and utilization. Int J Methods Psychiatr Res. 2012 Jun;21(2):88–97. doi: 10.1002/mpr.1349. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/mpr.1349</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3370145</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22351472</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trivers KF, Phillips E, Gentzke AS, Tynan MA, Neff LJ. Prevalence of cannabis use in electronic cigarettes among US youth. JAMA Pediatr. 2018 Nov 1;172(11):1097–1099. doi: 10.1001/jamapediatrics.2018.1920. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamapediatrics.2018.1920</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6248134</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30242366</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Timeline of marijuana policy reform in california. The Marijuana Policy Project. 2022.  [21-09-2022]. https://www.mpp.org/states/california URL. Accessed.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Midgette G, Reuter P. Has cannabis use among youth increased after changes in its legal status? A commentary on use of monitoring the future for analyses of changes in state cannabis laws. Prev Sci. 2020 Jan;21(1):137–145. doi: 10.1007/s11121-019-01068-4. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11121-019-01068-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6960330</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31792712</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu SH, Braden K, Zhuang YL, et al.   Center for Research and Intervention in Tobacco Control (CRITC), University of California San Diego; 2021. Results of the statewide 2019-20 California Student Tobacco Survey.https://www.cdph.ca.gov/Programs/CCDPHP/DCDIC/CTCB/CDPH%20Document%20Library/ResearchandEvaluation/FactsandFigures/2019-20CSTSBiennialReport_7-27-2021.pdf URL.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moritz ED, Zapata LB, Lekiachvili A, et al. Update: characteristics of patients in a national outbreak of e-cigarette, or vaping, product use-associated lung injuries—United States, October 2019. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2019 Nov 1;68(43):985–989. doi: 10.15585/mmwr.mm6843e1. doi. Medline.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm6843e1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6822806</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31671085</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>