<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39438029</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1399-6576</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>22</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Acta anaesthesiologica Scandinavica</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Acta Anaesthesiol Scand</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Veno-venous extracorporeal membrane oxygenation for severe COVID-19 associated acute respiratory distress syndrome: A retrospective, nationwide, Danish cohort study.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/aas.14522</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Severe acute respiratory syndrome (ARDS) may require veno-venous extracorporeal membrane oxygenation (V-V ECMO). The aim of this study was to provide data on patient selection and outcome in a nationwide cohort study of patients with COVID-19 associated ARDS supported with V-V ECMO.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">We identified all patients with COVID-19, who were supported with V-V ECMO in Denmark from March 10, 2020, to December 31, 2021, and retrieved data on patients who were referred to- and accepted for ECMO, demographics, outcome data, and complications. Risk factors for mortality were analysed using multivariate Cox regression analysis.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">During the study period, 1836 patients were admitted to Danish intensive care units (ICUs). In the same period, there were 197 enquiries for ECMO of whom 118 patients were considered eligible. Overall, 71 patients were cannulated for ECMO; three patients were cannulated for veno-arterial extracorporeal membrane oxygenation (V-A ECMO) due to right sided heart failure and 68 patients were cannulated for V-V ECMO. Two patients accepted for V-V ECMO died during cannulation. The median age was 55 years (IQR 45-60) and 66% were males. The median duration of ECMO support was 13 days (IQR 7-21), mechanical ventilation median 26 days (IQR 14-42), ICU stay median 34 days (IQR 17-46), and length of hospital stay median 41 days (IQR 25-56). Ninety-day mortality was 43%. Age of 60 years or more was associated with an increased risk of mortality. Pre-existing hypertension was associated with a decreased risk of mortality.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">A nationwide, Danish cohort study of 68 COVID-19 patients supported with V-V ECMO, showed a 90-day survival of 43%, which is in accordance with reports from comparable cohorts. Age of 60 years or more was associated with an increased risk of mortality. Pre-existing hypertension was associated with a decreased risk of mortality.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Acta Anaesthesiologica Scandinavica published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Acta Anaesthesiologica Scandinavica Foundation.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pedersen</LastName><ForeName>Finn Møller</ForeName><Initials>FM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0005-8375-4223</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiothoracic Anaesthesia and Intensive Care, Rigshospitalet, University Hospital of Copenhagen, Copenhagen, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Grønlykke</LastName><ForeName>Lars</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3693-8394</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiothoracic Anaesthesia and Intensive Care, Rigshospitalet, University Hospital of Copenhagen, Copenhagen, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Eschen</LastName><ForeName>Camilla Tofte</ForeName><Initials>CT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Anaesthesiology and Intensive Care, Herlev and Gentofte Hospital, University of Copenhagen, Copenhagen, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Adelsten</LastName><ForeName>Janne</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiothoracic Anaesthesia and Intensive Care, Rigshospitalet, University Hospital of Copenhagen, Copenhagen, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Madsen</LastName><ForeName>Søren Aalbæk</ForeName><Initials>SA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiothoracic Anaesthesia and Intensive Care, Rigshospitalet, University Hospital of Copenhagen, Copenhagen, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sørensen</LastName><ForeName>Marc</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiothoracic Anaesthesia and Intensive Care, Rigshospitalet, University Hospital of Copenhagen, Copenhagen, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gjedsted</LastName><ForeName>Jakob</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiothoracic Anaesthesia and Intensive Care, Rigshospitalet, University Hospital of Copenhagen, Copenhagen, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Møller-Sørensen</LastName><ForeName>Peter Hasse</ForeName><Initials>PH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiothoracic Anaesthesia and Intensive Care, Rigshospitalet, University Hospital of Copenhagen, Copenhagen, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nielsen</LastName><ForeName>Jonas</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Intensive Care Unit, Rigshospitalet, University Hospital of Copenhagen, Copenhagen, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Christensen</LastName><ForeName>Steffen</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Anaesthesiology and Intensive Care, University Hospital of Aarhus, Aarhus, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nielsen</LastName><ForeName>Dorthe Viemose</ForeName><Initials>DV</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Anaesthesiology and Intensive Care, University Hospital of Aarhus, Aarhus, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jørgensen</LastName><ForeName>Vibeke Lind</ForeName><Initials>VL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiothoracic Anaesthesia and Intensive Care, Rigshospitalet, University Hospital of Copenhagen, Copenhagen, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Acta Anaesthesiol Scand</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0370270</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0001-5172</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ARDS</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">V‐V ECMO</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>20</Hour><Minute>32</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39438029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/aas.14522</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Johns Hopkins University Coronavirus Resource Centre. https://coronavirus.jhu.edu/map.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barbaro RP, MacLaren G, Boonstra PS, et al. Extracorporeal membrane oxygenation support in COVID‐19: an international cohort study of the Extracorporeal Life Support Organization registry. Lancet. 2020;396:1071‐1078.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karagiannidis C, Slutsky AS, Bein T, et al. Complete countrywide mortality in COVID‐patients receiving ECMO in Germany throughout the first three waves of the pandemic. Crit Care. 2021;25:413‐414.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lebreton G, Schmidt M, Ponnaiah M, et al. Extracorporeal membrane oxygenation network organisation and clinical outcomes during the COVID‐19 pandemic in Greater Paris, France: a multicentre cohort study. Lancet Respir Med. 2021;9:851‐862.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmidt M, Hajage D, Lebreton G, et al. Extracorporeal membrane oxygenation for severe acute respiratory distress syndrome associated with COVID‐19: a retrospective cohort study. Lancet Respir Med. 2020;8:1121‐1131.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trejnowska E, Drobinski D, Knapik P, et al. Extracorporeal membrane oxygenation for severe COVID‐19‐associated acute respiratory distress syndrome in Poland: a multicenter cohort study. Crit Care. 2022;26(1):97.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lorusso R, De Piero ME, Mariani S, et al. In‐hospital and 6‐month outcomes in patients with COVID‐19 supported with extracorporeal membrane oxygenation (EuroECMO‐COVID): a multicentre, prospective observational study. Lancet Respir Med. 2023;11:151‐162.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Whebell S, Zhang J, Lewis R, et al. Survival benefit of extracorporeal membrane oxygenation in severe COVID‐19: a multi‐centre‐matched cohort study. Intensive Care Med. 2022;48:467‐478.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Badulak J, Antonini MV, Stead CM, et al. Extracorporeal membrane oxygenation for COVID‐19: updated 2021 guidelines from the extracorporeal life support organization. ASAIO J. 2021;67(6):485‐495.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Warren A, Camporota L, Vuylsteke A. Surge capacity and updated admission criteria: response of the NHS‐commissioned national respiratory extracorporeal membrane oxygenation network to the COVID‐19 pandemic. Br J Anaesth. 2020;125:e282‐e283.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gannon WD, Trindade AJ, Stokes JW, et al. Extracorporeal membrane oxygenation selection by multidisciplinary consensus: the ECMO council. ASAIO J. 2023;69:167‐173.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Riera J, Roncon‐Albuquerque R Jr, Fuset MP, et al. Increased mortality in patients with COVID‐19 receiving extracorporeal respiratory support during the second wave of the pandemic. Intensive Care Med. 2021;47:1490‐1493.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmidt M, Langouet E, Hajage D, et al. Evolving outcomes of extracorporeal membrane oxygenation support for severe COVID‐19 ARDS in Sorbonne hospitals, Paris. Crit Care. 2021;25:355.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herrmann J, Lotz C, Karagiannidis C, et al. Key characteristics impacting survival of COVID‐19 extracorporeal membrane oxygenation. Crit Care. 2022;26(1):190.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meier N, Perner A, Plovsing R, et al. Long‐term outcomes in COVID‐19 patients admitted to intensive care in Denmark: a nationwide observational study. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand. 2023;67:1239‐1248.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tonna JE, Abrams D, Brodie D, et al. Management of adult patients supported with venovenous extracorporeal membrane oxygenation (VV ECMO): guideline from the extracorporeal life support organization (ELSO). ASAIO J. 2021;67(6):601‐610.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmidt M, Bailey M, Sheldrake J, et al. Predicting survival after extracorporeal membrane oxygenation for severe acute respiratory failure. The respiratory extracorporeal membrane oxygenation survival prediction (RESP) score. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2014;189:1374‐1382.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luyt CE, Brechot N, Demondion P, et al. Brain injury during venovenous extracorporeal membrane oxygenation. Intensive Care Med. 2016;42:897‐907.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adelsten J, Grønlykke L, Pedersen FM, et al. Use of prone position ventilation in patients with COVID‐19 induced severe ARDS supported with V‐V ECMO: a Danish cohort study with focus on adverse events. Perfusion. 2023. doi:10.1177/02676591231198798</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beigel JH, Tomashek KM, Dodd LE, et al. Remdesivir for the treatment of COVID‐19 – final report. N Engl J Med. 2020;383:1813‐1826.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horby P, Lim WS, Emberson JR, et al. Dexamethasone in hospitalized patients with COVID‐19 – preliminary report. N Engl J Med. 2021;384:693‐704.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Extracorporeal Life Support Organization. ECLS Registry Report. International Summary, 2023, Ann Arbor, USA.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joshi H, Flanagan M, Subramanian R, Drouin M. Respiratory ECMO survival prediction (RESP) score for COVID‐19 patients treated with ECMO. ASAIO J. 2022;68:486‐491.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hippisley‐Cox J, Young D, Coupland C, et al. Risk of severe COVID‐19 disease with ACE inhibitors and angiotensin receptor blockers: cohort study including 8,3 million people. Heart. 2020;106:1503‐1511.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang P, Zhu L, Cai J, et al. Association of Inpatient use of angiotensin‐converting enzyme inhibitors and angiotensin II receptor blockers with mortality among patients with hypertension hospitalized with COVID‐19. Circ Res. 2020;126:1671‐1681.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmidt M, Hajage D, Landoll M, et al. Comparative outcomes of extracorporeal membrane oxygenation for COVID‐19 delivered in experienced European centres during successive SARS‐CoV‐2 variant outbreaks (ECMO‐SURGES): an international, multicentre, retrospective cohort study. Lancet Respir Med. 2023;11(2):163‐175.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levy D, Lebreton G, Pineton de Chambrun M, et al. Outcomes of patients denied extracorporeal membrane oxygenation during the COVID‐19 pandemic in Greater Paris, France. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2021;204:994‐997.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barbaro RP, MacLaren G, Boonstra PS, et al. Extracorporeal membrane oxygenation for COVID‐19: evolving outcomes from the international extracorporeal life support organization registry. Lancet. 2021;398:1230‐1238.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alessandri F, Di Nardo M, Ramanathan K, Brodie D, MacLaren G. Extracorporeal membrane oxygenation for COVID‐19‐related acute respiratory distress syndrome: a narrative review. J Intensive Care. 2023;11(1):5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mansour A, Flecher E, Schmidt M, et al. Bleeding and thrombotic events in patients with severe COVID‐19 supported with extracorporeal membrane oxygenation: a nationwide cohort study. Intensive Care Med. 2022;48:1039‐1052.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Combes A, Hajage D, Capellier G, et al. Extracorporeal membrane oxygenation for severe acute respiratory distress syndrome. N Engl J Med. 2018;378(21):1965‐1975.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalbhenn J, Glonnegger H, Wilke M, Bansbach J, Zieger B. Hypercoagulopathy, acquired coagulation disorders and anticoagulation before, during and after extracorporeal membrane oxygenation in COVID‐19: a case series. Perfusion. 2021;36:592‐602.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suero OR, Valluri SK, Farias‐Kovac MH, et al. Recovery of lung function after 149 days on extracorporeal membrane oxygenation for COVID‐19. Tex Heart Inst J. 2023;50(5):e238132.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Avella D, Bharat A. Lung transplantation in patients with lung disease secondary to coronavirus disease 2019 infection. Curr Opin Crit Care. 2022;28:681‐685.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>