<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39436819</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1536-0911</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>22</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Advances in neonatal care : official journal of the National Association of Neonatal Nurses</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Adv Neonatal Care</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The Impact of Pandemic-Induced Separation and Visitation Restrictions on the Maternal-Infant Dyad in Neonatal Units: A Systematic Review.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/ANC.0000000000001213</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The COVID-19 pandemic affected the maternal-infant dyad, especially due to visitation restrictions in neonatal units. These changes may impact the psychological, physical, and developmental health of mothers and newborns.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="PURPOSE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">This systematic review evaluates the impact of enforced separation and restrictive visitation policies in neonatal units during the pandemic, focusing on the maternal-infant dyad.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DATA SOURCES" NlmCategory="METHODS">Data sources include CINAHL, MEDLINE, Web of Science, APA PsycINFO, Academic Search Ultimate, and Embase, covering studies published between 2020 and 2024.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="STUDY SELECTION" NlmCategory="METHODS">A detailed search was conducted using terms related to COVID-19, maternal and neonatal health, and visitation restrictions in neonatal units. Articles were included if they were peer-reviewed, written in English, and focused on the impact of visitation restrictions on maternal and neonatal health.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DATA EXTRACTION" NlmCategory="METHODS">The data extraction process began with 789 references. After removing duplicates, we screened titles and abstracts. We then conducted a full-text assessment of the remaining studies, selecting 14 that met the inclusion criteria.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The analysis showed significant emotional, psychological, and developmental impacts on mothers and newborns due to pandemic-induced separation and inconsistent policies. It highlighted depressive symptoms, stress, bonding disruptions, and the effectiveness of virtual bonding.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="IMPLICATIONS FOR PRACTICE AND RESEARCH" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The review emphasizes the need for family-centered care, coping strategies, and virtual bonding in neonatal units. It calls for culturally sensitive policies to support mothers and infants during crises. The review also highlights the importance of studying the long-term effects of pandemic-induced separations and improving support for future health emergencies.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 by The National Association of Neonatal Nurses.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kain</LastName><ForeName>Victoria J</ForeName><Initials>VJ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8801-0040</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Author Affiliations: School of Nursing &amp; Midwifery, Griffith University, Brisbane, Australia (Prof Kain); and Faculty of Nursing, Prince of Songkhla University, Hat Yai Campus, Thailand (Drs Phumdoung, Vetcho and Chaisri).</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Phumdoung</LastName><ForeName>Sasitorn</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5514-3688</Identifier></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vetcho</LastName><ForeName>Siriporn</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0064-6616</Identifier></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chaisri</LastName><ForeName>Piyada</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8917-1628</Identifier></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Adv Neonatal Care</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101125644</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1536-0903</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>12</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39436819</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/ANC.0000000000001213</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00149525-990000000-00158</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World Health Organisation. Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) pandemic; 2020. https://wwwwhoint/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019. Accessed February, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organisation. Maintaining essential health services: operational guidance for the COVID-19 context: interim guidance. June 2020 (CC BY-NC-SA 3.0 IGO); 2020. https://appswhoint/iris/handle/10665/332240. Accessed February, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Institute for Patient and Family Centered Care. Patient and Family Centered Care Defined; 2020. https://wwwipfccorg/bestpractices/sustainable-partnerships/background/pfcc-definedhtml. Accessed February, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duff J, Curnen K, Reed A, Kranz C. Engaging parents of hospitalized neonates during a pandemic. J Neonatal Nurs. 2021;27(3):185-187. doi:10.1016/j.jnn.2020.11.013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jnn.2020.11.013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garfield H, Westgate B, Chaudhary R, King M, O’Curry S, Archibald SJ. Parental and staff experiences of restricted parental presence on a neonatal intensive care unit during COVID‐19. Acta Paediatr. 2021;110(12):3308-3314. doi:10.1111/apa.16085.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/apa.16085</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levesque BM, Tran A, Levesque E, et al. Implementation of a pilot program of Reach Out and Read® in the neonatal intensive care unit: a quality improvement initiative. J Perinatol. 2018;38(6):759-766. doi:10.1038/s41372-018-0060-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41372-018-0060-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding X, Zhu L, Zhang R, Wang L, Wang -T-T, Latour JM. Effects of family-centred care interventions on preterm infants and parents in neonatal intensive care units: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomised controlled trials. Aust Crit Care. 2019;32(1):63-75. doi:10.1016/j.aucc.2018.10.007.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.aucc.2018.10.007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Institute for Patient and Family Centered Care. Advancing the practice of patient- and family-centered care in hospitals: how to get started; 2017. http://wwwipfccorg/resources/getting_startedpdf. Accessed February, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carter BS, Willis T, Knackstedt A. Neonatal family-centered care in a pandemic. J Perinatol. 2021;41(5):1177-1179. doi:10.1038/s41372-021-00976-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41372-021-00976-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bainter J, Fry M, Miller B, et al. Family presence in the NICU: constraints and opportunities in the COVID-19 era. Pediatr Nurs. 2020;46(5):256-259.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salvatore CM, Han J-Y, Acker KP, et al. Neonatal management and outcomes during the COVID-19 pandemic: an observation cohort study. Lancet Child Adoles Health. 2020;4(10):721-727. doi:10.1016/S2352-4642(20)30235-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2352-4642(20)30235-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Renfrew MJ, Cheyne H, Dykes F, et al. Optimising mother-baby contact and infant feeding in a pandemic; 2020. https://wwwrcmorguk/media/4096/optimising-infant-feeding-and-contact-rapid-review-19th-may-2020-submittedpdf. Accessed February, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cavicchiolo ME, Trevisanuto D, Priante E, Moschino L, Mosca F, Baraldi E. Italian neonatologists and SARS-CoV-2: lessons learned to face coming new waves. Pediatr Res. 2022;91(3):513-521. doi:10.1038/s41390-021-01477-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41390-021-01477-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hunter New England Area Health Service (HNEAHS). Clinical management of COVID-19 by Newborn Services (Version 2.0); 2021. https://wwwhealthnswgovau/Infectious/covid-19/Pages/covid-19-neonatal-servicesaspx. Accessed February, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma X, Zhu J, Du L. Neonatal management during the coronavirus disease (COVID-19) outbreak: the Chinese experience. NeoReviews. 2020;21(5):e293-e297. doi:10.1542/neo.21-5-e293.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1542/neo.21-5-e293</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guttmann K, Patterson C, Haines T, et al. Parent stress in relation to use of bedside telehealth, an initiative to improve family-centeredness of care in the neonatal intensive care unit. J Patient Exp. 2020;7(6):1378-1383. doi:10.1177/2374373520950927.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/2374373520950927</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fonfe A, Clements D, McKechnie L. Parental access to neonatal units: inconsistency during the COVID-19 pandemic. Infant. 2021;17(2):71-75.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tedesco B, Borgese G, Cracco U, Casarotto P, Zanin A. Challenges to delivering family‐centred care during the coronavirus pandemic: voices of Italian paediatric intensive care unit nurses. Nurs Crit Care. 2021;26(1):10-12. doi: 10.1111/nicc.12578.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/nicc.12578</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raposa E, Hammen C, Brennan P, Najman J. The long-term effects of maternal depression: early childhood physical health as a pathway to offspring depression. J Adolesc Health. 2014;54(1):88-93. doi:10.1016/j.jadohealth.2013.07.038.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jadohealth.2013.07.038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leahy-Warren P, Coleman C, Bradley R, Mulcahy H. The experiences of mothers with preterm infants within the first-year post discharge from NICU: social support, attachment and level of depressive symptoms. BMC Pregnancy Childbirth. 2020;20(1):1-10. doi:10.1186/s12884-020-02956-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12884-020-02956-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khoury JE, Cunningham M, Jenkins E, Enlow MB, Lyons-Ruth K. Latent profiles of maternal disrupted communication: relations to affect and behaviour in early infancy. Br J Dev Psychol. 2023;41(2):99-116. doi:10.1111/bjdp.12438.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/bjdp.12438</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Veritas Health Innovation. Covidence systematic review software. Melbourne, Australia; 2023. Available at www.covidence.org. Accessed February, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tricco AC, Khalil H, Holly C, et al. Rapid reviews and the methodological rigor of evidence synthesis: a JBI position statement. JBI Evid Synth. 2022;20(4):944-949. doi:10.11124/JBIES-21-00371.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.11124/JBIES-21-00371</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Itoshima R, Tuura K, Toome L, et al. Depressive symptoms in mothers of preterm infants before and during COVID‐19 restrictions in neonatal intensive care units. Acta Paediatr. 2023;112(10):2164-2171. doi:10.1111/apa.16886.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/apa.16886</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deindl P, Witting A, Dür M, et al. Perceived stress of mothers and fathers on two NICUs before and during the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic. Sci Rep. 2023;13(1):14540. doi:10.1038/s41598-023-40836-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-023-40836-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manuela F, Barcos-Munoz F, Monaci MG, et al. Maternal stress, depression, and attachment in the neonatal intensive care unit before and during the COVID pandemic: an exploratory study. Front Psychol. 2021;12:1-8. doi:10.3389/fpsyg.2021.734640.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2021.734640</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morniroli D, Consales A, Colombo L, et al. Exploring the impact of restricted partners’ visiting policies on non-infected mothers’ mental health and breastfeeding rates during the COVID-19 pandemic. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18(12):6347. doi:10.3390/ijerph18126347.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph18126347</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vance AJ, Malin KJ, Miller J, Shuman CJ, Moore TA, Benjamin A. Parents’ pandemic NICU experience in the United States: a qualitative study. BMC Pediatr. 2021;21(1):1-13. doi:10.1186/s12887-021-03028-w.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12887-021-03028-w</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Broom M, Cochrane T, Cruickshank D, Carlisle H. Parental perceptions on the impact of visiting restrictions during COVID-19 in a tertiary neonatal intensive care unit. J Paediatr Child Health. 2022;58(10):1747-1752. doi:10.1111/jpc.16079.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jpc.16079</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erdei C, Liu CH, Machie M, Church PT, Heyne R. Parent mental health and neurodevelopmental outcomes of children hospitalized in the neonatal intensive care unit. Early Hum Dev. 2021;154:105278. doi:10.1016/j.earlhumdev.2020.105278.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.earlhumdev.2020.105278</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farhadi R, Mehrpisheh S, Philip RK. Mobile-assisted virtual bonding enables breast milk supply in critically ill mothers with COVID-19: a reflection on the feasibility of telelactation. Cureus. 2021;13(3). doi:10.7759/cureus.13699.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.13699</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giordano V, Fuiko R, Witting A, et al. The impact of pandemic restrictive visiting policies on infant wellbeing in a NICU. Pediatr Res. 2023;94:1098-1103. doi:10.1038/s41390-023-02562-w.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41390-023-02562-w</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muniraman H, Ali M, Cawley P, et al. Parental perceptions of the impact of neonatal unit visitation policies during COVID-19 pandemic. BMJ Paediatr Open. 2020;4(1):e000899. doi:10.1136/bmjpo-2020-000899.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjpo-2020-000899</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meesters N, van Dijk M, Sampaio de Carvalho F, et al. COVID-19 lockdown impacts the wellbeing of parents with infants on a Dutch neonatal intensive care unit. J Pediatr Nurs. 2022;62:106-112. doi:10.1016/j.pedn.2021.09.024.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pedn.2021.09.024</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kostenzer J, Hoffmann J, von Rosenstiel-pulver C, Walsh A, Zimmermann LJ, Mader S. Neonatal care during the COVID-19 pandemic-a global survey of parents’ experiences regarding infant and family-centred developmental care. EClinicalMedicine. 2021;39:101056. doi:10.1016/j.eclinm.2021.101056.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2021.101056</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pang EM, Sey R, De Beritto T, Lee HC, Powell CM. Advancing health equity by translating lessons learned from NICU family visitations during the COVID-19 pandemic. Neoreviews. 2021;22(1):e1–e6. doi:10.1542/neo.22-1-e1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1542/neo.22-1-e1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almeida M, Shrestha AD, Stojanac D, Miller LJ. The impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on women’s mental health. Arch Womens Ment Health. 2020;23(6):741-748. doi:10.1007/s00737-020-01092-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00737-020-01092-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carton A, Cordwell J, Steinhardt K. A framework synthesis reviewing the impact of neonatal care unit admission on early caregiver-infant relationships. J Adv Nurs. 2020;76(12):3258-3272. doi:10.1111/jan.14538.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jan.14538</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Penninx BWJH, Benros ME, Klein RS, Vinkers CH. How COVID-19 shaped mental health: from infection to pandemic effects. Nat Med. 2022;28(10):2027-2037. doi:10.1038/s41591-022-02028-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41591-022-02028-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choi KR, Records K, Low LK, et al. Promotion of maternal-infant mental health and trauma-informed care during the COVID-19 pandemic. J Obstet Gynecol Neonatal Nurs. 2020;49(5):409-415. doi:10.1016/j.jogn.2020.07.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jogn.2020.07.004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Dea GA, Youssef GJ, Hagg LJ, et al. Associations between maternal psychological distress and mother-infant bonding: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Arch Womens Ment Health. 2023;26(4):441-452. doi:10.1007/s00737-023-01332-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00737-023-01332-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Penna AL, de Aquino CM, Pinheiro MSN, et al. Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on maternal mental health, early childhood development, and parental practices: a global scoping review. BMC Public Health. 2023;23(1):388. doi:10.1186/s12889-023-15003-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12889-023-15003-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Michaelson V, Pilato KA, Davison CM. Family as a health promotion setting: a scoping review of conceptual models of the health-promoting family. PLoS One. 2021;16(4):e0249707. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0249707.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0249707</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corrigan CP, Kwasky AN, Groh CJ. Social support, postpartum depression, and professional assistance: a survey of mothers in the midwestern United States. J Perinat Educ. 2015;24(1):48-60. doi:10.1891/1058-1243.24.1.48.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1891/1058-1243.24.1.48</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scala M, Marchman VA, Brignoni-Pérez E, Morales MC, Dubner SE, Travis KE. Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on developmental care practices for infants born preterm. Early Hum Dev. 2021;163:105483. doi:10.1016/j.earlhumdev.2021.105483.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.earlhumdev.2021.105483</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dunham MM, Marin T. NICU maternal-infant bonding: virtual visitation as a bonding enhancement tool. J Perinat Neonatal Nurs. 2020;34(2):171-177. doi:10.1097/JPN.0000000000000484.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/JPN.0000000000000484</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davies SM, Silverio SA, Christiansen P, Fallon V. Maternal-infant bonding and perceptions of infant temperament: the mediating role of maternal mental health. J Affect Disord. 2021;282:1323-1329. doi:10.1016/j.jad.2021.01.023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2021.01.023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kostenzer J, Hoffmann J, von Rosenstiel-pulver C, Walsh A, Zimmermann LJI, Mader S. Neonatal care during the COVID-19 pandemic—a global survey of parents experiences regarding infant and family-centred developmental care. EClinicalMedicine. 2021;39:101056. doi:10.1016/j.eclinm.2021.101056.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2021.101056</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holmes EA, O’Connor RC, Perry VH, et al. Multidisciplinary research priorities for the COVID-19 pandemic: a call for action for mental health science. Lancet Psychiatry. 2020;7(6):547-560. doi:10.1016/S2215-0366(20)30168-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2215-0366(20)30168-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>