<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39435081</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2405-8440</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>19</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>15</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Heliyon</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Heliyon</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Prevalence, duration, and factors influencing post-COVID conditions among patients at several public hospitals, Alexandria governorate, Egypt 2022-2023.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e38764</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e38764</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e38764</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e38764</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Post-COVID conditions (PCC), characterized by persistent symptoms following acute infection, represent an emerging chronic illness that potentially affects millions of people worldwide. SARS-CoV-2 infection has resulted in a PCC incidence ranging from 10 to 30 % in non-hospitalized individuals to 50-70 % in hospitalized patients. Most PCC patients experience mild symptoms, while a minority report severe manifestations. We aimed to estimate the prevalence of PCC among COVID-19 patients who attended three public hospitals in Alexandria, Egypt between June 2022 and February 2023, and to investigate its risk factors.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">All COVID-19-confirmed patients aged &gt;18 years attended the selected hospitals, and their household contacts were contacted. Data were collected through telephone interviews using a questionnaire adapted from World Health Organization (WHO) and Penn Medicine tools, covering demographics, COVID-19 history, and PCC symptoms. PCC was defined as symptoms starting three months after the post-acute infection and lasting for at least two months beyond. Statistical analyses employed descriptive statistics, chi-square tests, and a logistic regression model, with a significance level of p &lt; 0.05.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A total of 1546 patients were enrolled. Their mean age was 39.7 ± 15.9 years, 46.0 % were males, and 13.9 % had comorbidities. Of them, 760 patients (49.2 %) reported PCC symptoms including, 52.6 % seen at outpatients, 26.7 % were admitted, and 0.5 % required admission to ICU. PCC symptoms included shortness of breath (94.2 %), mood changes (13.9 %), cough (13.0 %), and fatigue (8.8 %). PCC was associated with older age, hospitalization during acute COVID-19, comorbidities including asthma, hypertension, and diabetes, as well as treatment with different COVID-19 medications. Logistic regression shows that asthma, male gender, and treatment with medicines at the hospital remained significant in the model (ORs: 6.85, 0.36, and 0.88, p &lt; 0.001).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This study sheds light on PCC's prevalence and influencing factors following infection in Alexandria, Egypt. Common PCC symptoms included difficulty in breathing, fatigue, and psychological manifestations. The findings emphasize the critical need for early intervention and targeted management strategies, especially for high-risk groups such as asthma patients, to alleviate the long-term health consequences of COVID-19. Study results could guide the prevention of PCC e.g., through vaccination, management of long-term sequelae of PCC e.g., rehabilitation, and psychological support initiatives.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ashmawy</LastName><ForeName>Rasha</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Health Affairs Directorate, Ministry of Health and Population, 21554, Alexandria, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>El-Maradny</LastName><ForeName>Yousra A</ForeName><Initials>YA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pharmaceutical and Fermentation Industries Development Centre (PFIDC), the City of Scientific Research and Technological Applications (SRTA-City), New Borg El-Arab, 21934, Alexandria, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tahio</LastName><ForeName>Amira</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Health Affairs Directorate, Ministry of Health and Population, 21554, Alexandria, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Afifi</LastName><ForeName>Salma</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Ministry of Health and Population Consultant, Cairo, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Samy</LastName><ForeName>Sahar</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Preventive Medicine and Public Health Sector, Ministry of Health and Population, Cairo, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>BahaaEldin</LastName><ForeName>Hala</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Preventive Medicine and Public Health Sector, Ministry of Health and Population, Cairo, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gaber</LastName><ForeName>Nahla</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Health Affairs Directorate, Ministry of Health and Population, 21554, Alexandria, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abdelwahab</LastName><ForeName>Ibrahim A</ForeName><Initials>IA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, Faculty of Pharmacy, Pharos University, Alexandria, Egypt.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>30</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Heliyon</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101672560</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2405-8440</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Long-term adverse effects of COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Post-COVID conditions</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Prevalence</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Risk factors</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Social factors</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>28</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39435081</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11492249</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e38764</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2405-8440(24)14795-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (WHO)  Coronavirus disease (COVID-19): post COVID-19 condition. 2023. https://www.who.int/news-room/questions-and-answers/item/coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-post-covid-19-condition?gclid=Cj0KCQjw8NilBhDOARIsAHzpbLAts3vtR80kx_2CzD_X_c7rQkgbWiN-rheB_RZk5B0z5iAMQiEkQp4aAiRYEALw_wcB [accessed on 2023 Jul 19]. Available from:</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nalbandian A., Desai A.D., Wan E.Y. Annual review of medicine post-COVID-19 condition. Annu. Rev. Med. 2023;74(1):55–64.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35914765</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashmawy R., Hammouda E.A., El-Maradny Y.A., Aboelsaad I., Hussein M., Uversky V.N., Redwan E.M. Interplay between comorbidities and long COVID: challenges and multidisciplinary approaches. Biomolecules. 2024;14(7):835. doi: 10.3390/biom14070835.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/biom14070835</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11275036</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39062549</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salamanna F., Veronesi F., Martini L., Landini M.P., Fini M. Post-COVID-19 syndrome: the persistent symptoms at the post-viral stage of the disease. A systematic review of the current data. Front. Med. 2021 May 4;8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8129035</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34017846</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsampasian V., Elghazaly H., Chattopadhyay R., Debski M., Naing T.K.P., Garg P., et al. Risk factors associated with post-COVID-19 condition A systematic review and meta-analysis. JAMA Intern. Med. 2023 Jun 5;183(6)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10037203</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36951832</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nalbandian A., Sehgal K., Gupta A., Madhavan M.V., McGroder C., Stevens J.S., et al. Post-acute COVID-19 syndrome. Nat. Med. 2021 Apr;27(4):601–615.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8893149</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33753937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Center for disease control and prevention (CDC) Post-COVID Conditions: Information for Healthcare Providers. 2022 [accessed on 2023 Aug 5]. Available from: https://archive.cdc.gov/www_cdc_gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/clinical-care/post-covid-conditions.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen C., Haupert S.R., Zimmermann L., Shi X., Fritsche L.G., Mukherjee B. Global prevalence of post-coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) condition or long covid: a meta-analysis and systematic review. JID (J. Infect. Dis.) 2022 Nov 1;226(9):1593–1607.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9047189</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35429399</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdelhafiz A.S., Ali A., Maaly A.M., Mahgoub M.A., Ziady H.H., Sultan E.A. Predictors of post-COVID symptoms in Egyptian patients: drugs used in COVID-19 treatment are incriminated. PLoS One. 2022 Mar 31;17(3)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8970499</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35358268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gamal D.M., Ibrahim R.A., Samaan S.F. Post COVID-19 syndrome in a prospective cohort study of Egyptian patients. Egyptian Rheumatology and Rehabilitation. 2022 Dec;49(1):12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soriano J.B., Murthy S., Marshall J.C., Relan P., Diaz J.V. A clinical case definition of post-COVID-19 condition by a Delphi consensus. Lancet Infect. Dis. 2022 Apr 1;22(4):e102–e107.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8691845</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34951953</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (WHO)  Global COVID-19 clinical platform case report Form (CRF) for post COVID condition (post COVID-19 CRF) 2023. https://www.who.int/teams/health-care-readiness-clinical-unit/covid-19/data-platform [accessed on 2023 Aug 5]. Available from:</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Penn Medicine  Post-covid assessment and recovery clinic. 2023. https://www.pennmedicine.org/for-health-care-professionals/for-physicians/covid-information/post-covid19-assessment-and-recovery-clinic-at-penn [accessed on 2024 Jul 11]. Available from:</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Powers I.I.I.J.H., Howard K., Saretsky T., Clifford S., Hoffmann S., Llorens L., Talbot G. Patient-reported outcome assessments as endpoints in studies in infectious diseases. Clin. Infect. Dis. 2016 Aug 15;63(suppl_2):S52–S56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5006216</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27481954</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arjun M.C., Singh A.K., Roy P., Ravichandran M., Mandal S., Pal D., Das K., Gajjala A., Venkateshan M., Mishra B., Patro B.K. Long COVID following Omicron wave in Eastern India—a retrospective cohort study. J. Med. Virol. 2023 Jan;95(1)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9874641</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36224705</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tenforde M.W. Symptom duration and risk factors for delayed return to usual health among outpatients with COVID-19 in a multistate health care systems network—United States. MMWR. Morbidity and mortality weekly report. 2020;69(30):P993.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7392393</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32730238</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Förster C., Colombo M.G., Wetzel A.J., Martus P., Joos S. Persisting symptoms after COVID-19: prevalence and risk factors in a population-based cohort. Deutsches Ärzteblatt International. 2022 Mar;119(10):167.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9215272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35236547</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alghamdi S.A., Alfares M.A., Alsulami R.A., Alghamdi A.F., Almalawi A.M., Alghamdi M.S., Hazazi H.A. Post-COVID-19 syndrome: incidence, risk factor, and the most common persisting symptoms. Cureus. 2022 Nov;14(11)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9802640</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36600841</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Todt B.C., Szlejf C., Duim E., Linhares A.O., Kogiso D., Varela G., Campos B.A., Fonseca C.M., Polesso L.E., Bordon I.N., Cabral B.T. Clinical outcomes and quality of life of COVID-19 survivors: a follow-up of 3 months post hospital discharge. Respir. Med. 2021 Aug 1;184</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8116128</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34010740</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiong Q., Xu M., Li J., Liu Y., Zhang J., Xu Y., Dong W. Clinical sequelae of COVID-19 survivors in Wuhan, China: a single-centre longitudinal study. Clin. Microbiol. Infection. 2021 Jan 1;27(1):89–95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7510771</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32979574</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saheb Sharif-Askari F., Ali Hussain, Alsayed H., Saheb Sharif-Askari N., Saddik B., Al Sayed, Hussain A., Halwani R. Risk factors and early preventive measures for long COVID in non-hospitalized patients: analysis of a large cohort in the United Arab Emirates. Publ. Health. 2024 May 1;230:198–206.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38574425</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Aly Z., Xie Y., Bowe B. High-dimensional characterization of post-acute sequelae of COVID-19. Nature. 2021 Jun 10;594(7862):259–264.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33887749</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Townsend L., Dyer A.H., Jones K., Dunne J., Mooney A., Gaffney F., O'Connor L., Leavy D., O'Brien K., Dowds J., Sugrue J.A. Persistent fatigue following SARS-CoV-2 infection is common and independent of severity of initial infection. PLoS One. 2020 Nov 9;15(11)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7652254</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33166287</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie Y., Choi T., Al-Aly Z. Association of treatment with nirmatrelvir and the risk of post-COVID-19 condition. JAMA Intern. Med. 2023 Jun 5;183(6):554–564.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10037200</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36951829</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cabrera Martimbianco A.L., Pacheco R.L., Bagattini Â.M., Riera R. Frequency, signs and symptoms, and criteria adopted for long COVID‐19: a systematic review. Int. J. Clin. Pract. 2021 Oct;75(10)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8236920</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33977626</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ha T.V., Asada T., Arimura M. Changes in mobility amid the COVID-19 pandemic in Sapporo City, Japan: an investigation through the relationship between spatiotemporal population density and urban facilities. Transp. Res. Interdiscip. Perspect. 2023 Jan 1:17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9790881</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36590070</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>