<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39434905</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1663-9812</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>15</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Frontiers in pharmacology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Front Pharmacol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Diacerein reduces inflammasome activation and SARS-CoV-2 virus replication: a proof-of-concept translational study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1402032</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1402032</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1402032</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3389/fphar.2024.1402032</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) is linked to high mortality, primarily through an intense inflammatory response. Diacerein has emerged as a potential therapy for COVID-19 due to its potential impact in decreasing the inflammasome activation and coronavirus replication. This study aims to explore diacerein's influence in inhibiting both viral replication and the inflammatory response after SARS-CoV-2 infection.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Human peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) were obtained from healthy volunteers and infected <i>in vitro</i> with SARS-CoV-2. Additionally, we carried out a pilot randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study with 14 participants allocated to diacerein (n = 7) or placebo (n = 7) therapies every 12 h for 10 days. The primary endpoint was change in plasma markers of inflammasome activation (NLRP3, caspase-1, and gasdermin-D).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED"><i>In vitro</i> protocols have shown that rhein, diacerein's primary metabolite, decreased IL-1β secretion caused by SARS-CoV-2 infection in human PBMCs (<i>p</i> &lt; 0.05), and suppressed viral replication when administered either before or after the virus incubation (<i>p</i> &lt; 0.05). This later effect was, at least partially, attributed to its inhibitory effect on 3-chymotrypsin-like protease (SARS-CoV-2 3CL<sup>pro</sup>) and papain-like protease in the SARS-CoV-2 (SARS-CoV-2 PL<sup>pro</sup>) virus and in the phosphorylation of proteins related cytoskeleton network (<i>p</i> &lt; 0.05). Diacerein-treated COVID-19 patients presented a smaller area under the curve for NLRP3, caspase-1 and GSDM-D measured on days 2, 5, and 10 after hospitalization compared to those receiving a placebo (<i>p</i> &lt; 0.05).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The indicated mechanisms of action of diacerein/rhein can reduce viral replication and mitigate the inflammatory response related to SARS-CoV-2. These findings are preliminary and require confirmation in clinical trials.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Carmo, Castillo, Bonilha, Gomes, Barreto, Moura, Davanzo, de Brito Monteiro, Muraro, Fabiano de Souza, Morari, Galdino, Brunetti, Reis-de-Oliveira, Carregari, Nadruz, Martins-de-Souza, Farias, Velloso, Proenca-Modena, Mori, Loh, Bhatt, Yellon, Davidson, De Oliveira, Moraes-Vieira and Sposito.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Carmo</LastName><ForeName>Helison R P</ForeName><Initials>HRP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Vascular Biology and Atherosclerosis (Aterolab), State University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Castillo</LastName><ForeName>Alejandro Rossel</ForeName><Initials>AR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Vascular Biology and Atherosclerosis (Aterolab), State University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bonilha</LastName><ForeName>Isabella</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Vascular Biology and Atherosclerosis (Aterolab), State University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gomes</LastName><ForeName>Erica I L</ForeName><Initials>EIL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Vascular Biology and Atherosclerosis (Aterolab), State University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Barreto</LastName><ForeName>Joaquim</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Vascular Biology and Atherosclerosis (Aterolab), State University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Moura</LastName><ForeName>Filipe A</ForeName><Initials>FA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Brigham and Women's Hospital, Division of Cardiovascular Medicine, Brigham and Women's Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>TIMI Study Group, Division of Cardiovascular Medicine, Brigham and Women's Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Davanzo</LastName><ForeName>Gustavo Gastão</ForeName><Initials>GG</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Immunometabolism, Department of Genetics, Evolution, Microbiology and Immunology, Institute of Biology, University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>de Brito Monteiro</LastName><ForeName>Lauar</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Immunometabolism, Department of Genetics, Evolution, Microbiology and Immunology, Institute of Biology, University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Muraro</LastName><ForeName>Stéfanie Primon</ForeName><Initials>SP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Emerging Viruses, Department of Genetics, Microbiology and Immunology, Institute of Biology, University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fabiano de Souza</LastName><ForeName>Gabriela</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Emerging Viruses, Department of Genetics, Microbiology and Immunology, Institute of Biology, University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Morari</LastName><ForeName>Joseane</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Cell Signaling, Obesity and Comorbidities Research Center, University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Galdino</LastName><ForeName>Flávia Elisa</ForeName><Initials>FE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Chemistry, University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Brazilian Synchrotron Light Laboratory (LNLS), Brazilian Center for Research in Energy and Materials (CNPEM), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Brunetti</LastName><ForeName>Natália S</ForeName><Initials>NS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Autoimmune Research Laboratory, Department of Genetics, Microbiology and Immunology, Institute of Biology, University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Reis-de-Oliveira</LastName><ForeName>Guilherme</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Neuroproteomics, Institute of Biology, University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Carregari</LastName><ForeName>Victor Corasolla</ForeName><Initials>VC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Neuroproteomics, Institute of Biology, University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nadruz</LastName><ForeName>Wilson</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Vascular Biology and Atherosclerosis (Aterolab), State University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Martins-de-Souza</LastName><ForeName>Daniel</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Cell Signaling, Obesity and Comorbidities Research Center, University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Neuroproteomics, Institute of Biology, University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>D'Or Institute for Research and Education (IDOR), São Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Experimental Medicine Research Cluster (EMRC), University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Farias</LastName><ForeName>Alessandro S</ForeName><Initials>AS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Cell Signaling, Obesity and Comorbidities Research Center, University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Autoimmune Research Laboratory, Department of Genetics, Microbiology and Immunology, Institute of Biology, University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Experimental Medicine Research Cluster (EMRC), University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Velloso</LastName><ForeName>Licio A</ForeName><Initials>LA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Cell Signaling, Obesity and Comorbidities Research Center, University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Proenca-Modena</LastName><ForeName>José Luiz</ForeName><Initials>JL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Emerging Viruses, Department of Genetics, Microbiology and Immunology, Institute of Biology, University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Experimental Medicine Research Cluster (EMRC), University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mori</LastName><ForeName>Marcelo A</ForeName><Initials>MA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Cell Signaling, Obesity and Comorbidities Research Center, University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Experimental Medicine Research Cluster (EMRC), University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Aging Biology, Department of Biochemistry and Tissue Biology, Institute of Biology, University of Campinas, Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Loh</LastName><ForeName>Watson</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Chemistry, University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bhatt</LastName><ForeName>Deepak L</ForeName><Initials>DL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Mount Sinai Fuster Heart Hospital, Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai, New York, NY, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yellon</LastName><ForeName>Derek M</ForeName><Initials>DM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Hatter Cardiovascular Institute, University College London, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Davidson</LastName><ForeName>Sean M</ForeName><Initials>SM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Hatter Cardiovascular Institute, University College London, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>De Oliveira</LastName><ForeName>Pedro G</ForeName><Initials>PG</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Instituto de Ortopedia e Traumatologia, Hospital das Clinicas HCFMUSP, Faculdade de Medicina, Universidade de São Paulo (USP), São Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sport Traumatology Group, Department of Orthopaedics and Traumatology, Santa Casa de São Paulo School of Medical Sciences, São Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Moraes-Vieira</LastName><ForeName>Pedro M</ForeName><Initials>PM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Immunometabolism, Department of Genetics, Evolution, Microbiology and Immunology, Institute of Biology, University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Cell Signaling, Obesity and Comorbidities Research Center, University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Experimental Medicine Research Cluster (EMRC), University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sposito</LastName><ForeName>Andrei C</ForeName><Initials>AC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Vascular Biology and Atherosclerosis (Aterolab), State University of Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Front Pharmacol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101548923</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1663-9812</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">clinical trial</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">diacerein</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pre-clinical</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">rhein</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>DB discloses the following relationships - Advisory Board: Angiowave, Bayer, Boehringer Ingelheim, CellProthera, Cereno Scientific, Elsevier Practice Update Cardiology, High Enroll, Janssen, Level Ex, McKinsey, Medscape Cardiology, Merck, MyoKardia, NirvaMed, Novo Nordisk, PhaseBio, PLx Pharma, Stasys; Board of Directors: American Heart Association New York City, Angiowave (stock options), Bristol Myers Squibb (stock), DRS.LINQ (stock options), High Enroll (stock); Consultant: Broadview Ventures, GlaxoSmithKline, Hims, SFJ, Youngene; Data Monitoring Committees: Acesion Pharma, Assistance Publique-Hô pitaux de Paris, Baim Institute for Clinical Research (formerly Harvard Clinical Research Institute, for the PORTICO trial, funded by St. Jude Medical, now Abbott), Boston Scientific (Chair, PEITHO trial), Cleveland Clinic, Contego Medical (Chair, PERFORMANCE 2), Duke Clinical Research Institute, Mayo Clinic, Mount Sinai School of Medicine (for the ENVISAGE trial, funded by Daiichi Sankyo; for the ABILITY-DM trial, funded by Concept Medical; for ALLAY-HF, funded by Alleviant Medical), Novartis, Population Health Research Institute; Rutgers University (for the NIH-funded MINT Trial); Honoraria: American College of Cardiology (Senior Associate Editor, Clinical Trials and News, ACC.org; Chair, ACC Accreditation Oversight Committee), Arnold and Porter law firm (work related to Sanofi/Bristol-Myers Squibb clopidogrel litigation), Baim Institute for Clinical Research (formerly Harvard Clinical Research Institute; RE-DUAL PCI clinical trial steering committee funded by Boehringer Ingelheim; AEGIS-II executive committee funded by CSL Behring), Belvoir Publications (Editor in Chief, Harvard Heart Letter), Canadian Medical and Surgical Knowledge Translation Research Group (clinical trial steering committees), CSL Behring (AHA lecture), Cowen and Company, Duke Clinical Research Institute (clinical trial steering committees, including for the PRONOUNCE trial, funded by Ferring Pharmaceuticals), HMP Global (Editor in Chief, Journal of Invasive Cardiology), Journal of the American College of Cardiology (Guest Editor; Associate Editor), K2P (Co-Chair, interdisciplinary curriculum), Level Ex, Medtelligence/ReachMD (CME steering committees), MJH Life Sciences, Oakstone CME (Course Director, Comprehensive Review of Interventional Cardiology), Piper Sandler, Population Health Research Institute (for the COMPASS operations committee, publications committee, steering committee, and United States national co-leader, funded by Bayer), WebMD (CME steering committees), (steering committee); Other: Clinical Cardiology (Deputy Editor); Patent: Sotagliflozin (named on a patent for sotagliflozin assigned to Brigham and Women' s Hospital who assigned to Lexicon; neither I nor Brigham and Women' s Hospital receive any income from this patent); Research Funding: Abbott, Acesion Pharma, Afimmune, Aker Biomarine, Alnylam, Amarin, Amgen, AstraZeneca, Bayer, Beren, Boehringer Ingelheim, Boston Scientific, Bristol-Myers Squibb, Cardax, CellProthera, Cereno Scientific, Chiesi, CinCor, Cleerly, CSL Behring, Eisai, Ethicon, Faraday Pharmaceuticals, Ferring Pharmaceuticals, Forest Laboratories, Fractyl, Garmin, HLS Therapeutics, Idorsia, Ironwood, Ischemix, Janssen, Javelin, Lexicon, Lilly, Medtronic, Merck, Moderna, MyoKardia, NirvaMed, Novartis, Novo Nordisk, Otsuka, Owkin, Pfizer, PhaseBio, PLx Pharma, Recardio, Regeneron, Reid Hoffman Foundation, Roche, Sanofi, Stasys, Synaptic, The Medicines Company, Youngene, 89Bio; Royalties: Elsevier (Editor, Braunwald’s Heart Disease); Site Co-Investigator: Abbott, Biotronik, Boston Scientific, CSI, Endotronix, St. Jude Medical (now Abbott), Philips, SpectraWAVE, Svelte, Vascular Solutions; Trustee: American College of Cardiology; Unfunded Research: FlowCo. AS discloses the following relationships - Research Funding: Amgen, AstraZeneca, National Council for Scientific and Technological Development (CNPq) and Fundaç and#227; o de Apoio and#224; Pesquisa do Estado de Sã o Paulo (FAPESP). Dr. Pedro Gonç alves de Oliveira is responsible for R&amp;D activities at TRB Pharma Indú stria Quí mica e Farmace utica Ltda, SP, Brazil. TRB Pharma is the owner of the product ARTRODAR® a diacerein-based product for osteoarthritis treatment. The remaining authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>49</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39434905</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11491754</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fphar.2024.1402032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">1402032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Alcantara L. C. J., Nogueira E., Shuab G., Tosta S., Fristch H., Pimentel V., et al. (2022). SARS-CoV-2 epidemic in Brazil: how the displacement of variants has driven distinct epidemic waves. Virus Res. 315, 198785. 10.1016/j.virusres.2022.198785</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.virusres.2022.198785</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9022374</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35461905</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aminpour M., Hameroff S., Tuszynski J. A. (2022). How COVID-19 hijacks the cytoskeleton: therapeutic implications. Life (Basel, Switzerland) 12 (6), 814. 10.3390/life12060814</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/life12060814</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9225596</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35743845</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Basu A., Sarkar A., Maulik U. (2020). Molecular docking study of potential phytochemicals and their effects on the complex of SARS-CoV2 spike protein and human ACE2. Sci. Rep. 10 (1), 17699. 10.1038/s41598-020-74715-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-74715-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7573581</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33077836</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Codo A. C., Davanzo G. G., Monteiro L. B., de Souza G. F., Muraro S. P., Virgilio-da-Silva J. V., et al. (2020). Elevated glucose levels favor SARS-CoV-2 infection and monocyte response through a HIF-1α/Glycolysis-Dependent Axis. Cell Metab. 32, 498–499. 10.1016/j.cmet.2020.07.015</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2020.07.015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7462530</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32877692</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>da Costa L. S., Outlioua A., Anginot A., Akarid K., Arnoult D. (2019). RNA viruses promote activation of the NLRP3 inflammasome through cytopathogenic effect-induced potassium efflux. Cell Death Dis. 10 (5), 346. 10.1038/s41419-019-1579-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41419-019-1579-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6483999</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31024004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Oliveira P. G., Termini L., Durigon E. L., Lepique A. P., Sposito A. C., Boccardo E. (2020). Diacerein: a potential multi-target therapeutic drug for COVID-19. Med. hypotheses 144, 109920. 10.1016/j.mehy.2020.109920</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.mehy.2020.109920</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7263256</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32534337</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Distler U., Kuharev J., Navarro P., Tenzer S. (2016). Label-free quantification in ion mobility-enhanced data-independent acquisition proteomics. Nat. Protoc. 11 (4), 795–812. 10.1038/nprot.2016.042</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nprot.2016.042</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27010757</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dominguez I., Cruz-Gamero J. M., Corasolla V., Dacher N., Rangasamy S., Urbani A., et al. (2021). Okur-Chung neurodevelopmental syndrome-linked CK2α variants have reduced kinase activity. Hum. Genet. 140 (7), 1077–1096. 10.1007/s00439-021-02280-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00439-021-02280-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33944995</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Falavigna M., Belli K. C., Barbosa A. N., Zavascki A. P., Nastri A., Santana C. M., et al. (2022). Brazilian guidelines for the treatment of outpatients with suspected or confirmed COVID-19. A joint guideline of the Brazilian association of emergency medicine (abramede), Brazilian medical association (amb), Brazilian society of angiology and vascular surgery (sbacv), Brazilian society of geriatrics and gerontology (sbgg), Brazilian society of infectious diseases (SBI), Brazilian society of family and community medicine (sbfmc), and Brazilian thoracic society (sbpt). Braz J. Infect. Dis. 26 (2), 102347. 10.1016/j.bjid.2022.102347</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bjid.2022.102347</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8926872</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35341739</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hammond J., Leister-Tebbe H., Gardner A., Abreu P., Bao W., Wisemandle W., et al. (2022). Oral nirmatrelvir for high-risk, nonhospitalized adults with covid-19. New England J. Med. 386 (15), 1397–1408. 10.1056/NEJMoa2118542</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2118542</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8908851</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35172054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Henamayee S., Banik K., Sailo B. L., Shabnam B., Harsha C., Srilakshmi S., et al. (2020). Therapeutic emergence of rhein as a potential anticancer drug: a review of its molecular targets and anticancer properties. Molecules 25 (10), 2278. 10.3390/molecules25102278</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/molecules25102278</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7288145</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32408623</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ho T. Y., Wu S. L., Chen J. C., Li C. C., Hsiang C. Y. (2007). Emodin blocks the SARS coronavirus spike protein and angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 interaction. Antivir. Res. 74 (2), 92–101. 10.1016/j.antiviral.2006.04.014</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.antiviral.2006.04.014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7114332</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16730806</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kazmierski J., Friedmann K., Postmus D., Emanuel J., Fischer C., Jansen J., et al. (2022). Nonproductive exposure of PBMCs to SARS-CoV-2 induces cell-intrinsic innate immune responses. Mol. Syst. Biol. 18 (8), e10961. 10.15252/msb.202210961</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15252/msb.202210961</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9382356</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35975552</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan M. T., Irfan M., Ahsan H., Ahmed A., Kaushik A. C., Khan A. S., et al. (2021). Structures of SARS-CoV-2 RNA-binding proteins and therapeutic targets. Intervirology 64 (2), 55–68. 10.1159/000513686</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000513686</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7900486</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33454715</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Z., Li L. J., Sun Y., Li J. (2007). Identification of natural compounds with anti-hepatitis B virus activity from Rheum palmatum L. ethanol extract. Chemotherapy 53 (5), 320–326. 10.1159/000107690</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000107690</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17785969</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu M., Wang L., Wu X., Gao K., Wang F., Cui J., et al. (2021). Rhein protects 5/6 nephrectomized rat against renal injury by reducing inflammation via NF-κB signaling. Int. Urol. Nephrol. 53 (7), 1473–1482. 10.1007/s11255-020-02739-w</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11255-020-02739-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33763781</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lukhna K., do Carmo H. R. P., Castillo A. R., Davidson S. M., Geffen H., Giesz S., et al. (2022). Effect of remote ischaemic conditioning on the inflammatory cytokine cascade of COVID-19 (RIC in COVID-19): a randomized controlled trial. Cardiovasc. Drugs Ther. 38, 433–445. 10.1007/s10557-022-07411-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10557-022-07411-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9707178</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36445625</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malathi K., Siddiqui M. A., Dayal S., Naji M., Ezelle H. J., Zeng C., et al. (2014). RNase L interacts with Filamin A to regulate actin dynamics and barrier function for viral entry. mBio 5 (6), e02012. 10.1128/mBio.02012-14</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/mBio.02012-14</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4217177</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25352621</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manunta M. D. I., Lamorte G., Ferrari F., Trombetta E., Tirone M., Bianco C., et al. (2021). Impact of SARS-CoV-2 infection on the recovery of peripheral blood mononuclear cells by density gradient. Sci. Rep. 11 (1), 4904. 10.1038/s41598-021-83950-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-83950-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7921094</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33649400</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moustaqil M., Ollivier E., Chiu H. P., Van Tol S., Rudolffi-Soto P., Stevens C., et al. (2021). SARS-CoV-2 proteases PLpro and 3CLpro cleave IRF3 and critical modulators of inflammatory pathways (NLRP12 and TAB1): implications for disease presentation across species. Emerg. Microbes Infect. 10 (1), 178–195. 10.1080/22221751.2020.1870414</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/22221751.2020.1870414</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7850364</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33372854</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nalbandian A., Sehgal K., Gupta A., Madhavan M. V., McGroder C., Stevens J. S., et al. (2021). Post-acute COVID-19 syndrome. Nat. Med. 27 (4), 601–615. 10.1038/s41591-021-01283-z</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41591-021-01283-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8893149</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33753937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ng M. L., Lee J. W., Leong M. L., Ling A. E., Tan H. C., Ooi E. E. (2004). Topographic changes in SARS coronavirus-infected cells at late stages of infection. Emerg. Infect. Dis. 10 (11), 1907–1914. 10.3201/eid1011.040195</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3201/eid1011.040195</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3328989</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15550199</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Owczarek K., Szczepanski A., Milewska A., Baster Z., Rajfur Z., Sarna M., et al. (2018). Early events during human coronavirus OC43 entry to the cell. Sci. Rep. 8 (1), 7124. 10.1038/s41598-018-25640-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-25640-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5940804</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29740099</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan P., Shen M., Yu Z., Ge W., Chen K., Tian M., et al. (2021). SARS-CoV-2 N protein promotes NLRP3 inflammasome activation to induce hyperinflammation. Nat. Commun. 12 (1), 4664. 10.1038/s41467-021-25015-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-25015-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8329225</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34341353</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pandey K. P., Zhou Y. (2022). Influenza A virus infection activates NLRP3 inflammasome through trans-golgi network dispersion. Viruses. 14 (1), 88. 10.3390/v14010088</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/v14010088</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8778788</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35062292</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodrigues T. S., de Sa K. S. G., Ishimoto A. Y., Becerra A., Oliveira S., Almeida L., et al. (2021). Inflammasomes are activated in response to SARS-CoV-2 infection and are associated with COVID-19 severity in patients. J. Exp. Med. 218 (3), e20201707. 10.1084/jem.20201707</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1084/jem.20201707</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7684031</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33231615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tirupula K. C., Ithychanda S. S., Mohan M. L., Naga Prasad S. V., Qin J., Karnik S. S. (2015). G protein-coupled receptors directly bind filamin A with high affinity and promote filamin phosphorylation. Biochemistry 54 (44), 6673–6683. 10.1021/acs.biochem.5b00975</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.biochem.5b00975</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4642222</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26460884</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torina A. G., Reichert K., Lima F., de Souza Vilarinho K. A., de Oliveira P. P., do Carmo H. R., et al. (2015). Diacerein improves left ventricular remodeling and cardiac function by reducing the inflammatory response after myocardial infarction. PloS one 10 (3), e0121842. 10.1371/journal.pone.0121842</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121842</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4376692</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25816098</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vora S. M., Lieberman J., Wu H. (2021). Inflammasome activation at the crux of severe COVID-19. Nat. Rev. Immunol. 21 (11), 694–703. 10.1038/s41577-021-00588-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41577-021-00588-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8351223</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34373622</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Q. W., Su Y., Sheng J. T., Gu L. M., Zhao Y., Chen X. X., et al. (2018). Anti-influenza A virus activity of rhein through regulating oxidative stress, TLR4, Akt, MAPK, and NF-κB signal pathways. PloS one 13 (1), e0191793. 10.1371/journal.pone.0191793</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0191793</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5791991</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29385192</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wen Z., Zhang Y., Lin Z., Shi K., Jiu Y. (2020). Cytoskeleton-a crucial key in host cell for coronavirus infection. J. Mol. Cell Biol. 12 (12), 968–979. 10.1093/jmcb/mjaa042</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jmcb/mjaa042</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7454755</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32717049</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO (2020). A minimal common outcome measure set for COVID-19 clinical research. Lancet Infect. Dis. 20 (8), e192–e197. 10.1016/S1473-3099(20)30483-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(20)30483-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7292605</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32539990</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng J., Xie X., Feng X. L., Xu L., Han J. B., Yu D., et al. (2022). Specific inhibition of the NLRP3 inflammasome suppresses immune overactivation and alleviates COVID-19 like pathology in mice. EBioMedicine 75, 103803. 10.1016/j.ebiom.2021.103803</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ebiom.2021.103803</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8719059</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34979342</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao C., Zhao W. (2020). NLRP3 inflammasome-A key player in antiviral responses. Front. Immunol. 11, 211. 10.3389/fimmu.2020.00211</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2020.00211</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7040071</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32133002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou Y., Gao C., Vong C. T., Tao H., Li H., Wang S., et al. (2022). Rhein regulates redox-mediated activation of NLRP3 inflammasomes in intestinal inflammation through macrophage-activated crosstalk. Br. J. Pharmacol. 179 (9), 1978–1997. 10.1111/bph.15773</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/bph.15773</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34882785</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu W., Xu M., Chen C. Z., Guo H., Shen M., Hu X., et al. (2020). Identification of SARS-CoV-2 3CL protease inhibitors by a quantitative high-throughput screening. ACS Pharmacol. Transl. Sci. 3 (5), 1008–1016. 10.1021/acsptsci.0c00108</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsptsci.0c00108</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7507806</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33062953</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>