<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39447244</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1618-0631</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>263</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>27</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Pathology, research and practice</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Pathol Res Pract</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Impact of genetic variations of gene involved in regulation of metabolism, inflammation and coagulation on pathogenesis of cardiac injuries associated with COVID-19.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>155608</StartPage><MedlinePgn>155608</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.prp.2024.155608</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0344-0338(24)00519-3</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">SARS-CoV-2 infection can result in long-term chronic cardiovascular (CV) damage after the acute phase of the illness. COVID-19 frequently causes active myocarditis, SARS-CoV-2 can directly infect and kill cardiac cells, causing severe pathology and dysfunction across the organs and cells. Till now, the pathogenesis of COVID-19-associated cardiac injuries has not been understood, but there are several factors that contribute to the progression of cardiac injuries, such as genetic, dietary, and environmental. Among them ranges of host genetic factor including metabolizing, inflammation, and coagulation related genes have a role to contribute the cardiac injuries induced by COVID-19. Hereditary DNA sequence variations contribute to the risk of illness in almost all of these diseases. Hence, we comprehended the occurrence of genetic variations of metabolizing, inflammation and coagulation-related genes in the general population, their expression in various diseases, and their impact on cardiac injuries induced by COVID-19.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHOD" NlmCategory="METHODS">We utilized multiple databases, including PubMed (Medline), EMBASE, and Google Scholar, for literature searches.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DESCRIPTION" NlmCategory="METHODS">The genes involved in metabolism (APOE, MTHFR), coagulation (PAI-1, ACE2), and immune factors (CRP, ESR, and troponin I) may have a role in the progression of COVID-19-associated cardiac injuries. The risk factors for CVD are significantly varied between and within different regions. In healthy individuals, the ACE I allele is responsible for the predisposition to CAD, but the ACE D haplotype is responsible for susceptibility and severity, which ultimately leads to heart failure. Patients who carry the T allele of rs12329760 in the TMPRSS2 gene are at risk for developing the severe form of COVID-19. IL-6 (rs1800796/rs1800795) polymorphism is associated with an increased mortality rate and susceptibility to severe COVID-19 disease. While the putative role of IL-6 associated with chronic, inflammatory diseases like cardiac and cerebrovascular disease is well known.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The occurrence of genetic variations in the ACE-2, AGT, DPP-IV, TMPRSS2, FUIRN, IL-4, IL-6, IFN-γ, and CYP2D6 genes is varied among different populations. Examining the correlation between these variations and their protein levels and cardiac injuries induced by COVID-19 may provide valuable insights into the pathogenesis of cardiac injuries induced by COVID-19.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier GmbH. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Singh</LastName><ForeName>HariOm</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Molecular Biology, National AIDS Research Institute, Pune 411026, India. Electronic address: hariomsgpgims@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nair</LastName><ForeName>Aishwarya</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Molecular Biology, National AIDS Research Institute, Pune 411026, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mahajan</LastName><ForeName>Supriya D</ForeName><Initials>SD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, Jacobs School of Medicine &amp; Biomedical Sciences, University at Buffalo's Clinical Translational Research Center, 875 Ellicott Street, Buffalo, NY 14203, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Pathol Res Pract</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7806109</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0344-0338</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19-associated cardiac injuries</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Coagulation genes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Immune factors</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Inflammatory diseases</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Metabolizing gene</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of Competing Interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39447244</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.prp.2024.155608</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0344-0338(24)00519-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>