<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39446756</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1473-6527</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Current opinion in infectious diseases</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Curr Opin Infect Dis</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Antiviral combination treatment strategies for SARS-CoV-2 infection in immunocompromised patients.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/QCO.0000000000001070</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="PURPOSE OF REVIEW" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">The purpose of this review is to report the available evidence regarding the use of combination regimens of antivirals and/or antibody-based therapy in the treatment of SARS-CoV-2 in immunocompromised patients.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RECENT FINDINGS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Literature search identified 24 articles, excluding single case reports, which included mainly patients with hematological malignancies and/or B-cell depletion. Data were divided based on the timing and reason for administration of combination treatment, that is, early treatment to prevent progression to severe COVID-19 and treatment of prolonged or relapsed infection. We described the treated populations, treatment duration and composition of combination treatment. We briefly addressed new treatment options and we proposed an algorithm for the management of COVID-19 infection in patients affected by hematological malignancies.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="SUMMARY" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Combination treatment seems an effective (73-100%) and well tolerated (&lt;5% reported bradycardia, hepatotoxicity, neutropenia) strategy for treating prolonged/relapsed SARS-CoV-2 infections in the immunocompromised host, although its optimal composition and duration cannot be defined based on the currently available evidence. The role of combination treatment as an early treatment strategy for immunocompromised patients at a high risk of progression to severe disease/persistent shedding requires further evidence from comparison with monotherapy, even though high efficacy was reported for combinations of antivirals plus mAbs in case of previous viral variants.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sepulcri</LastName><ForeName>Chiara</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases, Department of Health Sciences (DISSAL), University of Genova.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bartalucci</LastName><ForeName>Claudia</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases, Department of Health Sciences (DISSAL), University of Genova.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>IRCCS Ospedale Policlinico San Martino, Genova, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mikulska</LastName><ForeName>Malgorzata</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases, Department of Health Sciences (DISSAL), University of Genova.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>IRCCS Ospedale Policlinico San Martino, Genova, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Curr Opin Infect Dis</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8809878</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0951-7375</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39446756</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/QCO.0000000000001070</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00001432-990000000-00191</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Evans RA, Dube S, Lu Y, et al. Impact of COVID-19 on immunocompromised populations during the Omicron era: insights from the observational population-based INFORM study. Lancet Reg Health Eur 2023; 35:100747.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blennow O, Salmanton-García J, Nowak P, et al. Outcome of infection with omicron SARS-CoV-2 variant in patients with hematological malignancies: an EPICOVIDEHA survey report. Am J Hematol 2022; 97:E312–E317.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raglow Z, Surie D, Chappell JD, et al. SARS-CoV-2 shedding and evolution in patients who were immunocompromised during the omicron period: a multicentre, prospective analysis. Lancet Microbe 2024; 5:e235–e246.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Belkin A, Leibowitz A, Shargian L, Yahav D. The unique presentation of SARS-CoV-2 Infection in patients with B-cell depletion: definition of ‘persistent inflammatory sero-negative COVID’. Clin Microbiol Infect 2023; 29:1–3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanchez E, Krantz EM, Yoke L, et al. Clinical outcomes and frequency of persistent infection among immunosuppressed patients treated with bebtelovimab for COVID-19 infection at an ambulatory cancer center. Transpl Infect Dis 2024; 26:e14223.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gandhi S, Klein J, Robertson AJ, et al. De novo emergence of a remdesivir resistance mutation during treatment of persistent SARS-CoV-2 infection in an immunocompromised patient: a case report. Nat Commun 2022; 13:1547.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garcia-Vidal C, Iglesias-Caballero M, Puerta-Alcalde P, et al. Emergence of progressive mutations in SARS-CoV-2 from a hematologic patient with prolonged viral replication. Front Microbiol 2022; 13:826883.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmadi AS, Zadheidar S, Sadeghi K, et al. SARS-CoV-2 intrahost evolution in immunocompromised patients in comparison with immunocompetent populations after treatment. J Med Virol 2023; 95:e28877.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zuckerman NS, Bucris E, Keidar-Friedman D, et al. Nirmatrelvir resistance—de novo E166 V/L50 V mutations in an immunocompromised patient treated with prolonged nirmatrelvir/ritonavir monotherapy leading to clinical and virological treatment failure: a case report. Clin Infect Dis 2023; ciad494.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Machkovech HM, Hahn AM, Garonzik Wang J, et al. Persistent SARS-CoV-2 infection: significance and implications. Lancet Infect Dis 2024; 24:e453–e462.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>El Chaer F, Auletta JJ, Chemaly RF. How I treat and prevent COVID-19 in patients with hematologic malignancies and recipients of cellular therapies. Blood 2022; 140:673–684.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Markov PV, Ghafari M, Beer M, et al. The evolution of SARS-CoV-2. Nat Rev Microbiol 2023; 21:361–379.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 Treatment Guidelines Panel. Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) Treatment Guidelines. National Institutes of Health. https://www.covid19treatmentguidelines.nih.gov/. [Accessed June 2024].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karniadakis I, Mazonakis N, Tsioutis C, et al. Oral molnupiravir and nirmatrelvir/ritonavir for the treatment of COVID-19: a literature review with a focus on real-world evidence. Infect Dis Rep 2023; 15:662–678.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kabinger F, Stiller C, Schmitzová J, et al. Mechanism of molnupiravir-induced SARS-CoV-2 mutagenesis. Nat Struct Mol Biol 2021; 28:740–746.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li P, Wang Y, Lavrijsen M, et al. SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant is highly sensitive to molnupiravir, nirmatrelvir, and the combination. Cell Res 2022; 32:322–324.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gidari A, Sabbatini S, Schiaroli E, et al. Synergistic activity of remdesivir-nirmatrelvir combination on a SARS-CoV-2 in vitro model and a case report. Viruses 2023; 15:1577.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bloch EM, Focosi D, Shoham S, et al. Guidance on the use of convalescent plasma to treat immunocompromised patients with Coronavirus disease 2019. Clin Infect Dis 2023; 76:2018–2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Misset B, Piagnerelli M, Hoste E, et al. Convalescent plasma for Covid-19-induced ARDS in mechanically ventilated patients. N Engl J Med 2023; 389:1590–1600.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ripoll JG, Tulledge-Scheitel SM, Stephenson AA, et al. Outpatient treatment with concomitant vaccine-boosted convalescent plasma for patients with immunosuppression and COVID-19. mBio 2024; 15:e0040024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dioverti MV, Gaston DC, Morris CP, et al. Combination therapy with casirivimab/imdevimab and remdesivir for protracted SARS-CoV-2 infection in B-cell-depleted patients. Open Forum Infect Dis 2022; 9:ofac064.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ford ES, Simmons W, Karmarkar EN, et al. Successful treatment of prolonged, severe Coronavirus disease 2019 lower respiratory tract disease in a B cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia patient with an extended course of remdesivir and nirmatrelvir/ritonavir. Clin Infect Dis 2023; 76:926–929.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trottier CA, Wong B, Kohli R, et al. Dual antiviral therapy for persistent Coronavirus disease 2019 and associated organizing pneumonia in an immunocompromised host. Clin Infect Dis 2023; 76:923–925.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wada D, Nakamori Y, Maruyama S, et al. Novel treatment combining antiviral and neutralizing antibody-based therapies with monitoring of spike-specific antibody and viral load for immunocompromised patients with persistent COVID-19 infection. Exp Hematol Oncol 2022; 11:53.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cesaro S, Mikulska M, Hirsch HH, et al. Update of recommendations for the management of COVID-19 in patients with haematological malignancies, haematopoietic cell transplantation and CAR T therapy, from the 2022 European Conference on Infections in Leukaemia (ECIL 9). Leukemia 2023; 37:1933–1938.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moriello NS, Buonomo AR, Scotto R, et al. Casirivimab/imdevimab + remdesivir in hospitalized patients with severe Covid-19: a single centre experience. Heliyon 2023; 9:e13126.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calderón-Parra J, Gutiérrez-Villanueva A, Ronda-Roca G, et al. Efficacy and safety of antiviral plus antispike monoclonal antibody combination therapy vs. monotherapy for high-risk immunocompromised patients with mild-to-moderate SARS-CoV2 infection during the Omicron era: a prospective cohort study. Int J Antimicrob Agents 2024; 63:107095.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gentile I, Foggia M, Silvitelli M, et al. Optimizing COVID-19 treatment in immunocompromised patients: early combination therapy with remdesivir, nirmatrelvir/ritonavir and sotrovimab. Virol J 2023; 20:301.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rotundo S, Berardelli L, Gullì S, et al. Early initiation of combined therapy in severely immunocompromised patients with COVID-19: a retrospective cohort study. BMC Infect Dis 2024; 24:564.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bavaro DF, Diella L, Belati A, et al. Efficacy of remdesivir and neutralizing monoclonal antibodies in monotherapy or combination therapy in reducing the risk of disease progression in elderly or immunocompromised hosts hospitalized for COVID-19: a single center retrospective study. Viruses 2023; 15:1199.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orth HM, Flasshove C, Berger M, et al. Early combination therapy of COVID-19 in high-risk patients. Infection 2024; 52:877–889.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scotto R, Buonomo AR, Iuliano A, et al. Remdesivir alone or in combination with monoclonal antibodies as an early treatment to prevent severe COVID-19 in patients with mild/moderate disease at high risk of progression: a single centre, real-life study. Vaccines (Basel) 2023; 11:200.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Magyari F, Pinczés LI, Páyer E, et al. Early administration of remdesivir plus convalescent plasma therapy is effective to treat COVID-19 pneumonia in B-cell depleted patients with hematological malignancies. Ann Hematol 2022; 101:2337–2345.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biscarini S, Villa S, Genovese C, et al. Safety profile and outcomes of early COVID-19 treatments in immunocompromised patients: a single-centre cohort study. Biomedicines 2022; 10:2002.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mikulska M, Testi D, Russo C, et al. Outcome of early treatment of SARS-CoV-2 infection in patients with haematological disorders. Br J Haematol 2023; 201:628–639.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lahouati M, Cazanave C, Labadie A, et al. Outcomes of targeted treatment in immunocompromised patients with asymptomatic or mild COVID-19: a retrospective study. Sci Rep 2023; 13:15357.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tadmor T, Alapi H, Rokach L. Effectiveness of nirmatrelvir plus ritonavir treatment for patients with chronic lymphocytic leukemia during the Omicron Surge. Blood 2023; 141:2239–2244.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Focosi D, Maggi F, D’Abramo A, et al. Antiviral combination therapies for persistent COVID-19 in immunocompromised patients. Int J Infect Dis 2023; 137:55–59.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Choudhary MC, Regan J, et al. SARS-CoV-2 viral clearance and evolution varies by type and severity of immunodeficiency. Sci Transl Med 2024; 16:eadk1599.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lanzafame M, Gottardi M, Guella L, et al. Successful treatment of persistent SARS-CoV-2 infection with nirmatrelvir/ritonavir plus sotrovimab in four immunocompromised patients. J Chemother 2023; 35:623–626.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hettle D, Hutchings S, Muir P, Moran E. Persistent SARS-CoV-2 infection in immunocompromised patients facilitates rapid viral evolution: Retrospective cohort study and literature review. Clin Infect Pract 2022; 16:100210.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dioverti V, Salto-Alejandre S, Haidar G. Immunocompromised patients with protracted COVID-19: a review of ‘Long Persisters’. Curr Transplant Rep 2022; 9:209–218.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herrera S, Aguado JM, Candel FJ, et al. Executive summary of the consensus statement of the group for the study of infection in transplantation and other immunocompromised host (GESITRA-IC) of the Spanish Society of Infectious Diseases and Clinical Microbiology (SEIMC) on the treatment of SARS-CoV-2 infection in solid organ transplant recipients. Transplant Rev 2023; 37:100788.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown L-AK, Moran E, Goodman A, et al. Treatment of chronic or relapsing COVID-19 in immunodeficiency. J Allergy Clin Immunol 2022; 149:557–561.e1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huygens S, Gharbharan A, Serroukh Y, et al. High-titer convalescent plasma plus nirmatrelvir/ritonavir treatment for nonresolving COVID-19 in six immunocompromised patients. J Antimicrob Chemother 2023; 78:1644–1648.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pasquini Z, Toschi A, Casadei B, et al. Dual combined antiviral treatment with remdesivir and nirmatrelvir/ritonavir in patients with impaired humoral immunity and persistent SARS-CoV-2 infection. Hematol Oncol 2023; 41:904–911.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blennow O, Vesterbacka J, Tovatt T, Nowak P. Successful combination treatment for persistent severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 infection. Clin Infect Dis 2023; 76:1864–1865.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Longo BM, Venuti F, Gaviraghi A, et al. Sequential or combination treatments as rescue therapies in immunocompromised patients with persistent SARS-CoV-2 infection in the Omicron era: a case series. Antibiotics 2023; 12:1460.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meijer SE, Halutz O, Adler A, et al. Dual antiviral treatment for persistent COVID-19 in immunocompromised hemato-oncological patients is associated with a favorable prognosis and minor side effects. J Infect Chemother 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Segura Fábrega A, Pérez Catalán I, Gómez Alfaro I, et al. Association of nirmatrelvir/ritonavir and remdesivir as treatment for SARS-CoV-2 infection in immunocompromised patients with hematologic malignancies. Series of four cases. Rev Esp Quimioter 2023; 36:655–657.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Götz V, Mathé P, Agarwal P, et al. Clinical phenotype and outcome of persistent SARS-CoV-2 replication in immunocompromised hosts: a retrospective observational study in the Omicron era. Infection 2024; 52:923–933.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faxén L, Edvinsson M. Persistent SARS-CoV-2 infection in patients with B-cell deficiency: a case series of successful antiviral treatment of four patients. Ups J Med Sci 2023; 128: doi: 10.48101/ujms.v128.9807.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.48101/ujms.v128.9807</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>D’Abramo A, Vita S, Maffongelli G, et al. Clinical management of patients with B-cell depletion agents to treat or prevent prolonged and severe SARS-COV-2 infection: defining a treatment pathway. Front Immunol 2022; 13:911339.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D’Abramo A, Vita S, Beccacece A, et al. B-cell-depleted patients with persistent SARS-CoV-2 infection: combination therapy or monotherapy? A real-world experience. Front Med 2024; 11:1344267.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brosh-Nissimov T, Ma’aravi N, Leshin-Carmel D, et al. Combination treatment of persistent COVID-19 in immunocompromised patients with remdesivir, nirmaltrevir/ritonavir and tixegavimab/cilgavimab. J Microbiol Immunol Infect 2024; 57:189–194.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mikulska M, Sepulcri C, Dentone C, et al. Triple combination therapy with 2 antivirals and monoclonal antibodies for persistent or relapsed severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 infection in immunocompromised patients. Clin Infect Dis 2023; 77:280–286.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yotsuyanagi H, Ohmagari N, Doi Y, et al. Efficacy and safety of 5-day oral ensitrelvir for patients with mild to moderate COVID-19: the SCORPIO-SR randomized clinical trial. JAMA Netw Open 2024; 7:e2354991.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>AstraZeneca. Sipavibart EMA regulatory submission accepted under accelerated assessment for COVID-19 prevention [Press Release]. n.d. [Accessed 5 July 2024].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Casadevall A, Focosi D, Pirofski L, Shoham S. Single monoclonal antibodies should not be used for Coronavirus disease 2019 therapy: a call for antiviral stewardship. Clin Infect Dis 2024; ciae408.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papadopoulou A, Karavalakis G, Papadopoulou E, et al. SARS-CoV-2-specific T cell therapy for severe COVID-19: a randomized phase 1/2 trial. Nat Med 2023; 29:2019–2029.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vasileiou S, Hill L, Kuvalekar M, et al. Allogeneic, off-the-shelf, SARS-CoV-2-specific T cells (ALVR109) for the treatment of COVID-19 in high-risk patients. Haematologica 2023; 108:1840–1850.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choi MH, Wan EYF, Wong ICK, et al. Comparative effectiveness of combination therapy with nirmatrelvir-ritonavir and remdesivir versus monotherapy with remdesivir or nirmatrelvir-ritonavir in patients hospitalised with COVID-19: a target trial emulation study. Lancet Infect Dis 2024.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>