<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39449289</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1573-2665</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of inherited metabolic disease</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Inherit Metab Dis</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Exploring RNA therapeutics for urea cycle disorders.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jimd.12807</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>RNA has triggered a significant shift in modern medicine, providing a promising way to revolutionize disease treatment methods. Different therapeutic RNA modalities have shown promise to replace, supplement, correct, suppress, or eliminate the expression of a targeted gene. Currently, there are 22 RNA-based drugs approved for clinical use, including the COVID-19 mRNA vaccines, whose unprecedented worldwide success has meant a definitive boost in the RNA research field. Urea cycle disorders (UCD), liver diseases with high mortality and morbidity, may benefit from the progress achieved, as different genetic payloads have been successfully targeted to liver using viral vectors, N-acetylgalactosamine (GalNAc) conjugations or lipid nanoparticles (LNP). This review explores the potential of RNA-based medicines for UCD and the ongoing development of applications targeting specific gene defects, enzymes, or transporters taking part in the urea cycle. Notably, LNP-formulated mRNA therapy has been assayed preclinically for citrullinemia type I (CTLN1), adolescent and adult citrin deficiency, argininosuccinic aciduria, arginase deficiency and ornithine transcarbamylase deficiency, in the latter case has progressed to the clinical trials phase.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Journal of Inherited Metabolic Disease published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of SSIEM.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Richard</LastName><ForeName>Eva</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9711-1417</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centro de Biología Molecular Severo Ochoa UAM-CSIC, IUBM, CIBERER, IdiPaz, Universidad Autónoma de Madrid, Madrid, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Martínez-Pizarro</LastName><ForeName>Ainhoa</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centro de Biología Molecular Severo Ochoa UAM-CSIC, IUBM, CIBERER, IdiPaz, Universidad Autónoma de Madrid, Madrid, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Desviat</LastName><ForeName>Lourdes R</ForeName><Initials>LR</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0492-3323</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centro de Biología Molecular Severo Ochoa UAM-CSIC, IUBM, CIBERER, IdiPaz, Universidad Autónoma de Madrid, Madrid, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>PID2022-137238OB-100</GrantID><Agency>MICIU/AEI</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><Agency>ERDF</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Inherit Metab Dis</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7910918</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0141-8955</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antisense oligonucleotides</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mRNA therapy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ornithine transcarbamylase deficiency</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pseudoexon</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">splicing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">urea cycle</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39449289</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jimd.12807</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Ah Mew N, Simpson KL, Gropman AL, et al. Urea cycle disorders overview. In: Adam MP, Feldman J, Mirzaa GM, et al., eds. GeneReviews®. University of Washington; 1993.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duff C, Alexander IE, Baruteau J. Gene therapy for urea cycle defects: An update from historical perspectives to future prospects. J Inherit Metab Dis. 2024;47:50‐62. doi:10.1002/jimd.12609</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Androsavich JR. Frameworks for transformational breakthroughs in RNA‐based medicines. Nat Rev Drug Discov. 2024;23:421‐444. doi:10.1038/s41573‐024‐00943‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oude Blenke E, Schiffelers RM, Mastrobattista E. Oligonucleotides and mRNA therapeutics. In: Crommelin DJA, Sindelar RD, Meibohm B, eds. Pharmaceutical Biotechnology: Fundamentals and Applications. Springer International Publishing; 2024:291‐321.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Villiger L, Joung J, Koblan L, Weissman J, Abudayyeh OO, Gootenberg JS. CRISPR technologies for genome, epigenome and transcriptome editing. Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol. 2024;25:464‐487. doi:10.1038/s41580‐023‐00697‐6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khvorova A, Watts JK. The chemical evolution of oligonucleotide therapies of clinical utility. Nat Biotechnol. 2017;35:238‐248. doi:10.1038/nbt.3765</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sahin U, Karikó K, Türeci Ö. mRNA‐based therapeutics—developing a new class of drugs. Nat Rev Drug Discov. 2014;13:759‐780. doi:10.1038/nrd4278</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Belgrad J, Fakih HH, Khvorova A. Nucleic acid therapeutics: successes, milestones, and upcoming innovation. Nucleic Acid Ther. 2024;34:52‐72. doi:10.1089/nat.2023.0068</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hammond SM, Aartsma‐Rus A, Alves S, et al. Delivery of oligonucleotide‐based therapeutics: challenges and opportunities. EMBO mol Med. 2021;13:e13243. doi:10.15252/emmm.202013243</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Callaway E, Naddaf M. Pioneers of mRNA COVID vaccines win medicine Nobel. Nature. 2023;622:228‐229. doi:10.1038/d41586‐023‐03046‐x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prakash TP, Graham MJ, Yu J, et al. Targeted delivery of antisense oligonucleotides to hepatocytes using triantennary N‐acetyl galactosamine improves potency 10‐fold in mice. Nucleic Acids Res. 2014;42:8796‐8807. doi:10.1093/nar/gku531</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akinc A, Querbes W, De S, et al. Targeted delivery of RNAi therapeutics with endogenous and exogenous ligand‐based mechanisms. Mol Ther. 2010;18:1357‐1364. doi:10.1038/mt.2010.85</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gebhardt R, Matz‐Soja M. Liver zonation: novel aspects of its regulation and its impact on homeostasis. World J Gastroenterol. 2014;20:8491‐8504. doi:10.3748/wjg.v20.i26.8491</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Truong B, Allegri G, Liu X‐B, et al. Lipid nanoparticle‐targeted mRNA therapy as a treatment for the inherited metabolic liver disorder arginase deficiency. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2019;116:21150‐21159. doi:10.1073/pnas.1906182116</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamazaki K, Kubara K, Ishii S, et al. Lipid nanoparticle‐targeted mRNA formulation as a treatment for ornithine‐transcarbamylase deficiency model mice. Mol Ther Nucleic Acids. 2023;33:210‐226. doi:10.1016/j.omtn.2023.06.023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prieve MG, Harvie P, Monahan SD, et al. Targeted mRNA therapy for ornithine transcarbamylase deficiency. Mol Ther. 2018;26:801‐813. doi:10.1016/j.ymthe.2017.12.024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martinez‐Pizarro A, Desviat LR. RNA solutions to treat inborn errors of metabolism. Mol Genet Metab. 2022;136:289‐295. doi:10.1016/j.ymgme.2022.07.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kp A, Kaliaperumal K, Sekar D. microRNAs and their therapeutic strategy in phase I and phase II clinical trials. Epigenomics. 2024;16:259‐271. doi:10.2217/epi‐2023‐0363</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koeberl D, Schulze A, Sondheimer N, et al. Interim analyses of a first‐in‐human phase 1/2 mRNA trial for propionic acidaemia. Nature. 2024;628:872‐877. doi:10.1038/s41586‐024‐07266‐7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoon S, Rossi JJ. Therapeutic potential of small activating RNAs (saRNAs) in human cancers. Curr Pharm Biotechnol. 2018;19:604‐610. doi:10.2174/1389201019666180528084059</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Albers S, Allen EC, Bharti N, et al. Engineered tRNAs suppress nonsense mutations in cells and in vivo. Nature. 2023;618:842‐848. doi:10.1038/s41586‐023‐06133‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gillmore JD, Gane E, Taubel J, et al. CRISPR‐Cas9 in vivo gene editing for transthyretin amyloidosis. N Engl J Med. 2021;385:493‐502. doi:10.1056/NEJMoa2107454</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jalil S, Keskinen T, Juutila J, et al. Genetic and functional correction of argininosuccinate lyase deficiency using CRISPR adenine base editors. Am J Hum Genet. 2024;111:714‐728. doi:10.1016/j.ajhg.2024.03.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Longhurst HJ, Lindsay K, Petersen RS, et al. CRISPR‐Cas9 in vivo gene editing of KLKB1 for hereditary angioedema. N Engl J Med. 2024;390:432‐441. doi:10.1056/NEJMoa2309149</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Villiger L, Rothgangl T, Witzigmann D, et al. In vivo cytidine base editing of hepatocytes without detectable off‐target mutations in RNA and DNA. Nat Biomed Eng. 2021;5:179‐189. doi:10.1038/s41551‐020‐00671‐z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baruteau J, Brunetti‐Pierri N, Gissen P. Liver‐directed gene therapy for inherited metabolic diseases. J Inherit Metab Dis. 2024;47:9‐21. doi:10.1002/jimd.12709</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crooke ST, Baker BF, Crooke RM, Liang X‐H. Antisense technology: an overview and prospectus. Nat Rev Drug Discov. 2021;20:427‐453. doi:10.1038/s41573‐021‐00162‐z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Havens MA, Hastings ML. Splice‐switching antisense oligonucleotides as therapeutic drugs. Nucleic Acids Res. 2016;44:6549‐6563. doi:10.1093/nar/gkw533</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuijper EC, Bergsma AJ, Pijnappel WWMP, Aartsma‐Rus A. Opportunities and challenges for antisense oligonucleotide therapies. J Inherit Metab Dis. 2021;44:72‐87. doi:10.1002/jimd.12251</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hodges PE, Rosenberg LE. The spfash mouse: a missense mutation in the ornithine transcarbamylase gene also causes aberrant mRNA splicing. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 1989;86:4142‐4146.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rivera‐Barahona A, Sánchez‐Alcudia R, Viecelli HM, et al. Functional characterization of the spf/ash splicing variation in OTC deficiency of mice and man. PLoS One. 2015;10:e0122966. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0122966</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martínez‐Pizarro A, Leal F, Holm LL, et al. Antisense oligonucleotide Rescue of Deep‐Intronic Variants Activating Pseudoexons in the 6‐Pyruvoyl‐Tetrahydropterin synthase gene. Nucleic Acid Ther. 2022;32:378‐390. doi:10.1089/nat.2021.0066</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perez B, Vilageliu L, Grinberg D, Desviat LR. Antisense mediated splicing modulation for inherited metabolic diseases: challenges for delivery. Nucleic Acid Ther. 2014;24:48‐56. doi:10.1089/nat.2013.0453</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spangsberg Petersen US, Dembic M, Martínez‐Pizarro A, et al. Regulating PCCA gene expression by modulation of pseudoexon splicing patterns to rescue enzyme activity in propionic acidemia. Mol Ther—Nucl Acids. 2024;35:102101. doi:10.1016/j.omtn.2023.102101</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaz‐Drago R, Custodio N, Carmo‐Fonseca M. Deep intronic mutations and human disease. Hum Genet. 2017;136:1093‐1111. doi:10.1007/s00439‐017‐1809‐4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dhir A, Buratti E. Alternative splicing: role of pseudoexons in human disease and potential therapeutic strategies. FEBS J. 2010;277:841‐855.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lykke‐Andersen S, Jensen TH. Nonsense‐mediated mRNA decay: an intricate machinery that shapes transcriptomes. Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol. 2015;16:665‐677. doi:10.1038/nrm4063</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perez B, Rodriguez‐Pascau L, Vilageliu L, et al. Present and future of antisense therapy for splicing modulation in inherited metabolic disease. J Inherit Metab Dis. 2010;33:397‐403. doi:10.1007/s10545‐010‐9135‐1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cummings BB, Marshall JL, Tukiainen T, et al. Improving genetic diagnosis in mendelian disease with transcriptome sequencing. Sci Transl Med. 2017;9:eaal5209. doi:10.1126/scitranslmed.aal5209</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gonorazky HD, Naumenko S, Ramani AK, et al. Expanding the boundaries of RNA sequencing as a diagnostic tool for rare mendelian disease. Am J Hum Genet. 2019;104:1007. doi:10.1016/j.ajhg.2019.04.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Truty R, Ouyang K, Rojahn S, et al. Spectrum of splicing variants in disease genes and the ability of RNA analysis to reduce uncertainty in clinical interpretation. Am J Hum Genet. 2021;108:696‐708. doi:10.1016/j.ajhg.2021.03.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Engel K, Nuoffer JM, Muhlhausen C, et al. Analysis of mRNA transcripts improves the success rate of molecular genetic testing in OTC deficiency. Mol Genet Metab. 2008;94:292‐297. doi:10.1016/j.ymgme.2008.03.009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar RD, Burrage LC, Bartos J, et al. A deep intronic variant is a common cause of OTC deficiency in individuals with previously negative genetic testing. Mol Genet Metab Rep. 2021;26:100706. doi:10.1016/j.ymgmr.2020.100706</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ogino W, Takeshima Y, Nishiyama A, et al. Mutation analysis of the ornithine transcarbamylase (OTC) gene in five Japanese OTC deficiency patients revealed two known and three novel mutations including a deep intronic mutation. Kobe J Med Sci. 2007;53:229‐240.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zabulica M, Srinivasan RC, Akcakaya P, et al. Correction of a urea cycle defect after ex vivo gene editing of human hepatocytes. Mol Ther. 2021;29:1903‐1917. doi:10.1016/j.ymthe.2021.01.024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sangermano R, Garanto A, Khan M, et al. Deep‐intronic ABCA4 variants explain missing heritability in Stargardt disease and allow correction of splice defects by antisense oligonucleotides. Genet Med. 2019;21:1751‐1760. doi:10.1038/s41436‐018‐0414‐9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang F, Zuroske T, Watts JK. RNA therapeutics on the rise. Nat Rev Drug Discov. 2020;19:441‐442. doi:10.1038/d41573‐020‐00078‐0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Damase TR, Sukhovershin R, Boada C, Taraballi F, Pettigrew RI, Cooke JP. The limitless future of RNA therapeutics. Front Bioeng Biotechnol. 2021;9:628137. doi:10.3389/fbioe.2021.628137</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hou X, Zaks T, Langer R, Dong Y. Lipid nanoparticles for mRNA delivery. Nat Rev Mater. 2021;6:1078‐1094. doi:10.1038/s41578‐021‐00358‐0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cao J, An D, Galduroz M, et al. mRNA therapy improves metabolic and behavioral abnormalities in a murine model of Citrin deficiency. Mol Ther. 2019;27:1242‐1251. doi:10.1016/j.ymthe.2019.04.017</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daly O, Mahiny AJ, Majeski S, et al. ASL mRNA‐LNP therapeutic for the treatment of Argininosuccinic aciduria enables survival benefit in a mouse model. Biomedicine. 2023;11:1735. doi:10.3390/biomedicines11061735</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gurung S, Timmermand OV, Perocheau D, et al. mRNA therapy corrects defective glutathione metabolism and restores ureagenesis in preclinical argininosuccinic aciduria. Sci Transl Med. 2024;16:eadh1334. doi:10.1126/scitranslmed.adh1334</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khoja S, Liu X‐B, Truong B, et al. Intermittent lipid nanoparticle mRNA administration prevents cortical dysmyelination associated with arginase deficiency. Mol Ther Nucleic Acids. 2022;28:859‐874. doi:10.1016/j.omtn.2022.04.012</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perocheau D, Gurung S, Touramanidou L, et al. Ex vivo precision‐cut liver slices model disease phenotype and monitor therapeutic response for liver monogenic diseases. F1000Res. 2023;12:1580. doi:10.12688/f1000research.142014.2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu H, Brewer E, Shields M, et al. Restoring ornithine transcarbamylase (OTC) activity in an OTC‐deficient mouse model using LUNAR‐OTC mRNA. Clin Transl Discov. 2022;2:e33. doi:10.1002/ctd2.33</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Y, Wang L, Bell P, et al. A dual AAV system enables the Cas9‐mediated correction of a metabolic liver disease in newborn mice. Nat Biotechnol. 2016;34:334‐338. doi:10.1038/nbt.3469</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee PC, Truong B, Vega‐Crespo A, et al. Restoring ureagenesis in hepatocytes by CRISPR/Cas9‐mediated genomic addition to arginase‐deficient induced pluripotent stem cells. Mol Ther Nucleic Acids. 2016;5:e394. doi:10.1038/mtna.2016.98</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nitzahn M, Truong B, Khoja S, et al. CRISPR‐mediated genomic addition to CPS1 deficient iPSCs is insufficient to restore nitrogen homeostasis. Yale J Biol Med. 2021;94:545‐557.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang L, Yang Y, Breton C, et al. A mutation‐independent CRISPR‐Cas9‐mediated gene targeting approach to treat a murine model of ornithine transcarbamylase deficiency. Sci Adv. 2020;6:eaax5701. doi:10.1126/sciadv.aax5701</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ginn SL, Christina S, Alexander IE. Genome editing in the human liver: Progress and translational considerations. Prog Mol Biol Transl Sci. 2021;182:257‐288. doi:10.1016/bs.pmbts.2021.01.030</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vlatkovic I. Non‐immunotherapy application of LNP‐mRNA: maximizing efficacy and safety. Biomedicine. 2021;9:530. doi:10.3390/biomedicines9050530</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Masarwy R, Stotsky‐Oterin L, Elisha A, Hazan‐Halevy I, Peer D. Delivery of nucleic acid based genome editing platforms via lipid nanoparticles: clinical applications. Adv Drug Deliv Rev. 2024;211:115359. doi:10.1016/j.addr.2024.115359</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adlat S, Vázquez Salgado AM, Lee M, Yin D, Wangensteen KJ. Emerging and potential use of CRISPR in human liver disease. Hepatology. 2023. doi:10.1097/HEP.0000000000000578</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>