<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39446296</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1920-7476</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Canadian journal of public health = Revue canadienne de sante publique</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Can J Public Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Experiences with discrimination during pregnancy in Canada and associations with depression and anxiety symptoms.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.17269/s41997-024-00933-2</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">Experiences of discrimination reported during pregnancy are common and are associated with poor mental health and adverse birth outcomes. No Canadian studies have investigated interpersonal discrimination during pregnancy. This study aimed to quantify and identify lived-experiences of discrimination in a Canadian cohort of pregnant individuals, and examine associations with concurrent prenatal anxiety and depression symptoms.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Pregnant individuals from the pan-Canadian Pregnancy During the Pandemic (PdP) study (n = 1943) completed the Everyday Discrimination Scale (EDS), demographic measures and self-report measures of depression and anxiety symptoms. Descriptive statistics and ANCOVA were used to assess prevalence of discrimination and associated mental health outcomes. Open-text responses (n = 189) to a question investigating reasons for discrimination were analyzed using conventional content analysis.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Approximately three quarters (72%) of pregnant individuals experienced at least one instance of discrimination during their pregnancy or within the year prior. Pregnant individuals experiencing more frequent and/or more types of discrimination were more likely to identify as non-white, not be partnered, have lower socioeconomic status, and have a pre-pregnancy history of anxiety and depression. The most common attributions for interpersonal discrimination were gender, age, and education/income level. Pregnant individuals who experienced more frequent discrimination and/or more types of discrimination were more likely to report clinically significant symptoms of depression and anxiety (n = 623; 35.2% and 49.1%, respectively) compared to those who reported no discrimination (n = 539; 11.5% and 19.1%, respectively). Conventional content analysis of open-text responses generated the following main themes: (1) personal attributes and sociodemographic characteristics, (2) occupation, (3) the COVID-19 pandemic, (4) pregnancy and parenting, and (5) causes outside the self.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Frequent discrimination was associated with more adverse concurrent mental health symptoms. Understanding experiences of discrimination can inform interventions that better address the needs of pregnant individuals and their infants.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s) under exclusive license to The Canadian Public Health Association.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Davis</LastName><ForeName>Kelsey P</ForeName><Initials>KP</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8123-552X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, McGill University, Montreal, QC, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Freeman</LastName><ForeName>Makayla</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4033-1712</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Educational and Counselling Psychology, and Special Education, University of British Columbia, Vancouver, BC, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fazal</LastName><ForeName>Pariza</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychology, University of Calgary, Calgary, AB, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cumming School of Medicine, University of Calgary, Calgary, AB, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Reynolds</LastName><ForeName>Kristin A</ForeName><Initials>KA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5367-7021</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychology, University of Manitoba, Winnipeg, MB, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rioux</LastName><ForeName>Charlie</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7943-0710</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychology, University of Oklahoma, Norman, OK, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Moody</LastName><ForeName>Danielle L Beatty</ForeName><Initials>DLB</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5499-566X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Social Work, Rutgers The State University of New Jersey, New Brunswick, NJ, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lai</LastName><ForeName>Beatrice Pui-Yee</ForeName><Initials>BP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cumming School of Medicine, University of Calgary, Calgary, AB, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Giesbrecht</LastName><ForeName>Gerald F</ForeName><Initials>GF</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7259-0685</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychology, University of Calgary, Calgary, AB, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, University of Calgary, Calgary, AB, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Alberta Children's Hospital Research Institute (ACHRI), Calgary, AB, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Health Sciences, University of Calgary, Calgary, AB, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lebel</LastName><ForeName>Catherine</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0344-4032</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Alberta Children's Hospital Research Institute (ACHRI), Calgary, AB, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiology, University of Calgary, Calgary, AB, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hotchkiss Brain Institute, Calgary, AB, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tomfohr-Madsen</LastName><ForeName>Lianne</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0860-5392</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Educational and Counselling Psychology, and Special Education, University of British Columbia, Vancouver, BC, Canada. lianne.tomfohrmadsen@ubc.ca.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Can J Public Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0372714</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0008-4263</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="fre"><AbstractText>RéSUMé: OBJECTIFS: En plus d’être courantes, les expériences de discrimination déclarées pendant la grossesse sont associées à des problèmes de santé mentale et à des issues défavorables de la grossesse. Aucune étude canadienne ne porte sur la discrimination interpersonnelle pendant la grossesse. Nous avons donc voulu chiffrer et identifier les expériences vécues de discrimination dans une cohorte canadienne de personnes enceintes, puis en étudier les associations avec les symptômes concomitants d’anxiété et de dépression prénatales. MéTHODE: Les personnes enceintes ayant participé à l’étude pancanadienne « Grossesse pendant la pandémie de COVID-19 » (n = 1 943) ont répondu au questionnaire « Échelle de discrimination dans la vie de tous les jours » (EDS) et fourni des indicateurs démographiques et des indicateurs autodéclarés de leurs symptômes de dépression et d’anxiété. Nous avons fait appel à la statistique descriptive et à l’analyse de covariance pour évaluer la prévalence de la discrimination et des résultats de santé mentale associés. Les réponses en texte libre (n = 189) à une question sur les motifs de discrimination ont été analysées au moyen d’une analyse de contenu conventionnelle. RéSULTATS: Environ les trois quarts (72 %) des personnes enceintes avaient vécu au moins un incident de discrimination pendant leur grossesse ou au cours de l’année antérieure. Les personnes enceintes ayant fait l’objet d’une discrimination fréquente ou de plusieurs types étaient plus susceptibles de s’identifier comme étant non-blanches, de ne pas avoir de partenaire, d’être de statut socioéconomique inférieur et d’avoir eu des antécédents d’anxiété et de dépression avant leur grossesse. Les attributs les plus courants de la discrimination interpersonnelle étaient le genre, l’âge et le niveau d’instruction/de revenu. Les personnes enceintes ayant fait l’objet d’une discrimination fréquente ou de plusieurs types étaient plus susceptibles de déclarer des symptômes cliniquement significatifs de dépression et d’anxiété (n = 623; 35,2 % et 49,1 %, respectivement) que les personnes ayant déclaré n’avoir pas fait l’objet de discrimination (n = 539; 11,5 % et 19,1 %, respectivement). L’analyse de contenu conventionnelle des réponses en texte libre a fait ressortir les thèmes suivants : (1) les attributs personnels et les caractéristiques sociodémographiques, (2) la profession, (3) la pandémie de COVID-19, (4) la grossesse et la parentalité et (5) des causes extérieures à soi. CONCLUSION: La discrimination fréquente était associée à des symptômes de problèmes de santé mentale concomitants plus défavorables. La compréhension des expériences de discrimination pourrait éclairer les interventions pour qu’elles répondent mieux aux besoins des personnes enceintes et de leurs nourrissons.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s) under exclusive license to The Canadian Public Health Association.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Anxiety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Depression</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Discrimination</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mental health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pregnancy</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>31</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>31</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39446296</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.17269/s41997-024-00933-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.17269/s41997-024-00933-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>American Psychological Association (APA). (2020, Jan 10). Discrimination: What it is, and how to cope. Retrieved August 14 from https://www.apa.org/topics/racism-bias-discrimination/types-stress . Accessed Sept 2023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bauer, A., Knapp, M., Parsonage, M. (2016). Lifetime costs of perinatal anxiety and depression.  Journal of Affective Disorders, 192, 83–90. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jad.2015.12.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barbosa-Leiker, C., Smith, C. L., Crespi, E. J., Brooks, O., Burduli, E., Ranjo, S., Carty, C. L., Hebert, L. E., Waters, S. F., &amp; Gartstein, M. A. (2021). Stressors, coping, and resources needed during the COVID-19 pandemic in a sample of perinatal women. BMC Pregnancy and Childbirth, 21(1), 171. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12884-021-03665-0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bedaso, A., Adams, J., Peng, W., Xu, F., &amp; Sibbritt, D. (2022). An examination of the association between marital status and prenatal mental disorders using linked health administrative data. BMC Pregnancy and Childbirth, 22(1), 735. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12884-022-05045-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12884-022-05045-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36182904</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9526285</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bennett, I. M., Culhane, J. F., Webb, D. A., Coyne, J. C., Hogan, V., Mathew, L., &amp; Elo, I. T. (2010). Perceived discrimination and depressive symptoms, smoking, and recent alcohol use in pregnancy. Birth (Berkeley, Calif.), 37(2), 90–97. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1523-536X.2010.00388.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1523-536X.2010.00388.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20557531</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bergink, V., Kooistra, L., Lambregtse-van den Berg, M. P., Wijnen, H., Bunevicius, R., van Baar, A., &amp; Pop, V. (2011). Validation of the Edinburgh Depression Scale during pregnancy. Journal of Psychosomatic Research, 70(4), 385–389. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpsychores.2010.07.008</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychores.2010.07.008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21414460</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bower, K. M., Geller, R. J., Jeffers, N., McDonald, M., &amp; Alhusen, J. (2023). Experiences of racism and perinatal depression: Findings from the pregnancy risk assessment monitoring system, 2018. Journal of Advanced Nursing, 79, 1982–1993. https://doi.org/10.1111/jan.15519</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jan.15519</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36630188</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braveman, P. A., Kumanyika, S., Fielding, J., Laveist, T., Borrell, L. N., Mandersheid, R., &amp; Troutman, A. (2011). Health disparities and health equity: The issue is justice. American Journal of Public Health, 101(S1), S149–S155. https://doi.org/10.2105/ajph.2010.300062</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2105/ajph.2010.300062</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21551385</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3222512</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Browne, A. J., Lavoie, J. G., McCallum, M. J. L., &amp; Canoe, C. B. (2022). Addressing anti-Indigenous racism in canadian health systems: Multi-tiered approaches are required. Canadian Journal of Public Health, 113(2), 222–226. https://doi.org/10.17269/s41997-021-00598-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.17269/s41997-021-00598-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35061212</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8975987</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campbell, S. B., Matestic, P., von Stauffenberg, C., Mohan, R., &amp; Kirchner, T. (2007). Trajectories of maternal depressive symptoms, maternal sensitivity, and children’s functioning at school entry. Developmental Psychology, 43(5), 1202. https://doi.org/10.1037/0012-1649.43.5.1202</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/0012-1649.43.5.1202</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17723045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Canady, R. B., Bullen, B. L., Holzman, C., Broman, C., &amp; Tian, Y. (2008). Discrimination and symptoms of depression in pregnancy among African American and White women. Women’s Health Issues, 18(4), 292–300. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.whi.2008.04.003</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.whi.2008.04.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18590883</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2872142</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cella, D., Riley, W., Stone, A., Rothrock, N., Reeve, B., Yount, S., Amtmann, D., Bode, R., Buysse, D., Choi, S., Cook, K., DeVellis, R., DeWalt, D., Fries, J. F., Gershon, R., Hahn, E. A., Lai, J. S., Pilkonis, P., Revicki, D., … PROMIS Cooperative Group. (2010). The patient-reported outcomes measurement information system (PROMIS) developed and tested its first wave of adult self-reported health outcome item banks: 2005-2008. Journal of Clinical Epidemiology, 63(11), 1179–1194.  https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclinepi.2010.04.011</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chalmers, B., Dzakpasu, S., Heaman, M., &amp; Kaczorowski, J. (2008). The Canadian Maternity Experiences Survey: An Overview of Findings. Journal of Obstetrics and Gynaecology Canada, 30(3), 217–228. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1701-2163(16)32758-X</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1701-2163(16)32758-X</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18364099</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cox, J. L., Holden, J. M., &amp; Sagovsky, R. (1987). Detection of postnatal depression. Development of the 10-item Edinburgh Postnatal Depression Scale. British Journal of Psychiatry, 150, 782–786. https://doi.org/10.1192/bjp.150.6.782</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1192/bjp.150.6.782</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dennis, C. L., Falah-Hassani, K., &amp; Shiri, R. (2017). Prevalence of antenatal and postnatal anxiety: systematic review and meta-analysis. British Journal of Psychiatry, 210(5), 315–323. https://doi.org/10.1192/bjp.bp.116.187179</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1192/bjp.bp.116.187179</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fischer, E. H., Dornelas, E. A., &amp; Goethe, J. W. (2001). Characteristics of people lost to attrition in psychiatric follow-up studies. The Journal of Nervous and Mental Disease, 189(1), 49–55. https://doi.org/10.1097/00005053-200101000-00009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/00005053-200101000-00009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11206665</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fox, A. B., &amp; Quinn, D. M. (2015). Pregnant women at work: The role of stigma in predicting women’s intended exit from the workforce. Psychology of Women Quarterly, 39(2), 226–242.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0361684314552653</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Francis, B., Klebanoff, M., &amp; Oza-Frank, R. (2017). Racial discrimination and perinatal sleep quality. Sleep Health, 3(4), 300–305. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.sleh.2017.05.012</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.sleh.2017.05.012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28709519</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freeman, M., Fischer, O., Lebel, C., Giesbrecht, G. F., &amp; Tomfohr-Madsen, L. (2024). Making diversity visible: Collecting gender identity and sexual orientation data in perinatal research. American Journal of Obstetrics and Gynecology, 230(2), 269–271. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajog.2023.09.098</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ajog.2023.09.098</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37788718</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giesbrecht, G. F., Bagshawe, M., van Sloten, M., MacKinnon, A. L., Dhillon, A., van de Wouw, M., Vaghef-Mehrabany, E., Rojas, L., Cattani, D., Lebel, C., &amp; Tomfohr-Madsen, L. (2021). Protocol for the Pregnancy during the COVID-19 Pandemic (PdP) study: A longitudinal cohort study of mental health among pregnant Canadians during the COVID-19 pandemic and developmental outcomes in their children. JMIR Research Protocols, 10(4), e25407. https://doi.org/10.2196/25407</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giurgescu, C., Zenk, S. N., Engeland, C. G., Garfield, L., &amp; Templin, T. N. (2017). Racial Discrimination and Psychological Wellbeing of Pregnant Women. MCN, The American Journal of Maternal Child Nursing, 42(1), 8–13. https://doi.org/10.1097/NMC.0000000000000297</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goldberg, A., Smith, J., &amp; Ross, L. (2020). 4. Postpartum Depression and Anxiety in Male-Partnered and Female-Partnered Sexual Minority Women: A Longitudinal Study. In H. Liu, C. Reczek, &amp; L. Wilkinson (Eds.), Marriage and Health: The Well-Being of Same-Sex Couples (pp. 53–70). Rutgers University Press. https://doi.org/10.36019/9781978803527-007</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.36019/9781978803527-007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goodman, J. S., &amp; Blum, T. C. (1996). Assessing the non-random sampling effects of subject attrition in longitudinal research. Journal of Management, 22(4), 627–652.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/014920639602200405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Government of Canada, Statistics Canada. (2024). Quality of life indicator: Discrimination and unfair-treatment.  https://www160.statcan.gc.ca/good-governance-saine-gouvernance/discrimination-eng.htm# . Accessed Sept 2023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hackney, K. J., Daniels, S. R., Paustian-Underdahl, S. C., Perrewé, P. L., Mandeville, A., &amp; Eaton, A. A. (2021). Examining the effects of perceived pregnancy discrimination on mother and baby health. Journal of Applied Psychology, 106(5), 774–783. https://doi.org/10.1037/apl0000788</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/apl0000788</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32614204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsieh, H., &amp; Shannon, S. E. (2005). Three approaches to qualitative content analysis. Qualitative Health Research, 15(9), 1277–1288. https://doi.org/10.1177/1049732305276687</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1049732305276687</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16204405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaiser, C. R., &amp; Major, B. (2006). A social psychological perspective on perceiving and reporting discrimination. Law &amp; Social Inquiry, 31(4), 801–830.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1747-4469.2006.00036.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kessler, R. C., Mickelson, K. D., &amp; Williams, D. R. (1999). The prevalence, distribution, and mental health correlates of perceived discrimination in the United States. Journal of Health and Social Behavior, 40(3), 208–230.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2307/2676349</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10513145</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kirubarajan, A., Barker, L. C., Leung, S., Ross, L. E., Zaheer, J., Park, B., Abramovich, A., Yudin, M. H., &amp; Lam, J. (2022). LGBTQ2S+ childbearing individuals and perinatal mental health: A systematic review. BJOG: An International Journal of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, 129(10), 1630–1643. https://doi.org/10.1111/1471-0528.17103</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1471-0528.17103</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35048502</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kotlar, B., Gerson, E. M., Petrillo, S., Langer, A., &amp; Tiemeier, H. (2021). The impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on maternal and perinatal health: A scoping review. Reproductive Health, 18(1), 10. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12978-021-01070-6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krieger, N., Smith, K., Naishadham, D., Hartman, C., &amp; Barbeau, E. M. (2005). Experiences of discrimination: Validity and reliability of a self-report measure for population health research on racism and health. Social Science and Medicine, 61(7), 1576–1596. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socscimed.2005.03.006</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2005.03.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16005789</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larrabee Sonderlund, A., Schoenthaler, A., &amp; Thilsing, T. (2021). The Association between maternal experiences of interpersonal discrimination and adverse birth outcomes: a systematic review of the evidence. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, 18(4). https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph18041465</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lebel, C., MacKinnon, A., Bagshawe, M., Tomfohr-Madsen, L., &amp; Giesbrecht, G. (2020). Elevated depression and anxiety symptoms among pregnant individuals during the COVID-19 pandemic. Journal of Affective Disorders, 277, 5–13. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jad.2020.07.126</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2020.07.126</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32777604</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7395614</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>MacGregor, C., Freedman, A., Keenan-Devlin, L., Grobman, W., Wadhwa, P., Simhan, H. N., Buss, C., &amp; Borders, A. (2020). Maternal perceived discrimination and association with gestational diabetes. American Journal of Obstetrics and Gynecology MFM, 2(4), 100222. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajogmf.2020.100222</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ajogmf.2020.100222</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33345930</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Masters, G. A., Asipenko, E., Bergman, A. L., Person, S. D., Brenckle, L., Moore Simas, T. A., Ko, J. Y., Robbins, C. L., &amp; Byatt, N. (2021). Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on mental health, access to care, and health disparities in the perinatal period. Journal of Psychiatric Research, 137, 126–130. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpsychires.2021.02.056</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2021.02.056</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33677216</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8084993</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Michaels, E., Thomas, M., Reeves, A., Price, M., Hasson, R., Chae, D., &amp; Allen, A. (2019). Coding the Everyday Discrimination Scale: Implications for exposure assessment and associations with hypertension and depression among a cross section of mid-life African American women. Journal of Epidemiology and Community Health, 73(6), 577–584. https://doi.org/10.1136/jech-2018-211230</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/jech-2018-211230</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30894420</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miconi, D., Li, Z. Y., Frounfelker, R. L., Santavicca, T., Cénat, J. M., Venkatesh, V., &amp; Rousseau, C. (2020). Ethno-cultural disparities in mental health during the COVID-19 pandemic: A cross-sectional study on the impact of exposure to the virus and COVID-19-related discrimination and stigma on mental health across ethno-cultural groups in Quebec (Canada). BJPsych Open, 7(1), e14. https://doi.org/10.1192/bjo.2020.146</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1192/bjo.2020.146</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33295270</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miconi, D., Li, Z. Y., Frounfelker, R. L., Venkatesh, V., &amp; Rousseau, C. (2021). Socio-cultural correlates of self-reported experiences of discrimination related to COVID-19 in a culturally diverse sample of Canadian adults. International Journal of Intercultural Relations, 81, 176–192. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijintrel.2021.01.013</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijintrel.2021.01.013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36540669</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9754949</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miller, R. B., &amp; Wright, D. W. (1995). Detecting and correcting attrition bias in longitudinal family research. Journal of Marriage and the Family, 57, 921–929.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2307/353412</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mongan, D., Lynch, J., Hanna, D., Shannon, C., Hamilton, S., Potter, C., Gorman, C., McCambridge, O., Morrow, R., &amp; Mulholland, C. (2019). Prevalence of self-reported mental disorders in pregnancy and associations with adverse neonatal outcomes: a population-based cross-sectional study. BMC Pregnancy Childbirth, 19(1), 412. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12884-019-2572-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12884-019-2572-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31703644</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6842147</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morgan, W. B., Walker, S. S., Hebl, M. M., &amp; King, E. B. (2013). A field experiment: Reducing interpersonal discrimination toward pregnant job applicants. Journal of Applied Psychology, 98(5), 799–809. https://doi.org/10.1037/a0034040</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/a0034040</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23957687</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Donnell, K. J., Glover, V., Barker, E. D., &amp; O’Connor, T. G. (2014). The persisting effect of maternal mood in pregnancy on childhood psychopathology. Development and Psychopathology, 26(2), 393–403. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0954579414000029</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0954579414000029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24621564</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Owais, S., Faltyn, M., Johnson, A. V., Gabel, C., Downey, B., Kates, N., &amp; Van Lieshout, R. J. (2020). The perinatal mental health of Indigenous women: A systematic review and meta-analysis. The Canadian Journal of Psychiatry, 65(3), 149–163. https://doi.org/10.1177/0706743719877029</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0706743719877029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31601125</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan-Canadian Public Health Network. (2018). Key health inequalities in Canada: A national portrait (Publication No. 180210). Public Health Agency of Canada. https://www.canada.ca/en/public-health/services/publications/science-research-data/key-health-inequalities-canada-national-portrait-executive-summary.html . Accessed Sept 2023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Potter, L. N., Brondolo, E., &amp; Smyth, J. M. (2019). Biopsychosocial correlates of discrimination in daily life: A review. Stigma and Health, 4(1), 38.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/sah0000120</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32524031</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robinson, A. M., Benzies, K. M., Cairns, S. L., Fung, T., &amp; Tough, S. C. (2016). Who is distressed? A comparison of psychosocial stress in pregnancy across seven ethnicities. BMC Pregnancy and Childbirth, 16, 1–11. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12884-016-1015-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12884-016-1015-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenthal, L., Earnshaw, V. A., Moore, J. M., Ferguson, D. N., Lewis, T. T., Reid, A. E., Lewis, J. B., Stasko, E. C., Tobin, J. N., &amp; Ickovics, J. R. (2018). Intergenerational consequences: women’s experiences of discrimination in pregnancy predict infant social-emotional development at 6 months and 1 year. Journal of Developmental and Behavioral Pediatrics, 39(3), 228–237. https://doi.org/10.1097/dbp.0000000000000529</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/dbp.0000000000000529</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29176360</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5866165</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ross, L. E., Salway, T., Tarasoff, L. A., MacKay, J. M., Hawkins, B. W., &amp; Fehr, C. P. (2018). Prevalence of depression and anxiety among bisexual people compared to gay, lesbian, and heterosexual individuals: A systematic review and meta-analysis. The Journal of Sex Research, 55(4–5), 435–456. https://doi.org/10.1080/00224499.2017.1387755</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/00224499.2017.1387755</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29099625</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmitt, M. T., Branscombe, N. R., Postmes, T., &amp; Garcia, A. (2014). The consequences of perceived discrimination for psychological well-being: A meta-analytic review. Psychological Bulletin, 140(4), 921.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/a0035754</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24547896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Statistics Canada. (2020). Experiences of discrimination during the COVID-19 pandemic. Retrieved September 21 from https://www150.statcan.gc.ca/n1/daily-quotidien/200917/dq200917a-eng.htm . Accessed Sept 2023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Statistics Canada. (2022). Discrimination before and since the start of the pandemic [Report].  https://www150.statcan.gc.ca/n1/en/pub/11-627-m/11-627-m2022021-eng.pdf?st=fCMCwWN0 . Accessed Sept 2023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stein, A., Pearson, R. M., Goodman, S. H., Rapa, E., Rahman, A., McCallum, M., Howard, L. M., &amp; Pariante, C. M. (2014). Effects of perinatal mental disorders on the fetus and child. Lancet, 384(9956), 1800–1819. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(14)61277-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(14)61277-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25455250</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stepanikova, I., &amp; Kukla, L. (2017). Is Perceived Discrimination in Pregnancy Prospectively Linked to Postpartum Depression? Exploring the Role of Education. Maternal and Child Health Journal, 21(8), 1669–1677. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10995-016-2259-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10995-016-2259-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28116534</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5515992</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sternthal, M. J., Slopen, N., &amp; Williams, D. R. (2011). Racial Disparities In Health: How much does stress really matter? Du Bois Review: Social Science Research on Race, 8(1), 95–113. https://doi.org/10.1017/s1742058x11000087</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/s1742058x11000087</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29887911</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thomeer, M. B., Moody, M. D., &amp; Yahirun, J. (2022). Racial and ethnic disparities in mental health and mental health care during the COVID-19 pandemic. Journal of Racial and Ethnic Health Disparities. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40615-022-01284-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40615-022-01284-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35318615</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8939391</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weinstock, M. (2008). The long-term behavioural consequences of prenatal stress. Neuroscience and Biobehavioral Reviews, 32(6), 1073–1086. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neubiorev.2008.03.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2008.03.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18423592</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams, D. R., &amp; Mohammed, S. A. (2009). Discrimination and racial disparities in health: Evidence and needed research. Journal of Behavioral Medicine, 32(1), 20–47. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10865-008-9185-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10865-008-9185-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19030981</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams, D. R., Yan, Y., Jackson, J. S., &amp; Anderson, N. B. (1997). Racial differences in physical and mental health: socio-economic status, stress and discrimination. J Health Psychol, 2(3), 335–351. https://doi.org/10.1177/135910539700200305</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/135910539700200305</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22013026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, K., Wu, J., &amp; Chen, X. (2022). Risk factors of perinatal depression in women: A systematic review and meta-analysis. BMC Psychiatry, 22(1), 63. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12888-021-03684-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12888-021-03684-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35086502</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8793194</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>