<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39443982</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1472-6920</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>24</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC medical education</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Med Educ</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>How COVID-19 pandemic and Ukrainian crisis shaped mental health services for medical students in Poland?</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1201</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1201</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1201</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12909-024-06224-1</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The mental health of medical students is a crucial concern in contemporary medical education. This manuscript reports the availability and shape of psychological support for medical students in Poland in the backdrop of the COVID-19 pandemic and the Ukrainian crisis. A survey comprising 10 questions was distributed to 22 medical schools in Poland, with a 59% response rate. The findings reveal that psychological support programs are predominantly managed by internal university units. Funding sources vary, with some universities utilizing internal budgets and others leveraging European funds or external projects. The support modalities are primarily hybrid, catering to student preferences. Limitations exist in the number of consultations, although some universities provide extended support based on student needs. Assistance is offered in multiple languages, with additional programs like stress-reduction workshops and mindfulness training being available in several universities. A notable increase in demand for psychological support post-COVID-19 was reported, with some universities establishing their programs during or after the pandemic. The commentary highlights the rising need for mental health services among medical students and underscores the importance of flexible, inclusive, and well-funded support. The effective functioning of these programs aligns with the broader objective of fostering a resilient and emotionally balanced healthcare workforce.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Guziak</LastName><ForeName>Mateusz</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5720-3410</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Quality of Life Research, Faculty of Health Sciences with the Institute of Maritime and Tropical Medicine, Medical University of Gdańsk, Gdańsk, Poland. mateusz.guziak@gumed.edu.pl.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory for Strengthening Capacity and Performance of Health Systems &amp; Workforce for Health Equity, Faculty of Medicine, University of Belgrade, Belgrade, Serbia. mateusz.guziak@gumed.edu.pl.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Walkiewicz</LastName><ForeName>Maciej</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5674-5875</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Quality of Life Research, Faculty of Health Sciences with the Institute of Maritime and Tropical Medicine, Medical University of Gdańsk, Gdańsk, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Med Educ</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101088679</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1472-6920</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013337" MajorTopicYN="Y">Students, Medical</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011044" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Poland</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008605" MajorTopicYN="Y">Mental Health Services</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000458" MajorTopicYN="N">organization &amp; administration</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000600" MajorTopicYN="N">supply &amp; distribution</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014455" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Ukraine</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008603" MajorTopicYN="N">Mental Health</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011795" MajorTopicYN="N">Surveys and Questionnaires</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Health workforce</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Medical education</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Medical students</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mental health support</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Psychological distress</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39443982</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12909-024-06224-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12909-024-06224-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11515519</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Rajapuram N, Langness S, Marshall MR, Sammann A. Medical students in distress: the impact of gender, race, debt, and disability. PLoS ONE. 2020;15(12 December):1–13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heinen I, Bullinger M, Kocalevent RD. Perceived stress in first year medical students - associations with personal resources and emotional distress. BMC Med Educ. 2017;17(1):1–14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5215143</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28056975</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quek TTC, Tam WWS, Tran BX, Zhang M, Zhang Z, Ho CSH et al. The global prevalence of anxiety among medical students: a meta-analysis. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2019;16(15).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rotenstein LS, Ramos MA, Torre M, Segal JB, Peluso MJ, Guille C, et al. Prevalence of Depression, depressive symptoms, and suicidal ideation among medical students: a systematic review and Meta-analysis. JAMA. 2016;316(21):2214–36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5613659</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27923088</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dyrbye L, Shanafelt T. A narrative review on burnout experienced by medical students and residents. Med Educ. 2016;50(1):132–49.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26695473</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Puthran R, Zhang MWB, Tam WW, Ho RC. Prevalence of depression amongst medical students: a meta-analysis. Med Educ. 2016;50(4):456–68.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26995484</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Voltmer E, Kötter T, Spahn C. Perceived medical school stress and the development of behavior and experience patterns in German medical students. Med Teach. 2012;34(10):840–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22917267</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shao R, He P, Ling B, Tan L, Xu L, Hou Y, et al. Prevalence of depression and anxiety and correlations between depression, anxiety, family functioning, social support and coping styles among Chinese medical students. BMC Psychol. 2020;8(1):1–19.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6941250</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31898551</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Monrad SU, Wolff M, Kurtz J, Deiorio NM, Sabo R, Stringer JK, et al. What is the association between student well-being and high-stakes examination scores? Med Educ. 2021;55(7):872–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33501719</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brady KJS, Trockel MT, Khan CT, Raj KS, Murphy M, Lou, Bohman B, et al. What do we Mean by Physician Wellness? A systematic review of its definition and measurement. Acad Psychiatry. 2018;42(1):94–108.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28913621</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dyrbye LN, Harper W, Durning SJ, Moutier C, Thomas MR, Massie FS, et al. Patterns of distress in US medical students. Med Teach. 2011;33(10):834–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21942482</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haykal KA, Pereira L, Power A, Fournier K. Medical student wellness assessment beyond anxiety and depression: a scoping review. PLoS ONE. 2022;17(10):1–12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Isralowitz R, Khamenka N, Konstantinov V, Gritsenko V, Reznik A, Fear. Depression, Substance Misuse and related conditions among Multi-national Medical students at the peak of the COVID-19 epidemic. J Loss Trauma. 2021;26(4):401–4. 10.1080/15325024.2020.1799521/ASSET//CMS/ASSET/6D0DD65E-2502-4760-97C3-61D138BFE521/15325024.2020.1799521.FP.PNG.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alsalman Z, Shafey MM, Al-Khofi A, et al. Barriers to mental health service utilisation among medical students in Saudi Arabia. Front Public Health. 2024;12:1371628. 10.3389/FPUBH.2024.1371628/BIBTEX.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11055457</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38680929</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaroszewska AA, Tyras S, Dziewit M, Jaroszewska J, Podhorodecka K. Prevalence of anxiety and depression among domestic and foreign medical students in Poland. Pol Ann Med. 2020;27(2):135–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walkiewicz M, Guziak M. Availability of psychological support for medical students in Poland. Int J Occup Med Environ Health. 2020;34(1):87–99.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33223542</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alsoufi A, Alsuyihili A, Msherghi A, Elhadi A, Atiyah H, Ashini A, et al. Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on medical education: medical students’ knowledge, attitudes, and practices regarding electronic learning. PLoS ONE. 2020;15(11 November):1–20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calhoun KE, Yale LA, Whipple ME, Allen SM, Wood DE, Tatum RP. The impact of COVID-19 on medical student surgical education: implementing extreme pandemic response measures in a widely distributed surgical clerkship experience. Am J Surg. 2020;220(1):44–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7186124</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32389331</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh S, Roy D, Sinha K, Parveen S, Sharma G, Joshi G. Impact of COVID-19 and lockdown on mental health of children and adolescents: a narrative review with recommendations. Psychiatry Res. 2020;293(May):113429.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7444649</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32882598</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khasawneh AI, Humeidan AA, Alsulaiman JW, Bloukh S, Ramadan M, Al-Shatanawi TN, et al. Medical students and COVID-19: knowledge, attitudes, and precautionary measures. A descriptive study from Jordan. Front Public Heal. 2020;8(May):1–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Riad A, Drobov A, Krobot M, Antalová N, Alkasaby MA, Peřina A et al. Mental Health Burden of the Russian–Ukrainian War 2022 (RUW-22): anxiety and depression levels among young adults in Central Europe. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19(14).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jankowski M, Gujski M. Editorial: the Public Health implications for the Refugee Population, particularly in Poland, due to the War in Ukraine. Med Sci Monit. 2022;28:1–4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roy S, Bhat V, Ozair A. Overseas Medical students in Ukraine and War-related interruption in education: Global Health considerations from India. Ann Glob Heal. 2022;88(1):1–20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarkar S. Medical students escape war torn Ukraine but face limbo. BMJ. 2022;1–2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Srichawla BS, Khazeei Tabari MA, Găman M-A, Muñoz-Valencia A, Bonilla-Escobar FJ. War on Ukraine: impact on Ukrainian Medical Students. Int J Med Students. 2022;10(1):15–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jain N, Panag DS, Srivastava M, Mohan S, Chodnekar SY, Akbari AR, et al. Fate and future of the medical students in Ukraine: a silently bubbling educational crisis. Med Educ. 2022;56(8):779–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9546411</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35502145</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ross DA. Creating a Quarantine Curriculum to Enhance Teaching and Learning during the COVID-19 pandemic. Bull R Coll Surg Engl. 2020;102(1):10–3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akers A, Blough C, Iyer MS. COVID-19 implications on clinical clerkships and the Residency application process for medical students. Cureus. 2020;12(4).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zis P, Artemiadis A, Bargiotas P, Nteveros A, Hadjigeorgiou GM. Medical studies during the COVID-19 pandemic: the impact of digital learning on medical students’ burnout and mental health. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18(1):1–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mospan N, Slipchuk V. COVID-19 impact on Medical Education: evidence of International Students. Univers J Educ Res. 2020;8(12B):8393–401.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng Q, Lin X, He L, Freudenreich T, Liu T. Impact of the Perceived Mental stress during the COVID-19 pandemic on medical students’ loneliness feelings and future Career choice: a preliminary Survey Study. Front Psychiatry. 2021;12. 10.3389/FPSYT.2021.666588.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Byrne L, Gavin B, McNicholas F. Medical students and COVID-19: the need for pandemic preparedness. J Med Ethics. 2020;46(9):623–6. 10.1136/MEDETHICS-2020-106353.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7316103</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32493713</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Konstantinov V, Gritsenko V, Reznik A, Isralowitz R. The impact of COVID-19 on Health and Well-Being: Foreign Medical students in Eastern Europe. Social Sci 2022. 2022;11(9):393. 10.3390/SOCSCI11090393.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Çimen İD, Alvur TM, Coşkun B, Şükür NEÖ. Mental health of Turkish medical students during the COVID-19 pandemic. https://doi.org/101177/00207640211066734. 2021;68(6):1253–62. 10.1177/00207640211066734</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chudzicka-Czupała A, Hapon N, Chiang SK, et al. Depression, anxiety and post-traumatic stress during the 2022 russo-ukrainian war, a comparison between populations in Poland, Ukraine, and Taiwan. Sci Rep. 2023;13(1). 10.1038/S41598-023-28729-3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Østergaard SD, Rohde C, Jefsen OH. Deterioration of patients with mental disorders in Denmark coinciding with the invasion of Ukraine. 10.1101/2022.03.26.22272974</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osokina O, Silwal S, Bohdanova T, Hodes M, Sourander A, Skokauskas N. Impact of the Russian Invasion on Mental Health of adolescents in Ukraine. J Am Acad Child &amp;Amp Adolesc Psychiatry. 2023;62(3):335–43. 10.1016/J.JAAC.2022.07.845.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quek TTC, Tam WWS, Tran BX, et al. The global prevalence of anxiety among medical students: a Meta-analysis. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2019;16(15). 10.3390/IJERPH16152735.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>