<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39440644</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2192-2659</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Advanced healthcare materials</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Adv Healthc Mater</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Enhancing Cytoplasmic Expression of Exogenous mRNA Through Dynamic Mechanical Stimulation.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e2401918</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e2401918</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/adhm.202401918</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Ionizable lipid nanoparticles (LNPs) are pivotal in combating COVID-19, and numerous preclinical and clinical studies have highlighted their potential in nucleic acid-based therapies and vaccines. However, the effectiveness of endosomal escape for the nucleic acid cargos encapsulated in LNPs is still low, leading to suboptimal treatment outcomes and side effects. Hence, improving endosomal escape is crucial for enhancing the efficacy of nucleic acid delivery using LNPs. Here, a mechanical oscillation (frequency: 65 Hz) is utilized to prompt the LNP-mediated endosomal escape. The results reveal this mechanical oscillation can induce the combination and fusion between LNPs with opposite surface charges, enhance endosomal escape of mRNA, and increase the transfection efficiency of mRNA. Additionally, cell viability remains high at 99.3% after treatment with oscillation, which is comparable to that of untreated cells. Furthermore, there is no obvious damage to mitochondrial membrane potential and Golgi apparatus integrity. Thus, this work presents a user-friendly and safe approach to enhancing endosomal escape of mRNA and boosting gene expression. As a result, this work can be potentially utilized in both research and clinical fields to facilitate LNP-based delivery by enabling more effective release of LNP-encapsulated cargos from endosomes.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Wiley‐VCH GmbH.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Jiawen</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7101-3034</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Engineering, Stevens Institute of Technology, Hoboken, NJ, 07030, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Patel</LastName><ForeName>Aneri</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Engineering, Stevens Institute of Technology, Hoboken, NJ, 07030, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mir</LastName><ForeName>Mohammad</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Engineering, Stevens Institute of Technology, Hoboken, NJ, 07030, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hudock</LastName><ForeName>Maria R</ForeName><Initials>MR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Engineering, Columbia University, New York, NY, 10032, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pinezich</LastName><ForeName>Meghan R</ForeName><Initials>MR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Engineering, Columbia University, New York, NY, 10032, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Guenthart</LastName><ForeName>Brandon</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiothoracic Surgery, Stanford University, Stanford, CA, 94304, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bacchetta</LastName><ForeName>Matthew</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiac Surgery, Vanderbilt University, Nashville, TN, 37232, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Engineering, Vanderbilt University, Nashville, TN, 37232, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vunjak-Novakovic</LastName><ForeName>Gordana</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Engineering, Columbia University, New York, NY, 10032, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kim</LastName><ForeName>Jinho</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4692-4407</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Engineering, Stevens Institute of Technology, Hoboken, NJ, 07030, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>2143620</GrantID><Agency>National Science Foundation</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>P41 EB027062</GrantID><Acronym>NH</Acronym><Agency>NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>VUNJAK23XX0</GrantID><Agency>Cystic Fibrosis Foundation</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Adv Healthc Mater</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101581613</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2192-2640</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CommentsCorrectionsList><CommentsCorrections RefType="UpdateOf"><RefSource>bioRxiv. 2024 Oct 10:2024.06.19.599708. doi: 10.1101/2024.06.19.599708</RefSource><PMID Version="1">38948864</PMID></CommentsCorrections></CommentsCorrectionsList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">endosomal escape</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">gene expression</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ionizable lipid nanoparticles</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mRNA therapy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mechanical oscillation</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39440644</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/adhm.202401918</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>a) K. Kariko, M. Buckstein, H. Ni, D. Weissman, Immunity 2005;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) K. Karikó, K. Whitehead, R. van der Meel, Cell Syst. 2021, 12, 757;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) D. Weissman, K. Kariko, Mol. Ther. 2015, 23, 1416.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. E. Scott, A. R. Bayly, C. Abell, J. Skidmore, Nat. Rev. Drug Discov. 2016, 15, 533.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) K. Bulaklak, C. A. Gersbach, Nat. Commun. 2020, 11, 5820;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) U. Sahin, K. Karikó, Ö. Türeci, Nat. Rev. Drug Discov. 2014, 13, 759;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) M. M. Żak, L. Zangi, Pharmaceutics 2021, 13, 1675.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) M. Lopes‐Pacheco, Front. Pharmacol. 2019, 10, 1662;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) D. P. Bondeson, C. M. Crews, Annu. Rev. Pharmacol. Toxicol. 2017, 57, 107;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) L. Mabonga, A. P. Kappo, Biophys. Rev. 2019, 11, 559.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) A. Zemella, L. Thoring, C. Hoffmeister, S. Kubick, ChemBioChem 2015, 16, 2420;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) V. Gupta, M. Sengupta, J. Prakash, B. C. Tripathy, V. Gupta, M. Sengupta, J. Prakash, B. C. Tripathy, Basic Appl. Aspects Biotechnol. 2017, 77.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) R. E. Rigby, J. Rehwinkel, Trends Immunol. 2015, 36, 179;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) K. D. Dyer, H. F. Rosenberg, Mol. Divers. 2006, 10, 585.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) F. Heil, H. Hemmi, H. Hochrein, F. Ampenberger, C. Kirschning, S. Akira, G. Lipford, H. Wagner, S. Bauer, Science 2004, 303, 1526;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) A. Pichlmair, O. Schulz, C. P. Tan, J. Rehwinkel, H. Kato, O. Takeuchi, S. Akira, M. Way, G. Schiavo, C. Reis e Sousa, J. Virol. 2009, 83, 10761;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) M. Schlee, A. Roth, V. Hornung, C. A. Hagmann, V. Wimmenauer, W. Barchet, C. Coch, M. Janke, A. Mihailovic, G. Wardle, Immunity 2009, 31, 25.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) E. Samaridou, J. Heyes, P. Lutwyche, Adv. Drug Deliv. Rev. 2020, 154–155, 37;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) Y. Li, Z. Ye, H. Yang, Q. Xu, Acta Pharm. Sin. B 2022, 12, 2624;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) X. Huang, N. Kong, X. Zhang, Y. Cao, R. Langer, W. Tao, Nat. Med. 2022, 28, 2273.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) M. J. Sun, K. K. Wang, D. Oupický, Adv. Healthcare Mater. 2018, 7, 1870018;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) A. S. Piotrowski‐Daspit, A. C. Kauffman, L. G. Bracaglia, W. M. Saltzman, Adv. Drug Deliv. Rev. 2020, 156, 119;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) R. Kumar, C. F. Santa Chalarca, M. R. Bockman, C. V. Bruggen, C. J. Grimme, R. J. Dalal, M. G. Hanson, J. K. Hexum, T. M. Reineke, Chem. Rev. 2021, 121, 11527.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) T. Lehto, K. Ezzat, M. J. A. Wood, S. El Andaloussi, Adv. Drug Deliv. Rev. 2016, 106, 172;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) V. Gopal, J. Control Release 2013, 167, 323.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Akinc, M. A. Maier, M. Manoharan, K. Fitzgerald, M. Jayaraman, S. Barros, S. Ansell, X. Du, M. J. Hope, T. D. Madden, B. L. Mui, S. C. Semple, Y. K. Tam, M. Ciufolini, D. Witzigmann, J. A. Kulkarni, R. van der Meel, P. R. Cullis, Nat. Nanotechnol. 2019, 14, 1084.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) Y. Jia, X. Wang, L. Li, F. Li, J. Zhang, X. J. Liang, Adv. Mater. 2024, 36, 2305300;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) Y. Yan, X. Y. Liu, A. Lu, X. Y. Wang, L. X. Jiang, J. C. Wang, J. Control Release 2022, 342, 241;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) N. Kimura, M. Maeki, Y. Sato, A. Ishida, H. Tani, H. Harashima, M. Tokeshi, ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces 2020, 12, 34011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Schlich, R. Palomba, G. Costabile, S. Mizrahy, M. Pannuzzo, D. Peer, P. Decuzzi, Bioeng. Transl. Med. 2021, 6, e10213.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Verma, I. Ozer, W. Xie, R. Gallagher, A. Teixeira, M. Choy, Nat. Rev. Drug Discov. 2023, 22, 349.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) J. Gilleron, W. Querbes, A. Zeigerer, A. Borodovsky, G. Marsico, U. Schubert, K. Manygoats, S. Seifert, C. Andree, M. Stoter, H. Epstein‐Barash, L. Zhang, V. Koteliansky, K. Fitzgerald, E. Fava, M. Bickle, Y. Kalaidzidis, A. Akinc, M. Maier, M. Zerial, Nat. Biotechnol. 2013, 31, 638;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) A. Wittrup, A. Ai, X. Liu, P. Hamar, R. Trifonova, K. Charisse, M. Manoharan, T. Kirchhausen, J. Lieberman, Nat. Biotechnol. 2015, 33, 870.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Nakamura, T. Nakade, K. Yamada, Y. Sato, H. Harashima, Int. J. Pharm. 2021, 609, 121140.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. M. Lee, Q. Cheng, X. Yu, S. Liu, L. T. Johnson, D. J. Siegwart, Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. Engl. 2021, 60, 5848.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Ding, H. Zhang, J. Cui, Q. Li, C. Yang, Biomater. Sci. 2021, 9, 7534.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) F. Freitag, E. Wagner, Adv. Drug Deliv. Rev. 2021, 168, 30;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) S. Patel, N. Ashwanikumar, E. Robinson, Y. Xia, C. Mihai, J. P. Griffith III, S. G. Hou, A. A. Esposito, T. Ketova, K. Welsher, Nat. Commun. 2020, 11, 983;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) E. Álvarez‐Benedicto, L. Farbiak, M. M. Ramírez, X. Wang, L. T. Johnson, O. Mian, E. D. Guerrero, D. J. Siegwart, Biomater. Sci. 2022, 10, 549.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) Y. Ding, Y. Wang, Y. Opoku‐Damoah, C. Wang, L. Shen, L. Yin, J. Zhou, Biomaterials 2015, 72, 90;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) I. G. Kim, W. H. Jung, G. You, H. Lee, Y. J. Shin, S. W. Lim, B. H. Chung, H. Mok, Macromol. Biosci. 2023, 2200423.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) G. N. Stoforos, B. E. Farkas, J. Simunovic, Food Bioproducts Process. 2016, 100, 551;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) G. Metcalfe, D. Lester, J. Food Eng. 2009, 95, 21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Yang, H. W. Huang, Science 2002, 297, 1877.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) P. R. Cullis, M. J. Hope, Mol. Ther. 2017, 25, 1467;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) I. Koltover, T. Salditt, J. O. Radler, C. R. Safinya, Science 1998, 281, 78.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) R. M. Conry, A. F. LoBuglio, M. Wright, L. Sumerel, M. J. Pike, F. Johanning, R. Benjamin, D. Lu, D. T. Curiel, Cancer Res. 1995, 55, 1397;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) D. Boczkowski, S. K. Nair, D. Snyder, E. Gilboa, J. Exp. Med. 1996, 184, 465;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) A. Heiser, D. Coleman, J. Dannull, D. Yancey, M. A. Maurice, C. D. Lallas, P. Dahm, D. Niedzwiecki, E. Gilboa, J. Vieweg, J. Clin. Invest. 2002, 109, 409.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. F. Jirikowski, P. P. Sanna, D. Maciejewski‐Lenoir, F. E. Bloom, Science 1992, 255, 996.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Okano, M. Nakamura, K. Yoshida, Y. Okada, O. Tsuji, S. Nori, E. Ikeda, S. Yamanaka, K. Miura, Circ. Res. 2013, 112, 523.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Gilbert, F. Sebastiani, M. Y. Arteta, A. Terry, A. Fornell, R. Russell, N. Mahmoudi, T. Nylander, J. Colloid Interface Sci. 2024, 660, 66.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. G. F. Souza, V. S. T. Ciminelli, N. D. S. Mohallem, J. Phys. Conf. Ser. 2016, 733, 012039.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. K. Wilson, R. K. Prud'homme, J. Colloid Interface Sci. 2021, 604, 208.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Cerciello, S. Rossi, E. Visona, K. Corona, F. Oliva, Muscles Ligaments Tendons J. 2016, 6, 147.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) U. Lachelt, P. Kos, F. M. Mickler, A. Herrmann, E. E. Salcher, W. Rodl, N. Badgujar, C. Brauchle, E. Wagner, Nanomedicine 2014, 10, 35;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) F. Salomone, F. Cardarelli, M. Di Luca, C. Boccardi, R. Nifosi, G. Bardi, L. Di Bari, M. Serresi, F. Beltram, J. Control Release 2012, 163, 293;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>c) J. S. Kim, D. K. Choi, J. Y. Shin, S. M. Shin, S. W. Park, H. S. Cho, Y. S. Kim, J. Control Release 2016, 235, 165;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>d) R. A. Jones, M. H. Poniris, M. R. Wilson, J. Control Release 2004, 96, 379.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) F. Hausig‐Punke, F. Richter, M. Hoernke, J. C. Brendel, A. Traeger, Macromol. Biosci. 2022, 22, 2200167;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) Y. Hu, T. Litwin, A. R. Nagaraja, B. Kwong, J. Katz, N. Watson, D. J. Irvine, Nano Lett. 2007, 7, 3056.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) L. D. Zorova, V. A. Popkov, E. Y. Plotnikov, D. N. Silachev, I. B. Pevzner, S. S. Jankauskas, V. A. Babenko, S. D. Zorov, A. V. Balakireva, M. Juhaszova, S. J. Sollott, D. B. Zorov, Anal. Biochem. 2018, 552, 50;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) A. Perelman, C. Wachtel, M. Cohen, S. Haupt, H. Shapiro, A. Tzur, Cell Death Dis. 2012, 3, e430.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) F. Xu, X. Huang, Y. Wang, S. Zhou, Adv. Mater. 2020, 32, 1906745;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) K. Han, Q. Lei, S. B. Wang, J. J. Hu, W. X. Qiu, J. Y. Zhu, W. N. Yin, X. Luo, X. Z. Zhang, Adv. Funct. Mater. 2015, 25, 2961.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. L. Brader, S. J. Williams, J. M. Banks, W. H. Hui, Z. H. Zhou, L. Jin, Biophys. J. 2021, 120, 2766.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. C. de Sá‐Caputo, A. Seixas, R. Taiar, M. Bernardo‐Filho, in Complementary therapies, IntechOpen, London 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. W. Gordon, G. A. Scangos, D. J. Plotkin, J. A. Barbosa, F. H. Ruddle, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 1980, 77, 7380.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) G. Kang, D. W. Carlson, T. H. Kang, S. Lee, S. J. Haward, I. Choi, A. Q. Shen, A. J. Chung, ACS Nano 2020, 14, 3048;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) M. E. Kizer, Y. Deng, G. Kang, P. E. Mikael, X. Wang, A. J. Chung, Lab Chip 2019, 19, 1747.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Zhang, S. Shrivastava, R. O. Cleveland, T. H. Rabbitts, ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces 2019, 11, 10481.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Suda, Y. Moriyama, N. Razali, Y. Chiu, Y. Masukagami, K. Nishimura, H. Barbee, H. Takase, S. Sugiyama, Y. Yamazaki, Y. Sato, T. Higashiyama, Y. Johmura, M. Nakanishi, K. Kono, Nat. Aging 2024, 4, 319.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) M. L. Cacicedo, M. J. Limeres, S. Gehring, Cells 2022, 11, 3328;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) B. Balakrishnan, D. An, V. Nguyen, C. DeAntonis, P. G. V. Martini, K. Lai, Mol. Ther. 2020, 28, 304.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Truong, G. Allegri, X. B. Liu, K. E. Burke, X. Zhu, S. D. Cederbaum, J. Haberle, P. G. V. Martini, G. S. Lipshutz, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 2019, 116, 21150.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. M. Ickenstein, P. Garidel, Expert Opin. Drug Deliv. 2019, 16, 1205.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) L. Wang, N. Wang, W. Zhang, X. Cheng, Z. Yan, G. Shao, X. Wang, R. Wang, C. Fu, Signal Transduct. Target Ther. 2022, 7, 48;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) M. R. Aronson, A. W. Simonson, L. M. Orchard, M. Llinas, S. H. Medina, Acta Biomater. 2018, 80, 269.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Xu, Y. Zheng, L. Wu, X. Zhu, Z. Zhang, Y. Huang, ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces 2018, 10, 9315.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>a) Y. Xu, C. Wang, F. Shen, Z. Dong, Y. Hao, Y. Chen, Z. Liu, L. Feng, ACS Appl. Bio Mater. 2022, 5, 1194;</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>b) A. K. Varkouhi, M. Scholte, G. Storm, H. J. Haisma, J. Control Release 2011, 151, 220.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>