<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39445116</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1687-8728</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>2024</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>International journal of dentistry</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Int J Dent</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A Study to Check the Readiness of Final-Year Dental Students Vis-à-Vis to a Safe and an Independent Practitioner in Sultanate of Oman Amidst the Recent Pandemic.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>7476437</StartPage><MedlinePgn>7476437</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">7476437</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1155/2024/7476437</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>It is essential for a dental student about to graduate to possess robust fundamentals in both basic and clinical dental science. There should be a perfect harmony and blend of basic and clinical science integration and application among final year graduating students. They should also demonstrate readiness and competence in performing various clinical skills independently, after correctly interpreting and diagnosing a dental disorder. Besides the clinical aspects of dentistry, the newly graduating dental student should understand the principles of professionalism and ethos. The main aim and objective were to conduct a study to assess the impact of COVID-19 on practice readiness among the fifth-year dental students at Oman Dental College (ODC). A study was conducted to measure self-preparedness among graduating students, especially during the challenging times of the COVID-19 pandemic when education was significantly impacted. This study used a validated Dental Undergraduates Preparedness Assessment Scale (DU-PAS). The DU-PAS consists of 50 items, including 24 items related to clinical skills (part A) and 26 items related to scientific knowledge and affective skills (part B). Each item in part A was scored on a three-point scale ranging from no experience (0), with verbal and/or practical input from a colleague (1), to independently (2). Items in part B of the DU-PAS are scored on a three-point scale: no experience (0), mostly (1), and always (2). The maximum score for the 50 items on the DU-PAS is 100. Interestingly, the current study showed that the ODC final-year students were confident in performing several clinical procedures and had a good understanding of various professional aspects of clinical dentistry. The didactic online classes and preclinical sessions conducted while adhering to social distancing and other safety norms during the COVID-19 pandemic, were positively received by the students.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Triveni Nalawade et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nalawade</LastName><ForeName>Triveni</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0004-9608</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Paediatric Dentistry, Child Dental Health, Oman Dental College, Muscat, Oman.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Saraf</LastName><ForeName>Sanjay</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5190-1883</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Oral Pathology, Oman Dental College, Muscat, Oman.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mallikarjuna</LastName><ForeName>Rachappa</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8793-5842</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Paediatric Dentistry, Child Dental Health, Oman Dental College, Muscat, Oman.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Haj-Hamed</LastName><ForeName>Belal</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Oman Dental College, Muscat, Oman.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kumar</LastName><ForeName>Siva</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>E-Learning, Oman Dental College, Muscat, Oman.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Al Harthy</LastName><ForeName>Nutayla</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9655-4494</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Adult Restorative Dentistry, Oman Dental College, Muscat, Oman.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Al Ismaily</LastName><ForeName>Mohamed</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0009-8967-328X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery, Oman Dental College, Muscat, Oman.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Egypt</Country><MedlineTA>Int J Dent</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101524183</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1687-8728</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">DU-PAS score</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">dental surgical procedures</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">professionalism</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">self-perceived preparedness</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39445116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11496577</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2024/7476437</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Ali K., Slade A., Kay E., Zahra D., Tredwin C. Preparedness of Undergraduate Dental Students in the United Kingdom: A National Study. British Dental Journal . 2017;222(6):472–477. doi: 10.1038/sj.bdj.2017.272.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/sj.bdj.2017.272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28337012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Field J. C., Cowpe J. G., Walmsley A. D. The Graduating European Dentist: A New Undergraduate Curriculum Framework. European Journal of Dental Education . 2017;21(Suppl 1):2–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29205782</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali K., Cockerill J., Zahra D., Qazi H. S., Raja U., Ataullah K. Self-Perceived Preparedness of Final Year Dental Students in a Developing Country—A Multi-Institution Study. European Journal of Dental Education . 2018;22(4):e745–e750. doi: 10.1111/eje.12389.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/eje.12389</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30098082</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manakil J., George R. Self-Perceived Work Preparedness of the Graduating Dental Students. European Journal of Dental Education . 2013;17(2):101–105. doi: 10.1111/eje.12016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/eje.12016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23574187</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ilić J., Radović K., Savić-Stanković T., et al. The Effect of COVID-19 Pandemic on Final Year Dental Students’ Self-Confidence Level in Performing Clinical Procedures. PLOS ONE . 2021;16(10) doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0257359.e0257359</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0257359</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8516192</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34648503</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suib F. N., Ismail I. E. S., Younis L. T., Bakri N. N., Hassan M. I. Preparedness of Undergraduate Dental Students: A National Study. Compendium of Oral Science . 2021;8(1):1–10. doi: 10.24191/cos.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.24191/cos</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mat Yudin Z., Ali K., Wan Ahmad W. M. A., et al. Self-Perceived Preparedness of Undergraduate Dental Students in Dental Public Universities in Malaysia: A National Study. European Journal of Dental Education . 2020;24(1):163–168. doi: 10.1111/eje.12480.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/eje.12480</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31698535</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Talsma K., Robertson K., Thomas C., Norris K. COVID-19 Beliefs, Self-Efficacy and Academic Performance in First-Year University Students: Cohort Comparison and Mediation Analysis. Frontiers in Psychology . 2021;12 doi: 10.3389/fpsyg.2021.643408.643408</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2021.643408</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8259881</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34239475</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khamis F., Al Rashidi B., Al-Zakwani I., Al Wahaibi A. H., Al Awaidy S. T. Epidemiology of COVID-19 Infection in Oman: Analysis of the First 1304 Cases. Oman Medical Journal . 2020;35(3) doi: 10.5001/omj.2020.60.e145</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5001/omj.2020.60</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7335452</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32647593</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abushammala M., Qazi W., Manchiryal R. K. The Impact of COVID-19 on the Private Higher Education System and Students in Oman. Journal of University Teaching and Learning Practice . 2021;18(3) doi: 10.53761/1.18.3.13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.53761/1.18.3.13</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gilmour A. S. M., Welply A., Cowpe J. G., Bullock A. D., Jones R. J. The Undergraduate Preparation of Dentists: Confidence Levels of Final Year Dental Students at the School of Dentistry in Cardiff. British Dental Journal . 2016;221(6):349–354. doi: 10.1038/sj.bdj.2016.686.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/sj.bdj.2016.686</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27659639</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohamed N. A., Abdulhadi N. N., Al-Maniri A. A., Al-Lawati N. R., Al-Qasmi A. M. The Trend of Feminization of Doctors’ Workforce in Oman: Is It a Phenomenon That Could Rouse the Health System? Proceedings of tHuman Resource Health . 2018;16(1)19</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5921264</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29699562</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Javed M. Q., Nawabi S., Bhatti U. A., et al. How Well Prepared Are Dental Students and New Graduates in Pakistan-A Cross-Sectional National Study. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health . 2023;20(2) doi: 10.3390/ijerph20021506.1506</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph20021506</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9859325</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36674261</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almahdi H., Alnaeem T. A., Alshawaf H. T., Alsubaya A. J., Bu Hulayqah A. A., Al Khars M. Y. Self-Perceived Preparedness of KFU Dental Graduates to Practice Dentistry: A Cross-Sectional Study. Advances in Medical Education and Practice . 2023;14:595–601. doi: 10.2147/AMEP.S409296.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/AMEP.S409296</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10274844</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37333622</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>General Dental Council UK. Preparedness for Practice of UK Graduates Report 2020. 2023.  
 https://www.gdc-uk.org/about-us/what-we-do/consultations-and-responses/lists/consultations-and-responses---closed-consultations/14449d37-04ff-4214-9707-bee5d5d4f519
.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abd A. I, AlAshqar Mays A., Susan H., et al. Self-Perceived Preparedness of Dental School Graduates and the Impact of COVID-19 Pandemic on Their Confidence. Saudi Journal of Oral Sciences . 2021;8(3):163–171. doi: 10.4103/sjos.SJOralSci_5_21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/sjos.SJOralSci_5_21</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hook C. R., Comer R. W., Trombly R. M., Guinn J. W., III, Shrout M. K. Treatment Planning Processes in Dental Schools. Journal of Dental Education . 2002;66(1):68–74. doi: 10.1002/j.0022-0337.2002.66.1.tb03509.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/j.0022-0337.2002.66.1.tb03509.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12358102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hertrampf K., Wenz H. J., Kaduszkiewicz H., Goetz K. Suspension of Face-to-Face Teaching and Ad Hoc Transition to Digital Learning under Covid-19 Conditions—A Qualitative Study among Dental Students and Lecturers. BMC Medical Education . 2022;22(1) doi: 10.1186/s12909-022-03335-5.257</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12909-022-03335-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8992419</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35395749</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Persky A. M., Wells M. A., Sanders K. A., Fiordalisi J., Downey C., Anksorus H. N. Improving Dental Students’ Long-Term Retention of Pharmacy Knowledge With “Medication Minutes. Journal of Dental Education . 2017;81(9):1077–1084. doi: 10.21815/JDE.017.062.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21815/JDE.017.062</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28864789</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raghavan S., Abu Alhaija E., Ali K. Orthodontic Curricula in Undergraduate Dental Education—A Scoping Review. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health . 2023;20(6) doi: 10.3390/ijerph20064914.4914</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph20064914</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10049316</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36981820</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bissoon S., Moodley R. Perceptions of Dental Therapy Students regarding the Teaching and Training With Dental Amalgam, in a Dental School in KwaZulu-Natal, South Africa. South African Dental Journal . 2021;76(5):258–269. doi: 10.17159/10.17159/2519-0105/2021/v76no5a4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.17159/10.17159/2519-0105/2021/v76no5a4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Donnell C. C., Thomas L. R., Foley J. I. Mind the ’GAPP’: A Pre-Graduation Assessment of Preparedness for Practice amid a Pandemic. Proceedings of the 2015 International Conference on Material Science and Applications Icmsa 2015 . 2022;232(8):556–567. doi: 10.1038/s41415-022-4154-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41415-022-4154-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9028899</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35459832</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pandarathodiyil A. K., Mani S. A., Ghani W. M. N., Ramanathan A., Talib R., Zamzuri A. T. Preparedness of Recent Dental Graduates and Final-Year Undergraduate Dental Students for Practice Amidst the COVID-19 Pandemic. European Journal of Dental Education . 2023;27(1):78–86. doi: 10.1111/eje.12779.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/eje.12779</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35100466</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hattar S., AlHadidi A., Sawair F. A., Alraheam I. A., El-Ma’aita A., Wahab F. K. Impact of COVID-19 Pandemic on Dental Education: Online Experience and Practice Expectations among Dental Students at the University of Jordan. BMC Medical Education . 2021;21(1) doi: 10.1186/s12909-021-02584-0.151</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12909-021-02584-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7938292</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33685451</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oetter N., Möst T., Weber M., et al. COVID-19 Pandemic and Its Impact on Dental Education: Digitalization— Progress or Regress? Example of an Online Hands-on Course. BMC Medical Education . 2022;22(1) doi: 10.1186/s12909-022-03638-7.591</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12909-022-03638-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9340732</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35915461</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Altan H., Gönder H. Y., Demirel E., et al. Readiness for Clinical Practice: Self-Perceived Confidence of Final Year Dental Students in Turkey—A Multi-Institutional Study. MedEdPublish . 2016;14</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11306955</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39118866</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>