<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39444473</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2251-6093</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>53</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Apr</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Iranian journal of public health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Iran J Public Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Effects of Psychological Intervention Based on the Self-Transcendence Theory on the Sleep Quality of Chinese Nurses.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>818</StartPage><EndPage>827</EndPage><MedlinePgn>818-827</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.18502/ijph.v53i4.15558</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">COVID-19 infection is transmitted easily and quickly, exposing medical care workers, especially nursing workers, to tremendous stress. Therefore, identifying the factors influencing the sleep quality of nurses and implementing corresponding interventions are conducive to improving the sleep quality of nurses and enhancing their nursing quality.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Form September to December 2022, a survey-based evaluation was conducted on 1074 front-line clinical nurses randomly selected from three hospitals in Zhejiang Province, China. Based on the survey results, 152 nurses were selected and randomly divided into the experimental group and the control group, with 76 nurses in each group. A 2-month psychological intervention based on the self-transcendence theory was conducted, and the two groups were compared before and after the intervention.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The average PSQI score of nurses was 7.19±3.65, with 471 of them suffering from poor sleep (PSQI&gt;7), accounting for 45.46%. In addition, 57.10% of the nurses were under excessive stress, whereas 62% of them had a Self-Rating Anxiety Scale score of ≥50. After the intervention, the PSQI score of the experimental group was significantly lower than that of the control group, with the difference being statistically significant (<i>P</i>&lt;0.05).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Clinical nurses in tertiary hospitals have poor sleep quality and more severe stress and anxiety problems during COVID-19 than during non-epidemic periods. Clinical interventions based on the self-transcendence theory can effectively improve the sleep quality of nurses. Results of this study provide reference for enhancing the sleep quality of nurses and ensuring their physical and mental health during epidemic.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright© 2024 Guofang et al. Published by Tehran University of Medical Sciences.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Guofang</LastName><ForeName>Wei</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Rehabilitation Nursing Department, Rainbow Fish College of Rehabilitation Nursing, Hangzhou Vocational and Technical College, Hangzhou, 310000, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Wei</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nursing Department, Affiliated Hospital, Hangzhou Normal University, Hangzhou, 310015, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhu</LastName><ForeName>Zhen</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Orthopedics Department, The Second Affiliated Hospital, Zhejiang University of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Hangzhou, 310053, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Iran</Country><MedlineTA>Iran J Public Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7505531</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2251-6085</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Epidemic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Nurses</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Self-transcendence theory</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sleep disorder</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>16</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39444473</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11493566</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18502/ijph.v53i4.15558</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">IJPH-53-818</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Jahrami H, BaHammam AS, Bragazzi NL, et al. (2021). Sleep problems during the COVID-19 pandemic by population: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Clin Sleep Med, 17(2): 299–313.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7853219</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33108269</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Otu A, Charles CH, Yaya S. (2020). Mental health and psychosocial well-being during the COVID-19 pandemic: The invisible elephant in the room. Int J Ment Health Syst, 14: 38.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7257210</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32514302</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bani-Issa WA, Al Nusair H, Altamimi A, et al. (2021). Self-Report Assessment of Nurses’ Risk for Infection After Exposure to Patients With Coronavirus Disease (COVID-19) in the United Arab Emirates. J Nurs Scholarsh , 53(2): 171–79.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8013464</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33476482</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han LN, Liu J. (2021). Investigation and analysis of the sleep and health status of nurses during the COVID-19 epidemic. J Changchun Univ Chin Med, 37(3): 662–65.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kitson A, Chirico A, Gaggioli A, et al. (2020). A review on research and evaluation methods for investigating self-transcendence. Front Psychol, 11: 547687.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7701337</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33312147</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang T, Sedikides C. (2022). Awe motivates authentic-self pursuit via self-transcendence: Implications for prosociality. J Pers Soc Psychol, 123(3): 576–96.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34855435</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdollahi A, Panahipour H, Allen KA, et al. (2021). Effects of death anxiety on perceived stress in individuals with multiple sclerosis and the role of self-transcendence. Omega (Westport), 84(1): 91–102.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31584337</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Er S, Şahin-Bayındır G, Kayış A, Buzlu S. (2022). The effect of psychosocial distress and self-transcendence on resilience in patients with cancer. Perspect Psychiatr Care, 58(4): 2631–638.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35535488</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu P, Zhang R, Li D. (2022). The effect and mechanisms of self-transcendence values on durable happiness. Adv Psychol Sci, 30(3): 660–69.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niu GF, Sun JP, Zhang H, et al. (2017). The correlation between self transcendence and quality of life in elderly chronic disease patients in the community. Chin J Gerontol, 37(13): 3332–333</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Indrayana IKS, Arisudhana GAB, Putra PWK. (2023). Hubungan Tingkat Spiritualitas dengan Self-Efficacy pada Pasien HIV/AIDS di Puskesmas Kuta II: Correlation between Spirituality with Self-Efficacy on HIV/AIDS Patient in Puskesmas Kuta II. J Nurs Res Publ Media (NURSEPEDIA), 2(2): 63–79.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soriano GP, Calong KAC. (2021). Spiritual well-being, self-transcendence, and spiritual practices among Filipino women with breast cancer. Palliat Support Care, 19(6): 723–26.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33678214</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garland EL, Hanley AW, Hudak J, et al. (2022). Mindfulness-induced endogenous theta stimulation occasions self-transcendence and inhibits addictive behavior. Sci Adv, 8(41): eabo4455.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9555770</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36223472</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haugan G, Kuven BM, Eide WM, et al. (2020). Nurse-patient interaction and self-transcendence: assets for a meaningful life in nursing home residents?. BMC Geriatr, 20(1):168.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7203905</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32381032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li YJ, Li XZ, Li JB, et al. (2021). Application of the Chinese version of the Stress Perception Scale in representative community adult population. Chin Ment Health J, 35(1): 67–72.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen S, Kamarck T, Mermelstein R. (1983). A global measure of perceived stress. J Health Soc Behav, 24(4): 385–96.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6668417</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buysse DJ, Reynolds CF, III, Monk TH, et al. (1989). The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index: a new instrument for psychiatric practice and research. Psychiatry Res, 28(2): 193–213.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2748771</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu XC, Tang MQ, Hu L, et al. (1996). Reliability and validity of the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index. Chin J Psychiat, 29(2):103–07.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zung WW. (1971). A rating instrument for anxieties orders. Psychosomatics, 12(6): 371–79.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">5172928</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al Maqbali M, Al Sinani M, Al-Lenjawi B. (2021) Prevalence of stress, depression, anxiety and sleep disturbance among nurses during the COVID-19 pandemic: A systematic review and meta-analysis. J Psychosom Res, 141: 110343.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7831768</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33360329</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheng JW, Wang J. (2021). The relationships among sleep quality,anxiety and depression of clinical nurses in tertiary hospitals. J Nurs Sci, 36(22):16–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang S, Xie L, Xu Y, et al. (2020). Sleep disturbances among medical workers during the outbreak of COVID-2019. Occup Med (Lond), 70(5): 364–69.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7239094</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32372077</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tu HY, Hou Y, Wang K, et al. (2020). Study on sleep quality, anxiety of frontline nurses against COVID-19 and its correlation with work environment. Chin Nurs Manage, 20(6): 857–60.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fatima Y, Doi SAR, Najman JM, et al. (2016). Exploring Gender Difference in Sleep Quality of Young Adults: Findings from a Large Population Study. Clin Med Res, 14: 138–44.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5302457</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28188139</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yin TT, Han QY, Zheng Y, et al. (2021). Study on the influencing factors of nurses’ sleep quality and mindfulness level during the COVID-19 epidemic. J Nurs Admin, 21(1): 15–20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim-Godwin YS, Lee MH, Logan JG, et al. (2021). Factors Influencing Sleep Quality among Female Staff Nurses during the Early COVID-19 Pandemic in the United States. Int J Environ Res Public Health, 18(9): 4827.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8124220</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33946606</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lou MX, Wang T, Li JF. (2022). Investigation on sleep and psychological status of nurses in different periods of COVID-19 epdemic. Chongqing Med, 51(22): 3884–889.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu M., Xing J, Li TT. (2023). Investigation and analysis on sleep quality of staff in a Grade A hospital during the COVID-19. Anhui Med J, 44(2): 224–28.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin JA, Ericson M, Berwaldt A, et al. (2023). Effects of two online positive psychology and meditation programs on persistent self-transcendence. Psychol Conscious, 10(3): 225–53.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu P, Wang X, Li D, et al. (2021). The benefits of self-transcendence: Examining the role of values on mental health among adolescents across regions in China. Front Psychol, 12: 630420.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7925830</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33679555</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>