<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39440533</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">0975-5764</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Annals of African medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Ann Afr Med</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>COVID-19 and Health-care Business Continuity in Africa: Perceptions of Risks and Vulnerabilities by Mid-level Management Staff in a Tertiary Care Hospital.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4103/aam.aam_145_21</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">The novel SARS-CoV-2 outbreak disrupted businesses globally and created fears in the general public and among health-care professionals. Almost universally, considerations about the coronavirus pandemic and its effects became priority in the daily operations of businesses, leaving hitherto pressing concerns in the back stage. Early in the pandemic, the management of University of Benin Teaching Hospital set up a Business Continuity Team which undertook an evaluation of the perceptions of mid-level hospital managers about their departments' and units' risks and vulnerabilities in the face of the ongoing pandemic.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A modified International Labour Organization (ILO) risk profile self-assessment tool which focused on "people," "processes," "profits," and "partnerships" was used to assess mid-level managers' perceptions of their respective departments' and units' risks and vulnerabilities, consequent on the COVID-19 pandemic. Responses were obtained from heads of departments and units using an online survey. Final scores were divided into terciles (three equal groups) in respect of perceived risks and adverse outcomes of the COVID-19 pandemic. Scores in the lower tercile were grouped as low risk/vulnerability, the middle group of scores as medium risk/vulnerability, and scores in the upper tercile as high risk/vulnerability.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Responses were obtained from 35 (49.3%) of the 71 clinical and nonclinical departments and units in the hospital. Fifteen of these (42.9%) were clinical. Nineteen (54.2%) departments were assessed to be at high risk/vulnerability, 9 (47.4%) of which were clinical. Twelve (34.3%) departments were assessed to be at medium risk/vulnerability - 4 (33.3%) of them, clinical. No department was assessed to be at low risk. The highest risk ratings were in the domains of "profits" and "partnerships:" 54 (84.4%) mid-level managers assessed their departments and units to be at high risk of the negative impacts of the coronavirus pandemic with respect to "profits" and 51 (79.7%) with respect to "partnerships."</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Mid-level managers in clinical and nonclinical departments and units assessed their departments and units to be at medium and high risk of the negative impacts of the COVID-19 pandemic, using the ILO's modified tool. Our findings enabled the management of the hospital and the Business Continuity Team to address the specific areas of concerns that were highlighted, develop contingency plans, and frame risk communication during the pandemic, with a view to fostering increased sense of safety in the workforce. This approach to risk assessment is repeatable, and we recommended it to other hospitals in Africa.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Copyright: © 2024 Annals of African Medicine.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ndubuisi</LastName><ForeName>Mokogwu</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Health, Special Statistics Unit, University of Benin Teaching Hospital, Benin City, Edo State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Akoria</LastName><ForeName>Obehi Aituaje</ForeName><Initials>OA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, Medical Advisory Committee, University of Benin Teaching Hospital, Benin City, Edo State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Obaseki</LastName><ForeName>Darlington Ewaen</ForeName><Initials>DE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Anatomic Pathology and Chief Medical Director, University of Benin Teaching Hospital, Benin City, Edo State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gregrey</LastName><ForeName>Oko-Oboh Agbonvihele</ForeName><Initials>OA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Health, Special Statistics Unit, University of Benin Teaching Hospital, Benin City, Edo State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>fre</Language><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>India</Country><MedlineTA>Ann Afr Med</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101231417</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0975-5764</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="fre"><AbstractText><b>Résumé</b> <b>Objectifs:</b>L’épidémie de la nouvelle souche de SARS-CoV-2 a perturbé les entreprises à l’échelle mondiale et suscité des craintes au sein du grand public et des professionnels de la santé. Presque universellement, les considérations concernant la pandémie de coronavirus et ses effets sont devenues une priorité dans les opérations quotidiennes des entreprises, reléguant ainsi à l’arrière-plan des préoccupations autrefois pressantes. Au début de la pandémie, la direction de l’Hôpital Universitaire du Bénin a mis en place une équipe de continuité des activités qui a entrepris une évaluation des perceptions des gestionnaires hospitaliers de niveau intermédiaire concernant les risques et vulnérabilités de leurs départements et unités face à la pandémie en cours.<b>Méthodes:</b>Un outil d’auto-évaluation du profil de risque modifié de l’Organisation internationale du Travail (OIT), axé sur les “personnes”, les “processus”, les “profits” et les “partenariats”, a été utilisé pour évaluer les perceptions des gestionnaires de niveau intermédiaire concernant les risques et vulnérabilités de leurs départements et unités respectifs, en raison de la pandémie de COVID-19. Les réponses ont été obtenues auprès des chefs de départements et d’unités à l’aide d’une enquête en ligne. Les scores finaux ont été divisés en terciles (trois groupes égaux) en fonction des risques perçus et des résultats négatifs de la pandémie de COVID-19. Les scores dans le tercile inférieur ont été regroupés comme présentant un faible risque/vulnérabilité, le groupe intermédiaire de scores comme un risque/moyenne vulnérabilité, et les scores dans le tercile supérieur comme un risque/haute vulnérabilité.<b>Résultats:</b>Les réponses ont été obtenues de 35 (49,3 %) des 71 départements cliniques et non cliniques de l’hôpital. Quinze d’entre eux (42,9 %) étaient cliniques. Dix-neuf départements (54,2 %) ont été évalués comme présentant un risque/haute vulnérabilité, dont neuf (47,4 %) étaient cliniques. Douze départements (34,3 %) ont été évalués comme présentant un risque/moyenne vulnérabilité – dont quatre (33,3 %) étaient cliniques. Aucun département n’a été évalué comme présentant un faible risque. Les évaluations de risque les plus élevées étaient dans les domaines des “profits” et des “partenariats”: 54 (84,4 %) gestionnaires de niveau intermédiaire ont évalué leurs départements et unités comme étant à haut risque d’impacts négatifs de la pandémie de coronavirus en ce qui concerne les “profits” et 51 (79,7 %) en ce qui concerne les “partenariats”.<b>Conclusion:</b>Les gestionnaires de niveau intermédiaire des départements cliniques et non cliniques ont évalué leurs départements et unités comme présentant un risque moyen à élevé d’impacts négatifs de la pandémie de COVID-19, en utilisant l’outil modifié de l’OIT. Nos résultats ont permis à la direction de l’hôpital et à l’équipe de continuité des activités de traiter les domaines spécifiques de préoccupation identifiés, de développer des plans de contingence et de formuler des communications sur les risques pendant la pandémie, dans le but de renforcer le sentiment de sécurité au sein de la main-d’œuvre. Cette approche d’évaluation des risques est reproductible, et nous la recommandons à d’autres hôpitaux en Afrique.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Copyright: © 2024 Annals of African Medicine.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39440533</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/aam.aam_145_21</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">01244624-990000000-00062</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>