<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39440023</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2752-6542</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>3</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>PNAS nexus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>PNAS Nexus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Quantifying energy transition vulnerability helps more just and inclusive decarbonization.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>pgae427</StartPage><MedlinePgn>pgae427</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">pgae427</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1093/pnasnexus/pgae427</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The COP28 agreement signals "beginning of the end" of the fossil fuel era, calling on countries to contribute to global efforts to transition away from fossil fuels in energy systems in a just, orderly and equitable manner. While a quantitative assessment of country's vulnerability in energy transition is a prerequisite for national and international policy makers to ensure a just and inclusive transition, it is notably absent in the existing research. Here, we develop a conceptual framework based on the vulnerability scoping diagram (VSD) method to assess differences in energy transition vulnerability across countries, with a specific focus on the challenges associated with transitioning away from fossil fuels. The resulting energy transition vulnerability index (ETVI) scores reveal that countries in the Global South generally exhibit higher vulnerability in their energy transition compared to those in the Global North, and this gap has widened over the past decade. Moreover, the COVID-19 pandemic has disrupted the decade-long trend of continuous decline in global energy transition vulnerability. This study also provides two important applications of ETVI scores, aligning them with major global sustainable development agenda. Firstly, we identify substantial differences in the dynamics of transition vulnerability across seven major party groups in the international climate change negotiations and distinguish four energy transition statuses in relation to achieving global climate goals: <i>Stressful</i>, <i>Leapfrog</i>, <i>Potential Challenges</i>, and <i>Less Painful</i>. Secondly, we demonstrate crucial synergies between energy transition resilience and the 2030 United Nations Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs).</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s) 2024. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of National Academy of Sciences.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shen</LastName><ForeName>Yifan</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4193-6537</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Economics and Finance, SILC Business School, Shanghai University, Shanghai 201899, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shi</LastName><ForeName>Xunpeng</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9653-7395</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Australia-China Relations Institute, University of Technology Sydney, Sydney, NSW 2007, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhao</LastName><ForeName>Zhibo</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Finance, School of Finance, Qilu University of Technology (Shandong Academy of Sciences), Jinan 250100, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Grafton</LastName><ForeName>R Quentin</ForeName><Initials>RQ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0048-9083</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Crawford School of Public Policy, The Australian National University, Acton, ACT 2601, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yu</LastName><ForeName>Jian</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9116-6046</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Economics, Central University of Finance and Economics, Beijing 102206, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shan</LastName><ForeName>Yuli</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5215-8657</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Geography, Earth and Environmental Sciences, University of Birmingham, Birmingham B15 2TT, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>PNAS Nexus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9918367777906676</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2752-6542</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39440023</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11495377</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/pnasnexus/pgae427</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">pgae427</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>IEA . 2016. Energy, climate change &amp; environment - 2016 insights. Int Energy Agency.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNFCCC . 2023. COP28 Agreement signals “beginning of the end” of the Fossil Fuel Era. UN Climate Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carley  S, Konisky  DM. 2020. The justice and equity implications of the clean energy transition. Nat Energy. 5:569–577.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>He  G, et al.  2020. Enabling a rapid and just transition away from coal in China. One Earth. 3:187–194.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7442150</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34173532</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jenkins  K, McCauley  D, Heffron  R, Stephan  H, Rehner  R. 2016. Energy justice: a conceptual review. Energy Res Soc Sci. 11:174–182.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>IPCC . 2014. Summary for policymakers: climate change 2014: impacts, adaptation and vulnerability - contributions of the working group II to the fifth assessment report. IPCC. p. 31. 10.1017/CBO9781107415324</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/CBO9781107415324</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adger  WN, Brown  K. 2009. Vulnerability and resilience to environmental change: ecological and social perspectives. In: Castree  N, Demeritt  D, Liverman  D, et al., editors. A companion to Environmental Geography. Blackwell Publishing Ltd. p. 109–122.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barnett  J. 2020. Global environmental change II: political economies of vulnerability to climate change. Prog Hum Geogr. 44:1172–1184.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polsky  C, Neff  R, Yarnal  B. 2007. Building comparable global change vulnerability assessments: the vulnerability scoping diagram. Glob Environ Chang. 17:472–485.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>IPCC . 2021. Summary for policymakers, in: climate change 2021: the physical science basis. Cambridge University Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carley  S, Evans  TP, Graff  M, Konisky  DM. 2018. A framework for evaluating geographic disparities in energy transition vulnerability. Nat Energy. 3:621–627.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi  X, Sun  Y, Shen  Y. 2021. China's ambitious energy transition plans. Science (1979).  373:170.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34244403</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bouzarovski  S, et al.  2017. Multiple transformations: theorizing energy vulnerability as a socio-spatial phenomenon. Geogr Ann Ser B Hum Geogr. 99:20–41.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calvo  R, et al.  2021. Territorial energy vulnerability assessment to enhance just energy transition of cities. Front Sustain Cities. 3:635976. 10.3389/frsc.2021.635976.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/frsc.2021.635976</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Axon  S, Morrissey  J. 2020. Just energy transitions? Social inequities, vulnerabilities and unintended consequences. Build Cities. 1:393–411.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Streimikiene  D, Kyriakopoulos  GL, Lekavicius  V, Siksnelyte-Butkiene  I. 2021. Energy poverty and low carbon just energy transition: comparative study in Lithuania and Greece. Soc Indic Res. 158:319–371.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8081766</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33941997</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Vliet  MTH, Wiberg  D, Leduc  S, Riahi  K. 2016. Power-generation system vulnerability and adaptation to changes in climate and water resources. Nat Clim Chang. 6:375–380.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Economic Forum . 2022. Fostering effective energy transition 2022 edition. World Economic Forum.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Füssel  H-M, Klein  RJT. 2006. Climate change vulnerability assessments: an evolution of conceptual thinking. Clim Change. 75:301–329.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raimi  D. 2021. Mapping county-level exposure and vulnerability to the US energy transition. Resources for the Future. 21–36.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raimi  D, Carley  S, Konisky  D. 2022. Mapping county-level vulnerability to the energy transition in US fossil fuel communities. Sci Rep. 12:15748.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9492708</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36130967</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McDowall  W, Reinauer  T, Fragkos  P, Miedzinski  M, Cronin  J. 2023. Mapping regional vulnerability in Europe's energy transition: development and application of an indicator to assess declining employment in four carbon-intensive industries. Clim Change. 176:7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Snyder  BF. 2018. Vulnerability to decarbonization in hydrocarbon-intensive counties in the United States: a just transition to avoid post-industrial decay. Energy Res Soc Sci. 42:34–43.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng  K, et al.  2023. The global power sector's low-carbon transition may enhance sustainable development goal achievement. Nat Commun. 14:3144.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10229651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37253805</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Editorial . 2019. Sustainable development through climate action. Nat Clim Chang. 9:491.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fuso Nerini  F, et al.  2019. Connecting climate action with other sustainable development goals. Nat Sustain. 2:674–680.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fuso Nerini  F, et al.  2018. Mapping synergies and trade-offs between energy and the sustainable development goals. Nat Energy. 3:10–15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bocca  R. 2020. Fostering effective energy transition. 2020 edition.  World Economic Forum.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Energy Council . 2021. World energy trilemma index 2021, World Energy Council. London: World Energy Council.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNFCCC . 2022. Party groupings. UN Climate Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNFCCC . 2015. The Paris agreement. United Nations Climate Change.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UN . 2015. Transforming our world: the 2030 agenda for sustainable development. United Nations.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Governnment of Iceland . 2022. Energy (profile). National Energy Authority of Iceland.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sachs  J, Kroll  C, Lafortune  G, Fuller  G, Woelm  F. 2021. The decade of action for the sustainable development goals: sustainable development report 2021. Cambridge University Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The United Nations . 2021. Global indicator framework for the sustainable development goals and targets of the 2030 Agenda for sustainable development. United Nations.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shan  Y, et al.  2018. City-level climate change mitigation in China. Sci Adv. 4:eaaq0390.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6021142</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29963621</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen  Y, Shi  X, Zhao  Z, Sun  Y, Shan  Y. 2023. Measuring the low-carbon energy transition in Chinese cities. iScience. 26:105803.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9803854</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36594025</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao  H, et al.  2022. Navigating Chinese cities to achieve sustainable development goals by 2030. Innovation. 3:100288.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9382565</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35990172</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quitzow  R, et al.  2021. The COVID-19 crisis deepens the gulf between leaders and laggards in the global energy transition. Energy Res Soc Sci. 74:101981..</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9766326</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36568909</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Le Billon  P, Lujala  P, Singh  D, Culbert  V, Kristoffersen  B. 2021. Fossil fuels, climate change, and the COVID-19 crisis: pathways for a just and green post-pandemic recovery. Clim Policy. 21:1347–1356.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barrett  S. 2011. Why cooperate?: The incentive to supply global public goods. Oxford University Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNFCCC . 2023. Introduction to climate finance. UN Climate Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNEP . 2022. What you need to know about the COP27 loss and damage fund. UN Climate Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCollum  DL, et al.  2018. Energy investment needs for fulfilling the Paris agreement and achieving the sustainable development goals. Nat Energy. 3:589–599.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soergel  B, et al.  2021. A sustainable development pathway for climate action within the UN 2030 agenda. Nat Clim Chang. 11:656–664.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rao  ND, Min  J. 2018. Decent living standards: material prerequisites for human wellbeing. Soc Indic Res. 138:225–244.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6013539</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29950752</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rao  ND, Min  J, Mastrucci  A. 2019. Energy requirements for decent living in India, Brazil and South Africa. Nat Energy. 4:1025–1032.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chancel  L. 2022. Global carbon inequality over 1990–2019. Nat Sustain. 5:931–938.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng  K, Chen  X, Malerba  D, Oswald  Y, Hubacek  K. 2023. A global just transition through carbon taxation and revenue recycling, arXiv, arXiv:rs.3.rs-2676301/v1, preprint: not peer reviewed.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oswald  Y, Millward-Hopkins  J, Steinberger  JK, Owen  A, Ivanova  D. 2023. Luxury-focused carbon taxation improves fairness of climate policy. One Earth. 6:884–898.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>International Energy Agency: IEA . 2024. CO2 emissions in 2023. International Energy Agency.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>King  LC, Savin  I, Drews  S. 2023. Shades of green growth scepticism among climate policy researchers. Nat Sustain. 6:1316–1320.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haberl  H, et al.  2020. A systematic review of the evidence on decoupling of GDP, resource use and GHG emissions, Part II: Synthesizing the insights. Environ Res Lett. 15:65003.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hickel  J. 2019. The contradiction of the sustainable development goals: growth versus ecology on a finite planet. Sustain Dev. 27:873–884.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hickel  J, Kallis  G. 2020. Is green growth possible?  New Polit Econ. 25:469–486.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kallis  G. 2011. In defence of degrowth. Ecol Econ. 70:873–880.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keyßer  LT, Lenzen  M. 2021. 1.5 C degrowth scenarios suggest the need for new mitigation pathways. Nat Commun. 12:2676.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8113441</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33976156</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tokic  D. 2012. The economic and financial dimensions of degrowth. Ecol Econ. 84:49–56.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van den Bergh  JCJM, Kallis  G. 2012. Growth, a-growth or degrowth to stay within planetary boundaries?  J Econ Issues. 46:909–920.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D’Alessandro  S, Cieplinski  A, Distefano  T, Dittmer  K. 2020. Feasible alternatives to green growth. Nat Sustain. 3:329–335.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hubacek  K, et al.  2017. Global carbon inequality. Energy Ecol Environ. 2:361–369.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rao  ND, Wilson  C. 2022. Advancing energy and well-being research. Nat Sustain. 5:98–103.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coletti  A, Howe  PD, Yarnal  B, Wood  NJ. 2013. A support system for assessing local vulnerability to weather and climate. Nat Hazards. 65:999–1008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Howe  PD, Yarnal  B, Coletti  A, Wood  NJ. 2013. The participatory vulnerability scoping diagram: deliberative risk ranking for community water systems. Ann Assoc Am Geogr. 103:343–352.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Henry  MS, Bazilian  MD, Markuson  C. 2020. Just transitions: histories and futures in a post-COVID world. Energy Res Soc Sci. 68:101668.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7351418</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32839696</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kartha  S, Caney  S, Dubash  NK, Muttitt  G. 2018. Whose carbon is burnable? Equity considerations in the allocation of a “right to extract”. Clim Change. 150:117–129.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>IEA . 2022. Tracking progress in clean energy transitions through key indicators across fuels and technologies. International Energy Agency.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ansari  D, Holz  F. 2020. Between stranded assets and green transformation: fossil-fuel-producing developing countries towards 2055. World Dev. 130:104947. 10.1016/j.worlddev.2020.104947.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.worlddev.2020.104947</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin  W, Shi  X, Zhang  L. 2021. Energy transition without dirty capital stranding. Energy Econ. 102:105508.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waddams Price  C, Brazier  K, Wang  W. 2012. Objective and subjective measures of fuel poverty. Energy Policy. 49:33–39.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hubacek  K, Baiocchi  G, Feng  K, Patwardhan  A. 2017. Poverty eradication in a carbon constrained world. Nat Commun. 8:912.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5783954</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29066777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kilian  L. 2008. The economic effects of energy price shocks. J Econ Lit. 46:871–909.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reames  TG. 2016. Targeting energy justice: exploring spatial, racial/ethnic and socioeconomic disparities in urban residential heating energy efficiency. Energy Policy. 97:549–558.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seefeldt  KS. 2015. Constant consumption smoothing, limited investments, and few repayments: the role of debt in the financial lives of economically vulnerable families. Soc Serv Rev. 89:263–300.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adger  WN. 1999. Social vulnerability to climate change and extremes in coastal Vietnam. World Dev. 27:249–269.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu  S, Zheng  X, Wei  C. 2017. Measurement of inequality using household energy consumption data in rural China. Nat Energy. 2:795–803.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Memmott  T, Carley  S, Graff  M, Konisky  DM. 2021. Sociodemographic disparities in energy insecurity among low-income households before and during the COVID-19 pandemic. Nat Energy. 6:186–193.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poyer  DA, Henderson  L, Teotia  APS. 1997. Residential energy consumption across different population groups: comparative analysis for Latino and non-Latino households in USA. Energy Econ. 19:445–463.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poyer  DA, Williams  M. 1993. Residential energy demand: additional empirical evidence by minority household type. Energy Econ. 15:93–100.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cutter  SL, Finch  C. 2008. Temporal and spatial changes in social vulnerability to natural hazards. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.  105:2301–2306.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2268131</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18268336</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flanagan  BE, Hallisey  EJ, Adams  E, Lavery  A. 2018. Measuring community vulnerability to natural and anthropogenic hazards: the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention’s Social Vulnerability Index. J Environ Health. 80:34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7179070</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32327766</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davidson  DJ. 2019. Exnovating for a renewable energy transition. Nat Energy. 4:254–256.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Markard  J. 2018. The next phase of the energy transition and its implications for research and policy. Nat Energy. 3:628–633.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Babayomi  OO, Dahoro  DA, Zhang  Z. 2022. Affordable clean energy transition in developing countries: pathways and technologies. iScience. 25:104178.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9019260</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35465049</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoggett  R. 2014. Technology scale and supply chains in a secure, affordable and low carbon energy transition. Appl Energy. 123:296–306.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kittner  N, Lill  F, Kammen  DM. 2017. Energy storage deployment and innovation for the clean energy transition. Nat Energy. 2:17125.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hao  L-N, Umar  M, Khan  Z, Ali  W. 2021. Green growth and low carbon emission in G7 countries: how critical the network of environmental taxes, renewable energy and human capital is?  Sci Total Environ. 752:141853.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32889278</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shahbaz  M, Song  M, Ahmad  S, Vo  XV. 2022. Does economic growth stimulate energy consumption? The role of human capital and R&amp;D expenditures in China. Energy Econ. 105:105662.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yao  Y, Ivanovski  K, Inekwe  J, Smyth  R. 2019. Human capital and energy consumption: evidence from OECD countries. Energy Econ. 84:104534.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fadly  D. 2019. Low-carbon transition: private sector investment in renewable energy projects in developing countries. World Dev. 122:552–569.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polzin  F, Sanders  M. 2020. How to finance the transition to low-carbon energy in Europe?  Energy Policy. 147:111863.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tian  J, Yu  L, Xue  R, Zhuang  S, Shan  Y. 2022. Global low-carbon energy transition in the post-COVID-19 era. Appl Energy. 307:118205.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8610812</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34840400</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu  Z, et al.  2020. Assessing progress towards sustainable development over space and time. Nature. 577:74–78.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31894145</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>