<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39442398</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1095-8630</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>370</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>22</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of environmental management</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Environ Manage</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Unlocking sustainable futures: Exploring the non-linear linkages between green finance and environmental sustainability in developing countries.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>122971</StartPage><MedlinePgn>122971</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.jenvman.2024.122971</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0301-4797(24)02957-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>In an era characterized by growing environmental concerns and the urgent call for climate action, the role of green finance in addressing ecological sustainability has become a subject of paramount importance. Owing to this need, the current study examines the nonlinear relationship between green finance and environmental sustainability in 51 developing countries from 2000 to 2022. We employ various advanced panel estimation techniques, including Driscoll-Kraay standard errors (D-K), Feasible generalized least squares (FGLS), Generalized linear model (GLM), and System GMM to examine the long-run impact of this association. The results are further validated using a unique bootstrap quantile approach as a robustness check. We find a nonlinear inverted U-shaped relationship between green finance and environmental sustainability. We extend our analysis to lower-income and lower-middle-income countries and see that this nexus is stronger in middle-income countries than lower-income ones. Our findings also confirm the green finance based-EKC across the sub-samples of lower- and lower-middle-income countries. We also document that this nonlinear relationship is weak during the COVID-19 pandemic. This underscores the complexity of the investigated nexus, emphasizing the need for tailored strategies to foster a sustainable environment in developing economies.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gul</LastName><ForeName>Raazia</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Management Sciences, SZABIST University, Islamabad, Pakistan. Electronic address: raazigul@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hussain</LastName><ForeName>Shahzad</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Business Administration, Rawalpindi Women University, Pakistan. Electronic address: shahzadhussainpeace@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Environ Manage</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0401664</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0301-4797</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">CO2 emissions</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">EKC</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Ecological footprint</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Environmental sustainability</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Green finance</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Nonlinear relationship</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper. The research presented in this manuscript is solely the result of the authors' academic investigation and is not influenced by any financial or commercial entities. All funding sources, if any, have been acknowledged in the manuscript, and the authors have adhered to the ethical guidelines of the Journal of Environmental Management throughout the research and publication process.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>6</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39442398</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2024.122971</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0301-4797(24)02957-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>