<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39445358</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1399-3046</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>28</Volume><Issue>7</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Pediatric transplantation</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Pediatr Transplant</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Pediatric Learning Health Networks in Solid Organ Transplantation-Engaging all Stakeholders to Achieve Health for Children Who Require Transplantation.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e14862</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e14862</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/petr.14862</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Learning Health Networks (LHN) have evolved within medicine over the past two decades, but their integration into transplantation has been more recent.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES AND METHODS" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">In this paper, we describe three LHNs in end-stage organ disease/transplantation, their common and unique features, and how their "actor-oriented" architecture allowed for rapid adaptation to meet the needs of their patients and practitioners during the recent COVID-19 pandemic.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULT" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The structure and focus of the Improving Renal Outcomes Collaborative (IROC), Starzl Network for Excellence in Pediatric Transplantation (SNEPT), and the Advanced Cardiac Therapies Improving Outcomes Network (ACTION) are reviewed. We discuss the critical role of patient and family engagement, focusing on collaboration with Transplant Families. Finally, we review challenges common to the LHN concept and potential common areas of alignment to achieve the goal of more rapid and sustained progress to improve health in pediatric transplantation.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">LHN in transplantation are essential to accelerate knowledge dissemination and improve outcomes.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>George</LastName><ForeName>Roshan P</ForeName><Initials>RP</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3853-967X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emory University and Children's Healthcare of Atlanta, Atlanta, Georgia, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Feldman</LastName><ForeName>Amy G</ForeName><Initials>AG</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4021-5615</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Digestive Health Institute, Children's Hospital Colorado and the University of Colorado, Aurora, Colorado, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>McQueen</LastName><ForeName>Melissa</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4268-1049</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Transplant Families, Scottsdale, Arizona, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Krise-Confair</LastName><ForeName>Cassandra</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0001-8515-1689</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Starzl Network for Excellence in Pediatric Transplantation, UPMC Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Smyth</LastName><ForeName>Lauren</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Heart Institute, Cincinnati Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati, Ohio, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lorts</LastName><ForeName>Angela</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1447-5456</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Heart Institute, Cincinnati Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati, Ohio, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Peng</LastName><ForeName>David M</ForeName><Initials>DM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7763-7518</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Cardiology, C.S. Mott Hospital, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mazariegos</LastName><ForeName>George V</ForeName><Initials>GV</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2624-8632</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hillman Center for Pediatric Transplantation, Thomas E. Starzl Transplantation Institute, UPMC Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hooper</LastName><ForeName>David K</ForeName><Initials>DK</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8732-4291</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, Cincinnati Children's Hospital Medical Center and University of Cincinnati College of Medicine, Cincinnati, Ohio, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Denmark</Country><MedlineTA>Pediatr Transplant</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9802574</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1397-3142</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016377" MajorTopicYN="Y">Organ Transplantation</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000080891" MajorTopicYN="Y">Learning Health System</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000458" MajorTopicYN="N">organization &amp; administration</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010372" MajorTopicYN="N">Pediatrics</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000458" MajorTopicYN="N">organization &amp; administration</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000073597" MajorTopicYN="N">Stakeholder Participation</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">children</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">heart failure</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">kidney transplantation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">learning health network</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">liver transplantation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">quality improvement</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>32</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39445358</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/petr.14862</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>J. C. Magee, S. M. Krishnan, M. R. Benfield, D. T. Hsu, and B. L. Shneider, “Pediatric Transplantation in the United States, 1997–2006,” American Journal of Transplantation 8, no. 4 Pt 2 (2008): 935–945.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. LaRosa, H. J. Baluarte, and K. E. Meyers, “Outcomes in Pediatric Solid‐Organ Transplantation,” Pediatric Transplantation 15, no. 2 (2011): 128–141.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. J. Kim and S. D. Marks, “Long‐Term Outcomes of Children After Solid Organ Transplantation,” Clinics (São Paulo, Brazil) 69, no. Suppl 1 (2014): 28–38.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. A. Elisofon, J. C. Magee, V. L. Ng, et al., “Society of Pediatric Liver Transplantation: Current Registry Status 2011‐2018,” Pediatric Transplantation 24, no. 1 (2020): e13605.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. A. Taylor, C. L. Kirby, E. J. Nehus, J. Goebel, and D. K. Hooper, “Composite Health Outcomes in Pediatric and Young Adult Kidney Transplant Recipients,” Journal of Pediatrics 204 (2019): 196–202.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. L. Ng, E. M. Alonso, J. C. Bucuvalas, et al., “Health Status of Children Alive 10 Years After Pediatric Liver Transplantation Performed in the US and Canada: Report of the Studies of Pediatric Liver Transplantation Experience,” Journal of Pediatrics 160, no. 5 (2012): 820–826.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Chua, C. Cramer, A. Moudgil, et al., “Kidney Transplant Practice Patterns and Outcome Benchmarks Over 30 Years: The 2018 Report of the NAPRTCS,” Pediatric Transplantation 23, no. 8 (2019): e13597.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. A. Olsen, The Learning Healthcare System (Washington, DC: National Academic Press, 2007).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. H. Wagner, B. T. Austin, and M. Von Korff, “Organizing Care for Patients With Chronic Illness,” Milbank Quarterly 74, no. 4 (1996): 511–544.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. L. Langley, R. Moen, K. M. Nolan, T. W. Nolan, C. L. Norman, and L. P. Provost, The Improvement Guide: A Practical Approach to Enhancing Organizational Performance (2nd Edition) San Francisco: Jossey‐Bass Publishers, 2009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. D. Varnell, Jr., P. Margolis, J. Goebel, and D. K. Hooper, “The Learning Health System for Pediatric Nephrology: Building Better Systems to Improve Health,” Pediatric Nephrology 38 (2022): 35–46.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Nehus, C. Liu, D. K. Hooper, M. Macaluso, and M. O. Kim, “Clinical Practice of Steroid Avoidance in Pediatric Kidney Transplantation,” American Journal of Transplantation 15, no. 8 (2015): 2203–2210.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. J. Steinbach, G. M. Barletta, H. P. Patel, D. K. Hooper, R. Garro, and L. A. Harshman, “Donor Specific Antibody Surveillance Among Pediatric Kidney Transplant Programs: A Report From the Improving Renal Outcome Collaborative,” Pediatric Transplantation 27, no. 3 (2023): e14498.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Villa, S. R. Auerbach, N. Bansal, et al., “Current Practices in Treating Cardiomyopathy and Heart Failure in Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy (DMD): Understanding Care Practices in Order to Optimize DMD Heart Failure Through ACTION,” Pediatric Cardiology 43, no. 5 (2022): 977–985.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O. D. Fjeldstad, J. K. Johnson, P. A. Margolis, M. Seid, P. Hoglund, and P. B. Batalden, “Networked Health Care: Rethinking Value Creation in Learning Health Care Systems,” Learning Health Systems 4, no. 2 (2020): e10212.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. T. Britto, S. C. Fuller, H. C. Kaplan, et al., “Using a Network Organisational Architecture to Support the Development of Learning Healthcare Systems,” British Medical Journal Quality &amp; Safety 27, no. 11 (2018): 937–946.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Batalden, P. Batalden, P. Margolis, et al., “Coproduction of Healthcare Service,” British Medical Journal Quality &amp; Safety 25, no. 7 (2016): 509–517.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Marsolo, P. A. Margolis, C. B. Forrest, R. B. Colletti, and J. J. Hutton, “A Digital Architecture for a Network‐Based Learning Health System: Integrating Chronic Care Management, Quality Improvement, and Research,” eGEMS (Wash DC) 3, no. 1 (2015): 1168.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. M. Neu, M. R. Miller, J. Stuart, et al., “Design of the Standardizing Care to Improve Outcomes in Pediatric End Stage Renal Disease Collaborative,” Pediatric Nephrology 29, no. 9 (2014): 1477–1484.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. B. Anderson, “Power of a Learning Network in Congenital Heart Disease,” World Journal for Pediatric and Congenital Heart Surgery 10, no. 1 (2019): 66–71.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. K. Hooper, J. Misurac, T. Blydt‐Hansen, and A. N. Chua, “Multicenter Data to Improve Health for Pediatric Renal Transplant Recipients in North America: Complementary Approaches of NAPRTCS and IROC,” Pediatric Transplantation 25, no. 1 (2021): e13891.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. E. Seifert, D. S. Dahale, M. Kamel, et al., “The Improving Renal Outcomes Collaborative: Blood Pressure Measurement in Transplant Recipients,” Pediatrics 146, no. 1 (2020): 2019–2833.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. R. Perito, J. E. Squires, D. Bray, et al., “A Learning Health System for Pediatric Liver Transplant: The Starzl Network for Excellence in Pediatric Transplantation,” Journal of Pediatric Gastroenterology and Nutrition 72, no. 3 (2021): 417–424.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. E. Squires, B. Logan, A. Lorts, et al., “A Learning Health Network for Pediatric Liver Transplantation: Inaugural Meeting Report From the Starzl Network for Excellence in Pediatric Transplantation,” Pediatric Transplantation 23, no. 6 (2019): e13528.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. J. Kwong, N. H. Ebel, W. R. Kim, et al., “OPTN/SRTR 2020 Annual Data Report: Liver,” American Journal of Transplantation 22, no. Suppl 2 (2022): 204–309.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. L. Ng, G. V. Mazariegos, B. Kelly, et al., “Barriers to Ideal Outcomes After Pediatric Liver Transplantation,” Pediatric Transplantation 23, no. 6 (2019): e13537.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. L. Ng, C. Dunphy, E. Shemesh, et al., “Feasibility of Using a Patient‐Reported Outcome Measure Into Clinical Practice Following Pediatric Liver Transplantation: The Starzl Network Experience,” Pediatric Transplantation 27, no. 1 (2023): e14409.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. K. Rasmussen, C. P. Lemoine, R. Superina, et al., “State of Pediatric Liver Transplantation in the United States and Achieving Zero Wait List Mortality With Ideal Outcomes: A Statement From the Starzl Network for Excellence in Pediatric Transplant Surgeon's Working Group,” Pediatric Transplantation 27, no. Suppl 1 (2023): e14283.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Nandi, C. S. Almond, and J. W. Rossano, “Epidemiology and Economics of Pediatric Heart Failure,” Heart Failure in the Child and Young Adult (2018): 151–160.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. R. Davies, M. A. McCulloch, S. Haldeman, S. S. Gidding, and C. Pizarro, “Urgent Listing Exceptions and Outcomes in Pediatric Heart Transplantation: Comparison to Standard Criteria Patients,” Journal of Heart and Lung Transplantation 36, no. 3 (2017): 280–288.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Lorts, L. Smyth, R. J. Gajarski, et al., “The Creation of a Pediatric Health Care Learning Network: The ACTION Quality Improvement Collaborative,” ASAIO Journal (American Society for Artificial Internal Organs: 1992) 66, no. 4 (2020): 441–446.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. M. Peng, D. N. Rosenthal, F. Zafar, L. Smyth, C. J. VanderPluym, and A. Lorts, “Collaboration and New Data in ACTION: A Learning Health Care System to Improve Pediatric Heart Failure and Ventricular Assist Device Outcomes,” Translational Pediatrics 8, no. 4 (2019): 349–355.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. D. Jaquiss, T. Humpl, C. E. Canter, D. L. Morales, D. N. Rosenthal, and C. D. Fraser, Jr., “Postapproval Outcomes: The Berlin Heart EXCOR Pediatric in North America,” ASAIO Journal (American Society for Artificial Internal Organs: 1992) 63, no. 2 (2017): 193–197.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. R. Villa, C. J. VanderPluym, and on behalf of the ACTION Investigators, “ABCs of Stroke Prevention: Improving Stroke Outcomes in Children Supported With a Ventricular Assist Device in a Quality Improvement Network,” Circulation: Cardiovascular Quality and Outcomes 13, no. 12 (2020): e006663.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. J. Romanelli, K. M. J. Azar, S. Sudat, D. Hung, D. L. Frosch, and A. R. Pressman, “Learning Health System in Crisis: Lessons From the COVID‐19 Pandemic,” Mayo Clinic Proceeding: Innovations, Quality &amp; Outcomes 5, no. 1 (2021): 171–176.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Lobritto, L. Danziger‐Isakov, M. G. Michaels, and G. V. Mazariegos, “Impact of COVID‐19 Pandemic on Pediatrics and Pediatric Transplantation Programs,” Frontiers in Pediatrics 8 (2020): 612627.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Nimmo, D. Gardiner, I. Ushiro‐Lumb, R. Ravanan, and J. L. R. Forsythe, “The Global Impact of COVID‐19 on Solid Organ Transplantation: Two Years Into a Pandemic,” Transplantation 106, no. 7 (2022): 1312–1329.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. J. Boyarsky, T. Po‐Yu Chiang, W. A. Werbel, et al., “Early Impact of COVID‐19 on Transplant Center Practices and Policies in the United States,” American Journal of Transplantation 20, no. 7 (2020): 1809–1818.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. J. Boyarsky, W. A. Werbel, C. M. Durand, et al., “Early National and Center‐Level Changes to Kidney Transplantation in the United States During the COVID‐19 Epidemic,” American Journal of Transplantation 20, no. 11 (2020): 3131–3139.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O. Charnaya, T. P. Chiang, R. Wang, et al., “Effects of COVID‐19 Pandemic on Pediatric Kidney Transplant in the United States,” Pediatric Nephrology 36, no. 1 (2021): 143–151.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. T. Strauss, B. J. Boyarsky, J. M. Garonzik‐Wang, et al., “Liver Transplantation in the United States During the COVID‐19 Pandemic: National and Center‐Level Responses,” American Journal of Transplantation 21 (2020): 1838–1847.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Kemme, D. Yoeli, S. S. Sundaram, M. A. Adams, and A. G. Feldman, “Decreased Access to Pediatric Liver Transplantation During the COVID‐19 Pandemic,” Pediatric Transplantation 26, no. 2 (2022): e14162.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O. Aubert, D. Yoo, D. Zielinski, et al., “COVID‐19 Pandemic and Worldwide Organ Transplantation: A Population‐Based Study,” Lancet Public Health 6, no. 10 (2021): e709–e719.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Wightman, A. Goldberg, and D. Diekema, “Considering a COVID‐19 Vaccine Mandate for Pediatric Kidney Transplant Candidates,” Pediatric Nephrology 37, no. 11 (2022): 2559–2569.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Ladin, A. M. Flescher, and P. P. Reese, “COVID‐19 Vaccine Mandates for Transplant Patients: Caring for Patients Versus Turning Them Away,” American Journal of Kidney Diseases 79, no. 6 (2022): 774–777.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. G. Feldman, B. Beaty, M. Everitt, et al., “Survey of Pediatric Transplant Center Practices Regarding COVID‐19 Vaccine Mandates for Transplant Candidates and Living Donors and Use of COVID‐19‐Positive Deceased Organs,” Pediatric Transplantation 27, no. 6 (2023): e14513.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. E. Dulek, M. I. Ardura, M. Green, et al., “Update on COVID‐19 Vaccination in Pediatric Solid Organ Transplant Recipients,” Pediatric Transplantation 26, no. 5 (2022): e14235.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Varnell, Jr., L. A. Harshman, L. Smith, et al., “COVID‐19 in Pediatric Kidney Transplantation: The Improving Renal Outcomes Collaborative,” American Journal of Transplantation 21, no. 8 (2021): 2740–2748.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Varnell, Jr., L. A. Harshman, C. Liu, et al., “COVID‐19 in Pediatric Kidney Transplantation: A Follow‐Up Report of the Improving Renal Outcomes Collaborative,” Pediatric Nephrology 38 (2022): 537–547.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Bansal, E. Azeka, C. Neunert, et al., “Multisystem Inflammatory Syndrome Associated With COVID‐19 Anti‐Thrombosis Guideline of Care for Children by Action,” Pediatric Cardiology 42, no. 7 (2021): 1635–1639.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. J. Downes, V. A. Statler, R. C. Orscheln, et al., “Return to School and COVID‐19 Vaccination for Pediatric Solid Organ Transplant Recipients in the United States: Expert Opinion for 2021–2022,” Journal of the Pediatric Infectious Diseases Society 11, no. 2 (2022): 43–54.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. R. Perito, M. McQueen, J. Lau, et al., “Patient‐Centered Research in Pediatric Transplant: Engaging Families and Recipients,” American Journal of Transplantation 24, no. 5 (2024): 857–864.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. D. Varnell, Jr., P. Margolis, J. Goebel, and D. K. Hooper, “The Learning Health System for Pediatric Nephrology: Building Better Systems to Improve Health,” Pediatric Nephrology 38, no. 1 (2023): 35–46.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. A. Olsen, D. Aisner, and J. M. McGinnis eds., The Learning Healthcare System: Workshop Summary (Washington (DC): National Academies Press, 2007).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. B. Forrest, P. Margolis, M. Seid, and R. B. Colletti, “PEDSnet: How a Prototype Pediatric Learning Health System is Being Expanded Into a National Network,” Health Affairs (Millwood) 33, no. 7 (2014): 1171–1177.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Institute of Medicine, Roundtable on Value and Science‐Driven Health Care (Washington, DC: National Academies Press, 2006).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Institute of Medicine, The Learning Healthcare System: Workshop Summary (Washington, DC: National Academies Press, 2007).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>