<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39442074</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1612-1880</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Chemistry &amp; biodiversity</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Chem Biodivers</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Design, Synthesis, Biological Evaluation and Molecular Docking Studies of New Thiazolidinone Derivatives as NNRTIs and SARS-CoV-2 Main Protease Inhibitors.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e202401697</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e202401697</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/cbdv.202401697</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>HIV-1 remains a major health problem worldwide since the virus has developed drug-resistant strains, so, the need for novel agents is urgent. The protein reverse transcriptase plays fundamental role in the viruses' replication cycle. FDA approved Delavirdine bearing a sulfonamide moiety, while thiazolidinone has demonstrated significant anti-HIV activity as a core heterocycle or derivative of substituted heterocycles. In this study, thirty new thiazolidinone derivatives (series A, B and C) bearing sulfonamide group were designed, synthesized and evaluated for their HIV-1 RT inhibition activity predicted by computer program PASS taking into account the best features of available NNRTIs as well as against SARS-COV-2 main protease. Seven compounds showed good anti-HIV inhibitory activity, with two of them, C1 and C2 being better (IC<sub>50</sub> 0.18 μΜ &amp; 0.12 μΜ respectively) than the reference drug nevirapine (IC<sub>50</sub> 0.31 μΜ). The evaluation of molecules to inhibit the main protease revealed that 6 of the synthesized compounds exhibited excellent to moderate activity with two of them (B4 and B10) having better IC<sub>50</sub> values (0.15 &amp; 0.19 μΜ respectively) than the reference inhibitor GC376 (IC<sub>50</sub> 0.439 μΜ). The docking studies is coincides with experimental results, showing good binding mode to both enzymes.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Chemistry &amp; Biodiversity published by Wiley-VHCA AG.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fesatidou</LastName><ForeName>Maria</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmaceutical Chemistry, School of Pharmacy, Aristotle University of Thessaloniki, Thessaloniki, 54124, Greece.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Petrou</LastName><ForeName>Anthi</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmaceutical Chemistry, School of Pharmacy, Aristotle University of Thessaloniki, Thessaloniki, 54124, Greece.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Geronikaki</LastName><ForeName>Athina</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9894-7777</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmaceutical Chemistry, School of Pharmacy, Aristotle University of Thessaloniki, Thessaloniki, 54124, Greece.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>HEAL-Link</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Chem Biodivers</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101197449</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1612-1872</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">AIDS</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">HIV-1 reverse transcriptase</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Molecular docking</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sulfonamides</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Synthesis design</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Thiazolidinone</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>28</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>28</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39442074</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/cbdv.202401697</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>E. Ndashimye, P. S. Reyes, E. J. Arts, FEMS Microbiol. Rev. 2023, 47, 1–22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNAIDS/WHO estimates, 2023, HIV data and statistics. https://www.who.int/teams/global-hiv-hepatitis-and-stis-programmes/hiv/strategic-information/hiv-data-and-statistics.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Zhuang, C. Pannecouque, E. De Clercq, F. Chen, Acta Pharm. Sin. B 2020, 10, 961–978.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. K. Singh, A. Kumar, S. Arora, R. Kumar, A. Verma, H. Khalilullah, M. Jaremko, A.-H. Emwas, P. Kumar, Chem. Biol. Drug Des. 2024, 103, 14372–14393.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Levintov, H. Vashisth, RNA Biol. 2024, 21, 1–32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. M. Johnson, Clin. Med. (Lond.) 2023, 23, 106–114.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. K. Singh, K. Das, Viruses 2022, 14, 1027–1045.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Gao, L. Song, Y. Cheng, F. Zhao, D. Kang, S. Song, M. Yang, B. Ye, W. Zhao, Y. Tang, E. De Clercq, C. Pannecouque, P. Zhan, X. Liu, Acta Pharm. Sin. B 2023, 13, 2747–2764.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. A. Salubi, J. Chem. 2023, 2023(3601764), 22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Suryawanshi, S. Jadhav, N. Makwana, D. Desai, D. Chaturbhuj, A. Sonawani, S. Idicula-Thomas, V. Murugesan, S. B. Katti, S. Tripathy, R. Paranjape, S. Kulkarni, Bioorg. Chem. 2017, 71, 211–218.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. R. Buemi, R. Gitto, L. Ielo, C. Pannecouque, L. De Luca, Bioorg. Med. Chem. 2020, 28, 115431–115437.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. A. Pasha, S. Mondal, N. Panigrahi, G. Shetye, R. Ma, S. G. Franzblau, Y.-T. Zheng, S. Murugesan, Curr. HIV Res. 2022, 20, 255–271.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Pervaiz, A. Riaz, A. Munir, Z. Saeed, S. Hussain, A. Rashid, U. Younas, A. Adnan, J. Mol. Struct. 2020, 1202, 127284–127293.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. A. Azzam, R. E. Elsayed, G. H. Elgemeie, ACS Omega 2020, 5, 10401–10414.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Ovung, J. Bhattacharyya, Biophys. Rev. Lett. 2021, 13, 259–272.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Wan, G. Fang, H. Chen, X. Deng, Z. Tang, Eur. J. Med. Chem. 2021, 226, 113837–113858.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Rubab, S. Afroz, S. Ahmad, S. Hussain, I. Nawaz, A. Irfan, F. Batool, K. Kotwica-Mojzych, M. Mojzych, Molecules 2022, 27, 1604–1635.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. A. Wani, S. Zargar, H. M. Alkahtani, N. Altwaijry, L. S. Al-Rasheed, Int. J. Mol. Sci. 2023, 24, 7953–7978.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Ren, X. Li, L. Yin, D. Jiang, D. Hu, ACS Omega 2020, 5, 19721–19726.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. A. Azzam, H. A. Elboshi, G. H. Elgemeie, ACS Omega 2020, 5, 30023–30036.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Y. Moskalik, Molecules 2023, 28, 51–66.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. M. Soliman, H. M. Karam, M. H. Mekkawy, M. M. Ghorab, Eur. J. Med. Chem. 2020, 197, 112333–112345.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. C. Egbujor, J. Garrido, F. Borges, L. Saso, Mini-Rev. Org. Chem. 2023, 20, 190–209.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Taha, F. J. Alshamrani, F. Rahim, E. H. Anouar, N. Uddin, S. Chigurupati, N. B. Almandil, R. K. Farooq, N. Iqbal, M. Aldubayan, V. Venugopal, K. M. Khan, J. King Saud Univ. Sci. 2021, 33, 101401–101414.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. M. Abdelazeem, W. M. Aboulthana, A. S. Hassan, A. A. Almehizia, A. M. Naglah, H. M. Alkahtani, SPJ 2024, 32, 102025.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. T. Salve, S. B. JadhavSr, IJPER 2021, 55, 1145–1150.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. C. Asogwa, E. C. Ogechi, H. Louis, U. D. Izuchukwu, C. G. Apebende, E. U. Florence, M. C. Ekeleme, E. A. James, O. J. Ikenyirimba, A. I. Ikeuba, A. E. Owen, O. U. Chris, Results Chem. 2022, 4, 100672–100682.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Khamees Thabet, A. Ragab, M. Imran, M. H. Helal, S. I. Alaqel, A. Alshehri, A. A. Mohd, S. Saad Alshammari, Y. A. Ammar, M. S. Abusaif, RSC Adv. 2024, 14, 15691–15705.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. A. Iqbal, A. Husain, O. Alam, S. A. Khan, A. Ahmad, M. R. Haider, M. A. Alam, Arch. Pharm. 2020, 353, 2000071–2000095.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Roszczenko, S. Holota, O. K. Szewczyk, R. Dudchak, K. Bielawski, A. Bielawska, R. Lesyk, Int. J. Mol. Sci. 2022, 23, 13135–1359.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. C. Desai, Y. M. Rupala, A. G. Khasiya, K. N. Shah, U. P. Pandit, V. M. Khedkar, J. Heterocycl. Chem. 2022, 59, 75–87.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X.-C. Yang, P.-L. Zhang, K. V. Kumar, S. Li, R.-X. Geng, C.-H. Zhou, Eur. J. Med. Chem. 2022, 232, 114192–114211.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. M. Shawky, M. A. S. Abourehab, A. N. Abdalla, A. M. Gouda, Eur. J. Med. Chem. 2020, 185, 111780–111799.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Haroun, A. Petrou, C. Tratrat, K. Kositsi, A. Gavalas, A. Geronikaki, K. N. Venugopala, N. Sreeharsha, SAR and QSAR Env. Res. 2022, 33, 485–497.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Trotsko, Eur. J. Med. Chem. 2021, 215, 113266–113288.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. Kumar, P. Shetty, A. H. S. S. Chandra, K. R. Ramu, S. M. Patil, A. Baliga, V. M. Rai, S. S. M. V. Udupi, V. Poojary, B. Poojary, Chem. Biodiversity 2022, 19, e202100532–547.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. B. Taj, A. Raheel, W. Alelwani, A. M. Alnajeebi, R. B. Alnoman, T. Javed, Russ. J. Gen. Chem. 2023, 93, 912–919.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>I. H. Ali, R. M. Hassan, A. M. El Kerdawy, M. T. Abo-Elfadl, H. M. I. Abdallah, F. Sciandra, I. A. Y. Ghannam, Eur. J. Med. Chem. 2024, 269, 116279–116305.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Augello, V. Bono, R. Rovito, C. Tincati, G. Marchetti, Curr. HIV/AIDS Rep. 2023, 20, 51–75.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Kerkour, N. Chafai, O. Moumeni, S. Chafaa, J. Mol. Struct. 2023, 1272, 134196–134205.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T. Cooper, B. Woodward, S. Alom, A. Harky, HIV Med. 2020, 21, 567–577.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Gatechompol, A. Avihingsanon, O. Putcharoen, K. Ruxrungtham, D. Kuritzkes, AIDS Res. Ther. 2021, 18, 28–37.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Basoulis, E. Mastrogianni, P.-M. Voutsinas, M. Psichogiou, Viruses 2023, 15, 577–598.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Kerkour, O. Moumeni, N. Rabhi, M. Mehri, A. Boublia, N. Chafai, S. Chafaa, J. Mol. Struct. 2024, 1315, 138842–138854.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Kumar, K. Zhi, A. Mukherji, K. Gerth, Viruses 2020, 12, 486–501.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Mahdi, J. Mótyán, Z. Szojka, M. Golda, M. Miczi, J. Tözsér, Virol. J. 2020, 17, 190–198.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Magro, I. Zanella, M. Pescarolo, F. Castelli, E. Quiros-Roldan, Biomed. J. 2020, 44, 43–53.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Pereira, N. Vale, Biomol. Eng. 2022, 12, 944–958.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Chauhan, S. Soni, A. Gupta, M. Aslam, U. Jain, J. Med. Virol. 2021, 93, 1967–1982.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Banerjee, L. Perera, L. M. V. Tillekeratne, Drug Discovery Today 2021, 26, 804–816.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. A. Elfiky, J. Biomol. Struct. Dyn. 2021, 39, 3204–3212.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Zhang, D. Lin, X. Sun, U. Curth, C. Drosten, L. Sauerhering, S. Becker, K. Rox, R. Hilgenfeld, Science 2020, 368, 409–412.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>C. Liu, Q. Zhou, Y. Li, L. V. Garner, S. P. Watkins, L. J. Carter, J. Smoot, A. C. Gregg, A. D. Daniels, S. Jervey, D. Albaiuet, ACS Cent. Sci. 2020, 6, 315–331.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Hilgenfeld, FEBS J. 2014, 281, 4085–4096.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. R. Naik, M. Munikumar, U. Ramakrishna, M. Srujana, G. Goudar, P. Naresh, B. N. Kumar, R. Hemalatha, J. Biomol. Struct. Dyn. 2020, 1–14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Parastoo, A. Shervin, K. Mohammadreza, Z. Milad, Z. Arghavan, L. Tayebe, T. Alireza, R. Akam, Z. Armin, Z. Amirmohammad, A. Behnam, S. Saber, F. Abbas, Rev. Res. Med. Microbiol. 2022, 33, 161–179.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Elkolli, N. Chafai, S. Chafaa, I. Kadi, C. Bensouici, A. Hellal, J. Mol. Struct. 2022, 1268, 133701–133714.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Tabbiche, A. Bouchama, N. Chafai, F. Zaidi, C. Chiter, M. Yahiaoui, A. Abiza, J. Med. Struct. 2022, 1261, 132865–132879.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Tlidjane, N. Chafai, S. Chafaa, C. Bensouici, K. Benbouguerra, J. Med. Struct. 2022, 1250, 131853–131865.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Benbouguerra, N. Chafai, S. Chafaa, Y. I. Touahria, H. Tlidjane, J. Med. Struct. 2021, 1239, 130480–130490.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>I. Seck, F. Nguemo, Res. Chem. 2021, 3, 100132–100141.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Pitta, A. Geronikaki, S. Surmava, P. Eleftheriou, V. P. Mehta, E. V. Van Der Eycken, J. Enzyme Inhib. Med. Chem. 2013, 28, 113–122.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Petrou, P. Eleftheriou, A. Geronikaki, M. G. Akrivou, I. Vizirianakis, Molecules 2019, 24, 3821–3850.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Eleftheriou, D. Amanatidou, A. Petrou, A. Geronikaki, Molecules 2020, 25, 2529–2549.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Petrou, P. Zagaliotis, N. F. Theodoroula, G. A. Mystridis, I. S. Vizirianakis, T. J. Walsh, A. Geronikaki, Molecules 2022, 27, 2180–2194.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. Poroikov, D. Filimonov, A. Lagunin, T. Gloriozova, A. Zakharov, SAR QSAR Environ. Res. 2007, 18, 101–110.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. De Clercq, Biochem. Pharmacol. 2012, 84, 241–248.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. M. Silverstein, F. X. Webster, D. J. Kiemle, Spectrometric Identification of Organic Compounds, John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York 2005.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. H. Stuart, Infrared Spectroscopy: Fundamentals and Applications, John Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester 2004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Daina, O. Michielin, V. Zoete, Sci. Rep. 2017, 7, 42717–42730.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. A. Filimonov, A. A. Lagunin, T. A. Gloriozova, A. V. Rudik, D. S. Druzhilovskii, P. V. Pogodin, V. V. Poroikov, Chem. Heterocycl. Compd. 2014, 50, 444–457.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. S. Nadaraia, L. S. Amiranashvili, M. Merlani, M. L. Kakhabrishvili, N. N. Barbakadze, A. Geronikaki, A. Petrou, V. Poroikov, A. Ciric, J. Glamoclija, M. Sokovic, Steroids 2019, 144, 52–65.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Banerjee, A. O. Eckert, A. K. Schrey, R. Preissner, NAR 2018, 46, W257–W263.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Banerjee, E. Kemmler, M. Dunkel, R. Preissner, NAR 2024, 52, W513–W520.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. M. Morris, R. Huey, W. Lindstrom, M. F. Sanner, R. K. Belew, D. S. Goodsell, A. J. Olson, J. Comput. Chem. 2009, 16, 2785–2791.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G. Wolber, T. Langer, J. Chem. Inf. Model. 2005, 45, 160–169.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. B. Lansdon, K. M. Brendza, M. Hung, J. Med. Chem. 2010, 53, 4295–4299.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. X. Su, W. F. Zhao, Acta Pharmacol. Sin. 2020, 41, 1167–1177.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Wrapp, N. Wang, K. S. Corbett, J. A. Goldsmith, C. Hsieh, O. Abiona, B. S. Graham, J. S. McLellan, Science 2020, 367, 1260–1263.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Osipiuk, S. A. Azizi, S. Dvorkin, M. Endres, R. Jedrzejczak, K. A. Jones, S. Kang, R. S. Kathayat, Y. Kim, V. G. Lisnyak, S. L. Maki, V. Nicolaescu, C. A. Taylor, C. Tesar, Y. Zhang, Z. Zhou, G. Randall, K. Michalska, S. A. Snyder, B. C. Dickinson, A. Joachimiak, Nat. Commun. 2021, 12, 743–752.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>