<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39444293</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1600-0463</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>APMIS : acta pathologica, microbiologica, et immunologica Scandinavica</Title><ISOAbbreviation>APMIS</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Epidemiological and pathological characterization of acute respiratory infections.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/apm.13484</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>This research comprehensively investigates the epidemiological features and pathogen profile of acute respiratory infections (ARI) in Shihezi City, Xinjiang. A pivotal aspect of this study is the construction of a Bayes discriminant function for principal pathogen infections. This innovative methodology aims to furnish a robust scientific basis for the prevention and clinical management of ARI, potentially guiding more effective strategies in both public health and clinical settings. We compiled and examined data from January 2020 to June 2023, pertaining to patients admitted with acute respiratory infections at the First Affiliated Hospital of Shihezi University. This investigation focused on discerning patterns in epidemiology and pathogen etiology. Among 2110 cases of acute respiratory infections (ARI), 1736 underwent pathogenetic testing. Of these, 595 cases tested positive for at least one pathogen, marking a positivity rate of 34.27%. Viral detections, at a rate of 27.47%, were notably higher than bacterial detections, which stood at 6.51%. The most prevalent viruses identified were Human respiratory syncytial virus (hRSV), Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), and Human adenovirus (HAdV), while the dominant bacterial pathogens included Klebsiella pneumoniae, Haemophilus influenzae, and Staphylococcus aureus. Co-infections were observed in 76 cases, accounting for 12.77% of positive diagnoses, predominantly involving hRSV in conjunction with other pathogens. In cases of acute bronchiolitis, hRSV was the most frequent pathogen, contributing to 23.10% of such cases. Similarly, in severe pneumonia cases, SARS-CoV-2 was predominant, accounting for 25.4% of these infections. The group with bacterial positivity exhibited elevated levels of C-reactive protein (CRP, 19.17 mg/L) and neutrophilic granulocyte percentage (NE%, 54.7%). The Bayes discriminant function demonstrated an initial validation accuracy of 74.9% and a cross-validation accuracy of 63.7%. The study underscores that hRSV, SARS-CoV-2, and HAdV are the primary pathogens in acute respiratory infections in the Shihezi region. Pathogen susceptibility exhibits variation across different age groups, with a higher pathogen detection rate in children compared to adults. The Bayes discriminant function shows significant promise in the classification and diagnosis of major pathogenic infections.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Scandinavian Societies for Pathology, Medical Microbiology and Immunology.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Mengyun</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shihezi University School of Medicine, Shihezi, Xinjiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>He</LastName><ForeName>Wenying</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>First Affiliated Hospital of Shihezi University School of Medicine, Shihezi, Xinjiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xie</LastName><ForeName>Songsong</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0307-6425</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>First Affiliated Hospital of Shihezi University School of Medicine, Shihezi, Xinjiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ren</LastName><ForeName>Zhongye</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shihezi University School of Medicine, Shihezi, Xinjiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Jie</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shihezi University School of Medicine, Shihezi, Xinjiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nuerbolati</LastName><ForeName>Bahejianati</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Shihezi University School of Medicine, Shihezi, Xinjiang, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Denmark</Country><MedlineTA>APMIS</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8803400</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0903-4641</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Acute respiratory infection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bayes model</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pathology</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39444293</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/apm.13484</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Wang X, Li Y, Mei X, Bushe E, Campbell H, Nair H. Global hospital admissions and in‐hospital mortality associated with all‐cause and virus‐specific acute lower respiratory infections in children and adolescents aged 5–19 years between 1995 and 2019: a systematic review and modelling study. BMJ Glob Health. 2021;6:e006014.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Global Burden of Disease Study 2013 Collaborators. Global, regional, and national incidence, prevalence, and years lived with disability for 301 acute and chronic diseases and injuries in 188 countries, 1990‐2013: a systematic analysis for the global burden of disease study 2013. Lancet. 2015;386:743–800.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hongjun L, Yan C, Yana Y, Fang H, Juan D, Shuai W, et al. Surveillance of nine viral pathogens of acute respiratory tract infection in children in Tongzhou District, Beijing from 2011 to 2018. Chin J Infect Control. 2019;18:713–718.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jingjing L, Jianying H, Miaoling L, Yuanhong X, Ke W, Xiaoni Z, et al. Disease burden and prevalence of common pathogens of respiratory tract infections in children in Guangzhou from 2017 to 2022. Chin J Infect Control. 2023;22:44–51.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaoyao Y, Weili Y, Qiaolin L. Viral etiological characteristics of patients with acute respiratory tract infection in Xi'an from 2016 to 2020. Prev Med South China. 2021;47:1417–1419. +1423.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuming M, Fujie S, Yijun W, Jian C, Yaxu Z, Dechuan K, et al. Etiological surveillance of adult cases of acute respiratory tract infection in Huangpu District, Shanghai from 2015 to 2017. Mod Prev Med. 2019;46:2243–2247.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ziyi W, Jian W, Hongzhu W, Ying S, Guixia L, Xikai C, et al. Etiology of acute respiratory tract infection in Taizhou, Zhejiang Province from 2020 to 2021. Shanghai J Prev Med. 2022;34:638–641.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moriyama M, Hugentobler WJ, Iwasaki A. Seasonality of respiratory viral infections. Annu Rev Virol. 2020;7:83–101.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ho NT, Thompson C, Nhan LNT, van HMT, Dung NT, Tran My P, et al. Retrospective analysis assessing the spatial and temporal distribution of paediatric acute respiratory tract infections in Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam. BMJ Open. 2018;8:e016349.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mengfeng L. Etiological Surveillance and Detection Technology of Febrile Respiratory Syndrome. Guangzhou: Sun Yat‐sen University Press; 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mei Y, Lei M, Lixia N, Xiaojuan J, Wanqi Z, Xuezhao L, et al. Pathogen surveillance of febrile respiratory syndrome in Gansu Province from 2010 to 2015. Chin J Dis Cont. 2018;22:908–911.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu G, Xu D, Zhang Y, Wang T, Zhang L, Gu W, et al. Epidemiological characteristics of four common respiratory viral infections in children. Virol J. 2021;18:10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krishnan A, Kumar R, Broor S, Gopal G, Saha S, Amarchand R, et al. Epidemiology of viral acute lower respiratory infections in a community‐based cohort of rural north Indian children. J Glob Health. 2019;9:e010433.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aili C, Zhen Z, Naiying M, Xie ZB, Guan LY, Hu KX, et al. Analysis of common viral infections in surveillance cases of febrile respiratory syndrome in nine provinces of China from 2009 to 2021. Chin J Prev Med. 2022;56:912–918.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jun L, Chunyan L, Zhengde X, Lili R, Baoping X, Jianwei W, et al. Comparative study of single infection and mixed infection of acute lower respiratory syncytial virus in children. Chin J Pract Pediatr. 2015;30:848–851.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goka EA, Vallely PJ, Mutton KJ, Klapper PE. Single and multiple respiratory virus infections and severity of respiratory disease: a systematic review. Paediatr Respir Rev. 2013;15:363–370.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perez A, Lively JY, Curns A. Respiratory virus surveillance among children with acute respiratory illnesses ‐ new vaccine surveillance network, United States, 2016‐2021. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2022;71:1253–1259.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jayaweera JAAS, Morel AJ, Abeykoon AMSB, Pitchai FNN, Kothalawela HS, Peiris JSM, et al. Viral burden and diversity in acute respiratory tract infections in hospitalized children in wet and dry zones of Sri Lanka. PLoS One. 2021;16:e0259443.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Wang X, Blau DM, Caballero MT, Feikin DR, Gill CJ, et al. Global, regional, and national disease burden estimates of acute lower respiratory infections due to respiratory syncytial virus in children younger than 5 years in 2019: a systematic analysis. Lancet. 2022;399:2047–2064.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perin J, Mulick A, Yeung D, Villavicencio F, Lopez G, Strong KL, et al. Global, regional, and national causes of under ‐ 5 mortality in 2000–19:an updated systematic analysis with implications for the sustainable development goals. Lancet Child Adolesc Health. 2022;6:106–115.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen‐Van‐Tam JS, O'Leary M, Martin ET, Heijnen E, Callendret B, Fleischhackl R, et al. Burden of respiratory syncytial virus infection in older and high‐risk adults: a systematic review and meta‐analysis of the evidence from developed countries. Eur Respir Rev. 2022;31:220105.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mazur NI, Terstappen J, Baral R, Bardají A, Beutels P, Buchholz UJ, et al. Respiratory syncytial virus prevention within reach: the vaccine and monoclonal antibody landscape. Lancet Infect Dis. 2023;23:e2–e21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papi A, Ison MG, Langley JM, Lee DG, Leroux‐Roels I, Martinon‐Torres F, et al. Respiratory syncytial virus prefusion F protein vaccine in older adults. N Engl J Med. 2023;388:595–608.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiu X, Xu S, Lu Y, Luo Z, Yan Y, Wang C, et al. Development of mRNA vaccines against respiratory syncytial virus (RSV). Cytokine Growth Factor Rev. 2022;68:37–53.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mazur NI, Higgins D, Nunes MC, Melero JA, Langedijk AC, Horsley N, et al. The respiratory syncytial virus vaccine landscape: lessons from the graveyard and promising candidates. Lancet Infect Dis. 2018;18:e295–e311.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmoele‐Thoma B, Zareba AM, Jiang Q, Maddur MS, Danaf R, Mann A, et al. Vaccine efficacy in adults in a respiratory syncytial virus challenge study. N Engl J Med. 2022;386:2377–2386.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ananworanich J, Heaton PM. Bringing preventive RSV monoclonal antibodies to infants in low‐ and middle‐income countries: challenges and opportunities. Vaccines (Basel). 2021;9:961.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hepper HJ, Sieber C, Walger P, Bahrmann P, Singler K. Infections in the elderly. Crit Care Clin. 2013;29:757–774.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kollef MH, Torres A, Shorr AF, Martin‐Loeches I, Micek ST. Nosocomial infection. Crit Care Med. 2021;49:169–187.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hora SC. Sample size determination in Bayesian discriminant analysis. J Am Stat Assoc. 1978;73:569–572.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duan S, Gu X, Fan G, Zhou F, Zhu G, Cao B. C‐reactive protein or procalcitonin combined with rhinorrhea for discrimination of viral from bacterial infections in hospitalized adults in non‐intensive care units with lower respiratory tract infections. BMC Pulm Med. 2021;21:308.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Henriquez KM, Hayney MS, Rakel DP, Barrett B. Procalcitonin levels in acute respiratory infection. Viral Immunol. 2016;29:128–131.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Min L, Zhang X. Usefulness of procalcitonin (PCT), C‐reactive protein (CRP), and white blood cell (WBC) levels in the differential diagnosis of acute bacterial, viral, and mycoplasmal respiratory tract infections in children. BMC Pulm Med. 2021;21:386.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang X, Zhang Y, Lin H, Zhong H, Wu Z. Diagnostic value of the triple combination of serum heparin‐binding protein, procalcitonin, and C‐reactive protein in children with acute bacterial upper respiratory tract infection. J Healthc Eng. 2022;2022:1877960.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Franz AR, Steinbach G, Kron M, Pohlandt F. Reduction of unnecessary antibiotic therapy in newborn infants using interleukin‐8 and C‐reactive protein as markers of bacterial infections. Pediatrics. 1999;104:447–453.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang N, Wang L, Deng X, Liang R, Su M, He C, et al. Recent advances in the detection of respiratory virus infection in humans. J Med Virol. 2020;92:408–417.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fox JD. Nucleic acid amplification tests for detection of respiratory viruses. J Clin Virol. 2007;40(Suppl 1):S15–S23.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhenqiu S, Yong X. Medical statistics. 4th ed. Beijing: People's Medical Publishing House; 2014. p. 307–308.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>