<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39442699</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1573-2517</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>21</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of affective disorders</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Affect Disord</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Oops, we missed a spot: Comparing data substitution methods for non-random missing survey data in a longitudinal study.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0165-0327(24)01766-X</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.jad.2024.10.070</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Imputation methods for missing data may not always be applicable, namely, when the data were completely missing for the whole sample. To estimate the missing data, we compared three missing item substitution methods: (1) mean substitution; (2) last observation carried forward (LOCF); and (3) regression-predicted values. A total of 384 parents reported their 8- to 18-year-old children's anxiety level using the 9-item Screen for Child Anxiety Related Disorders at baseline (Time 1) and two later time points, drawing from a larger longitudinal study (Ontario COVID-19 and Kids' Mental Health Study). We predicted a survey item measured one month after baseline (Time 2) using: (1) the mean value of the rest of the test items; (2) the value of the same item measured at baseline; and (3) the predicted value from the linear regression with all other test items as predictors. Within-Subjects ANOVA results showed a main effect of substitution methods on total score at Time 2. Post-hoc analysis indicated that mean substitution was significantly different from the actual data. Regression-predicted values overestimated the median compared to the actual values, while the LOCF estimation produced comparable means and identical medians. Similar results were found while using other indicators and extending the analysis to a larger 4-month time interval (Time 3), suggesting LOCF is more accurate and reliable than mean substitution or regression-prediction. This study proposes when advanced substitution methods are not applicable, a systematic comparison of alternative methods may help researchers to arrive at a more informed decision in data processing.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024. Published by Elsevier B.V.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cheung</LastName><ForeName>Theodore C K</ForeName><Initials>TCK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, The Hospital for Sick Children, Toronto, Ontario, Canada; SickKids Research Institute, The Hospital for Sick Children, Toronto, Ontario, Canada. Electronic address: teddy.cheung@sickkids.ca.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cost</LastName><ForeName>Katherine T</ForeName><Initials>KT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>SickKids Research Institute, The Hospital for Sick Children, Toronto, Ontario, Canada; Department of Psychiatry and Behavioural Neurosciences, McMaster University, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Esser</LastName><ForeName>Kayla</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, The Hospital for Sick Children, Toronto, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Anagnostou</LastName><ForeName>Evdokia</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Paediatrics, Temerty Faculty of Medicine, University of Toronto, Ontario, Canada; Department of Paediatrics, Holland Bloorview Kids Rehabilitation Hospital, Toronto, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Birken</LastName><ForeName>Catherine S</ForeName><Initials>CS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, Temerty Faculty of Medicine, University of Toronto, Ontario, Canada; Division of Paediatric Medicine, The Hospital for Sick Children, Toronto, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Charach</LastName><ForeName>Alice</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, The Hospital for Sick Children, Toronto, Ontario, Canada; Department of Psychiatry, Temerty Faculty of Medicine, University of Toronto, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Monga</LastName><ForeName>Suneeta</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, The Hospital for Sick Children, Toronto, Ontario, Canada; Department of Psychiatry, Temerty Faculty of Medicine, University of Toronto, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Korczak</LastName><ForeName>Daphne J</ForeName><Initials>DJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, The Hospital for Sick Children, Toronto, Ontario, Canada; Department of Psychiatry, Temerty Faculty of Medicine, University of Toronto, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Crosbie</LastName><ForeName>Jennifer</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, The Hospital for Sick Children, Toronto, Ontario, Canada; Department of Psychiatry, Temerty Faculty of Medicine, University of Toronto, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>J Affect Disord</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7906073</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0165-0327</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescents</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Children</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Data substitution</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Last observation carried forward</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Missing data</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest T.C.K.C. has received the Gary Hurvitz Health Scientist Fellowship by the Gary Hurvitz Centre for Brain and Mental Health, Hospital for Sick Children, Toronto. K.T.C. has received grants from The Hospital for Sick Children, University of Toronto, and Canadian Institutes of Health Research. They also acted as a statistical consultant for Unity Health and University of Toronto and conference/meeting attendance support from Merit Network. E.A. has received consultation fees from Roche and Quadrant, research funding from Roche and in-kind support from Amo Pharma. She has received book royalties from APPI and Springer, and editorial honoraria from Wiley. She holds a patent for the device, “Tully” (formally “Anxiety Meter”) and in-kind support for all Province of Ontario Neurodevelopmental Network data from the Ontario Brain Institute during the conduct of the study. C.S.B. has received grants from Canadian Institutes of Health Research, Heart &amp; Stroke Foundation of Canada, Physician Services Inc., The Edwin S.H. Leong Centre for Healthy Children, University of Toronto and Hospital for Sick Children, The Center for Addiction and Mental Health, Walmart Canada Regional Community on addressing food insecurity in children admitted to hospital. A.C. has received grants from the Hospital for Sick Children and Leong Centre for Healthy Children. J.C. has received grants from Canadian Institutes of Health Research, Ontario Brain Institute, and the Hospital for Sick Children Foundation. S.M. has received grants from Cundill Centre for Youth Depression at the Centre for Addiction and Mental Health, book royalties from Springer Publishers, and grants from Canadian Institutes of Health Research outside the submitted work. She has received research support as the holder of the TD Bank Financial Group Chair in Child and Adolescent Psychiatry. D.J.K. has received grants from Canadian Institutes of Health Research, Hospital for Sick Children, Gary Hurvitz Centre for Brain and Mental Health, the University of Toronto, and conference/meeting attendance support from the Canadian Paediatric Society and the Canadian Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry. All other authors have no conflicts of interest to declare.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39442699</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2024.10.070</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0165-0327(24)01766-X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>