<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39446094</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1469-445X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Experimental physiology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Exp Physiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Mexican Hispanics show significant improvement in lung function approximately 1 year after having severe COVID-19.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1113/EP091934</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The long-term effects of COVID-19 on lung function are not understood, especially for periods extending beyond 1 year after infection. This observational, longitudinal study investigated lung function in Mexican Hispanics who experienced severe COVID-19, focusing on how the length of recovery affects lung function improvements. At a specialized COVID-19 follow-up clinic in Yucatan, Mexico, lung function and symptoms were assessed in patients who had recovered from severe COVID-19. We used z-scores, and Wilcoxon's signed rank test to analyse changes in lung function over time. Lung function was measured twice in 82 patients: the first and second measurements were taken a median of 94 and 362 days after COVID-19 diagnosis, respectively. Initially, 61% of patients exhibited at least one of several pulmonary function abnormalities (lower limit of normal = -1.645), which decreased to 22% of patients by 390 days post-recovery. Considering day-to-day variability in lung function, 68% of patients showed improvement by the final visit, while 30% had unchanged lung function from the initial assessment. Computed tomography (CT) scans revealed ground-glass opacities in 33% of patients. One year after infection, diffusing capacity of the lungs for carbon monoxide z-scores accounted for 30% of the variation in CT fibrosis scores. There was no significant correlation between the length of recovery and improvement in lung function based on z-scores. In conclusion, 22% of patients who recovered from severe COVID-19 continued to show at least one lung function abnormality 1 year after recovery, indicating a prolonged impact of COVID-19 on lung health.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Experimental Physiology published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of The Physiological Society.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cortes-Telles</LastName><ForeName>Arturo</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5322-5604</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clínica de Enfermedades Respiratorias, Hospital Regional de Alta Especialidad de la Península de Yucatán, IMSS-Bienestar, Mérida, Mexico.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Solís-Díaz</LastName><ForeName>Luis Alberto</ForeName><Initials>LA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3212-1929</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clínica de Enfermedades Respiratorias, Hospital Regional de Alta Especialidad de la Península de Yucatán, IMSS-Bienestar, Mérida, Mexico.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mateos-Toledo</LastName><ForeName>Heidegger</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6125-2565</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clínica de Enfermedades Intersticiales del Pulmón, Instituto Nacional de Enfermedades Respiratorias, CdMx, Mexico.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Guenette</LastName><ForeName>Jordan A</ForeName><Initials>JA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4387-4547</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Heart Lung Innovation, Providence Research, The University of British Columbia and St. Paul's Hospital, Vancouver, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physical Therapy, The University of British Columbia, Vancouver, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zavorsky</LastName><ForeName>Gerald Stanley</ForeName><Initials>GS</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4473-1601</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physiology and Membrane Biology, University of California, Davis, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Exp Physiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9002940</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0958-0670</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS‐CoV‐2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">diffusing capacity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">obstruction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">recovery</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">restriction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">spirometry</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39446094</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1113/EP091934</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Abdallah, S. J., Voduc, N., Corrales‐Medina, V. F., Mcguinty, M., Pratt, A., Chopra, A., Law, A., Garuba, H. A., Thavorn, K., Reid, R. E. R., Lavoie, K. L., Crawley, A., Chirinos, J. A., &amp; Cowan, J. (2021). Symptoms, pulmonary function and functional capacity four months after COVID‐19. Annals of the American Thoracic Society, 18(11), 1912–1917.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Angeles Montero‐Fernandez, M., &amp; Pardo‐Garcia, R. (2021). Histopathology features of the lung in COVID‐19 patients. Diagnostic Histopathology, 27(3), 123–127.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bellan, M., Baricich, A., Patrucco, F., Zeppegno, P., Gramaglia, C., Balbo, P. E., Carriero, A., Amico, C. S., Avanzi, G. C., Barini, M., Battaglia, M., Bor, S., Cantaluppi, V., Cappellano, G., Ceruti, F., Chiocchetti, A., Clivati, E., Giordano, M., Cuneo, D., … Pirisi, M. (2021). Long‐term sequelae are highly prevalent one year after hospitalization for severe COVID‐19. Scientific Reports, 11(1), 22666.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bellan, M., Soddu, D., Balbo, P. E., Baricich, A., Zeppegno, P., Avanzi, G. C., Baldon, G., Bartolomei, G., Battaglia, M., Battistini, S., Binda, V., Borg, M., Cantaluppi, V., Castello, L. M., Clivati, E., Cisari, C., Costanzo, M., Croce, A., Cuneo, D., … Pirisi, M. (2021). Respiratory and psychophysical sequelae among patients with COVID‐19 four months after hospital discharge. The Journal of The American Medical Association Network Open, 4(1), e2036142.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benjamini, Y., &amp; Yekutieli, D. (2001). The control of the false discovery rate in multiple testing under dependency. Annals of Statistics, 29(4), 1165–1188.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blanco, J.‐R., Cobos‐Ceballos, M.‐J., Navarro, F., Sanjoaquin, I., Arnaiz De Las Revillas, F., Bernal, E., Buzon‐Martin, L., Viribay, M., Romero, L., Espejo‐Perez, S., Valencia, B., Ibañez, D., Ferrer‐Pargada, D., Malia, D., Gutierrez‐Herrero, F.‐G., Olalla, J., Jurado‐Gamez, B., &amp; Ugedo, J. (2021). Pulmonary long‐term consequences of COVID‐19 infections after hospital discharge. Clinical Microbiology and Infection, 27(6), 892–896.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bland, J. M., &amp; Altman, D. G. (1996). Measurement error. British Medical Journal, 312(7047), 1654.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bowerman, C., Bhakta, N. R., Brazzale, D., Cooper, B. R., Cooper, J., Gochicoa‐Rangel, L., Haynes, J., Kaminsky, D. A., Lan, L. T. T., Masekela, R., Mccormack, M. C., Steenbruggen, I., &amp; Stanojevic, S. (2023). A race‐neutral approach to the interpretation of lung function measurements. American Journal of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine, 207(6), 768–774.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brems, J. H., Balasubramanian, A., Raju, S., Putcha, N., Fawzy, A., Hansel, N. N., Wise, R. A., &amp; Mccormack, M. C. (2024). Changes in spirometry interpretative strategies: Implications for classifying COPD and predicting exacerbations. Chest, 166(2), 294–303.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chommeloux, J., Valentin, S., Winiszewski, H., Adda, M., Pineton De Chambrun, M., Moyon, Q., Mathian, A., Capellier, G., Guervilly, C., Levy, B., Jaquet, P., Sonneville, R., Voiriot, G., Demoule, A., Boussouar, S., Painvin, B., Lebreton, G., Combes, A., &amp; Schmidt, M. (2023). One‐year mental and physical health assessment in survivors after extracorporeal membrane oxygenation for COVID‐19‐related acute respiratory distress syndrome. American Journal of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine, 207(2), 150–159.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corsi, A., Caroli, A., Bonaffini, P. A., Conti, C., Arrigoni, A., Mercanzin, E., Imeri, G., Anelli, M., Balbi, M., Pace, M., Zanoletti, A., Capelli, M., Di Marco, F., &amp; Sironi, S. (2022). Structural and functional pulmonary assessment in severe COVID‐19 survivors at 12 months after discharge. Tomography, 8(5), 2588–2603.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cortes‐Telles, A., Figueroa‐Hurtado, E., Ortiz‐Farias, D. L., &amp; Zavorsky, G. S. (2022). Clinical predictors of lung function in patients recovering from mild COVID‐19. BioMed Central Pulmonary Medicine, 22(1), 294.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cortés‐Telles, A., López‐Romero, S., Figueroa‐Hurtado, E., Pou‐Aguilar, Y. N., Wong, A. W., Milne, K. M., Ryerson, C. J., &amp; Guenette, J. A. (2021). Pulmonary function and functional capacity in COVID‐19 survivors with persistent dyspnoea. Respiratory Physiology &amp; Neurobiology, 288, 103644.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ekbom, E., Frithiof, R., Emilsson, O., Larson, L. M., Lipcsey, M., Rubertsson, S., Wallin, E., Janson, C., &amp; Hultström, M. (2021). Impaired diffusing capacity for carbon monoxide is common in critically ill Covid‐19 patients at four months post‐discharge. Respiratory Medicine, 182, 106394.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fraser, E., St Noble, V., Hoyles, R. K., Benamore, R., &amp; Ho, L. P. (2020). Readily accessible CT scoring method to quantify fibrosis in IPF. British Medical Journal Open Respiratory Research, 7(1), e000584.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fumagalli, A., Misuraca, C., Bianchi, A., Borsa, N., Limonta, S., Maggiolini, S., Bonardi, D. R., Corsonello, A., Di Rosa, M., Soraci, L., Lattanzio, F., &amp; Colombo, D. (2022). Long‐term changes in pulmonary function among patients surviving to COVID‐19 pneumonia. Infection, 50(4), 1019–1022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghasemi, A., &amp; Zahediasl, S. (2012). Normality tests for statistical analysis: A guide for non‐statisticians. International Journal of Endocrinology and Metabolism, 10(2), 486–489.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gochicoa‐Rangel, L., Hernández‐Morales, A. P., Salles‐Rojas, A., Madrid‐Mejía, W., Guzmán‐Valderrábano, C., González‐Molina, A., Salas‐Escamilla, I., Durán‐Cuellar, A., Silva‐Cerón, M., Hernández‐Morales, V., Reyes‐García, A., Alvarado‐Amador, I., Lozano‐Martínez, L., Enright, P., Pensado‐Piedra, L. E., &amp; Torre‐Bouscoulet, L. (2021). Gas exchange impairment during COVID‐19 recovery. Respiratory Care, 66(10), 1610–1617.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gochicoa‐Rangel, L. G., De‐Los‐Santos Martinez, A., Reyes‐Garcia, A., Briseno, D. M., Vargas, M. H., &amp; Lechuga‐Trejo, I. (2024). Reference equations for DLNO &amp; DLCO in Mexican Hispanics: Influence of altitude and race. British Medical Journal Open Respiratory Research, 11(1), e002341.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goh, N. S. L., Desai, S. R., Veeraraghavan, S., Hansell, D. M., Copley, S. J., Maher, T. M., Corte, T. J., Sander, C. R., Ratoff, J., Devaraj, A., Bozovic, G., Denton, C. P., Black, C. M., Du Bois, R. M., &amp; Wells, A. U. (2008). Interstitial lung disease in systemic sclerosis: A simple staging system. American Journal of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine, 177(11), 1248–1254.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guler, S. A., Ebner, L., Aubry‐Beigelman, C., Bridevaux, P.‐O., Brutsche, M., Clarenbach, C., Garzoni, C., Geiser, T. K., Lenoir, A., Mancinetti, M., Naccini, B., Ott, S. R., Piquilloud, L., Prella, M., Que, Y.‐A., Soccal, P. M., Von Garnier, C., &amp; Funke‐Chambour, M. (2021). Pulmonary function and radiological features 4 months after COVID‐19: First results from the national prospective observational Swiss COVID‐19 lung study. European Respiratory Journal, 57(4), 2003690.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han, X., Fan, Y., Alwalid, O., Li, N., Jia, X., Yuan, M., Li, Y., Cao, Y., Gu, J., Wu, H., &amp; Shi, H. (2021). Six‐month follow‐up chest CT findings after severe COVID‐19 pneumonia. Radiology, 299(1), E177–E186.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hellemons, M. E., Huijts, S., Bek, L. M., Berentschot, J. C., Nakshbandi, G., Schurink, C. A. M., Vlake, J. H., Van Genderen, M. E., Van Bommel, J., Gommers, D., Odink, A., Ciet, P., Shamier, M. C., Geurts Van Kessel, C., Baart, S. J., Ribbers, G. M., Van Den Berg‐Emons, R. J. G., Heijenbrok‐Kal, M. H., &amp; Aerts, J. G. J. V. (2022). Persistent health problems beyond pulmonary recovery up to 6 months after hospitalization for COVID‐19: A longitudinal study of respiratory, physical, and psychological outcomes. Annals of the American Thoracic Society, 19(4), 551–561.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hopkins, W. G. (2000). Measures of reliability in sports medicine and science. Sports Medicine, 30(1), 1–15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang, Y., Tan, C., Wu, J., Chen, M., Wang, Z., Luo, L., Zhou, X., Liu, X., Huang, X., Yuan, S., Chen, C., Gao, F., Huang, J., Shan, H., &amp; Liu, J. (2020). Impact of coronavirus disease 2019 on pulmonary function in early convalescence phase. Respiratory Research, 21(1), 163.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Konsberg, Y., Szaro, P., Aneman, A., Kjellberg, S., Solidakis, N., Svedlund, S., Nellgård, B., &amp; Dalla, K. (2023). Radiological appearance and lung function six months after invasive ventilation in ICU for COVID‐19 pneumonia: An observational follow‐up study. PLoS ONE, 18(9), e0289603.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lavin, K. M., Guenette, J. A., Smoliga, J. M., &amp; Zavorsky, G. S. (2015). Controlled‐frequency breath swimming improves swimming performance and running economy. Scandinavian Journal of Medicine &amp; Science in Sports, 25(1), 16–24.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang, L., Yang, B., Jiang, N., Fu, W., He, X., Zhou, Y., Ma, W.‐L., &amp; Wang, X. (2020). Three‐month follow‐up study of survivors of Coronavirus disease 2019 after discharge. Journal of Korean Medical Science, 35(47), e418.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, K., Zhang, W., Yang, Y., Zhang, J., Li, Y., &amp; Chen, Y. (2020). Respiratory rehabilitation in elderly patients with COVID‐19: A randomized controlled study. Complementary Therapies in Clinical Practice, 39, 101166.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mainous, A. G., 3rd, Rooks, B. J., Wu, V., &amp; Orlando, F. A. (2021). COVID‐19 post‐acute sequelae among adults: 12 month mortality risk. Frontiers in Medicine, 8, 778434.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mo, X., Jian, W., Su, Z., Chen, M., Peng, H., Peng, P., Lei, C., Chen, R., Zhong, N., &amp; Li, S. (2020). Abnormal pulmonary function in COVID‐19 patients at time of hospital discharge. European Respiratory Journal, 55(6), 2001217.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morin, L., Savale, L., Pham, T., Colle, R., Figueiredo, S., Harrois, A., Gasnier, M., Lecoq, A. L., Meyrignac, O., Noel, N., Baudry, E., Bellin, M. F., Beurnier, A., Choucha, W., Corruble, E., Dortet, L., Hardy‐Leger, I., Radiguer, F., Sportouch, S., … Monnet, X. (2021). Four‐month clinical status of a cohort of patients after hospitalization for COVID‐19. Journal of the American Medical Association, 325, 1525–1534.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qin, W., Chen, S., Zhang, Y., Dong, F., Zhang, Z., Hu, B., Zhu, Z., Li, F., Wang, X., Wang, Y., Zhen, K., Wang, J., Wan, Y., Li, H., Elalamy, I., Li, C., Zhai, Z., &amp; Wang, C. (2021). Diffusion capacity abnormalities for carbon monoxide in patients with COVID‐19 at 3‐month follow‐up. European Respiratory Journal, 58(1), 2003677.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quanjer, P. H., Stanojevic, S., Cole, T. J., Baur, X., Hall, G. L., Culver, B. H., Enright, P. L., Hankinson, J. L., Ip, M. S. M., Zheng, J., &amp; Stocks, J. (2012). Multi‐ethnic reference values for spirometry for the 3‐95‐yr age range: The global lung function 2012 equations. European Respiratory Journal, 40(6), 1324–1343.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah, A. S., Wong, A. W., Hague, C. J., Murphy, D. T., Johnston, J. C., Ryerson, C. J., &amp; Carlsten, C. (2021). A prospective study of 12‐week respiratory outcomes in COVID‐19‐related hospitalisations. Thorax, 76(4), 402–404.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sonnweber, T., Sahanic, S., Pizzini, A., Luger, A., Schwabl, C., Sonnweber, B., Kurz, K., Koppelstätter, S., Haschka, D., Petzer, V., Boehm, A., Aichner, M., Tymoszuk, P., Lener, D., Theurl, M., Lorsbach‐Köhler, A., Tancevski, A., Schapfl, A., Schaber, M., … Tancevski, I. (2021). Cardiopulmonary recovery after COVID‐19: An observational prospective multicentre trial. European Respiratory Journal, 57(4), 2003481.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stanojevic, S., Graham, B. L., Cooper, B. G., Thompson, B. R., Carter, K. W., Francis, R. W., &amp; Hall, G. L. (2017). Official ERS technical standards: Global Lung Function Initiative reference values for the carbon monoxide transfer factor for Caucasians. European Respiratory Journal, 50(3), 1700010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stanojevic, S., Kaminsky, D. A., Miller, M. R., Thompson, B., Aliverti, A., Barjaktarevic, I., Cooper, B. G., Culver, B., Derom, E., Hall, G. L., Hallstrand, T. S., Leuppi, J. D., MacIntyre, N., McCormack, M., Rosenfeld, M., &amp; Swenson, E. R. (2022). ERS/ATS technical standard on interpretive strategies for routine lung function tests. European Respiratory Journal, 60(1), 2101499.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steinbeis, F., Knape, P., Mittermaier, M., Helbig, E. T., Tober‐Lau, P., Thibeault, C., Lippert, L. J., Xiang, W., Müller‐Plathe, M., Steinbrecher, S., Meyer, H.‐J., Ring, R. M., Ruwwe‐Glösenkamp, C., Alius, F., Li, Y., Müller‐Redetzky, H., Uhrig, A., Lingscheid, T., Grund, D., … Zoller, T. (2022). Functional limitations 12 months after SARS‐CoV‐2 infection correlate with initial disease severity: An observational study of cardiopulmonary exercise capacity testing in COVID‐19 convalescents. Respiratory Medicine, 202, 106968.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tarraso, J., Safont, B., Carbonell‐Asins, J. A., Fernandez‐Fabrellas, E., Sancho‐Chust, J. N., Naval, E., Amat, B., Herrera, S., Ros, J. A., Soler‐Cataluña, J. J., Rodriguez‐Portal, J. A., Andreu, A. L., Marín, M., Rodriguez‐Hermosa, J. L., Gonzalez‐Villaescusa, C., Soriano, J. B., Signes‐Costa, J., García, Y., Blasco, N., … Vargas, G. (2022). Lung function and radiological findings 1 year after COVID‐19: A prospective follow‐up. Respiratory Research, 23(1), 242.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Den Borst, B., Peters, J. B., Brink, M., Schoon, Y., Bleeker‐Rovers, C. P., Schers, H., Van Hees, H. W. H., Van Helvoort, H., Van Den Boogaard, M., Van Der Hoeven, H., Reijers, M. H., Prokop, M., Vercoulen, J., &amp; Van Den Heuvel, M. (2021). Comprehensive health assessment 3 months after recovery from Acute Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID‐19). Clinical Infectious Diseases, 73(5), e1089–e1098.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. (2023). Clinical management of COVID‐19: Living guideline, 18 August 2023 (pp. 1–186) Geneva. (WHO/2019‐nCoV/clinical/2023.2). License: CC BY‐NC‐SA 3.0 IGO. World Health Organization (WHO).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong, A. W., López‐Romero, S., Figueroa‐Hurtado, E., Vazquez‐Lopez, S., Milne, K. M., Ryerson, C. J., Guenette, J. A., &amp; Cortés‐Telles, A. (2021). Predictors of reduced 6‐minute walk distance after COVID‐19: A cohort study in Mexico. Pulmonology, 27(6), 563–565.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, W. J., Huang, W. M., Liang, C. H., &amp; Yun, C. H. (2022). Pulmonary vascular volume is associated with DLCO and fibrotic score in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis: An observational study. BioMed Central Medical Imaging, 22(1), 76.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, X., Liu, X., Zhou, Y., Yu, H., Li, R., Zhan, Q., Ni, F., Fang, S., Lu, Y., Ding, X., Liu, H., Ewing, R. M., Jones, M. G., Hu, Y., Nie, H., &amp; Wang, Y. (2021). 3‐month, 6‐month, 9‐month, and 12‐month respiratory outcomes in patients following COVID‐19‐related hospitalisation: A prospective study. Lancet Respiratory Medicine, 9(7), 747–754.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zavorsky, G. S., &amp; Cao, J. (2022). Reference equations for pulmonary diffusing capacity using segmented regression show similar predictive accuracy as GAMLSS models. British Medical Journal Open Respiratory Research, 9(1), e001087.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zavorsky, G. S., &amp; Cortes‐Telles, A. (2024a). Changes in spirometry and pulmonary diffusing capacity in Mexican Hispanics approximately one year after having severe COVID‐19: A dataset. Data in Brief. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.dib.2024.110998</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zavorsky, G. S., &amp; Cortes‐Telles, A. (2024b). Long‐term changes in spirometry and diffusing capacity in Mexican Hispanics with previous severe COVID‐19, Mendeley Data, V4. https://doi.org/10.17632/xmmyb9rgjj.4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, Y., Yang, C., An, X., Xiong, Y., Shang, Y., He, J., Qiu, Y., Zhang, N., Huang, L., Jia, J., Xu, Q., Zhang, L., Zhao, J., Pei, G., Luo, H., Wang, J., Li, Q., Gao, Y., &amp; Xu, A. (2021). Follow‐up study on COVID‐19 survivors one year after discharge from hospital. International Journal of Infectious Diseases, 112, 173–182.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, Y.‐M., Shang, Y.‐M., Song, W.‐B., Li, Q.‐Q., Xie, H., Xu, Q.‐F., Jia, J.‐L., Li, L.‐M., Mao, H.‐L., Zhou, X.‐M., Luo, H., Gao, Y.‐F., &amp; Xu, A.‐G. (2020). Follow‐up study of the pulmonary function and related physiological characteristics of COVID‐19 survivors three months after recovery. eClinicalMedicine, 25, 100463.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou, F., Tao, M., Shang, L., Liu, Y., Pan, G., Jin, Y., Wang, L., Hu, S., Li, J., Zhang, M., Fu, Y., &amp; Yang, S. (2021). Assessment of sequelae of COVID‐19 nearly 1 year after diagnosis. Frontiers in Medicine, 8, 717194.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>