<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39447707</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1879-0038</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>22</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Gene</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Gene</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Optimal control analysis on the spread of COVID-19: Impact of contact transmission and environmental contamination.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>149033</StartPage><MedlinePgn>149033</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.gene.2024.149033</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0378-1119(24)00914-4</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The study investigates the intricate dynamics of SARS-CoV-2 transmission, with a particular focus on both close-contact interactions and environmental factors. Using advanced mathematical modeling and epidemiological analysis, explored the effects of these transmission pathways on the spread of COVID-19. The equilibrium points for both the disease-free and endemic states calculated and evaluated their global stability. Additionally, the basic reproduction number (R<sub>0</sub>) is derived to quantify the transmission potential of the virus. To ensure model accuracy, numerical simulations are performed using MATLAB, utilizing daily COVID-19 case data from India. Parameter values are sourced from existing literature, with certain parameters estimated through fitting the model to observed data. Crucially, the model incorporates environmental transmission factors, such as surface contamination and airborne spread. The inclusion of these factors provides a more comprehensive understanding of the virus's spread, demonstrating the importance of interventions like use of face masks, environmental sanitization, vaccine efficacy, availability of treatment resources underappreciated when focusing solely on direct human contact. A sensitivity analysis is conducted to assess the impact of different parameters on R<sub>0</sub>, with results visualized through heat maps to identify the most influential factors. Furthermore, Pontryagin's maximum principle is employed to develop an optimal control model, enabling the formulation of effective intervention strategies. By analysing both interpersonal and environmental transmission mechanisms, this study offers a more holistic framework for understanding SARS-CoV-2 transmission. The insights gained are critical for informing public health strategies, emphasizing the necessity of addressing both direct contact and environmental sources of infection to more effectively manage current and future outbreaks.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024. Published by Elsevier B.V.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Singh Negi</LastName><ForeName>Sunil</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Mathematics, National Institute of Technology, Uttarakhand, Srinagar Garhwal 246174, India. Electronic address: negisunil94@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ravina</LastName><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Mathematics, National Institute of Technology, Uttarakhand, Srinagar Garhwal 246174, India. Electronic address: ravinayadav9582@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sharma</LastName><ForeName>Nitin</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Mathematics, National Institute of Technology, Uttarakhand, Srinagar Garhwal 246174, India. Electronic address: drnitinsharma@hotmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Priyadarshi</LastName><ForeName>Anupam</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Mathematics, Institute of Science, Banaras Hindu University, Varanasi, India. Electronic address: anupampriya@bhu.ac.in.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Gene</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7706761</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0378-1119</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mathematical modelling</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Optimal control</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pontryagin’s maximum principle</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>25</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39447707</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.gene.2024.149033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0378-1119(24)00914-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>