<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39445780</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1098-5336</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Applied and environmental microbiology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Appl Environ Microbiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The structure of lipopeptides impacts their antiviral activity and mode of action against SARS-CoV-2 <i>in vitro</i>.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e0103624</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e0103624</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1128/aem.01036-24</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="UNLABELLED">Microbial lipopeptides are synthesized by nonribosomal peptide synthetases and are composed of a hydrophobic fatty acid chain and a hydrophilic peptide moiety. These structurally diverse amphiphilic molecules can interact with biological membranes and possess various biological activities, including antiviral properties. This study aimed to evaluate the cytotoxicity and antiviral activity against severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) of 15 diverse lipopeptides to understand their structure-activity relationships. Non-ionic lipopeptides were generally more cytotoxic than charged ones, with cationic lipopeptides being less cytotoxic than anionic and non-ionic variants. At 100 µg/mL, six lipopeptides reduced SARS-CoV-2 RNA to undetectable levels in infected Vero E6 cells, while six others achieved a 2.5- to 4.1-log reduction, and three had no significant effect. Surfactin, white line-inducing principle (WLIP), fengycin, and caspofungin emerged as the most promising anti-SARS-CoV-2 agents. Detailed analysis revealed that these four lipopeptides affected various stages of the viral life cycle involving the viral envelope. Surfactin and WLIP significantly reduced viral RNA levels in replication assays, comparable to neutralizing serum. Surfactin uniquely inhibited viral budding, while fengycin impacted viral binding after pre-infection treatment of the cells. Caspofungin demonstrated a lower antiviral effect compared to the others. Key structural traits of lipopeptides influencing their cytotoxic and antiviral activities were identified. Lipopeptides with a high number of amino acids, especially charged (preferentially anionic) amino acids, showed potent anti-SARS-CoV-2 activity. This research paves the way for designing new lipopeptides with low cytotoxicity and high antiviral efficacy, potentially leading to effective treatments.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="IMPORTANCE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">This study advances our understanding of how lipopeptides, which are molecules mostly produced by bacteria, with both fat and protein components, can be used to fight viruses like severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2). By analyzing 15 different lipopeptides, researchers identified key structural features that make some of these molecules particularly effective at reducing viral levels while being less harmful to cells. Specifically, lipopeptides with certain charged amino acids were found to have the strongest antiviral effects. This research lays the groundwork for developing new antiviral treatments that are both potent against viruses and safe for human cells, offering hope for better therapeutic options in the future.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hoste</LastName><ForeName>Alexis C R</ForeName><Initials>ACR</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6724-6062</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MiPI, TERRA Teaching and Research Centre, Joint Research Unit BioEcoAgro, UMRt 1158, Gembloux Agro-Bio Tech, University of Liège, Gembloux, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Veterinary Pathology, FARAH Research Centre, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Liège, Liège, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Smeralda</LastName><ForeName>Willy</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>LBMI, TERRA Teaching and Research Centre, Joint Research Unit BioEcoAgro, UMRt 1158, Gembloux Agro-Bio Tech, University of Liège, Gembloux, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cugnet</LastName><ForeName>Aurélien</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MiPI, TERRA Teaching and Research Centre, Joint Research Unit BioEcoAgro, UMRt 1158, Gembloux Agro-Bio Tech, University of Liège, Gembloux, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Brostaux</LastName><ForeName>Yves</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Applied Statistics, Computer Science and Modelling laboratory, TERRA Teaching and Research Centre, Gembloux Agro-Bio Tech, University of Liège, Gembloux, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Deleu</LastName><ForeName>Magali</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>LBMI, TERRA Teaching and Research Centre, Joint Research Unit BioEcoAgro, UMRt 1158, Gembloux Agro-Bio Tech, University of Liège, Gembloux, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Garigliany</LastName><ForeName>Mutien</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Veterinary Pathology, FARAH Research Centre, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Liège, Liège, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Jacques</LastName><ForeName>Philippe</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4392-9525</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MiPI, TERRA Teaching and Research Centre, Joint Research Unit BioEcoAgro, UMRt 1158, Gembloux Agro-Bio Tech, University of Liège, Gembloux, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Appl Environ Microbiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7605801</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0099-2240</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">WLIP</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antiviral</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">caspofungin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cytotoxicity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">fengycin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">lipopeptides</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">structure-activity relationship</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">surfactin</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39445780</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/aem.01036-24</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>