<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39449272</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1525-1446</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Public health nursing (Boston, Mass.)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Public Health Nurs</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Relationship Between Primary School Teachers' COVID-19 Fear Levels and COVID-19 Vaccine Attitudes After the Start of Face-to-face Education During the Pandemic Period: A School Health Study.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/phn.13469</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="CONTEXT" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Starting face-to-face education while the COVID-19 pandemic was ongoing was a risk for public health. Determining teachers' initial reactions to public health practices during this high-risk period may contribute to the redesign of public health and school nursing policies.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">The aim of this research is to examine the relationship between primary school teachers' COVID-19 fear levels and COVID-19 vaccine attitudes.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DESIGN" NlmCategory="METHODS">The research has a descriptive correlational design. The data were obtained from teachers working in primary schools (n = 430). Simple random sampling method was used in the data collection process. Data were obtained with the Scale of Attitudes Towards COVID-19 Vaccine and Fear of COVID-19 Scale.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">In the study, 50.5% of teachers reported that they were afraid of catching COVID-19, 41.9% said their risk of catching COVID-19 was "high," and 87.7% reported that they voluntarily got the COVID-19 vaccine. Of the teachers, 4.6% (n = 20) stated that they regretted getting vaccinated. A positive and significant relationship was found between teachers' Fear of COVID-19 Scale and COVID-19 Vaccine Attitude Scale scores (r = 0.133, p &lt; 0.001).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">During the pandemic, it was observed that teachers' fear level of COVID-19 increased with the start of face-to-face education. In addition, it is seen that teachers started to have doubts about some public health practices. This may indicate that public health nurses should take a more active role in school health practices.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Public Health Nursing published by Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tayhan</LastName><ForeName>Ali</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health Nursing, Faculty of Health Sciences, Manisa Celal Bayar University, Manisa, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Işık</LastName><ForeName>Kübra</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hafsa Sultan Hospital, Manisa Celal Bayar University, Manisa, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>1919B012107711</GrantID><Agency>Scientific and Technical Research Council of Turkey</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Public Health Nurs</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8501498</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0737-1209</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">face to face education</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">public health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">school nursing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">teacher</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vaccination</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39449272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/phn.13469</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>Ahorsu, D. K., C. Y. Lin, V. Imani, M. Saffari, M. D. Griffiths, and A. H. Pakpour. 2022. “The Fear of COVID‐19 Scale: Development and Initial Validation.” International Journal of Mental Health and Addiction 20, no. 3: 1537–1545. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11469‐020‐00270‐8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braun, V., and V. Clarke. 2021. Thematic Analysis: A Practical Guide. Thousand Oaks, CA: SAGE.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brownson, R. C., T. A. Burke, G. A. Colditz, and J. M. Samet. 2020. “Reimagining Public Health in the Aftermath of a Pandemic.” American Journal of Public Health 110, no. 11: 1605–1610. https://doi.org/10.2105/AJPH.2020.305861.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Budak, F., and Ş. Korkmaz. 2020. “COVID‐19 Pandemi sürecine yönelik Genel Bir Değerlendirme: Türkiye örneği.” Sosyal Araştırmalar Ve Yönetim Dergisi 1: 62–79. https://doi.org/10.35375/sayod.738657.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buonsenso, D., D. Roland, C. De Rose, et al. 2021. “Schools Closures During the COVID‐19 Pandemic: A Catastrophic Global Situation.” The Pediatric Infectious Disease Journal 40, no. 4: e146–e150. https://doi.org/10.1097/INF.0000000000003052.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Colosi, E., G. Bassignana, D. A. Contreras, et al. 2022. “Screening and Vaccination Against COVID‐19 to Minimise School Closure: A Modelling Study.” The Lancet. Infectious Diseases 22, no. 7: 977–989. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1473‐3099(22)00138‐4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cuschieri, S. 2019. “The STROBE Guidelines.” Saudi Journal of Anaesthesia 13, no. 1: 31–34. https://doi.org/10.4103/sja.SJA_543_18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galanti, C. 2022. “National Heroes, Disposable Workers. How Collective Action in the Health and Social Care Sector During the Pandemic Negotiated With the Self‐sacrificing Worker Ideal.” Gender Work and Organization 31, no. 26: 1–19. https://doi.org/10.1111/gwao.12852.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Geniş, B., N. Gürhan, M. Koç, et al. 2020. “Development of Perception and Attitude Scales Related With COVID‐19 Pandemia.” Pearson Journal of Social Sciences—Humanities 5, no. 7: 306–328. https://doi.org/10.46872/pj.127.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>George, D., and P. Mallery, eds. 2018. “Descriptive Statistics.” In IBM SPSS Statistics 25 Step by Step, 15th edition, 126–134. New York: Routledge.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hommes, F., W. van Loon, M. Thielecke, et al. 2021. “SARS‐CoV‐2 Infection, Risk Perception, Behaviour and Preventive Measures at Schools in Berlin, Germany, During the Early Post‐Lockdown Phase: A Cross‐Sectional Study.” International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 18, no. 5: 2739. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph18052739.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horton, D., P. Spigelmyer, R. Zoucha, and T. Rebmann. 2023. “Disaster Preparedness in K‐12 Schools: An Integrative Review.” Journal of School Health 93, no. 8: 726–732. https://doi.org/10.1111/josh.13319.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jennings, W., G. Stoker, H. Bunting, et al. 2021. “Lack of Trust, Conspiracy Beliefs, and Social Media Use Predict COVID‐19 Vaccine Hesitancy.” Vaccines 9, no. 6: 593. https://doi.org/10.3390/vaccines9060593.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kadam, P., and S. Bhalerao. 2010. “Sample Size Calculation.” International Journal of Ayurveda Research 1, no. 1: 55–57. https://doi.org/10.4103/0974‐7788.59946.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ladikli, N., E. Bahadir, F. N. Yumuşak, H. Akkuzu, G. Karaman, and Z. Türkkan. 2020. “Kovid‐19 Korkusu Ölçeği'nin Türkçe güvenirlik Ve geçerlik çalişmasi.” International Journal of Social Science 3, no. 2: 71–80.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Latkin, C., L. Dayton, J. Miller, et al. 2022. “A Longitudinal Study of Vaccine Hesitancy Attitudes and Social Influence as Predictors of COVID‐19 Vaccine Uptake in the US.” Human Vaccines &amp; Immunotherapeutics 18, no. 5: 2043102. https://doi.org/10.1080/21645515.2022.2043102.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, N., and X. Yu. 2024. “Characteristic Analysis of China's Actions Against the COVID‐19 in Schools and Comparison With Other Countries.” Public Health Nursing 41, no. 2: 255–263. https://doi.org/10.1111/phn.13275.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, Q., Y. Miao, X. Zeng, C. S. Tarimo, C. Wu, and J. Wu. 2020. “Prevalence and Factors for Anxiety During the Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID‐19) Epidemic Among the Teachers in China.” Journal of Affective Disorders 277: 153–158. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jad.2020.08.017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo, C., W. Jiang, H. X. Chen, and T. H. Tung. 2022. “Post‐Vaccination Adverse Reactions, Decision Regret, and Willingness to Pay for the Booster Dose of COVID‐19 Vaccine Among Healthcare Workers: A Mediation Analysis.” Human Vaccines &amp; Immunotherapeutics 18, no. 6: 2146964. https://doi.org/10.1080/21645515.2022.2146964.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munro, A., D. Buonsenso, S. González‐Dambrauskas, et al. 2023. “In‐Person Schooling Is Essential Even During Periods of High Transmission of COVID‐19.” BMJ Evidence‐Based Medicine 28, no. 3: 175–179. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjebm‐2023‐112277.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muz, F. N. Ö., S. Metintaş, M. F. Önsüz, C. Çam, A. Kılınç, and S. A. Gedik. 2022. “Assessment of Teachers' Knowledge and Attitudes Toward Vaccines.” Journal of Current Pediatrics/Guncel Pediatrics 20, no. 3: 310–317. https://doi.org/10.4274/jcp.2022.24654.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okagbue, E. F., U. P. Ezeachikulo, I. S. Nchekwubemchukwu, et al. 2023. “The Effects of COVID‐19 Pandemic on the Education System in Nigeria: The Role of Competency‐Based Education.” International Journal of Educational Research Open 4: 100219. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijedro.2022.100219.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryan, J., N. Koehler, T. Cruickshank, S. L. Rogers, and M. Stanley. 2023. “‘Teachers Are the Guinea Pigs’: Teacher Perspectives on a Sudden Reopening of Schools During the COVID‐19 Pandemic.” Australian Educational Researcher 51, no. 1: 1–17. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13384‐022‐00577‐6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santiago, I. S. D., E. P. Dos Santos, J. A. daSilva, et al. 2023. “The Impact of the COVID‐19 Pandemic on the Mental Health of Teachers and Its Possible Risk Factors: A Systematic Review.” International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 20, no. 3: 1747. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph20031747.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Savadori, L., and M. Lauriola. 2021. “Risk Perception and Protective Behaviors During the Rise of the COVID‐19 Outbreak in Italy.” Frontiers in Psychology 11: 577331. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2020.577331.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tatarkova, M., R. Ulbrichtova, V. Svihrova, et al. 2022. “Secondary School Teachers and Outpatient Physicians: Differences in Attitudes towards Vaccination Against COVID‐19 in Slovakia.” Vaccines 10, no. 11: 1858. https://doi.org/10.3390/vaccines10111858.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNESCO. 2024. Monitoring Teacher Vaccination against COVID‐19. Accessed September 21, 2024. Available online. https://www.unesco.org/en/articles/monitoring‐teacher‐vaccination‐against‐COVID‐19.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walger, P., U. Heininger, M. Knuf, et al. 2020. “Children and Adolescents in the COVID‐19 Pandemic: Schools and Daycare Centers Are to be Opened Again Without Restrictions. The Protection of Teachers, Educators, Carers and Parents and the General Hygiene Rules Do Not Conflict With This.” GMS Hygiene and Infection Control 15, no. 1: 1–18. https://doi.org/10.3205/dgkh000346.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weinert, S., A. Thronicke, M. Hinse, F. Schad, and H. Matthes. 2021. “School Teachers' Self‐Reported Fear and Risk Perception During the COVID‐19 Pandemic‐A Nationwide Survey in Germany.” International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 18, no. 17: 9218. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph18179218.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. 2023. Coronavirus (COVID‐19) Dashboard. Geneva: WHO. Accessed August 1, 2023. Available at: https://COVID19.who.int/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. 2023. Advice for the Public: Coronavirus Disease (COVID‐19). Geneva: WHO. Accessed August 19, 2023. Available at: https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel‐coronavirus‐2019/advice‐for‐public.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>