<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39443953</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1471-2458</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>24</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC public health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Public Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Food purchase and consumption behavior during the COVID-19 pandemic lockdown in Bangladesh: association between sociodemographic composition.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>2943</StartPage><MedlinePgn>2943</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">2943</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12889-024-19982-w</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Bangladesh suffered a severe COVID-19 wave from June to August 2021, which forced the government to impose emergency nationwide lockdown measures for three months with discontinuities. The sudden lockdown strongly affected the dietary preferences, financial circumstances, and social interactions of citizens.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">In this comprehensive study, we collected sociodemographic information as well as data on food purchase and consumption behaviors from 1,350 adults in Bangladesh during the weeks of enforced confinement. The association between the sociodemographic factors (viz., gender, age, education status, income, occupation, and household size) and food purchase and consumption behaviors were determined by conducting bivariate and multivariate logistic regression models reporting as odds ratios.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The descriptive result reveals that 49.63% of the participants experienced wage reductions, with many people enduring reductions of up to 75%; 12.22% lost their jobs. Besides, a decline in the frequency of shopping was observed by 35.04%; and 24.52% avoided outdoor shopping during the pandemic period. Additionally, 28.74% of participants purchased less overall, while 19.48% purchased significantly fewer items per trip compared to the pre-pandemic period. The multivariate analysis shows a prominent increase in online grocery shopping (OR: 4.03, 95% CI: 2.38-6.83, p &lt; 0.001) and meal delivery services (OR = 5.19, 95% CI = 3.21-7.17, p &lt; 0.001) among higher educated individuals compared to the individuals having no institutional education. The personnel having formal jobs purchased 2.34 times more from online grocery sites (95% CI = 0.34-4.08, p = 0.003) compared to the unemployed one. In contrast, a notable increase in panic buying and stockpiling was observed, driven by scarcity and escalating prices of essential food items. The frequency of meals with families, active engagement in meal preparation, and the exploration of novel recipes also increased notably.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The consumption of takeaway food and inter-meal snacks increased significantly with the education level of individuals. These findings highlighted that a prolonged pandemic could magnify economic vulnerability in Bangladesh.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Arif</LastName><ForeName>Ishtiaq</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Organic Agricultural Sciences, University of Kassel, Steinstraße 19, Witzenhausen, 37213, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nutritional, Food and Consumer Sciences, Fulda University of Applied Sciences, Leipziger Straße 123, Fulda, 36037, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shourove</LastName><ForeName>Jahid Hasan</ForeName><Initials>JH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Engineering and Tea Technology, Shahjalal University of Science and Technology, Sylhet, Bangladesh.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sarker</LastName><ForeName>Taposh</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Agricultural and Food Sciences and Environmental Management, University of Debrecen, Egyetem Tér 1, Debrecen, 4032, Hungary.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rahman</LastName><ForeName>Md Mosiur</ForeName><Initials>MM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Population Science and Human Resource Development, University of Rajshahi, Rajshahi, 6205, Bangladesh.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Islam</LastName><ForeName>G M Rabiul</ForeName><Initials>GMR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Food Engineering and Tea Technology, Shahjalal University of Science and Technology, Sylhet, Bangladesh. rabi-ttc@sust.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Public Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100968562</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1471-2458</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001459" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Bangladesh</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055815" MajorTopicYN="N">Young Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000091569" MajorTopicYN="Y">Sociodemographic Factors</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003258" MajorTopicYN="N">Consumer Behavior</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000293" MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescent</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012959" MajorTopicYN="N">Socioeconomic Factors</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005247" MajorTopicYN="N">Feeding Behavior</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011790" MajorTopicYN="N">Quarantine</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003140" MajorTopicYN="N">Communicable Disease Control</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Buying behavior</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Eating behavior</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Food purchase</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Stockpiling</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>40</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39443953</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12889-024-19982-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12889-024-19982-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11515636</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Organization WH. WHO Director-General’s opening remarks at the media briefing on COVID-19–11 March 2020. https://www.who.int/director-general/speeches/detail/who-director-general-s-opening-remarks-at-the-media-briefing-on-covid-19---11-march-2020. Accessed 22 Jun 2023. 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>AlTarrah D, AlShami E, AlHamad N, AlBesher F, Devarajan S. The Impact of Coronavirus COVID-19 Pandemic on Food Purchasing, Eating Behavior, and Perception of Food Safety in Kuwait. Sustainability. 2021;13(16):8987. 10.3390/su13168987.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bölek S. Food purchasing, preservation, and eating behavior during COVID-19 pandemic. Ital J Food Saf. (2021);33(3):14–24, 10.15586/ijfs.v33i3.2048.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferreira Rodrigues J, Cunha dos Santos Filho MT, Aparecida de Oliveira LE, Brandemburg Siman I, Barcelos AdF, de Paiva Anciens Ramos GL, et al. Effect of the COVID-19 pandemic on food habits and perceptions: A study with Brazilians. Trends Food Sci Tech. (2021);116:992–1001, 10.1016/j.tifs.2021.09.005.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gordon-Wilson S. Consumption practices during the COVID-19 crisis. Int J Consum Stud. 2022;46(2):575–88. 10.1111/ijcs.12701.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8237011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34220342</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Güney OI, Sangün L. How COVID-19 affects individuals’ food consumption behaviour: a consumer survey on attitudes and habits in Turkey. British Food J. 2021;123(7):2307–20. 10.1108/BFJ-10-2020-0949.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marinković V, Lazarević J. Eating habits and consumer food shopping behaviour during COVID-19 virus pandemic: insights from Serbia. British Food J. 2021;123(12):3970–87. 10.1108/BFJ-11-2020-1072.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murphy B, Benson T, McCloat A, Mooney E, Elliott C, Dean M, Lavelle F. Changes in Consumers’ Food Practices during the COVID-19 Lockdown, Implications for Diet Quality and the Food System: A Cross-Continental Comparison. Nutrients. 2021;13(1):20. 10.3390/nu13010020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Russo C, Simeone M, Demartini E, Marescotti ME, Gaviglio A. Psychological pressure and changes in food consumption: the effect of COVID-19 crisis. Heliyon. 2021;7(4):e06607. 10.1016/j.heliyon.2021.e06607.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8042433</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33869860</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim H, Kang Y. Perceived Impact of COVID-19 on the Dietary Behaviors and Food Security of People in Rural Bangladesh. Curr Dev Nutr. 2021;5:230. 10.1093/cdn/nzab029_031.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruszczyk HA, Rahman MF, Bracken LJ, Sudha S. Contextualizing the COVID-19 pandemic’s impact on food security in two small cities in Bangladesh. Environ Urban. 2020;33(1):239–54. 10.1177/0956247820965156.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zabir AA, Mahmud A, Islam MA, Antor SC, Yasmin F, Dasgupta A. COVID-19 and Food Supply in Bangladesh: A Review. S Asia J Soc Stud Econ. 2021;10(1):15–23. 10.9734/sajsse/2021/v10i130252.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Institute of Epidemiology, Disease Control and Research. COVID-19 general information. 2020. https://old.iedcr.gov.bd/index.php/component/content/article/11-others/227-pressrelease. Accessed 14 May 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saha P, Gulshan J. Systematic Assessment of COVID-19 Pandemic in Bangladesh: Effectiveness of Preparedness in the First Wave. Front Public Health. 2021;9:628931. 10.3389/fpubh.2021.628931.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8567082</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34746068</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. Bangladesh: WHO Coronavirus (COVID-19) Dashboard. 2021. https://covid19.who.int/region/searo/country/bd. Accessed 31 Dec 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamruzzaman M. Bangladesh records highest-ever single-day spike in COVID cases, deaths: New infections and fatalities also reported in country's Rohingya refugee camps. 2021. https://www.aa.com.tr/en/asia-pacific/bangladesh-records-highest-ever-single-day-spike-in-covid-cases-deaths/2315107#. Accessed 14 Sep 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Business Standard. Bangladesh to impose nationwide 'hard lockdown' from June 28 for 7 days. Business Standard. 2021. https://www.business-standard.com/article/current-affairs/bangladesh-to-impose-nationwide-hard-lockdown-from-june-28-for-7-days-121062600120_1.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al Jazeera. Bangladesh logs single-day records for COVID cases, deaths. Al Jazeera. 2021. https://www.aljazeera.com/news/2021/7/27/bangladesh-record-coronavirus-cases-deaths.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Business Standard. Bangladesh records highest daily coronavirus deaths, cases today. Business Standard. 7/26/2021. https://www.tbsnews.net/coronavirus-chronicle/covid-19-bangladesh/highest-ever-247-covid-19-deaths-15192-cases-reported.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daria S, Islam MR. The Second Wave of COVID-19 Pandemic in Bangladesh: An Urgent Call to Save Lives. Asia Pac J Public Health. 2021;33(5):665–6. 10.1177/10105395211021686.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34060346</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aday S, Aday MS. Impact of COVID-19 on the food supply chain. Food Qual Saf. 2020;4(4):167–80. 10.1093/fqsafe/fyaa024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Janssen M, Chang BPI, Hristov H, Pravst I, Profeta A, Millard J. Changes in Food Consumption During the COVID-19 Pandemic: Analysis of Consumer Survey Data From the First Lockdown Period in Denmark, Germany, and Slovenia. Front Nutr. 2021;8:635859. 10.3389/fnut.2021.635859.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7982667</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33763443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAO. Responding to the impact of the COVID-19 outbreak on food value chains through efficient logistics. Rome. (2020), 10.4060/ca8466en.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Talukder B, vanLoon GW, Hipel KW, Orbinski J. COVID-19’s implications on agri-food systems and human health in Bangladesh. Curr Res Environ Sustain. 2021;3:100033. 10.1016/j.crsust.2021.100033.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7945872</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34977606</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahman MT, Akter S, Rana MR, Sabuz AA, Jubayer MF. How COVID-19 pandemic is affecting achieved food security in Bangladesh: A perspective with required policy interventions. J Agric Food Res. 2022;7:100258. 10.1016/j.jafr.2021.100258.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8837400</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35187503</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>GAIN. Impact of COVID-19 on food systems: a situation report. https://www.gainhealth.org/resources/reports-and-publications/impact-covid-19-food-systems-situation-report-iii.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>FAO. Second rapid assessment of food and nutrition security in the context of COVID-19 in Bangladesh. Dhaka: Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations; 2020. 10.4060/cb1018en.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mandal SC, Boidya P, Haque MI-M, Hossain A, Shams Z, and Mamun A-A. The impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on fish consumption and household food security in Dhaka city, Bangladesh. Glob Food Secur. (2021);29:100526, 10.1016/j.gfs.2021.100526.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rabbi MF, Oláh J, Popp J, Máté D, Kovács S. Food Security and the COVID-19 Crisis from a consumer buying behaviour perspective—The case of Bangladesh. Foods. 2021;10(12):3073. 10.3390/foods10123073.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8701356</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34945624</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bangladesh National Nutrition Council (BNNC). Determining the Impact of COVID-19 on Nutrition: Projection of the Possible Malnutrition Burden in Post COVID-19 Period in Bangladesh; 2020. https://bnnc.portal.gov.bd/sites/default/files/files/bnnc.portal.gov.bd/notices/1d0efb69_0b94_45f9_835a_c56e65a99cb3/2020-06-01-23-20-e9a24538b4ad647fbc65f3f26c95623d.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bender KE, Badiger A, Roe BE, Shu Y, and Qi D. Consumer behavior during the COVID-19 pandemic: An analysis of food purchasing and management behaviors in U.S. households through the lens of food system resilience. Socio-Economic Plan Sci. (2022);82:101107, 10.1016/j.seps.2021.101107.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ben Hassen T, El Bilali H, Allahyari MS, Berjan S, Fotina O. Food purchase and eating behavior during the COVID-19 pandemic: A cross-sectional survey of Russian adults. Appetite. 2021;165:105309. 10.1016/j.appet.2021.105309.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9756772</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34015307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cavallo C, Sacchi G, Carfora V. Resilience effects in food consumption behaviour at the time of Covid-19: perspectives from Italy. Heliyon. 2020;6(12):e05676. 10.1016/j.heliyon.2020.e05676.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7722488</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33313439</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duffy EW, Lo A, Hall MG, Taillie LS, Ng SW. Prevalence and demographic correlates of online grocery shopping: results from a nationally representative survey during the COVID-19 pandemic. Public Health Nutr. 2022;25(11):3079–85. 10.1017/S1368980022001756.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9464506</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35983641</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Truong D, Truong MD. How do customers change their purchasing behaviors during the COVID-19 pandemic? J Retail Consum. 2022;67:102963. 10.1016/j.jretconser.2022.102963.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alaimo LS, Fiore M, Galati A. How the Covid-19 Pandemic is changing online food shopping human behaviour in Italy. Sustainability. 2020;12(22):9594. 10.3390/su12229594.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poelman MP, Gillebaart M, Schlinkert C, Dijkstra SC, Derksen E, Mensink F, et al. Eating behavior and food purchases during the COVID-19 lockdown: A cross-sectional study among adults in the Netherlands. Appetite. 2021;157:105002. 10.1016/j.appet.2020.105002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7554484</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33068668</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chenarides L, Grebitus C, Lusk JL, Printezis I. Food consumption behavior during the COVID-19 pandemic. Agribus. 2021;37(1):44–81. 10.1002/agr.21679.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muresan IC, Harun R, Arion FH, Brata AM, Chereches IA, Chiciudean GO, et al. Consumers’ Attitude towards Sustainable Food Consumption during the COVID-19 Pandemic in Romania. Agric. 2021;11(11):1050. 10.3390/agriculture11111050.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dumitras DE, Harun R, Arion FH, Chiciudean DI, Kovacs E, Oroian CF, et al. Food Consumption Patterns in Romania during the COVID-19 Pandemic. Foods. 2021;10(11):2712. 10.3390/foods10112712.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8623437</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34828993</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El Bilali H, Ben Hassen T, Baya Chatti C, Abouabdillah A, Alaoui SB. Exploring household food dynamics during the COVID-19 pandemic in Morocco. Front Nutr. 2021;8:724803. 10.3389/fnut.2021.724803.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8502820</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34646850</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li S, Kallas Z, Rahmani D, Gil JM. Trends in food preferences and sustainable behavior during the COVID-19 lockdown: evidence from Spanish Consumers. Foods. 2021;10(8):1898. 10.3390/foods10081898.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8391569</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34441675</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ogundijo DA, Tas AA, Onarinde BA. Exploring the impact of COVID-19 pandemic on eating and purchasing behaviours of people living in England. Nutrients. 2021;13(5):1499. 10.3390/nu13051499.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8146722</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33946799</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li S, Kallas Z, Rahmani D. Did the COVID-19 lockdown affect consumers’ sustainable behaviour in food purchasing and consumption in China? Food Control. 2022;132:108352. 10.1016/j.foodcont.2021.108352.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9716012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36474958</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fanelli RM. Changes in the Food-Related Behaviour of Italian Consumers during the COVID-19 Pandemic. Foods. 2021;10(1):169. 10.3390/foods10010169.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7830422</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33467727</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scacchi A, Catozzi D, Boietti E, Bert F, Siliquini R. COVID-19 Lockdown and Self-Perceived Changes of Food Choice, Waste, Impulse Buying and Their Determinants in Italy: QuarantEat, a Cross-Sectional Study. Foods. 2021;10(2):306. 10.3390/foods10020306.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7913081</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33540825</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naresh K. Malhotra, David F. Birks, Wills P. Marketing Research: An Applied Approach. 4th ed. Harlow, England: Pearson Education. (2012), https://search.worldcat.org/title/Marketing-Research-:-an-applied-approach/oclc/901448811.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>United Nations System Standing Committee on Nutrition. UNSCN COVID-19 Questionnaire - UNSCN. 2020. https://www.unscn.org/en/news%20-events/recent-news?idnews=2045. Accessed 18 Mar 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The International Business Machines Corporation. IBM Study: COVID-19 Is Significantly Altering U.S. Consumer Behavior and Plans Post-Crisis. 2020. https://newsroom.ibm.com/2020–05–01.IBM-Study-COVID-19-Is-Significantly-Altering-U-S-Consumer-Behavior-and-Plans-Post-Crisis. Accessed 14 Jun 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Batterton KA and Hale KN. The Likert Scale What It Is and How To Use It. Phalanx. (2017);50(2):32–39, http://www.jstor.org/stable/26296382.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Bank. GDP per capita (current US$) – Bangladesh. 2023. https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/NY.GDP.PCAP.CD?%20locations=BD&amp;locations=BD. Accessed 22 Jun 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amicarelli V, Lagioia G, Sampietro S, Bux C. Has the COVID-19 pandemic changed food waste perception and behavior? Evidence from Italian consumers. Socio-Economic Plan Sci. 2022;82:101095. 10.1016/j.seps.2021.101095.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grunert KG, De Bauw M, Dean M, Lähteenmäki L, Maison D, Pennanen K, et al. No lockdown in the kitchen: How the COVID-19 pandemic has affected food-related behaviours. Food Res Int. 2021;150:110752. 10.1016/j.foodres.2021.110752.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8520572</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34865770</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Figliozzi M, Unnikrishnan A. Exploring the impact of socio-demographic characteristics, health concerns, and product type on home delivery rates and expenditures during a strict COVID-19 lockdown period: A case study from Portland. OR Transp Res A: Policy Pract. 2021;153:1–19. 10.1016/j.tra.2021.08.012.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bogevska Z, Berjan S, El Bilali H, Sadegh Allahyari M, Radosavac A, Davitkovska M. Exploring food shopping, consumption and waste habits in North Macedonia during the COVID-19 pandemic. Socio-Economic Plan Sci. 2022;82:101150. 10.1016/j.seps.2021.101150.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grashuis J, Skevas T, and Segovia MS. Grocery Shopping Preferences during the COVID-19 Pandemic. Sustainability. (2020);12(13):5369, https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/12/13/5369.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Termeer EEW, Brouwer ID, &amp; de Boef WS. (2020, Jul 17). Rapid country assessment: Bangladesh: The impact of COVID-19 on the food system . Wageningen University &amp; Research. https://edepot.wur.nl/550648.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahman HZ, Das N, Matin I, Wazed MA, Ahmed S, Jahan N, Zillur U. Livelihoods, coping, and support during COVID-19 crisis; 2020. https://bigd.bracu.ac.bd/publications/livelihoods-coping-and-support-during-covid-19-crisis-report/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baarsma B, Groenewegen J. COVID-19 and the Demand for Online Grocery Shopping: Empirical Evidence from the Netherlands. De Economist. 2021;169(4):407–21. 10.1007/s10645-021-09389-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8262585</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34253932</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen J, Zhang Y, Zhu S, Liu L. Does COVID-19 Affect the Behavior of Buying Fresh Food? Evidence from Wuhan, China. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18(9):4469. 10.3390/ijerph18094469.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8122813</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33922354</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ellison B, McFadden B, Rickard BJ, Wilson NLW. Examining Food Purchase Behavior and Food Values During the COVID-19 Pandemic. Appl Econ Perspect Policy. 2021;43(1):58–72. 10.1002/aepp.13118.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cummins S, Berger N, Cornelsen L, Eling J, Er V, Greener R, et al. COVID-19: impact on the urban food retail system and dietary inequalities in the UK. Cities &amp; Health. 2021;5(sup1):S119–22. 10.1080/23748834.2020.1785167.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dannenberg P, Fuchs M, Riedler T, Wiedemann C. Digital Transition by COVID-19 Pandemic? The German Food Online Retail. Tijdschr Econ Soc Geogr. 2020;111(3):543–60. 10.1111/tesg.12453.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7323036</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32836487</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang H-H, Meyerhoefer CD. COVID-19 and the demand for online food shopping services: empirical evidence from Taiwan. American J Agric Econ. 2021;103(2):448–65. 10.1111/ajae.12170.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hobbs JE. Food supply chains during the COVID-19 pandemic. Canadian J Agric Econ. 2020;68(2):171–6. 10.1111/cjag.12237.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gerhold L. COVID-19: Risk perception and Coping strategies: Center for Open Science; 2020. 10.31234/osf.io/xmpk4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohinur A and Nadia Afroze D. Exploring consumer behavior for app-based food delivery in bangladesh during COVID-19. Bangladesh J Integ Thoughts. (2021);17(1), 10.52805/bjit.v17i1.188.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Husain W, Ashkanani F. Does COVID-19 change dietary habits and lifestyle behaviours in Kuwait: a community-based cross-sectional study. Environ Health Prev Med. 2020;25(1):61. 10.1186/s12199-020-00901-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7548533</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33045996</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ben Hassen T, El Bilali H, Allahyari MS. Impact of COVID-19 on food behavior and consumption in Qatar. Sustainability. 2020;12(17):6973. 10.3390/su12176973.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de la Torre-Moral A, Fàbregues S, Bach-Faig A, Fornieles-Deu A, Medina FX, Aguilar-Martínez A, Sánchez-Carracedo D. Family Meals, Conviviality, and the Mediterranean Diet among Families with Adolescents. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18(5):2499. 10.3390/ijerph18052499.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7967627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33802507</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scarmozzino F, Visioli F. Covid-19 and the subsequent lockdown modified dietary habits of almost half the population in an Italian sample. Foods. 2020;9(5):675. 10.3390/foods9050675.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7278864</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32466106</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Romeo-Arroyo E, Mora M, Vázquez-Araújo L. Consumer behavior in confinement times: Food choice and cooking attitudes in Spain. Int J Gastron Food Sci. 2020;21:100226. 10.1016/j.ijgfs.2020.100226.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7272181</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32528560</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gerritsen S, Egli V, Roy R, Haszard J, Backer CD, Teunissen L, et al. Seven weeks of home-cooked meals: changes to New Zealanders’ grocery shopping, cooking and eating during the COVID-19 lockdown. J Roy Soc New Zealand. 2021;51(sup1):S4–22. 10.1080/03036758.2020.1841010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Constant A, Conserve DF, Gallopel-Morvan K, and Raude J. Socio-cognitive factors associated with lifestyle changes in response to the COVID-19 epidemic in the general population: results from a cross-sectional study in France. Front psychol. (2020);11, 10.3389/fpsyg.2020.579460.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Górnicka M, Drywień ME, Zielinska MA, Hamułka J. Dietary and lifestyle changes during COVID-19 and the subsequent lockdowns among polish adults: a cross-sectional online survey PLifeCOVID-19 Study. Nutrients. 2020;12(8):2324. 10.3390/nu12082324.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7468840</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32756458</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kriaucioniene V, Bagdonaviciene L, Rodríguez-Pérez C, Petkeviciene J. Associations between Changes in Health Behaviours and Body Weight during the COVID-19 Quarantine in Lithuania: The Lithuanian COVIDiet Study. Nutrients. 2020;12(10):3119. 10.3390/nu12103119.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7599784</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33065991</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papandreou C, Arija V, Aretouli E, Tsilidis KK, Bulló M. Comparing eating behaviours, and symptoms of depression and anxiety between Spain and Greece during the COVID-19 outbreak: Cross-sectional analysis of two different confinement strategies. Eur Eat Disord Rev. 2020;28(6):836–46. 10.1002/erv.2772.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7436917</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32754986</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robinson E, Boyland E, Chisholm A, Harrold J, Maloney NG, Marty L, et al. Obesity, eating behavior and physical activity during COVID-19 lockdown: A study of UK adults. Appetite. 2021;156: 104853. 10.1016/j.appet.2020.104853.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7540284</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33038479</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giacalone D, Frøst MB, and Rodríguez-Pérez C. Reported changes in dietary habits during the COVID-19 lockdown in the Danish population: The Danish COVIDiet Study. Front Nutr. (2020);7, 10.3389/fnut.2020.592112.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muscogiuri G, Barrea L, Savastano S, Colao A. Nutritional recommendations for CoVID-19 quarantine. Eur J Clin Nutr. 2020;74(6):850–1. 10.1038/s41430-020-0635-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7155155</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32286533</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pellegrini M, Ponzo V, Rosato R, Scumaci E, Goitre I, Benso A, et al. Changes in weight and nutritional habits in adults with obesity during the “Lockdown” period caused by the COVID-19 virus emergency. Nutrients. 2020;12(7):2016. 10.3390/nu12072016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7400808</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32645970</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alam GMM, Khatun MN. Impact of COVID-19 on vegetable supply chain and food security: Empirical evidence from Bangladesh. PLoS ONE. 2021;16(3):e0248120. 10.1371/journal.pone.0248120.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7949487</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33667256</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WorldFish. Field Notes: Bangladesh in times of COVID-19 and food security implications. 2020. https://worldfishcenter.org/blog/field-notes-bangladesh-times-covid-19-and-food-security-implications-0. Accessed 14 Jan 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dev D, Kabir K. COVID-19 and food security in Bangladesh: a chance to look back at what is done and what can be done. J Agric Food Syst Community Dev. 2020;9(4):143–5. 10.5304/jafscd.2020.094.008.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>