<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39443877</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1472-6920</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>24</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC medical education</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Med Educ</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Assessment of the development of social skills among undergraduate medical students through participation in a socio-educational project during the coronavirus disease (COVID)-19 pandemic: a Brazilian pilot study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1197</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1197</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12909-024-06188-2</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Coronavirus disease (COVID)-19 had an impact on medical graduation, causing weaknesses arising from social isolation and remote emergency teaching, with an emphasis on deficits in the development of non-technical skills (soft skills). In this context, the interaction between a group of medical students and adolescents who develop activities at the Center for Learning and Mobilization for Citizenship in Campinas/SP, Brazil, was evaluated about the development of soft skills during the COVID-19 pandemic. The observational study was carried out using an electronic questionnaire based on a Likert scale on the feelings of undergraduate medical students regarding participation in project activities in the context of the development of social skills. The study demonstrated an important positive impact of student participation in a socio-educational project for the development of soft skills, emphasizing the ability to deal with adverse situations, decision-making, and the ability to deal with the fear of not corresponding. However, the existence of limitations and difficulties in the development of non-technical skills by students was revealed, further reinforced by the challenges brought by the COVID-19 pandemic. In this aspect, the study demonstrated participation in a voluntary social project as an important strategy to improve the teaching of these skills.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Medeiros</LastName><ForeName>Michelle Marchi</ForeName><Initials>MM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3332-3757</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, University of Campinas, São Paulo, SP, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Arcanjo</LastName><ForeName>Mariana Armani</ForeName><Initials>MA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9105-0676</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, University of Campinas, São Paulo, SP, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Belluomini</LastName><ForeName>Fernando</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7975-2971</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, University of Campinas, São Paulo, SP, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Palamim</LastName><ForeName>Camila Vantini Capasso</ForeName><Initials>CVC</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6825-1154</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Molecular Biology and Genetics, São Francisco University, Bragança Paulista, SP, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Clinical and Molecular Microbiology, São Francisco University, Bragança Paulista, SP, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>LunGuardian Research Group - Epidemiology of Respiratory and Infectious Diseases, São Francisco University, Bragança Paulista, SP, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Marson</LastName><ForeName>Fernando Augusto Lima</ForeName><Initials>FAL</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4955-4234</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Molecular Biology and Genetics, São Francisco University, Bragança Paulista, SP, Brazil. fernandolimamarson@hotmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Clinical and Molecular Microbiology, São Francisco University, Bragança Paulista, SP, Brazil. fernandolimamarson@hotmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>LunGuardian Research Group - Epidemiology of Respiratory and Infectious Diseases, São Francisco University, Bragança Paulista, SP, Brazil. fernandolimamarson@hotmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>de Melo Alexandre Fraga</LastName><ForeName>Andrea</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0999-5350</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pediatrics, University of Campinas, São Paulo, SP, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>LunGuardian Research Group - Epidemiology of Respiratory and Infectious Diseases, São Francisco University, Bragança Paulista, SP, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D064888">Observational Study</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Med Educ</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101088679</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1472-6920</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001938" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Brazil</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010865" MajorTopicYN="N">Pilot Projects</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004504" MajorTopicYN="Y">Education, Medical, Undergraduate</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013337" MajorTopicYN="Y">Students, Medical</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D066107" MajorTopicYN="Y">Social Skills</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000293" MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescent</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Medical teaching</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Medicine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Non-technical skills</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Soft Skills</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>37</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39443877</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12909-024-06188-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12909-024-06188-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>Ariyananda P. Soft skills for physicians: have we addressed it enough? J of Cey Coll of Phy. 2014;44(1–2):32–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4038/jccp.v44i1-2.7686</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baig LA, Violato C, Crutcher RA. Assessing clinical communication skills in physicians: are the skills context specific or generalizable. BMC Med Educ. 2009;9:22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1472-6920-9-22</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Learning objectives for medical student education--guidelines for medical schools: report I of the Medical School Objectives Project. Acad Med. 1999;74(1):13–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Why Soft Skills are Essential in Healthcare. Accessed on https://onlineprograms.case.edu/mba/blog/why-soft-skills-are-important-in-healthcare/ . Accessed on 01 Oct 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marson FAL, Ortega MM. COVID-19 in Brazil. Pulmonology. 2020;26(4):241–4. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pulmoe.2020.04.008 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pulmoe.2020.04.008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martins JP, Siqueira BA, Sansone NMS, Marson FAL. COVID-19 in Brazil: a 3-year update. Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis. 2023;107(4): 116074.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2023.116074</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boschiero MN, Palamim CVC, Ortega MM, Mauch RM, Marson FAL. One year of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) in Brazil: A political and social overview. Ann Glob Health. 2021;87(1):44.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5334/aogh.3182</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Benedetto MAC, Moreto G, Vachi VHB. Medical Narratives: Empathy and Communication Skills in Covid-19 Times. Arch Med Fam. 2020;22(3):109–18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rossini G, De Benedetto MAC, Moreto G, Levites MR, Blasco PG. One year with the COVID-19 pandemic: reflections and learning in long term facilities. Acta Fisiátrica. 2021;28(2):126–32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.11606/issn.2317-0190.v28i2a187070</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed H, Allaf M, Elghazaly H. COVID-19 and medical education. Lancet Infect Dis. 2020;20(7):777–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(20)30226-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santos BM, Cordeiro MEC, Schneider IJC, Ceccon RF. Medical Education during the Covid-19 Pandemic: a Scoping Review. Rev Bras Edu Med. 2020;44: e139.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/1981-5271v44.supl.1-20200383</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loh AZH, Tan JSY, Lee JJM, Koh GCH. Voluntary community service in medical school: a qualitative study on student leaders’ motivations, experiences, and outcomes. Med Teach. 2016;38(7):683–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3109/0142159X.2016.1150985</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Likert R. A technique for the measurement of attitudes. Arch Psychol. 1932;22(140):55.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamilton AL, Kerins J, MacCrossan MA, Tallentire VR. Medical students’ non-technical skills (Medi-StuNTS): preliminary work developing a behavioral marker system for the non-technical skills of medical students in acute care. BMJ Simul. 2019;5(3):130–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Statistical Package for the Social Sciences – IBM SPSS Statistics for Macintosh, Version 29.0.2.0 Armonk, NY: IBM Corp</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>GraphPad Prism version 10.2.3 for Macintosh, GraphPad Software, Boston, Massachusetts USA, www.graphpad.com ”.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iorio S, Cilione M, Martini M, Tofani M, Gazzaniga V. Soft Skills Are Hard Skills-A Historical Perspective. Medicina (Kaunas). 2022;58(8):1044.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/medicina58081044</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The difference between hard skills and soft skills - do you need both?. Accessed on https://www.leaderstat.com/knowledge-base/the-difference-between-hard-skills-and-soft-skills-do-you-need-both . Accessed on 01 Oct 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Howe A, Anna S, Andrea S. Towards an understanding of resilience and its relevance to medical training. Med Educ. 2012;46(4):349–56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2923.2011.04188.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siqueira MAM, Torsani MB, Gameiro GR, Chinelatto LA, Mikahil BC, Tempski PZ, Martins MA. Medical students’ participation in the volunteering Program during the COVID-19 pandemic: a qualitative study about motivation and the development of new competencies. BMC Med Educ. 2022;22(1):111.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12909-022-03147-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Howe A, Smajdor A, Stöckl A. Towards an understanding of resilience and its relevance to medical training. Med Educ. 2012;46(3):341–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zwack J, Schweitzer J. If every fifth physician is affected by burnout, what about the other four? Resilience strategies of experienced physicians. Acad Med. 2013;88(3):382–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/ACM.0b013e318281696b</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McAllister M, McKinnon J. The importance of teaching and learning resilience in the health disciplines: a critical review of the literature. Nurse Educ Today. 2009;29(4):371–9. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.nedt.2008.10.011 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.nedt.2008.10.011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fraher EP, Pittman P, Frogner BK, Spetz J, Moore J, Beck AJ, Armstrong D, Buerhaus PI. Ensuring and Sustaining a Pandemic Workforce. N Engl J Med. 2020;382(23):2181–3. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMp2006376 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMp2006376</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agarwal A, Hunt B, Stegemann M, Rochwerg B, Lamontagne F, Siemieniuk RA, Agoritsas T, Askie L, Lytvyn L, Leo YS, Macdonald H, Zeng L, Alhadyan A, Muna A, Amin W, da Silva ARA, Aryal D, Barragan FAJ, Bausch FJ, Burhan E, Calfee CS, Cecconi M, Chacko B, Chanda D, Dat VQ, De Sutter A, Du B, Freedman S, Geduld H, Gee P, Haider M, Gotte M, Harley N, Hashimi M, Hui D, Ismail M, Jehan F, Kabra SK, Kanda S, Kim YJ, Kissoon N, Krishna S, Kuppalli K, Kwizera A, Lado Castro-Rial M, Lisboa T, Lodha R, Mahaka I, Manai H, Mendelson M, Migliori GB, Mino G, Nsutebu E, Peter J, Preller J, Pshenichnaya N, Qadir N, Ranganathan SS, Relan P, Rylance J, Sabzwari S, Sarin R, Shankar-Hari M, Sharland M, Shen Y, Souza JP, Swanstrom R, Tshokey T, Ugarte S, Uyeki T, Evangelina VC, Venkatapuram S, Vuyiseka D, Wijewickrama A, Tran L, Zeraatkar D, Bartoszko JJ, Ge L, Brignardello-Petersen R, Owen A, Guyatt G, Diaz J, Kawano-Dourado L, Jacobs M, Vandvik PO. A living WHO guideline on drugs for covid-19. BMJ. 2020;370: m3379.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.m3379</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kache S, Chisti MJ, Gumbo F, Mupere E, Zhi X, Nallasamy K, Nakagawa S, Lee JH, Di Nardo M, de la Oliva P, Katyal C, Anand KJS, de Souza DC, Lanziotti VS, Carcillo J. COVID-19 PICU guidelines: for high- and limited-resource settings. Pediatr Res. 2020;88(5):705–16. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41390-020-1053-9 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41390-020-1053-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 rapid guideline: managing COVID-19. London: National Institute for Health and Care Excellence (NICE); 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Therapeutics and COVID-19: living guideline. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aziz S, Arabi YM, Alhazzani W, Evans L, Citerio G, Fischkoff K, Salluh J, Meyfroidt G, Alshamsi F, Oczkowski S, Azoulay E, Price A, Burry L, Dzierba A, Benintende A, Morgan J, Grasselli G, Rhodes A, Møller MH, Chu L, Schwedhelm S, Lowe JJ, Bin D, Christian MD. Managing ICU surge during the COVID-19 crisis: rapid guidelines. Intensive Care Med. 2020;46(7):1303–25. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00134-020-06092-5 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00134-020-06092-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 rapid guideline: critical care in adults. London: National Institute for Health and Care Excellence (NICE); 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodewald LE, Shen KL, Yang YH, Wong GW, Namazova-Baranova L, Rosenwasser LJ, Alharbi AS, Chang AB, Buttery J, Elnazir B, Etzel RA, Goh A, Hoey H, Horne R, Kerem E, Muraro A, O’Callaghan C, Ouchi K, Singh V, Wang JY, Li S, Guan Y, Global Pediatric Pulmonology Alliance (GPPA) Council, Zheng YJ, Xie Z, Lu G, Jiang Y, Li XW, Jiang RM, Wang XC, Deng JK, Lu XX, Xu BP, Wei Z, Feng LZ, Zhao ZY. Global Pediatric Pulmonology Alliance (GPPA) Expert Panel on Infectious Diseases and COVID-19. Global Pediatric Pulmonology Alliance (GPPA) proposal for COVID-19 vaccination in children. World J Pediatr. 2021;17(5):458–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12519-021-00459-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu E, Smyth RL, Li Q, Qaseem A, Florez ID, Mathew JL, Amer YS, Estill J, Lu Q, Fu Z, Lu X, Chan ES, Schwarze J, Wong GW, Fukuoka T, Ahn HS, Lee MS, Nurdiati D, Cao B, Tu W, Qian Y, Zhao S, Dong X, Luo X, Chen Z, Li G, Zhang X, Zhao X, Xu H, Xu F, Shi Y, Zhao R, Zhao Y, Lei J, Zheng X, Wang M, Yang S, Feng X, Wu L, He Z, Liu S, Wang Q, Song Y, Luo Z, Zhou Q, Guyatt G, Chen Y, Li Q. Guidelines for the prevention and management of children and adolescents with COVID-19. Eur J Pediatr. 2022;181(12):4019–37.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00431-022-04615-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hayden MK, Hanson KE, Englund JA, Lee F, Lee MJ, Loeb M, Morgan DJ, Patel R, El Alayli A, El Mikati IK, Sultan S, Falck-Ytter Y, Mansour R, Amarin JZ, Morgan RL, Murad MH, Patel P, Bhimraj A, Mustafa RA. The Infectious Diseases Society of America Guidelines on the Diagnosis of COVID-19: Antigen Testing (January 2023). Clin Infect Dis. 2024;78(7):e350–84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/ciad032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valencise FE, Boschiero MN, Palamim CVC, Marson FAL. The COVID-19 impact on the scientific production on the 25 main death causes according to world region. Pulmonology. 2022;28(1):1–3. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pulmoe.2021.05.011 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pulmoe.2021.05.011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carvalho TA, Lima TM, Melani VF, Mendes MF, Pereira LR, Marson FAL. The scientific production during 2009 swine flu pandemic and 2019/2020 COVID-19 pandemic. Pulmonology. 2020;26(6):340–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pulmoe.2020.07.009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boschiero MN, Carvalho TA, Marson FAL. Retraction in the era of COVID-19 and its influence on evidence-based medicine: is science in jeopardy? Pulmonology. 2021;27(2):97–106. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pulmoe.2020.10.011 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pulmoe.2020.10.011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valencise FE, Palamim CVC, Marson FAL. Retraction of Clinical Trials about the SARS-CoV-2 Infection: An Unaddressed Problem and Its Possible Impact on Coronavirus Disease (COVID)-19 Treatment. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2023;20(3):1835.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph20031835</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faihs L, Neumann-Opitz C, Kainberger F, Druml C. Ethics teaching in medical school: the perception of medical students. Wien Klin Wochenschr. 2024;136(5–6):129–36. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00508-022-02127-7 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00508-022-02127-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>MacKinnon K, Marcellus L, Rivers J, Gordon C, Ryan M, Butcher D. Student and educator experiences of maternal-child simulation-based learning: a systematic review of qualitative evidence protocol. JBI Database System Rev Implement Rep. 2015;13(1):14–26.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.11124/jbisrir-2015-1694</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schünemann HJ, Reinap M, Piggott T, Laidmäe E, Köhler K, Pōld M, Ens B, Irs A, Akl EA, Cuello CA, Falavigna M, Gibbens M, Neamtiu L, Parmelli E, Jameleddine M, Pyke L, Verstijnen I, Alonso-Coello P, Tugwell P, Zhang Y, Saz-Parkinson Z, Kuchenmüller T, Moja L. The ecosystem of health decision making: from fragmentation to synergy. Lancet Public Health. 2022;7(4):e378–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2468-2667(22)00057-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cassell EJ. Diagnosing suffering: a perspective. Ann Intern Med. 1999;131(7):531–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-131-7-199910050-00009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weurlander M, Lönn A, Seeberger A, Hult H, Thornberg R, Wernerson A. Emotional challenges of medical students generate feelings of uncertainty. Med Educ. 2019;53(10):1037–48.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/medu.13934</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Batt-Rawden SA, Chisolm MS, Anton B, Flickinger TE. Teaching empathy to medical students: an updated, systematic review. Acad Med. 2013;88(8):1171–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/ACM.0b013e318299f3e3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thomas MR, Dyrbye LN, Huntington JL, Lawson KL, Novotny PJ, Sloan JA, Shanafelt TD. How do distress and well-being relate to medical student empathy? A multicenter study. J Gen Intern Med. 2007;22(2):177–83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11606-006-0039-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borges NJ, Manuel RS, Elam CL, Jones BJ. Comparing millennial and generation X medical students at one medical school. Acad Med. 2006;81(6):571–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/01.ACM.0000225222.38078.47</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thompson G, McBride RB, Hosford CC, Halaas G. Resilience Among Medical Students: The Role of Coping Style and Social Support. Teach Learn Med. 2016;28(2):174–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10401334.2016.1146611</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Connolly N, Abdalla ME. Impact of COVID-19 on medical education in different income countries: a scoping review of the literature. Med Educ Online. 2022;27(1):2040192.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10872981.2022.2040192</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boschiero MN, Palamim CVC, Marson FAL. The hindrances to perform the COVID-19 vaccination in Brazil. Hum Vaccin Immunother. 2021;17(11):3989–4004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/21645515.2021.1955607</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martins JP, Marson FAL. Forgetting what should not be forgotten: the new normal after the COVID-19 pandemic in Brazil. Front Psychol. 2024;15:1362183.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2024.1362183</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>