<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39448706</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2730-664X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>4</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Communications medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Commun Med (Lond)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Comparing role of religion in perception of the COVID-19 vaccines in Africa and Asia Pacific.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>212</StartPage><MedlinePgn>212</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">212</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1038/s43856-024-00628-2</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">In the midst of the global COVID-19 vaccine distribution challenge, religion stands out as a key determinant of vaccine hesitancy and health choices. Notably, the multifaceted religious environments of Africa and the Asia Pacific remain under-researched in this context.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Utilizing data from two survey waves conducted between 2021 and 2022, this cross-sectional study investigated the effects of religious beliefs on perceptions of compatibility between religion and vaccines and COVID-19 vaccine acceptance in Africa and Asia Pacific. Logistic regression models were employed, with interaction terms between socio-economic factors incorporated to account for variations among diverse subpopulations.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Among the eight religious groups identified, Atheists and Buddhists in the Asia Pacific exhibit the lowest agreement, with fewer than 60% acknowledging the religious compatibility of vaccines. Willingness to accept vaccines, however, is consistently higher in Asia Pacific by at least four percentage points compared to Africa, with the disparity widening further in the second wave. Impacts of education on vaccine perceptions vary across religious groups, while acknowledging vaccine compatibility with religion positively contributed to vaccine acceptance. Dynamics between region, religion, and other socio-demographic factors have changed substantially over time. All but Atheists and Muslims exhibit a higher propensity to endorse vaccines during Survey Wave 2.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Our study reveals complex, context-dependent connections between vaccine attitudes and religion and the heterogeneous effects of time and education among different religious affiliations. Understanding the underlying drivers of these temporal variations helps inform tailored approaches aimed at addressing vaccine hesitancy, promoting vaccine uptake, and improving the well-being of each religious group.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jin</LastName><ForeName>Shihui</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0079-7390</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Saw Swee Hock School of Public Health, National University of Singapore and National University Health System, Singapore, Singapore.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cook</LastName><ForeName>Alex R</ForeName><Initials>AR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Saw Swee Hock School of Public Health, National University of Singapore and National University Health System, Singapore, Singapore.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Statistics and Data Science, National University of Singapore, Singapore, Singapore.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kanwagi</LastName><ForeName>Robert</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Disease Epidemiology, London School of Hygiene &amp; Tropical Medicine, London, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Larson</LastName><ForeName>Heidi J</ForeName><Initials>HJ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8477-7583</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Disease Epidemiology, London School of Hygiene &amp; Tropical Medicine, London, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for the Evaluation of Vaccination, Vaccine &amp; Infectious Disease Institute, University of Antwerp, Antwerp, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Metrics Sciences, University of Washington, Seattle, WA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lin</LastName><ForeName>Leesa</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4123-4762</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Disease Epidemiology, London School of Hygiene &amp; Tropical Medicine, London, UK. Leesa.Lin@lshtm.ac.uk.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Laboratory of Data Discovery for Health (D24H), Hong Kong Science Park, Hong Kong SAR, China. Leesa.Lin@lshtm.ac.uk.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>WHO Collaborating Centre for Infectious Disease Epidemiology and Control, School of Public Health, LKS Faculty of Medicine, The University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong SAR, China. Leesa.Lin@lshtm.ac.uk.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Commun Med (Lond)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9918250414506676</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2730-664X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><OtherAbstract Type="plain-language-summary" Language="eng"><AbstractText>This study examined the effects of religious beliefs on thoughts about agreement between religion and vaccines, and COVID-19 vaccine acceptance in Africa and Asia Pacific. Data came from surveys of individuals across many regions during the COVID-19 pandemic in 2021 and 2022. We found lower agreement to compatibility between vaccine and religious belief among Atheists and Buddhists in the Asia Pacific, while Africans were generally less likely to accept the COVID-19 vaccines. In addition, education influenced vaccine views differently across religious groups, and those who felt vaccination was compatible with their religion were more likely to accept a vaccine. These findings show we should monitor vaccine confidence and tailor efforts to reduce vaccine hesitancy among different subgroups of people.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><CoiStatement>The authors declare the following competing interests: RK, HJL, and LL are members of the Vaccine Confidence Project<sup>TM</sup>, a global research consortium that has received research grants from GlaxoSmithKline (GSK), Merck, and Janssen. These research grants are not associated with the project at hand but are related to research on vaccine confidence around different vaccines.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39448706</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11502740</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s43856-024-00628-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1038/s43856-024-00628-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 Vaccines with WHO Emergency Use Listing. WHO - prequalification of medical products (IVDs, medicines, vaccines and immunization devices, vector control) https://extranet.who.int/pqweb/vaccines/vaccinescovid-19-vaccine-eul-issued (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Figueiredo, A., Simas, C. &amp; Larson, H. J. COVID-19 vaccine acceptance and its socio-demographic and emotional determinants: a multi-country cross-sectional study. Vaccine41, 354–364 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9647027</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36414475</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watson, O. J. et al. Global impact of the first year of COVID-19 vaccination: a mathematical modelling study. Lancet Infect. Dis.22, 1293–1302 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9225255</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35753318</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, N. et al. Long-term effectiveness of COVID-19 vaccines against infections, hospitalisations, and mortality in adults: findings from a rapid living systematic evidence synthesis and meta-analysis up to December, 2022. Lancet Respir. Med.11, 439–452 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9917454</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36780914</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hale, T. et al. A global panel database of pandemic policies (Oxford COVID-19 government response tracker). Nat. Hum. Behav.5, 529–538 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33686204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rydland, H. T., Friedman, J., Stringhini, S., Link, B. G. &amp; Eikemo, T. A. The radically unequal distribution of Covid-19 vaccinations: a predictable yet avoidable symptom of the fundamental causes of inequality. Humanit. Soc. Sci. Commun.9, 1–6 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Share of people who received at least one dose of COVID-19 vaccine. Our World in datahttps://ourworldindata.org/grapher/share-people-vaccinated-covid. (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WDI - The World by Income and Region. https://datatopics.worldbank.org/world-development-indicators/the-world-by-income-and-region.html. (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>MacDonald, N. E. Vaccine hesitancy: definition, scope and determinants. Vaccine33, 4161–4164 (2015).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25896383</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larson, H. J. Defining and measuring vaccine hesitancy. Nat. Hum. Behav.6, 1609–1610 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9684976</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36418535</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lazarus, J. V. et al. A survey of COVID-19 vaccine acceptance across 23 countries in 2022. Nat. Med.29, 366–375 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36624316</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larson, H. J. et al. The state of vaccine confidence 2016: global insights through a 67-country survey. EBioMedicine12, 295–301 (2016).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5078590</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27658738</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trepanowski, R. &amp; Drążkowski, D. Cross-national comparison of religion as a predictor of COVID-19 vaccination rates. J. Relig. Health61, 2198–2211 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9095816</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35556198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong, L. P., Alias, H., Wong, P.-F., Lee, H. Y. &amp; AbuBakar, S. The use of the health belief model to assess predictors of intent to receive the COVID-19 vaccine and willingness to pay. Hum. Vaccines Immunother.16, 2204–2214 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7553708</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32730103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olagoke, A. A., Olagoke, O. O. &amp; Hughes, A. M. Intention to vaccinate against the novel 2019 coronavirus disease: the role of health locus of control and religiosity. J. Relig. Health60, 65–80 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7596314</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33125543</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corcoran, K. E., Scheitle, C. P. &amp; DiGregorio, B. D. Christian nationalism and COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy and uptake. Vaccine39, 6614–6621 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8489517</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34629205</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Milligan, M. A., Hoyt, D. L., Gold, A. K., Hiserodt, M. &amp; Otto, M. W. COVID-19 vaccine acceptance: influential roles of political party and religiosity. Psychol. Health Med.27, 1907–1917 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34407721</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Costa, J. C., Weber, A. M., Darmstadt, G. L., Abdalla, S. &amp; Victora, C. G. Religious affiliation and immunization coverage in 15 countries in Sub-Saharan Africa. Vaccine38, 1160–1169 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6995994</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31791811</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pew Research Center. The global religious landscape. Pew research center’s religion &amp; public life projecthttps://www.pewresearch.org/religion/2012/12/18/global-religious-landscape-exec/ (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Vaccine Confidence Project. https://www.vaccineconfidence.org.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R Core Team. R: a language and environment for statistical computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lumley, T., Gao, P. &amp; Schneider, B. Survey: analysis of complex survey samples. (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paul Murrell. The grid graphics package. (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cragun, R. T. Nonreligion and Atheism. In: Handbook of Religion and Society (ed. Yamane, D.) 301–320 10.1007/978-3-319-31395-5_16. (Springer International Publishing, Cham, 2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Syed Alwi, S. A. R. et al. A survey on COVID-19 vaccine acceptance and concern among Malaysians. BMC Public Health21, 1129 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8196915</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34118897</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mutombo, P. N. et al. COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy in Africa: a call to action. Lancet Glob. Health10, e320–e321 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8687664</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34942117</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scrima, F., Miceli, S., Caci, B. &amp; Cardaci, M. The relationship between fear of COVID-19 and intention to get vaccinated. The serial mediation roles of existential anxiety and conspiracy beliefs. Pers. Individ. Differ.184, 111188 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8354796</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34393312</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jafar, A. et al. COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy in Malaysia: exploring factors and identifying highly vulnerable groups. PLoS One17, e0270868 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9269452</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35802652</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bergen, N. et al. Global state of education-related inequality in COVID-19 vaccine coverage, structural barriers, vaccine hesitancy, and vaccine refusal: findings from the Global COVID-19 trends and impact survey. Lancet Glob. Health11, e207–e217 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9771421</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36565702</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oduwole, E. O., Esterhuizen, T. M., Mahomed, H. &amp; Wiysonge, C. S. Estimating vaccine confidence levels among healthcare staff and students of a tertiary institution in South Africa. Vaccines9, 1246 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8618030</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34835177</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shiloh, S., Peleg, S. &amp; Nudelman, G. Vaccination against COVID-19: a longitudinal trans-theoretical study to determine factors that predict intentions and behavior. Ann. Behav. Med.56, 357–367 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34864833</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassan, M. A.-K. &amp; Aliyu, S. Delayed access to COVID-19 vaccines: a perspective on low-income countries in Africa. Int. J. Health Serv.52, 323–329 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9047600</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35469499</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nemes, S., Jonasson, J. M., Genell, A. &amp; Steineck, G. Bias in odds ratios by logistic regression modelling and sample size. BMC Med. Res. Methodol.9, 56 (2009).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2724427</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19635144</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, K., Lee, C., Ihm, J. &amp; Kim, Y. A comprehensive examination of association between belief in vaccine misinformation and vaccination intention in the COVID-19 context. J. Health Commun.27, 495–509 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36205037</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hara, M., Ishibashi, M., Nakane, A., Nakano, T. &amp; Hirota, Y. Differences in COVID-19 vaccine acceptance, hesitancy, and confidence between healthcare workers and the general population in Japan. Vaccines9, 1389 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8707052</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34960135</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong, L. P. et al. Acceptability for COVID-19 vaccination: perspectives from Muslims. Hum. Vaccines Immunother.18, 2045855 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9196781</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35439106</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>İkiışık, H., Akif Sezerol, M., Taşçı, Y. &amp; Maral, I. COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy: a community-based research in Turkey. Int. J. Clin. Pract.75, e14336 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8237055</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33973322</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saito, K., Komasawa, M., Aung, M. N. &amp; Khin, E. T. COVID-19 vaccination willingness in Four Asian Countries: a comparative study including Thailand, Indonesia, the Philippines, and Vietnam. Int. J. Environ. Res. Public. Health19, 12284 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9566518</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36231586</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nomura, S. et al. Characterising reasons for reversals of COVID-19 vaccination hesitancy among Japanese people: one-year follow-up survey. Lancet Reg. Health West. Pac.27, 100541 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9302916</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35892010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. Statement on the fifteenth meeting of the IHR (2005). Emergency Committee on the COVID-19 pandemic. https://www.who.int/news/item/05-05-2023-statement-on-the-fifteenth-meeting-of-the-international-health-regulations-(2005)-emergency-committee-regarding-the-coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-pandemic (2023).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>