<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39448870</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1476-5497</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>International journal of obesity (2005)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Int J Obes (Lond)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Drugs used in psychiatry causing an increase in body weight in children-a review.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1038/s41366-024-01662-9</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Body weight gain is a prevalent adverse effect observed in psychiatric medication therapy. With the notable increase in mental health diagnoses among children and adolescents over the last decade, exacerbated by the COVID-19 pandemic, the use of medications associated with weight gain poses an additional risk for obesity development. This study aimed to identify psychiatric drugs that may induce weight gain in children as a side effect. Twenty-nine publications were included in this systematic review, investigating the effects of nineteen different drugs on children's weight. The majority of these drugs belonged to atypical antipsychotics and anticonvulsants. Nearly all included articles reported that the examined substances resulted in weight gain in children. As childhood obesity has become a significant problem with various metabolic, psychological and social consequences, it is crucial to carefully consider therapy options. In addition to evaluating effectiveness, it is important to also assess the potential for weight gain. Clinicians and nutrition specialists should individually evaluate patients' nutritional needs, evaluate obesity risk, and provide appropriate dietary guidance to minimalize the risk of weight gain.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer Nature Limited.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kuźbicka</LastName><ForeName>Karolina</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2240-0788</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacology, Medical University of Gdańsk, Dębowa 23, 80-204, Gdańsk, Poland. k.kuzbicka@gumed.edu.pl.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pawłowska</LastName><ForeName>Iga</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacology, Medical University of Gdańsk, Dębowa 23, 80-204, Gdańsk, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kocić</LastName><ForeName>Ivan</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacology, Medical University of Gdańsk, Dębowa 23, 80-204, Gdańsk, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Int J Obes (Lond)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101256108</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0307-0565</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>56</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39448870</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41366-024-01662-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1038/s41366-024-01662-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Medici V, McClave SA, Miller KR. Common medications which lead to unintended alterations in weight gain or organ lipotoxicity. Curr Gastroenterol Rep. 2016;18:2 https://doi.org/10.1007/s11894-015-0479-4 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11894-015-0479-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26700070</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verhaegen AA, Van Gaal LF. Drugs that affect body weight, body fat distribution, and metabolism. In: Feingold KR, Anawalt B, Blackman MR, et al., eds. Endotext. South Dartmouth (MA): MDText.com, Inc.; 2000.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tkacz J, Brady BL. Increasing rate of diagnosed childhood mental illness in the United States: incidence, prevalence and costs. Public Health Pr Oxf Engl. 2021;2:100204. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.puhip.2021.100204 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.puhip.2021.100204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Racine N, McArthur BA, Cooke JE, Eirich R, Zhu J, Madigan S. Global prevalence of depressive and anxiety symptoms in children and adolescents during COVID-19: a meta-analysis. JAMA Pediatr. 2021;175:1142–50. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamapediatrics.2021.2482 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamapediatrics.2021.2482</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34369987</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee J. Mental health effects of school closures during COVID-19. Lancet Child Adolesc Health 2020;4:421. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2352-4642(20)30109-7 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2352-4642(20)30109-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32302537</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7156240</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takahashi F, Honda H. Prevalence of clinical-level emotional/behavioral problems in schoolchildren during the coronavirus disease 2019 pandemic in Japan: a prospective cohort study. JCPP Adv. 2021;1:e12007. https://doi.org/10.1111/jcv2.12007 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jcv2.12007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34485986</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8206658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moulin F, Bailhache M, Monnier M, Thierry X, Vandentorren S, Côté SM, et al. Longitudinal impact of psychosocial status on children’s mental health in the context of COVID-19 pandemic restrictions. Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2023;32:1073–82. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00787-022-02010-w .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00787-022-02010-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35652982</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Onis M, Blössner M, Borghi E. Global prevalence and trends of overweight and obesity among preschool children. Am J Clin Nutr. 2010;92:1257–64. https://doi.org/10.3945/ajcn.2010.29786 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3945/ajcn.2010.29786</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20861173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuźbicka K, Rachoń D. Bad eating habits as the main cause of obesity among children. Pediatr Endocrinol Diabetes Metab. 2013;19:106–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25577898</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dietz WH. Health consequences of obesity in youth: childhood predictors of adult disease. Pediatrics 1998;101:518–25.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1542/peds.101.S2.518</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12224658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Griffiths LJ, Dezateux C, Hill A. Is obesity associated with emotional and behavioural problems in children? Findings from the millennium cohort study. Int J Pediatr Obes IJPO J Int Assoc Study Obes. 2011;6:e423–432. https://doi.org/10.3109/17477166.2010.526221 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3109/17477166.2010.526221</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kelsey MM, Zaepfel A, Bjornstad P, Nadeau KJ. Age-related consequences of childhood obesity. Gerontology. 2014;60:222–8. https://doi.org/10.1159/000356023 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000356023</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24434909</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Page MJ, McKenzie JE, Bossuyt PM, Boutron I, Hoffmann TC, Mulrow CD, et al. The PRISMA 2020 statement: an updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews. BMJ. 2021;372:n71 https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.n71 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.n71</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33782057</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8005924</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jahangard L, Akbarian S, Haghighi M, Ahmadpanah M, Keshavarzi A, Bajoghli H, et al. Children with ADHD and symptoms of oppositional defiant disorder improved in behavior when treated with methylphenidate and adjuvant risperidone, though weight gain was also observed—results from a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trial. Psychiatry Res. 2017;251:182–91. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.psychres.2016.12.010 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2016.12.010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28213188</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ceylan MF, Erdogan B, Tural Hesapcioglu S, Cop E. Effectiveness, adverse effects and drug compliance of long-acting injectable risperidone in children and adolescents. Clin Drug Investig. 2017;37:947–56. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40261-017-0555-7 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40261-017-0555-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28726075</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gagliano A, Germanò E, Pustorino G, Impallomeni C, D'Arrigo C, Calamoneri F, et al. Risperidone treatment of children with autistic disorder: effectiveness, tolerability, and pharmacokinetic implications. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2004;14:39–47. https://doi.org/10.1089/104454604773840472 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/104454604773840472</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15142390</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jedrzejczak J, Kuncíková M, Magureanu S. An observational study of first-line valproate monotherapy in focal epilepsy. Eur J Neurol. 2008;15:66–72. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1468-1331.2007.02003.x .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1468-1331.2007.02003.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18042239</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Savitz AJ, Lane R, Nuamah I, Gopal S, Hough D. Efficacy and safety of paliperidone extended release in adolescents with schizophrenia: a randomized, double-blind study. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2015;54:126–137.e1. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jaac.2014.11.009 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jaac.2014.11.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25617253</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chadwick D. Safety and efficacy of vigabatrin and carbamazepine in newly diagnosed epilepsy: a multicentre randomised double-blind study. Vigabatrin European Monotherapy Study Group. Lancet Lond Engl. 1999;354:13–9. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0140-6736(98)10531-7 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s0140-6736(98)10531-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fraguas D, Merchán-Naranjo J, Laita P, Parellada M, Moreno D, Ruiz-Sancho A, et al. Metabolic and hormonal side effects in children and adolescents treated with second-generation antipsychotics. J Clin Psychiatry. 2008;69:1166–75. https://doi.org/10.4088/jcp.v69n0717 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4088/jcp.v69n0717</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18588363</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Findling RL, Johnson JL, McClellan J, Frazier JA, Vitiello B, Hamer RM, et al. Double-blind maintenance safety and effectiveness findings from the treatment of early-onset Schizophrenia Spectrum (TEOSS) study. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2010;49:583–94. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jaac.2010.03.013 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jaac.2010.03.013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20494268</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2882800</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jensen KG, Correll CU, Rudå D, Klauber DG, Decara MS, Fagerlund B, et al. Cardiometabolic adverse effects and its predictors in children and adolescents with first-episode psychosis during treatment with quetiapine-extended release versus aripiprazole: 12-week results from the tolerance and effect of antipsychotics in children and adolescents with psychosis (TEA) trial. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2019;58:1062–78. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jaac.2019.01.015 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jaac.2019.01.015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30858012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghaleiha A, Mohammadi E, Mohammadi MR, Farokhnia M, Modabbernia A, Yekehtaz K, et al. Riluzole as an adjunctive therapy to risperidone for the treatment of irritability in children with autistic disorder: a double-blind, placebo-controlled, randomized trial. Paediatr Drugs. 2013;15:505–14. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40272-013-0036-2 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40272-013-0036-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23821414</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fleischhaker C, Heiser P, Hennighausen K, Herpertz-Dahlmann B, Holtkamp K, Mehler-Wex C, et al. Clinical drug monitoring in child and adolescent psychiatry: side effects of atypical neuroleptics. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2006;16:308–16. https://doi.org/10.1089/cap.2006.16.308 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/cap.2006.16.308</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16768638</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pavuluri MN, Henry DB, Findling RL, Parnes S, Carbray JA, Mohammed T, et al. Double-blind randomized trial of risperidone versus divalproex in pediatric bipolar disorder. Bipolar Disord. 2010;12:593–605. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1399-5618.2010.00850.x .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1399-5618.2010.00850.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20868458</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3013630</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumra S, Kranzler H, Gerbino-Rosen G, Kester HM, DeThomas C, Cullen K, et al. Clozapine versus “high-dose” olanzapine in refractory early-onset schizophrenia: an open-label extension study. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2008;18:307–16. https://doi.org/10.1089/cap.2007.0089 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/cap.2007.0089</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18759640</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2935826</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Detke HC, DelBello MP, Landry J, Usher RW. Olanzapine/Fluoxetine combination in children and adolescents with bipolar I depression: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2015;54:217–24. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jaac.2014.12.012 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jaac.2014.12.012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25721187</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pagsberg AK, Jeppesen P, Klauber DG, Jensen KG, Ruda D, Stentebjerg-Olesen M, et al. Quetiapine extended release versus aripiprazole in children and adolescents with first-episode psychosis: the multicentre, double-blind, randomised tolerability and efficacy of antipsychotics (TEA) trial. Lancet Psychiatry. 2017;4:605–18. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2215-0366(17)30166-9 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2215-0366(17)30166-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28599949</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biton V, Levisohn P, Hoyler S, Vuong A, Hammer AE. Lamotrigine versus valproate monotherapy-associated weight change in adolescents with epilepsy: results from a post hoc analysis of a randomized, double-blind clinical trial. J Child Neurol. 2003;18:133–9. https://doi.org/10.1177/08830738030180021701 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/08830738030180021701</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12693782</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Correll CU, Manu P, Olshanskiy V, Napolitano B, Kane JM, Malhotra AK. Cardiometabolic risk of second-generation antipsychotic medications during first-time use in children and adolescents. JAMA. 2009;302:1765–73. https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2009.1549 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2009.1549</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19861668</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3055794</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ondo WG, Jong D, Davis A. Comparison of weight gain in treatments for Tourette syndrome: tetrabenazine versus neuroleptic drugs. J Child Neurol. 2008;23:435–7. https://doi.org/10.1177/0883073807307108 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0883073807307108</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18192650</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arango C, Buitelaar JK, Fegert JM, Olivier V, Penelaud PF, Mrx U, et al. Safety and efficacy of agomelatine in children and adolescents with major depressive disorder receiving psychosocial counselling: a double-blind, randomised, controlled, phase 3 trial in nine countries. Lancet Psychiatry. 2022;9:113–24. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2215-0366(21)00390-4 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2215-0366(21)00390-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34919834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Findling RL, Robb A, McNamara NK, Pavuluri MN, Kafantaris V, Scheffer R, et al. Lithium in the acute treatment of bipolar I disorder: a double-blind, placebo-controlled study. Pediatrics. 2015;136:885–94. https://doi.org/10.1542/peds.2015-0743 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1542/peds.2015-0743</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26459650</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4621794</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Findling RL, McNamara NK, Pavuluri M, Frazier JA, Rynn M, Scheffer R, et al. Lithium for the maintenance treatment of bipolar I disorder: a double-blind, placebo-controlled discontinuation study. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2019;58:287–.e4. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jaac.2018.07.901 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jaac.2018.07.901</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30738555</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haas M, Delbello MP, Pandina G, Kushner S, Van Hove I, Augustyns I, et al. Risperidone for the treatment of acute mania in children and adolescents with bipolar disorder: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study. Bipolar Disord. 2009;11:687–700. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1399-5618.2009.00750.x .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1399-5618.2009.00750.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19839994</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reyes M, Buitelaar J, Toren P, Augustyns I, Eerdekens M. A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study of risperidone maintenance treatment in children and adolescents with disruptive behavior disorders. Am J Psychiatry. 2006;163:402–10. https://doi.org/10.1176/appi.ajp.163.3.402 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.163.3.402</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16513860</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buitelaar JK, van der Gaag RJ, Cohen-Kettenis P, Melman CT. A randomized controlled trial of risperidone in the treatment of aggression in hospitalized adolescents with subaverage cognitive abilities. J Clin Psychiatry. 2001;62:239–48. https://doi.org/10.4088/jcp.v62n0405 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4088/jcp.v62n0405</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11379837</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rao WW, Zong QQ, Zhang JW, An FR, Jackson T, Ungvari GS, et al. Obesity increases the risk of depression in children and adolescents: results from a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Affect Disord. 2020;267:78–85. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jad.2020.01.154 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2020.01.154</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32063576</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ells LJ, Lang R, Shield JPH, Wilkinson JR, Lindstone JSM, Coulton S, et al. Obesity and disability—a short review. Obes Rev J Int Assoc Study Obes. 2006;7:341–5. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-789X.2006.00233.x .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1467-789X.2006.00233.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koskentausta T, Iivanainen M, Almqvist F. Psychiatric disorders in children with intellectual disability. Nord J Psychiatry. 2002;56:126–31. https://doi.org/10.1080/080394802753617944 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/080394802753617944</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11960565</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Slevin E, Truesdale-Kennedy M, McConkey R, Livingstone B, Fleming P. Obesity and overweight in intellectual and non-intellectually disabled children. J Intellect Disabil Res JIDR. 2014;58:211–20. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2788.2012.01615.x .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2788.2012.01615.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22957929</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Emerson E, Robertson J, Baines S, Hatton C. Obesity in British children with and without intellectual disability: cohort study. BMC Public Health. 2016;16:644 https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889-016-3309-1 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12889-016-3309-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27460572</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4962444</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choi E, Park H, Ha Y, Hwang WJ. Prevalence of overweight and obesity in children with intellectual disabilities in Korea. J Appl Res Intellect Disabil JARID. 2012;25:476–83. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1468-3148.2012.00694.x .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1468-3148.2012.00694.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22890948</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuan YQ, Liu Y, Wang MJ, Hou X, Zhang SH, Wang XL, et al. Prevalence of overweight and obesity in children and adolescents with intellectual disabilities in China. J Intellect Disabil Res JIDR. 2021;65:655–65. https://doi.org/10.1111/jir.12840 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jir.12840</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33851750</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maïano C, Hue O, Morin AJS, Moullec G. Prevalence of overweight and obesity among children and adolescents with intellectual disabilities: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Obes Rev J Int Assoc Study Obes. 2016;17:599–611. https://doi.org/10.1111/obr.12408 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/obr.12408</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wiedeman AM, Panagiotopoulos C, Devlin AM. Treatment-related weight gain and metabolic complications in children with mental health disorders: potential role for lifestyle interventions. Appl Physiol Nutr Metab Physiol Appl Nutr Metab. 2021;46:193–204. https://doi.org/10.1139/apnm-2020-0259 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1139/apnm-2020-0259</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martínez-Ortega JM, Funes-Godoy S, Díaz-Atienza F, Gutiérrez-Rojas L, Pérez-Costillas L, Gurpegui M. Weight gain and increase of body mass index among children and adolescents treated with antipsychotics: a critical review. Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2013;22:457–79. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00787-013-0399-5 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00787-013-0399-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23503976</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Libowitz MR, Nurmi EL. The burden of antipsychotic-induced weight gain and metabolic syndrome in children. Front Psychiatry. 2021;12:623681. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2021.623681 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2021.623681</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33776816</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7994286</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lifshitz F. Obesity in children. J Clin Res Pediatr Endocrinol. 2008;1:53–60. https://doi.org/10.4008/jcrpe.v1i2.35 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4008/jcrpe.v1i2.35</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21318065</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3005642</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bégarie J, Maïano C, Leconte P, Ninot G. The prevalence and determinants of overweight and obesity among French youths and adults with intellectual disabilities attending special education schools. Res Dev Disabil. 2013;34:1417–25. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ridd.2012.12.007 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ridd.2012.12.007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23474994</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pillinger T, McCutcheon RA, Vano L, Mizuno Y, Arumuham A, Hindley G, et al. Comparative effects of 18 antipsychotics on metabolic function in patients with schizophrenia, predictors of metabolic dysregulation, and association with psychopathology: a systematic review and network meta-analysis. Lancet Psychiatry. 2020;7:64–77. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2215-0366(19)30416-X .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2215-0366(19)30416-X</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31860457</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7029416</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Correll CU. Addressing adverse effects of antipsychotic treatment in young patients with schizophrenia. J Clin Psychiatry. 2011;72:e01 https://doi.org/10.4088/JCP.9101tx6c .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4088/JCP.9101tx6c</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21272508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Safer DJ. A comparison of risperidone-induced weight gain across the age span. J Clin Psychopharmacol. 2004;24:429–36. https://doi.org/10.1097/01.jcp.0000130558.86125.5b .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/01.jcp.0000130558.86125.5b</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15232335</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nehme H, Saulnier P, Ramadan AA, Cassisa V, Guillet C, Eveillard M, et al. Antibacterial activity of antipsychotic agents, their association with lipid nanocapsules and its impact on the properties of the nanocarriers and on antibacterial activity. PloS ONE. 2018;13:e0189950 https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0189950 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0189950</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29298353</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5752010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuan X, Zhang P, Wang Y, Liu Y, Li X, Kumar BU, et al. Changes in metabolism and microbiota after 24-week risperidone treatment in drug naïve, normal weight patients with first episode schizophrenia. Schizophr Res. 2018;201:299–306. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.schres.2018.05.017 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.schres.2018.05.017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29859859</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ait Chait Y, Mottawea W, Tompkins TA, Hammami R. Unravelling the antimicrobial action of antidepressants on gut commensal microbes. Sci Rep. 2020;10:17878 https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-74934-9 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-74934-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33087796</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7578019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ignacio A, Fernandes MR, Rodrigues VAA, Groppo FC, Cardoso AL, Avila-Campos MJ, et al. Correlation between body mass index and faecal microbiota from children. Clin Microbiol Infect Publ Eur Soc Clin Microbiol Infect Dis. 2016;22:258–e1-8. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmi.2015.10.031 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmi.2015.10.031</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carabotti M, Scirocco A, Maselli MA, Severi C. The gut-brain axis: interactions between enteric microbiota, central and enteric nervous systems. Ann Gastroenterol. 2015;28:203–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25830558</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4367209</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang J, Hei GR, Yang Y, Liu CC, Xiao JM, Long YJ, et al. Increased appetite plays a key role in olanzapine-induced weight gain in first-episode schizophrenia patients. Front Pharm. 2020;11:739. https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2020.00739 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fphar.2020.00739</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen H, Cao T, Zhang B, Cai H. The regulatory effects of second-generation antipsychotics on lipid metabolism: potential mechanisms mediated by the gut microbiota and therapeutic implications. Front Pharm. 2023;14:1097284. https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2023.1097284 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fphar.2023.1097284</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Endomba FT, Tankeu AT, Nkeck JR, Tochie JN. Leptin and psychiatric illnesses: does leptin play a role in antipsychotic-induced weight gain? Lipids Health Dis. 2020;19:22 https://doi.org/10.1186/s12944-020-01203-z .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12944-020-01203-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32033608</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7006414</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan Z, Wu Y, Shen J, Ji T, Zhan R. Schizophrenia and the risk of cardiovascular diseases: a meta-analysis of thirteen cohort studies. J Psychiatr Res. 2013;47:1549–56. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpsychires.2013.07.011 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2013.07.011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23953755</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abenavoli L, Scarpellini E, Colica C, Boccuto L, Salehi B, Sharifi-Rad J, et al. Gut microbiota and obesity: a role for probiotics. Nutrients. 2019;11. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu11112690 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balanzá Martínez V. Nutritional supplements in psychotic disorders. Actas Esp Psiquiatr. 2017;45:16–25.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29171643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Camfield P, Camfield C. Incidence, prevalence and aetiology of seizures and epilepsy in children. Epileptic Disord Int Epilepsy J Videotape. 2015;17:117–23. https://doi.org/10.1684/epd.2015.0736 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1684/epd.2015.0736</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verrotti A, D’Egidio C, Mohn A, Coppola G, Chiarelli F. Weight gain following treatment with valproic acid: pathogenetic mechanisms and clinical implications. Obes Rev J Int Assoc Study Obes. 2011;12:e32–43. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-789X.2010.00800.x .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1467-789X.2010.00800.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Howard JK, Flier JS. Attenuation of leptin and insulin signaling by SOCS proteins. Trends Endocrinol Metab Tem. 2006;17:365–71. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tem.2006.09.007 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tem.2006.09.007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17010638</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown R, Imran SA, Ur E, Wilkinson M. Valproic acid and CEBPalpha-mediated regulation of adipokine gene expression in hypothalamic neurons and 3T3-L1 adipocytes. Neuroendocrinology. 2008;88:25–34. https://doi.org/10.1159/000113927 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000113927</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18212493</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dinesen H, Gram L, Andersen T, Dam M. Weight gain during treatment with valproate. Acta Neurol Scand. 1984;70:65–69. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1600-0404.1984.tb00804.x .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0404.1984.tb00804.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6435386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Espinosa PS, Salazar JC, Yu L, Mendiondo MS, Robertson WC, Baumann RJ. Lack of valproic acid-associated weight gain in prepubertal children. Pediatr Neurol. 2008;39:177–80. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pediatrneurol.2008.05.006 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pediatrneurol.2008.05.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18725062</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watanabe N, Omori IM, Nakagawa A, Cipriani A, Barbui C, McGuire H, et al. Safety reporting and adverse-event profile of mirtazapine described in randomized controlled trials in comparison with other classes of antidepressants in the acute-phase treatment of adults with depression: systematic review and meta-analysis. CNS Drugs. 2010;24:35–53. https://doi.org/10.2165/11319480-000000000-00000 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2165/11319480-000000000-00000</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20030418</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lechner K, Heel S, Uhr M, Dose T, Holsboer F, Lucae S, et al. Weight-gain independent effect of mirtazapine on fasting plasma lipids in healthy men. Naunyn Schmiedebergs Arch Pharm. 2023;396:1999–2008. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00210-023-02448-y .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00210-023-02448-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Selph SS, McDonagh MS. Depression in children and adolescents: evaluation and treatment. Am Fam Physician. 2019;100:609–17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31730312</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greil W, de Bardeci M, Müller-Oerlinghausen B, Nievergelt N, Stassen H, Hasler G, et al. Controversies regarding lithium-associated weight gain: case-control study of real-world drug safety data. Int J Bipolar Disord. 2023;11:34 https://doi.org/10.1186/s40345-023-00313-8 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40345-023-00313-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37840048</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10577117</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mozes T, Greenberg Y, Spivak B, Tyano S, Weizman A, Mester R. Olanzapine treatment in chronic drug-resistant childhood-onset schizophrenia: an open-label study. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2003;13:311–7. https://doi.org/10.1089/104454603322572642 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/104454603322572642</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14642019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Redden L, DelBello M, Wagner KD, Wilens TE, Malhotra A, Wozniak P, et al. Long-term safety of divalproex sodium extended-release in children and adolescents with bipolar I disorder. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2009;19:83–89. https://doi.org/10.1089/cap.2008.0106 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/cap.2008.0106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19232026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Findling RL, Groark J, Tourian KA, Ramaker SA, Chiles D, Yang L, et al. Pharmacokinetics and tolerability of single-ascending doses of desvenlafaxine administered to children and adolescents with major depressive disorder. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2016;26:909–21. https://doi.org/10.1089/cap.2016.0009 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/cap.2016.0009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27428303</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jan MMS, Zuberi SA, Alsaihati BA. Pregabalin: preliminary experience in intractable childhood epilepsy. Pediatr Neurol. 2009;40:347–50. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pediatrneurol.2008.12.016 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pediatrneurol.2008.12.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19380070</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mrakotsky C, Masek B, Biederman J, Raches D, Hsin O, Forbes P, et al. Prospective open-label pilot trial of mirtazapine in children and adolescents with social phobia. J Anxiety Disord. 2008;22:88–97. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.janxdis.2007.01.005 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.janxdis.2007.01.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17419001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heck A, Holleman A. Growth of Dutch Children. Presented at: 2001; AMSTEL Institute; available at: https://staff.fnwi.uva.nl/a.j.p.heck/research/growth/taskA.pdf .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Israel EJ, Levitsky LL, Anupindi SA, Pitman MB. Case records of the Massachusetts General Hospital. Weekly clinicopathological exercises. Case 3-2005. A 14-year-old boy with recent slowing of growth and delayed puberty. N. Engl J Med. 2005;352:393–403. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMcpc049032 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMcpc049032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15673806</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>