<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39440918</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1471-2865</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>29</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Physiotherapy research international : the journal for researchers and clinicians in physical therapy</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Physiother Res Int</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Artists' satisfaction with telerehabilitation in physiotherapy during the COVID-19 pandemic: A cross-sectional study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70002</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70002</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/pri.70002</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND AND PURPOSE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To our knowledge, there is currently no research on telerehabilitation concerning artists. This study aims to assess the feasibility, acceptability, and effectiveness of utilizing video-based telerehabilitation in physiotherapy among artists during the COVID-19 pandemic.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Fifty-one artists who accessed virtual physiotherapy between November 2020 and February 2022 at a healthcare center that provides specialized healthcare services to artists of all disciplines who reside or work in Ontario, Canada were asked to complete a 26-item online questionnaire about their experience with virtual physiotherapy.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The 51 respondents were from a range of artistic disciplines, with the largest portion being musicians (n = 22; 43%). Of the respondents, 86% (n = 44) felt the virtual physiotherapy met their expectations in therapeutic benefits, 78% (n = 40) were confident in performing all the exercises that the physiotherapist demonstrated on the virtual platform, 80% (n = 41) did not run into many technological challenges when booking or attending virtual sessions, and 54% (n = 20) reported similar treatment outcomes between virtual and in-person sessions. Although artists liked the convenience of accessing physiotherapy from home, 53% (n = 17) of respondents rated the lack of physical contact as a major limitation in telerehabilitation.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Telerehabilitation for artists during the COVID-19 pandemic has shown potential to be an effective and viable alternative to in-person physiotherapy, as demonstrated by high satisfaction levels and comparable treatment outcomes, especially when public health restrictions were in place. Future research can explore hybrid models (mix of in-person and virtual sessions) in physiotherapy to meet the needs for physical contact during sessions.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Physiotherapy Research International published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jiang</LastName><ForeName>Coco</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0000-2466-2357</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Al &amp; Malka Green Artists' Health Centre, University Health Network, Toronto, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Departments of Cell &amp; Systems Biology, Molecular Genetics, and Computer Science, Faculty of Arts &amp; Science, University of Toronto, Toronto, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>de Youngster</LastName><ForeName>Sesinam</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0006-4679-3714</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Al &amp; Malka Green Artists' Health Centre, University Health Network, Toronto, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hawkins</LastName><ForeName>Vicki</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Al &amp; Malka Green Artists' Health Centre, University Health Network, Toronto, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Shelly-Anne</ForeName><Initials>SA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0189-0880</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Al &amp; Malka Green Artists' Health Centre, University Health Network, Toronto, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Family &amp; Community Medicine, Temerty Faculty of Medicine, University of Toronto, Toronto, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Physiother Res Int</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9612022</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1358-2267</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000534" MajorTopicYN="N">rehabilitation</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000069350" MajorTopicYN="Y">Telerehabilitation</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003430" MajorTopicYN="N">Cross-Sectional Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D026741" MajorTopicYN="Y">Physical Therapy Modalities</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011795" MajorTopicYN="N">Surveys and Questionnaires</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009864" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Ontario</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">musculoskeletal</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">occupational health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">physiotherapy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">questionnaire</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">rehabilitation services</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>37</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39440918</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/pri.70002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Aily, J. B., Barton, C. J., Mattiello, S. M., De Oliveira Silva, D., &amp; De Noronha, M. (2020). Telerehabilitation for knee osteoarthritis in Brazil: A feasibility study. International Journal of Telerehabilitation, 12(2), 137–148. https://doi.org/10.5195/ijt.2020.6323</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Albahrouh, S. I., &amp; Buabbas, A. J. (2021). Physiotherapists’ perceptions of and willingness to use telerehabilitation in Kuwait during the COVID‐19 pandemic. BMC Medical Informatics and Decision Making, 21(1), 122. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12911‐021‐01478‐x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alsobayel, H., Alodaibi, F., Albarrati, A., Alsalamah, N., Alhawas, F., &amp; Alhowimel, A. (2021). Does telerehabilitation help in reducing disability among people with musculoskeletal conditions? A preliminary study. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, 19(1), 72. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph19010072</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anders Ericsson, K. (2008). Deliberate practice and acquisition of expert performance: A general overview. Academic Emergency Medicine, 15(11), 988–994. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1553‐2712.2008.00227.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Angelini, F., Castellani, M., &amp; Pattitoni, P. (2023). Artist names as human brands: Brand determinants, creation and co‐creation mechanisms. Empirical Studies of the Arts, 41(1), 80–107. https://doi.org/10.1177/02762374211072964</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azma, K., RezaSoltani, Z., Rezaeimoghaddam, F., Dadarkhah, A., &amp; Mohsenolhosseini, S. (2018). Efficacy of tele‐rehabilitation compared with office‐based physical therapy in patients with knee osteoarthritis: A randomized clinical trial. Journal of Telemedicine and Telecare, 24(8), 560–565. https://doi.org/10.1177/1357633x17723368</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bakken, S., Grullon‐Figueroa, L., Izquierdo, R., Lee, N. J., Morin, P., Palmas, W., Teresi, J., Weinstock, R. S., Shea, S., &amp; Starren, J. (2006). Development, validation, and use of English and Spanish versions of the telemedicine satisfaction and usefulness questionnaire. Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association, 13(6), 660–667. https://doi.org/10.1197/jamia.m2146</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barton, C. J., Ezzat, A. M., Merolli, M., Williams, C., Haines, T., Mehta, N., &amp; Malliaras, P. (2022). “It’s second best”: A mixed‐methods evaluation of the experiences and attitudes of people with musculoskeletal pain towards physiotherapist delivered telehealth during the COVID‐19 pandemic. Musculoskeletal Science and Practice, 58, 102500. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.msksp.2021.102500</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bennell, K. L., Lawford, B. J., Metcalf, B., Mackenzie, D., Russell, T., van den Berg, M., Finnin, K., Crowther, S., Aiken, J., Fleming, J., &amp; Hinman, R. S. (2021). Physiotherapists and patients report positive experiences overall with telehealth during the COVID‐19 pandemic: A mixed‐methods study. Journal of Physiotherapy, 67(3), 201–209. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jphys.2021.06.009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown, J., Doherty, D., Claus, A. P., Gilbert, K., &amp; Nielsen, M. (2022). In a pandemic that limits contact, can videoconferencing enable interdisciplinary persistent pain services and what are the patient’s perspectives? Archives of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, 103(3), 418–423. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apmr.2021.10.018</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buabbas, A. J., Albahrouh, S. E., Alrowayeh, H. N., &amp; Alshawaf, H. (2022). Telerehabilitation during the COVID‐19 pandemic: Patients and physical therapists’ experiences. Medical Principles and Practice, 31(2), 156–164. https://doi.org/10.1159/000523775</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burkle, C. M., &amp; Cascino, G. D. (2011). Medicine and the media: Balancing the public’s right to know with the privacy of the patient. Mayo Clinic Proceedings, 86(12), 1192–1196. https://doi.org/10.4065/mcp.2011.0520</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cartwright, A. J. (2023). The elephant in the room: Cybersecurity in healthcare. Journal of Clinical Monitoring and Computing, 37(5), 1123–1132. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10877‐023‐01013‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Costa, F., Janela, D., Molinos, M., Lains, J., Francisco, G. E., Bento, V., &amp; Dias Correia, F. (2022). Telerehabilitation of acute musculoskeletal multi‐disorders: Prospective, single‐arm, interventional study. BMC Musculoskeletal Disorders, 23(1), 29. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12891‐021‐04891‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Demiris, G., Speedie, S., &amp; Finkelstein, S. (2000). A questionnaire for the assessment of patients’ impressions of the risks and benefits of home telecare. Journal of Telemedicine and Telecare, 6(5), 278–284. https://doi.org/10.1258/1357633001935914</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elor, A., Conde, S., Powell, M., Robbins, A., Chen, N. N., &amp; Kurniawan, S. (2022). Physical therapist impressions of telehealth and virtual reality needs amidst a pandemic. Frontiers in Virtual Reality, 3, 915332. https://doi.org/10.3389/frvir.2022.915332</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grona, S. L., Bath, B., Busch, A., Rotter, T., Trask, C., &amp; Harrison, E. (2018). Use of videoconferencing for physical therapy in people with musculoskeletal conditions: A systematic review. Journal of Telemedicine and Telecare, 24(5), 341–355. https://doi.org/10.1177/1357633x17700781</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hajesmaeel‐Gohari, S., &amp; Bahaadinbeigy, K. (2021). The most used questionnaires for evaluating telemedicine services. BMC Medical Informatics and Decision Making, 21(1), 36. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12911‐021‐01407‐y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harper, K. J., Fitzgerald, S., Xiyin, P., Kuzich, J., Leow, S. H., Jacques, A., &amp; Harris, C. (2022). Does the integration of telehealth into occupational therapy practice impact clinical outcomes for hand and upper limb rehabilitation? A matched case control study. International Journal of Telerehabilitation, 14(2). Epub ahead of print 13 December 2022. https://doi.org/10.5195/ijt.2022.6505</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hawley‐Hague, H., Lasrado, R., Martinez, E., Stanmore, E., &amp; Tyson, S. (2022). A scoping review of the feasibility, acceptability, and effects of physiotherapy delivered remotely. Disability &amp; Rehabilitation, 0(23), 1–17. https://doi.org/10.1080/09638288.2022.2138574</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hill, K. A. (2019). Statistical profile of artists in Canada in 2016 (Vol. 49). Hill Strategies Research.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hinkamp, D. L., McCann, M., &amp; Babin, A. (2017). Occupational health and the arts. Journal of Occupational and Environmental Medicine, 59(9), 835–842. https://doi.org/10.1097/jom.0000000000001027</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Honrado, J., Bay, R. C., &amp; Lam, K. C. (2021). Epidemiology of patients with dance‐related injuries presenting to emergency departments in the United States, 2014‐2018. Sport Health, 13(5), 471–475. https://doi.org/10.1177/1941738120984113</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeong, I. C., Karpatkin, H., &amp; Finkelstein, J. (2021). Physical telerehabilitation improves quality of life in patients with multiple sclerosis. Studies in Health Technology and Informatics, 284, 384–388.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jørgensen, K., &amp; Laursen, B. (2013). Absence from work due to occupational and non‐occupational accidents. Scandinavian Journal of Public Health, 41(1), 18–24. https://doi.org/10.1177/1403494812468518</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kichloo, A., Albosta, M., Dettloff, K., Wani, F., El‐Amir, Z., Singh, J., Aljadah, M., Chakinala, R. C., Kanugula, A. K., Solanki, S., &amp; Chugh, S. (2020). Telemedicine, the current COVID‐19 pandemic and the future: A narrative review and perspectives moving forward in the USA. Fam Med Community Health, 8(3), e000530. https://doi.org/10.1136/fmch‐2020‐000530</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kok, L. M., Huisstede, B. M. A., Voorn, V. M. A., Schoones, J. W., &amp; Nelissen, R. G. H. H. (2016). The occurrence of musculoskeletal complaints among professional musicians: A systematic review. International Archives of Occupational and Environmental Health, 89(3), 373–396. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00420‐015‐1090‐6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mattiussi, A. M., Shaw, J. W., Williams, S., Price, P. D., Brown, D. D., Cohen, D. D., Clark, R., Kelly, S., Retter, G., Pedlar, C., &amp; Tallent, J. (2021). Injury epidemiology in professional ballet: A five‐season prospective study of 1596 medical attention injuries and 543 time‐loss injuries. British Journal of Sports Medicine, 55(15), 843–850. https://doi.org/10.1136/bjsports‐2020‐103817</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McBride, C., &amp; Bronner, S. (2022). Injury characteristics in professional modern dancers: A 15‐year analysis of work‐related injury rates and patterns. Journal of Sports Sciences, 40(7), 821–837. https://doi.org/10.1080/02640414.2021.2021030</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niarchou, M., Lin, G. T., Lense, M. D., Gordon, R. L., &amp; Davis, L. K. (2021). Medical phenome of musicians: An investigation of health records collected on 9803 musically active individuals. Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences, 1505(1), 156–168. https://doi.org/10.1111/nyas.14671</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ostwald, P. F., Baron, B. C., Byl, N. M., et al. (1994). Performing arts medicine. Western Journal of Medicine, 160, 48.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peretti, A., Amenta, F., Tayebati, S. K., Nittari, G., &amp; Mahdi, S. S. (2017). Telerehabilitation: Review of the state‐of‐the‐art and areas of application. JMIR Rehabilitation and Assistive Technologies, 4(2), e7511. https://doi.org/10.2196/rehab.7511</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quigley, A., Johnson, H., &amp; McArthur, C. (2021). Transforming the provision of physiotherapy in the time of COVID‐19: A call to action for telerehabilitation. Physiotherapie Canada, 73, 1–2. https://doi.org/10.3138/ptc‐2020‐0031‐gee</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rabanifar, N., &amp; Abdi, K. (2021). Barriers and challenges of implementing telerehabilitation: A systematic review. IRJ, 19(2), 121–128. https://doi.org/10.32598/irj.19.2.1404.1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rabanifar, N., Hoseini, M. A., &amp; Abdi, K. (2022). Exploring barriers to implementing telerehabilitation from experiences of managers, policymakers, and providers of rehabilitation services in Iran: A qualitative study. Medical Journal of the Islamic Republic of Iran, 36, 157.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richmond, T., Peterson, C., Cason, J., Billings, M., Terrell, E. A., Lee, A. C. W., Towey, M., Parmanto, B., Saptano, A., Cohn, E. R., &amp; Brennan, D. (2017). American telemedicine association’s principles for delivering telerehabilitation services. International Journal of Telerehabilitation, 9(2), 63–68. https://doi.org/10.5195/ijt.2017.6232</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saaei, F., &amp; Klappa, S. G. (2021). Rethinking telerehabilitation: Attitudes of physical therapists and patients. Journal of Patient Experience, 8, 23743735211034336. https://doi.org/10.1177/23743735211034335</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suso‐Martí, L., La Touche, R., Herranz‐Gómez, A., Angulo‐Díaz‐Parreño, S., Paris‐Alemany, A., &amp; Cuenca‐Martínez, F. (2021). Effectiveness of telerehabilitation in physical therapist practice: An umbrella and mapping review with meta–meta‐analysis. Physical Therapy, 101(5), pzab075. https://doi.org/10.1093/ptj/pzab075</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Szekeres, M., &amp; Valdes, K. (2022). Virtual health care and telehealth: Current therapy practice patterns. Journal of Hand Therapy, 35(1), 124–130. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jht.2020.11.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tarakci, E., Tarakci, D., Hajebrahimi, F., &amp; Budak, M. (2021). Supervised exercises versus telerehabilitation. Benefits for persons with multiple sclerosis. Acta Neurologica Scandinavica, 144(3), 303–311. https://doi.org/10.1111/ane.13448</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vassallo, A. J., Pappas, E., Stamatakis, E., &amp; Hiller, C. E. (2019). Injury fear, stigma, and reporting in professional dancers. Saf Health Work, 10(3), 260–264. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.shaw.2019.03.001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wundersitz, C., Caelli, A., Georgy, J., Musovic, A., Manning, R., Prause, M., Robertson, J., &amp; Taylor, N. F. (2020). Conducting community rehabilitation review sessions via videoconference: A feasibility study. Australian Journal of Rural Health, 28(6), 603–612. https://doi.org/10.1111/ajr.12665</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zalpour, C., Ballenberger, N., &amp; Avermann, F. (2021). A physiotherapeutic approach to musicians’ health – Data from 614 patients from a physiotherapy clinic for musicians (INAP/O). Frontiers in Psychology, 12, 568684. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2021.568684</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>