<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39446835</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2767-3375</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>4</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>PLOS global public health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>PLOS Glob Public Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Controlling the first wave of the COVID-19 pandemic in Malawi: Results from a multi-round study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e0003474</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e0003474</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e0003474</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1371/journal.pgph.0003474</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>We investigated behavioral responses to COVID-19 in Malawi, where a first wave of the pandemic occurred between June and August 2020. Contrary to many countries on the African continent, the Government of Malawi did not impose a lockdown or a stay-at-home order in response to the initial spread of SARS-CoV-2. We hypothesized that, in the absence of such requirements to restrict social interactions, individuals would primarily seek to reduce the risk of SARS-CoV-2 transmission during contacts, rather than reduce the extent of their social contacts. We analyzed 4 rounds of a panel survey spanning time periods before, during and after the first wave of the COVID-19 pandemic in Malawi. Five hundred and forty-three participants completed 4 survey interviews between April and November 2020. We found that the likelihood of attending various places and events where individuals work and/or socialize remained largely unchanged during that time. Over the same time frame, however, participants reported adopting on a large scale several behaviors that reduce the transmissibility of SARS-CoV-2 during contacts. The percentage of panel participants who reported practicing physical distancing thus increased from 9.8% to 47.0% in rural areas between April-May 2020 and June-July 2020, and from 11.4% to 59.4% in urban areas. The percentage of respondents who reported wearing a facial mask to prevent the spread of SARS-CoV-2 also increased, reaching 67.7% among rural residents in August-September 2020, and 89.6% among urban residents. The pace at which these behaviors were adopted varied between population groups, with early adopters of mask use more commonly found among more educated office workers, residing in urban areas. The adoption of mask use was also initially slower among women, but later caught up with mask use among men. These findings stress the importance of behavioral changes in containing future SARS-CoV-2 outbreaks in settings where access to vaccination remains low. They also highlight the need for targeted outreach to members of socioeconomic groups in which the adoption of protective behaviors, such as mask use, might be delayed.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: © 2024 Banda et al. This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Banda</LastName><ForeName>Jethro</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8075-8564</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Malawi Epidemiology and Intervention Research Unit, Lilongwe, Malawi.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dube</LastName><ForeName>Albert N</ForeName><Initials>AN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Malawi Epidemiology and Intervention Research Unit, Lilongwe, Malawi.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Health, Kamuzu University of Health Sciences, Blantyre, Malawi.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Brumfield</LastName><ForeName>Sarah</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4966-5965</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, School of Public Health, Boston University, Boston, Massachusetts, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Crampin</LastName><ForeName>Amelia C</ForeName><Initials>AC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Malawi Epidemiology and Intervention Research Unit, Lilongwe, Malawi.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Population Health, London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Health and Wellbeing, University of Glasgow, Glasgow, Scotland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Reniers</LastName><ForeName>Georges</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6582-1692</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Population Health, London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Amoah</LastName><ForeName>Abena S</ForeName><Initials>AS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Malawi Epidemiology and Intervention Research Unit, Lilongwe, Malawi.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Population Health, London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Helleringer</LastName><ForeName>Stéphane</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5921-9651</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Program in Social Research and Public Policy, Division of Social Science, New York University-Abu Dhabi, Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>PLOS Glob Public Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9918283779606676</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2767-3375</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>54</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39446835</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11500973</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pgph.0003474</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">PGPH-D-23-02229</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Salyer SJ, Maeda J, Sembuche S, Kebede Y, Tshangela A, Moussif M, et al.. The first and second waves of the COVID-19 pandemic in Africa: a cross-sectional study. The Lancet. 2021;397: 1265–1275. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(21)00632-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(21)00632-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8046510</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33773118</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adetifa IMO, Uyoga S, Gitonga JN, Mugo D, Otiende M, Nyagwange J, et al.. Temporal trends of SARS-CoV-2 seroprevalence during the first wave of the COVID-19 epidemic in Kenya. Nat Commun. 2021;12: 3966. doi: 10.1038/s41467-021-24062-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-24062-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8233334</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34172732</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chibwana MG, Jere KC, Kamng’ona R, Mandolo J, Katunga-Phiri V, Tembo D, et al.. High SARS-CoV-2 seroprevalence in health care workers but relatively low numbers of deaths in urban Malawi. Wellcome Open Res. 2020;5: 199. doi: 10.1101/2020.07.30.20164970</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/2020.07.30.20164970</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7402052</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32766597</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mwananyanda L, Gill CJ, MacLeod W, Kwenda G, Pieciak R, Mupila Z, et al.. Covid-19 deaths in Africa: prospective systematic postmortem surveillance study. BMJ. 2021;372: n334. doi: 10.1136/bmj.n334</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.n334</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7887952</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33597166</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olayanju O, Bamidele O, Edem F, Eseile B, Amoo A, Nwaokenye J, et al.. SARS-CoV-2 Seropositivity in Asymptomatic Frontline Health Workers in Ibadan, Nigeria. The American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene. 2021;104: 91–94. doi: 10.4269/ajtmh.20-1235</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.20-1235</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7790104</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33185181</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uyoga S, Adetifa IMO, Karanja HK, Nyagwange J, Tuju J, Wanjiku P, et al.. Seroprevalence of anti-SARS-CoV-2 IgG antibodies in Kenyan blood donors. Science. 2021;371: 79–82. doi: 10.1126/science.abe1916</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.abe1916</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7877494</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33177105</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng C, Barceló J, Hartnett AS, Kubinec R, Messerschmidt L. COVID-19 Government Response Event Dataset (CoronaNet v.1.0). Nat Hum Behav. 2020;4: 756–768. doi: 10.1038/s41562-020-0909-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41562-020-0909-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32576982</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patel P, Adebisi YA, Steven M, Iii DEL-P. Addressing COVID-19 in Malawi. The Pan African Medical Journal. 2020;35. doi: 10.11604/pamj.supp.2020.35.2.23960</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.11604/pamj.supp.2020.35.2.23960</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7875776</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33623595</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hale T, Angrist N, Goldszmidt R, Kira B, Petherick A, Phillips T, et al.. A global panel database of pandemic policies (Oxford COVID-19 Government Response Tracker). Nat Hum Behav. 2021;5: 529–538. doi: 10.1038/s41562-021-01079-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41562-021-01079-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33686204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carlitz RD, Makhura MN. Life under lockdown: Illustrating tradeoffs in South Africa’s response to COVID-19. World Development. 2021;137: 105168. doi: 10.1016/j.worlddev.2020.105168</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.worlddev.2020.105168</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7455114</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32895596</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bottan N, Hoffmann B, Vera-Cossio DA. Stepping up during a crisis: The unintended effects of a noncontributory pension program during the Covid-19 pandemic. Journal of Development Economics. 2021;150: 102635. doi: 10.1016/j.jdeveco.2021.102635</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jdeveco.2021.102635</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9188659</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35721766</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gourlay S, Kilic T, Martuscelli A, Wollburg P, Zezza A. Viewpoint: High-frequency phone surveys on COVID-19: Good practices, open questions. Food Policy. 2021;105: 102153. doi: 10.1016/j.foodpol.2021.102153</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.foodpol.2021.102153</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8405596</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34483442</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hirvonen K, de Brauw A, Abate GT. Food Consumption and Food Security during the COVID-19 Pandemic in Addis Ababa. American Journal of Agricultural Economics. 2021;103: 772–789. doi: 10.1111/ajae.12206</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ajae.12206</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8013419</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33821007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krauss JE, Artur L, Brockington D, Castro E, Fernando J, Fisher J, et al.. ‘To prevent this disease, we have to stay at home, but if we stay at home, we die of hunger’–Livelihoods, vulnerability and coping with Covid-19 in rural Mozambique. World Development. 2022;151: 105757. doi: 10.1016/j.worlddev.2021.105757</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.worlddev.2021.105757</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8612814</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34848914</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahmud M, Riley E. Household response to an extreme shock: Evidence on the immediate impact of the Covid-19 lockdown on economic outcomes and well-being in rural Uganda. World Development. 2021;140: 105318. doi: 10.1016/j.worlddev.2020.105318</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.worlddev.2020.105318</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8446716</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34548741</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Durizzo K, Asiedu E, Van der Merwe A, Van Niekerk A, Günther I. Managing the COVID-19 pandemic in poor urban neighborhoods: The case of Accra and Johannesburg. World Development. 2021;137: 105175. doi: 10.1016/j.worlddev.2020.105175</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.worlddev.2020.105175</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7455159</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32904458</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferree KE, Harris AS, Dulani B, Kao K, Lust E, Metheney E. Stigma, Trust, and procedural integrity: Covid-19 testing in Malawi. World Development. 2021;141: 105351. doi: 10.1016/j.worlddev.2020.105351</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.worlddev.2020.105351</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7803152</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33456104</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hensel L, Witte M, Caria AS, Fetzer T, Fiorin S, Götz FM, et al.. Global Behaviors, Perceptions, and the Emergence of Social Norms at the Onset of the COVID-19 Pandemic. Journal of Economic Behavior &amp; Organization. 2022;193: 473–496. doi: 10.1016/j.jebo.2021.11.015</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jebo.2021.11.015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8684329</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34955573</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kohler IV, Kämpfen F, Ciancio A, Mwera J, Mwapasa V, Kohler H-P. Curtailing Covid-19 on a dollar-a-day in Malawi: Role of community leadership for shaping public health and economic responses to the pandemic. World Development. 2022;151: 105753. doi: 10.1016/j.worlddev.2021.105753</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.worlddev.2021.105753</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8612821</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34848913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harling G, Gómez-Olivé FX, Tlouyamma J, Mutevedzi T, Kabudula CW, Mahlako R, et al.. Protective Behaviors and Secondary Harms Resulting From Nonpharmaceutical Interventions During the COVID-19 Epidemic in South Africa: Multisite, Prospective Longitudinal Study. JMIR Public Health and Surveillance. 2021;7: e26073. doi: 10.2196/26073</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/26073</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8121138</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33827046</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kollamparambil U, Oyenubi A. Behavioural response to the Covid-19 pandemic in South Africa. PLOS ONE. 2021;16: e0250269. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0250269</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0250269</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8051761</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33861811</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCreesh N, Dlamini V, Edwards A, Olivier S, Dayi N, Dikgale K, et al.. Impact of the Covid-19 epidemic and related social distancing regulations on social contact and SARS-CoV-2 transmission potential in rural South Africa: analysis of repeated cross-sectional surveys. BMC Infectious Diseases. 2021;21: 928. doi: 10.1186/s12879-021-06604-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12879-021-06604-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8424154</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34496771</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seror V, Maradan G, Ba E-H, Cortaredona S, Berenger C, L’Haridon O, et al.. COVID-19-related attitudes, risk perceptions, preventive behaviours and economic impact in sub-Saharan African countries: implementing a longitudinal phone-based survey protocol in rural Senegalese households. BMJ Open. 2021;11: e050090. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2021-050090</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2021-050090</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8288240</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34272224</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banda J, Dube A, Brumfield S, Amoah A, Crampin A, Reniers G, et al.. Knowledge, risk perceptions, and behaviors related to the COVID-19 pandemic in Malawi. Demographic Research. 2021;44: 459–480. doi: 10.4054/DemRes.2021.44.20</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4054/DemRes.2021.44.20</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abaluck J, Kwong LH, Styczynski A, Haque A, Kabir MA, Bates-Jefferys E, et al.. Impact of community masking on COVID-19: A cluster-randomized trial in Bangladesh. Science. 2022;375: eabi9069. doi: 10.1126/science.abi9069</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.abi9069</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9036942</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34855513</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tadesse DB, Gebrewahd GT, Demoz GT. Knowledge, attitude, practice and psychological response toward COVID-19 among nurses during the COVID-19 outbreak in northern Ethiopia, 2020. New Microbes and New Infections. 2020;38: 100787. doi: 10.1016/j.nmni.2020.100787</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.nmni.2020.100787</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7556253</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33072339</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quaife M, Zandvoort K, Gimma A, Shah K, McCreesh N, Prem K, et al.. The impact of COVID-19 control measures on social contacts and transmission in Kenyan informal settlements. BMC Medicine. 2020;18: 316. doi: 10.1186/s12916-020-01779-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12916-020-01779-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7533154</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33012285</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asare-Nuamah P, Onumah JA, Dick-Sagoe C, Kessie KO. Perceptions and Coping Strategies to COVID-19 in a Rural Ghanaian Community. In: Faghih N, Forouharfar A, editors. Socioeconomic Dynamics of the COVID-19 Crisis: Global, Regional, and Local Perspectives. Cham: Springer International Publishing; 2022. pp. 403–421.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rogers EM. Diffusion of Innovations, 4th Edition. Simon and Schuster; 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams R. Understanding and interpreting generalized ordered logit models. The Journal of Mathematical Sociology. 2016;40: 7–20. doi: 10.1080/0022250X.2015.1112384</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/0022250X.2015.1112384</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li G, Li W, He X, Cao Y. Asymptomatic and Presymptomatic Infectors: Hidden Sources of Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19). Clinical Infectious Diseases. 2020;71: 2018–2018. doi: 10.1093/cid/ciaa418</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/ciaa418</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7184467</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32271372</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gandhi Rajesh T., Lynch John B., del Rio Carlos. Mild or Moderate Covid-19. New England Journal of Medicine. 2020;383: 1757–1766. doi: 10.1056/NEJMcp2009249</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMcp2009249</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32329974</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berlin David A., Gulick Roy M., Martinez Fernando J. Severe Covid-19. New England Journal of Medicine. 2020;383: 2451–2460. doi: 10.1056/NEJMcp2009575</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMcp2009575</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32412710</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh AK, Gillies CL, Singh R, Singh A, Chudasama Y, Coles B, et al.. Prevalence of co-morbidities and their association with mortality in patients with COVID-19: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Diabetes, Obesity and Metabolism. 2020;22: 1915–1924. doi: 10.1111/dom.14124</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/dom.14124</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7361304</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32573903</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang R, Elhusseiny KM, Yeh Y-C, Sun W-Z. COVID-19 ICU and mechanical ventilation patient characteristics and outcomes—A systematic review and meta-analysis. PLOS ONE. 2021;16: e0246318. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0246318</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0246318</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7877631</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33571301</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coccia M. High potential of technology to face new respiratory viruses: mechanical ventilation devices for effective healthcare to next pandemic emergencies. Technol Soc. 2023;73: 102233. doi: 10.1016/j.techsoc.2023.102233</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.techsoc.2023.102233</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10028215</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36993793</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dietz K. The estimation of the basic reproduction number for infectious diseases. Stat Methods Med Res. 1993;2: 23–41. doi: 10.1177/096228029300200103</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/096228029300200103</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8261248</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anderson RM, May RM. Infectious Diseases of Humans: Dynamics and Control. OUP Oxford; 1992.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bai Y, Yao L, Wei T, Tian F, Jin D-Y, Chen L, et al.. Presumed Asymptomatic Carrier Transmission of COVID-19. JAMA. 2020;323: 1406–1407. doi: 10.1001/jama.2020.2565</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.2565</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7042844</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32083643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siemieniuk RA, Bartoszko JJ, Ge L, Zeraatkar D, Izcovich A, Kum E, et al.. Drug treatments for covid-19: living systematic review and network meta-analysis. BMJ. 2020;370: m2980. doi: 10.1136/bmj.m2980</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.m2980</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7390912</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32732190</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pepperrell T, Ellis L, Wang J, Hill A. Barriers to Worldwide Access for Paxlovid, a New Treatment for COVID-19. Open Forum Infectious Diseases. 2022;9: ofac174. doi: 10.1093/ofid/ofac174</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ofid/ofac174</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9383702</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36176569</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Metcalf CJE, Ferrari M, Graham AL, Grenfell BT. Understanding Herd Immunity. Trends in Immunology. 2015;36: 753–755. doi: 10.1016/j.it.2015.10.004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.it.2015.10.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26683689</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng C, Shao W, Chen X, Zhang B, Wang G, Zhang W. Real-world effectiveness of COVID-19 vaccines: a literature review and meta-analysis. International Journal of Infectious Diseases. 2022;114: 252–260. doi: 10.1016/j.ijid.2021.11.009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2021.11.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8595975</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34800687</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lipsitch M, Kahn R. Interpreting vaccine efficacy trial results for infection and transmission. Vaccine. 2021;39: 4082–4088. doi: 10.1016/j.vaccine.2021.06.011</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2021.06.011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8197448</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34130883</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eyre DW, Taylor D, Purver M, Chapman D, Fowler T, Pouwels KB, et al.. Effect of Covid-19 Vaccination on Transmission of Alpha and Delta Variants. New England Journal of Medicine. 2022;386: 744–756. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa2116597</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2116597</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8757571</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34986294</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polack FP, Thomas SJ, Kitchin N, Absalon J, Gurtman A, Lockhart S, et al.. Safety and Efficacy of the BNT162b2 mRNA Covid-19 Vaccine. New England Journal of Medicine. 2020;383: 2603–2615. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa2034577</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2034577</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7745181</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33301246</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Massinga Loembé M, Nkengasong JN. COVID-19 vaccine access in Africa: Global distribution, vaccine platforms, and challenges ahead. Immunity. 2021;54: 1353–1362. doi: 10.1016/j.immuni.2021.06.017</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2021.06.017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8276532</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34260880</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamey G, Garcia P, Hassan F, Mao W, McDade KK, Pai M, et al.. It is not too late to achieve global covid-19 vaccine equity. BMJ. 2022;376: e070650. doi: 10.1136/bmj-2022-070650</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj-2022-070650</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8943596</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35331982</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ray I. Viewpoint–Handwashing and COVID-19: Simple, right there…? World Development. 2020;135: 105086. doi: 10.1016/j.worlddev.2020.105086</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.worlddev.2020.105086</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7359802</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32834382</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lewnard JA, Lo NC. Scientific and ethical basis for social-distancing interventions against COVID-19. Lancet Infect Dis. 2020;20: 631–633. doi: 10.1016/S1473-3099(20)30190-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(20)30190-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7118670</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32213329</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greenhalgh T, Schmid MB, Czypionka T, Bassler D, Gruer L. Face masks for the public during the covid-19 crisis. BMJ. 2020;369: m1435. doi: 10.1136/bmj.m1435</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.m1435</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32273267</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali N, Islam F. The Effects of Air Pollution on COVID-19 Infection and Mortality—A Review on Recent Evidence. Front Public Health. 2020;8. doi: 10.3389/fpubh.2020.580057</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2020.580057</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7725793</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33324598</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Copat C, Cristaldi A, Fiore M, Grasso A, Zuccarello P, Signorelli SS, et al.. The role of air pollution (PM and NO2) in COVID-19 spread and lethality: A systematic review. Environmental Research. 2020;191: 110129. doi: 10.1016/j.envres.2020.110129</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2020.110129</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7444490</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32853663</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coccia M. The effects of atmospheric stability with low wind speed and of air pollution on the accelerated transmission dynamics of COVID-19. International Journal of Environmental Studies. 2021;78: 1–27. doi: 10.1080/00207233.2020.1802937</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/00207233.2020.1802937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coccia M. How do low wind speeds and high levels of air pollution support the spread of COVID-19? Atmos Pollut Res. 2021;12: 437–445. doi: 10.1016/j.apr.2020.10.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.apr.2020.10.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7541047</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33046960</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coccia M. Sources, diffusion and prediction in COVID-19 pandemic: lessons learned to face next health emergency. AIMS Public Health. 2023;10: 145–168. doi: 10.3934/publichealth.2023012</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3934/publichealth.2023012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10091135</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37063362</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Z, Xue T, Jin X. Effects of meteorological conditions and air pollution on COVID-19 transmission: Evidence from 219 Chinese cities. Science of The Total Environment. 2020;741: 140244. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.140244</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.140244</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7832158</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32592975</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qi H, Xiao S, Shi R, Ward MP, Chen Y, Tu W, et al.. COVID-19 transmission in Mainland China is associated with temperature and humidity: A time-series analysis. Science of The Total Environment. 2020;728: 138778. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.138778</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.138778</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7167225</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32335405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahimi NR, Fouladi-Fard R, Aali R, Shahryari A, Rezaali M, Ghafouri Y, et al.. Bidirectional association between COVID-19 and the environment: A systematic review. Environ Res. 2021;194: 110692. doi: 10.1016/j.envres.2020.110692</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2020.110692</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7833965</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33385384</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akan AP, Coccia M. Transmission of COVID-19 in Cities with Weather Conditions of High Air Humidity: Lessons Learned from Turkish Black Sea Region to Face Next Pandemic Crisis. COVID. 2023;3: 1648–1662. doi: 10.3390/covid3110113</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/covid3110113</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosario DKA, Mutz YS, Bernardes PC, Conte-Junior CA. Relationship between COVID-19 and weather: Case study in a tropical country. Int J Hyg Environ Health. 2020;229: 113587. doi: 10.1016/j.ijheh.2020.113587</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijheh.2020.113587</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7303605</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32917371</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hwang SE, Chang JH, Oh B, Heo J. Possible aerosol transmission of COVID-19 associated with an outbreak in an apartment in Seoul, South Korea, 2020. International Journal of Infectious Diseases. 2021;104: 73–76. doi: 10.1016/j.ijid.2020.12.035</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2020.12.035</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7834623</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33346125</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morawska L, Tang JW, Bahnfleth W, Bluyssen PM, Boerstra A, Buonanno G, et al.. How can airborne transmission of COVID-19 indoors be minimised? Environment International. 2020;142: 105832. doi: 10.1016/j.envint.2020.105832</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2020.105832</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7250761</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32521345</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kadi N, Khelfaoui M. Population density, a factor in the spread of COVID-19 in Algeria: statistic study. Bull Natl Res Cent. 2020;44: 138. doi: 10.1186/s42269-020-00393-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s42269-020-00393-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7439635</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32843835</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sy KTL, White LF, Nichols BE. Population density and basic reproductive number of COVID-19 across United States counties. PLOS ONE. 2021;16: e0249271. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0249271</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0249271</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8059825</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33882054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bontempi E, Coccia M. International trade as critical parameter of COVID-19 spread that outclasses demographic, economic, environmental, and pollution factors. Environ Res. 2021;201: 111514. doi: 10.1016/j.envres.2021.111514</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2021.111514</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8204848</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34139222</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grépin KA, Aston J, Burns J. Effectiveness of international border control measures during the COVID-19 pandemic: a narrative synthesis of published systematic reviews. Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society A: Mathematical, Physical and Engineering Sciences. 2023;381: 20230134. doi: 10.1098/rsta.2023.0134</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1098/rsta.2023.0134</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10446907</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37611627</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hellewell J, Abbott S, Gimma A, Bosse NI, Jarvis CI, Russell TW, et al.. Feasibility of controlling COVID-19 outbreaks by isolation of cases and contacts. The Lancet Global Health. 2020;8: e488–e496. doi: 10.1016/S2214-109X(20)30074-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2214-109X(20)30074-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7097845</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32119825</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benati I, Coccia M. Effective Contact Tracing System Minimizes COVID-19 Related Infections and Deaths: Policy Lessons to Reduce the Impact of Future Pandemic Diseases. Journal of Public Administration and Governance. 2022;12: 19–33. doi: 10.5296/jpag.v12i3.19834</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5296/jpag.v12i3.19834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braithwaite I, Callender T, Bullock M, Aldridge RW. Automated and partly automated contact tracing: a systematic review to inform the control of COVID-19. The Lancet Digital Health. 2020;2: e607–e621. doi: 10.1016/S2589-7500(20)30184-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2589-7500(20)30184-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7438082</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32839755</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Viner RM, Russell SJ, Croker H, Packer J, Ward J, Stansfield C, et al.. School closure and management practices during coronavirus outbreaks including COVID-19: a rapid systematic review. The Lancet Child &amp; Adolescent Health. 2020;4: 397–404. doi: 10.1016/S2352-4642(20)30095-X</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2352-4642(20)30095-X</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7270629</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32272089</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brynjolfsson E, Horton JJ, Ozimek A, Rock D, Sharma G, TuYe H-Y. COVID-19 and Remote Work: An Early Look at US Data. National Bureau of Economic Research; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parker M, MacGregor H, Akello G. COVID-19, Public Authority and Enforcement. Medical Anthropology. 2020;39: 666–670. doi: 10.1080/01459740.2020.1822833</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/01459740.2020.1822833</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7614895</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33026253</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haider N, Osman AY, Gadzekpo A, Akipede GO, Asogun D, Ansumana R, et al.. Lockdown measures in response to COVID-19 in nine sub-Saharan African countries. BMJ Global Health. 2020;5: e003319. doi: 10.1136/bmjgh-2020-003319</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjgh-2020-003319</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7542624</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33028699</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mboera LEG, Akipede GO, Banerjee A, Cuevas LE, Czypionka T, Khan M, et al.. Mitigating lockdown challenges in response to COVID-19 in Sub-Saharan Africa. International Journal of Infectious Diseases. 2020;96: 308–310. doi: 10.1016/j.ijid.2020.05.018</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2020.05.018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7211664</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32437938</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shodunke AO. Enforcement of COVID-19 pandemic lockdown orders in Nigeria: Evidence of public (non)compliance and police illegalities. International Journal of Disaster Risk Reduction. 2022;77: 103082. doi: 10.1016/j.ijdrr.2022.103082</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijdrr.2022.103082</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9172274</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35692959</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sebeelo TB, Mashumba L. Policing the Pandemic: an Investigation of Enforcement Practices During COVID-19 in Botswana. J Police Crim Psych. 2023;38: 1044–1053. doi: 10.1007/s11896-023-09622-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11896-023-09622-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osseni IA. Benin responds to covid-19: sanitary cordon without generalized containment or lockdown? Tropical Medicine and Health. 2020;48: 46. doi: 10.1186/s41182-020-00235-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s41182-020-00235-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7293962</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32547307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garba SM, Lubuma JM-S, Tsanou B. Modeling the transmission dynamics of the COVID-19 Pandemic in South Africa. Mathematical Biosciences. 2020;328: 108441. doi: 10.1016/j.mbs.2020.108441</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.mbs.2020.108441</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7402282</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32763338</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Skrip LA, Fallah MP, Bedson J, Hébert-Dufresne L, Althouse BM. Coordinated support for local action: Modeling strategies to facilitate behavior adoption in urban-poor communities of Liberia for sustained COVID-19 suppression. Epidemics. 2021;37: 100529. doi: 10.1016/j.epidem.2021.100529</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.epidem.2021.100529</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8641945</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34871942</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amodan BO, Bulage L, Katana E, Ario AR, Fodjo JNS, Colebunders R, et al.. Level and Determinants of Adherence to COVID-19 Preventive Measures in the First Stage of the Outbreak in Uganda. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020;17. doi: 10.3390/ijerph17238810</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph17238810</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7734576</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33260900</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ayandele O, Ramos-Vera CA, Iorfa SK, Chovwen CO, Olapegba PO. Exploring the Complex Pathways between the Fear of COVID-19 and Preventive Health Behavior among Nigerians: Mediation and Moderation Analyses. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2021;105: 701–707. doi: 10.4269/ajtmh.20-0994</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.20-0994</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8592328</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34237014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonful HA, Addo-Lartey A, Aheto JMK, Ganle JK, Sarfo B, Aryeetey R. Limiting spread of COVID-19 in Ghana: Compliance audit of selected transportation stations in the Greater Accra region of Ghana. PLOS ONE. 2020;15: e0238971. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0238971</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0238971</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7485755</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32915888</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iloanusi N-JR, Iloanusi S, Mgbere O, Ajayi A, Essien EJ. COVID-19 Related Knowledge, Attitude and Practices in a Southeastern City in Nigeria: A Cross-Sectional Survey. Rochester, NY: Social Science Research Network; 2020 Sep. Report No.: ID 3683766.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nwonwu EU, Ossai EN, Umeokonkwo CD, Ituma IB. Knowledge and preventive practice to COVID-19 among household heads in Enugu metropolis, South-East Nigeria. Pan Afr Med J. 2020;37: 63. doi: 10.11604/pamj.2020.37.63.23986</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.11604/pamj.2020.37.63.23986</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7680221</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33244326</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rawlings NN, Akwah EA, Musisi J, Awanchiri K, Babirye R, Emalieu D, et al.. Perceived risks of COVID-19, attitudes towards preventive guidelines and impact of the lockdown on students in Uganda: A cross-sectional study. PLOS ONE. 2022;17: e0266249. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0266249</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0266249</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8979440</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35377918</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reuben RC, Danladi MMA, Saleh DA, Ejembi PE. Knowledge, Attitudes and Practices Towards COVID-19: An Epidemiological Survey in North-Central Nigeria. J Community Health. 2020. [cited 9 Dec 2020]. doi: 10.1007/s10900-020-00881-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10900-020-00881-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7338341</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32638198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sengeh P, Jalloh MB, Webber N, Ngobeh I, Samba T, Thomas H, et al.. Community knowledge, perceptions and practices around COVID-19 in Sierra Leone: a nationwide, cross-sectional survey. BMJ Open. 2020;10: e040328. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2020-040328</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2020-040328</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7500298</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32948576</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilson JB, Deckert A, Shah R, Kyei N, Dahn LC, Doe-Rogers R, et al.. COVID-19-related knowledge, attitudes and practices: a mixed-mode cross-sectional survey in Liberia. BMJ Open. 2021;11: e049494. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2021-049494</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2021-049494</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8318717</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34315797</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bicalho C, Platas MR, Rosenzweig LR. “If we move, it moves with us:” Physical distancing in Africa during COVID-19. World Development. 2021;142: 105379. doi: 10.1016/j.worlddev.2020.105379</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.worlddev.2020.105379</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9758735</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36568882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kao K, Lust E, Dulani B, Ferree KE, Harris AS, Metheney E. The ABCs of Covid-19 prevention in Malawi: Authority, benefits, and costs of compliance. World Development. 2021;137: 105167. doi: 10.1016/j.worlddev.2020.105167</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.worlddev.2020.105167</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7455236</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32904501</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Odenigbo C, Crighton E. Exploring COVID-19 from the perspectives of healthcare personnel in Malawi. Health Care Science. 2023;2: 242–254. doi: 10.1002/hcs2.58</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/hcs2.58</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11080770</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38939524</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anscombe C, Lissauer S, Thole H, Rylance J, Dula D, Menyere M, et al.. A comparison of four epidemic waves of COVID-19 in Malawi; an observational cohort study. BMC Infectious Diseases. 2023;23: 79. doi: 10.1186/s12879-022-07941-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12879-022-07941-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9902830</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36750921</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akalu Y, Ayelign B, Molla MD. Knowledge, Attitude and Practice Towards COVID-19 Among Chronic Disease Patients at Addis Zemen Hospital, Northwest Ethiopia. Infect Drug Resist. 2020;13: 1949–1960. doi: 10.2147/IDR.S258736</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/IDR.S258736</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7322118</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32612371</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qanche Q, Asefa A, Nigussie T, Hailemariam S, Duguma T. Knowledge of COVID-19 and preventive behaviors among waiters working in food and drinking establishments in Southwest Ethiopia. PLOS ONE. 2021;16: e0245753. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0245753</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0245753</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7833477</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33493226</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nicholas T, Mandaah FV, Esemu SN, Vanessa ABT, Gilchrist KTD, Vanessa LF, et al.. COVID-19 knowledge, attitudes and practices in a conflict affected area of the South West Region of Cameroon. Pan Afr Med J. 2020;35: 34. doi: 10.11604/pamj.supp.2020.35.2.22963</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.11604/pamj.supp.2020.35.2.22963</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7875723</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33623559</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azene ZN, Merid MW, Muluneh AG, Geberu DM, Kassa GM, Yenit MK, et al.. Adherence towards COVID-19 mitigation measures and its associated factors among Gondar City residents: A community-based cross-sectional study in Northwest Ethiopia. PLOS ONE. 2020;15: e0244265. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0244265</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0244265</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7773181</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33378332</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kassa AM, Mekonen AM, Yesuf KA, Tadesse AW, Bogale GG. Knowledge level and factors influencing prevention of COVID-19 pandemic among residents of Dessie and Kombolcha City administrations, North-East Ethiopia: a population-based cross-sectional study. BMJ Open. 2020;10: e044202. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2020-044202</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2020-044202</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7668362</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33191269</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tshotetsi L, Hajison P, Jella CD, Mpachika-Mfipa F, Chimatiro CS. Knowledge, practices and adherence to COVID-19 preventive measures by community members in the Phalombe District Malawi: a cross-sectional qualitative study. Glob Health Promot. 2023; 17579759231204353. doi: 10.1177/17579759231204353</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/17579759231204353</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38063073</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chawinga W, Singini W, Phuka J, Chimbatata N, Mitambo C, Sambani C, et al.. Combating coronavirus disease (COVID-19) in rural areas of Malawi: Factors affecting the fight. Afr J Prim Health Care Fam Med. 2023;15: 3464. doi: 10.4102/phcfm.v15i1.3464</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4102/phcfm.v15i1.3464</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9900245</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36744457</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Statistical Office. 2018 Malawi Population and Housing Census. Zomba, Malawi; 2019. http://www.nsomalawi.mw/index.php%3Foption%3Dcom_content%26view%3Darticle%26id%3D226:2018-malawi-population-and-housing-census%26catid%E2%80%89%3D%E2%80%898:reports%26Itemid%E2%80%89%3D%E2%80%896</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>United Nations. World population prospects Volume 1, Volume 1,. 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chihana M, Floyd S, Molesworth A, Crampin AC, Kayuni N, Price A, et al.. Adult mortality and probable cause of death in rural northern Malawi in the era of HIV treatment. Trop Med Int Health. 2012;17: e74–83. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-3156.2012.02929.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3156.2012.02929.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3443368</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22943382</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Floyd S, Molesworth A, Dube A, Banda E, Jahn A, Mwafulirwa C, et al.. Population-level reduction in adult mortality after extension of free anti-retroviral therapy provision into rural areas in northern Malawi. PLoS ONE. 2010;5: e13499. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0013499</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0013499</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2957442</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20976068</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kanyuka M, Ndawala J, Mleme T, Chisesa L, Makwemba M, Amouzou A, et al.. Malawi and Millennium Development Goal 4: a Countdown to 2015 country case study. The Lancet Global Health. 2016;4: e201–e214. doi: 10.1016/S2214-109X(15)00294-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2214-109X(15)00294-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26805586</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chilunga FP, Musicha C, Tafatatha T, Geis S, Nyirenda MJ, Crampin AC, et al.. Investigating associations between rural-to-urban migration and cardiometabolic disease in Malawi: a population-level study. Int J Epidemiol. 2019. doi: 10.1093/ije/dyz198</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ije/dyz198</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6929524</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31603469</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cabore JW, Karamagi HC, Kipruto H, Asamani JA, Droti B, Seydi ABW, et al.. The potential effects of widespread community transmission of SARS-CoV-2 infection in the World Health Organization African Region: a predictive model. BMJ Global Health. 2020;5: e002647. doi: 10.1136/bmjgh-2020-002647</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjgh-2020-002647</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7252960</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32451366</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Public Health Institute of Malawi. National COVID-19 Preparedness and Response Plan. Lilongwe, Malawi: Public Health Institute of Malawi; 2020. https://malawipublichealth.org/index.php/resources/COVID-19%20National%20Preparedness%20and%20Response%20Plan/National-COVID-19-Preparedness-and-Response-Plan_Version1_April%202020%201.pdf/detail</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chirwa GC, Dulani B, Sithole L, Chunga JJ, Alfonso W, Tengatenga J. Malawi at the Crossroads: Does the Fear of Contracting COVID-19 Affect the Propensity to Vote? Eur J Dev Res. 2021. [cited 11 Feb 2021]. doi: 10.1057/s41287-020-00353-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1057/s41287-020-00353-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7781184</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33424140</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brumfield S, Dube A, Reniers G, Helleringer S. Comparing Approaches to Collecting Self-Reported Data on HIV Status in Population-Based Surveys. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr. 2020;85: e55–e57. doi: 10.1097/QAI.0000000000002441</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/QAI.0000000000002441</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32658128</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crampin AC, Dube A, Mboma S, Price A, Chihana M, Jahn A, et al.. Profile: the Karonga Health and Demographic Surveillance System. Int J Epidemiol. 2012;41: 676–685. doi: 10.1093/ije/dys088</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ije/dys088</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3396313</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22729235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jahn A, Branson K, Crampin A, Fine PE, Glynn JR, McGrath N, et al.. Evaluation of a village-informant driven demographic surveillance system in Karonga, Northern Malawi. Demographic Research. 2007;16: 219–248. doi: 10.4054/DemRes.2007.16.8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4054/DemRes.2007.16.8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hensen B, Mackworth-Young CRS, Simwinga M, Abdelmagid N, Banda J, Mavodza C, et al.. Remote data collection for public health research in a COVID-19 era: ethical implications, challenges and opportunities. Health Policy Plan. 2021;36: 360–368. doi: 10.1093/heapol/czaa158</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/heapol/czaa158</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7928874</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33881138</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lienhardt C, Fielding K, Sillah J, Tunkara A, Donkor S, Manneh K, et al.. Risk Factors for Tuberculosis Infection in Sub-Saharan Africa. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2003;168: 448–455. doi: 10.1164/rccm.200212-1483OC</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1164/rccm.200212-1483OC</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12773322</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pelissari DM, Diaz-Quijano FA. Household crowding as a potential mediator of socioeconomic determinants of tuberculosis incidence in Brazil. PLOS ONE. 2017;12: e0176116. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0176116</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0176116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5395230</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28419146</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Atchison, Bowman L, Vrinten C, Redd R, Pristera P, Eaton JW, et al.. Perceptions and behavioural responses of the general public during the COVID-19 pandemic: A cross-sectional survey of UK Adults. Public and Global Health; 2020. Apr. doi: 10.1101/2020.04.01.20050039</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/2020.04.01.20050039</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7783373</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33397669</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Long JS. Regression models for categorical and limited dependent variables. Thousand Oaks, CA, US: Sage Publications, Inc; 1997. pp. xxx, 297.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams R. Generalized Ordered Logit/Partial Proportional Odds Models for Ordinal Dependent Variables. The Stata Journal. 2006;6: 58–82. doi: 10.1177/1536867X0600600104</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1536867X0600600104</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Egger D, Miguel E, Warren SS, Shenoy A, Collins E, Karlan D, et al.. Falling living standards during the COVID-19 crisis: Quantitative evidence from nine developing countries. Science Advances. 2021;7: eabe0997. doi: 10.1126/sciadv.abe0997</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/sciadv.abe0997</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7864564</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33547077</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kwon S, Joshi AD, Lo C-H, Drew DA, Nguyen LH, Guo C-G, et al.. Association of social distancing and face mask use with risk of COVID-19. Nat Commun. 2021;12: 3737. doi: 10.1038/s41467-021-24115-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-24115-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8213701</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34145289</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nanque LM, Jensen AM, Diness A, Nielsen S, Cabral C, Cawthorne D, et al.. Effect of distributing locally produced cloth facemasks on COVID-19-like illness and all-cause mortality–a cluster-randomised controlled trial in urban Guinea-Bissau. PLOS Global Public Health. 2024;4: e0002901. doi: 10.1371/journal.pgph.0002901</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pgph.0002901</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10863890</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38349910</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wenham C, Smith J, Morgan R. COVID-19: the gendered impacts of the outbreak. The Lancet. 2020;395: 846–848. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30526-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30526-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7124625</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32151325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jakubowski A, Egger D, Nekesa C, Lowe L, Walker M, Miguel E. Self-reported vs Directly Observed Face Mask Use in Kenya. JAMA Network Open. 2021;4: e2118830. doi: 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.18830</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.18830</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8325070</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34328505</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barden-O’Fallon JL, deGraft-Johnson J, Bisika T, Sulzbach S, Benson A, Tsui AO. Factors Associated with HIV/AIDS Knowledge and Risk Perception in Rural Malawi. AIDS Behav. 2004;8: 131–140. doi: 10.1023/B:AIBE.0000030244.92791.63</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1023/B:AIBE.0000030244.92791.63</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15187475</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Helleringer S, Kohler H-P. Social networks, perceptions of risk, and changing attitudes towards HIV/AIDS: new evidence from a longitudinal study using fixed-effects analysis. Popul Stud (Camb). 2005;59: 265–282. doi: 10.1080/00324720500212230</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/00324720500212230</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16249149</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>