<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39443979</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1753-2000</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>18</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Child and adolescent psychiatry and mental health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Child Adolesc Psychiatry Ment Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Development will (try to) find its way: a qualitative study of Chilean adolescent mental health during and after lockdown.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>136</StartPage><MedlinePgn>136</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">136</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s13034-024-00808-x</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The COVID-19 pandemic has had a well-evidenced impact on adolescents, who are especially sensitive to pandemic disruptions given the critical role of socialization in their development. In Chile too, evidence shows increases in mental health complaints among adolescents over the lockdown period. Our study aimed at exploring the experiences of Chilean adolescents regarding their mental health during the lockdown and school closure (March 2020-December 2021), and during the return to on-site education (2022) as informed by adolescents and school staff, with a focus on family, school, and social sources of risk and support for adolescents' wellbeing during these periods.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Using a qualitative approach, we conducted semi-structured interviews with 19 adolescents and 16 staff members from schools in an urban area of Chile.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Through thematic analysis, we generated five themes: [1] Adolescents in a mental health crisis, comprising a range of distressing experiences and mental health problems. This crisis was fueled by alterations in the functioning of adolescents' systems: [2] Broken support systems (peers and school); [3] The school agenda must go on, reflecting schools' strict compliance with the educational curriculum; and [4] Blurred boundaries between home and school life and within the family. Finally [5], Development will (try to) find its way describes how most participants experienced a bouncing back to wellbeing in the course of the school year upon return, and how some developmental milestones took place despite the abnormal conditions, providing evidence for resilience amid pandemic adversity.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The findings give insight into how the exchanges between the adolescent and the social systems they are embedded in were interfered. The results help us understand the challenges for mental health during and after the pandemic, and highlight adolescents' capacity to thrive as normality was restored. The results also underscore the importance of upholding stability across adolescents' systems and routines, in order to mitigate impacts on wellbeing amid abnormal circumstances. The findings are relevant for development-informed initiatives in policy design in the aftermath of the pandemic and in future crisis management responses.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Espinoza</LastName><ForeName>Camila</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Education and Child Studies, Faculty of Social and Behavioral Sciences, Leiden University, Wassenaarseweg 52, Leiden, The Netherlands. c.p.espinoza.chaparro@fsw.leidenuniv.nl.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Canessa</LastName><ForeName>Florencia</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Education and Child Studies, Faculty of Social and Behavioral Sciences, Leiden University, Wassenaarseweg 52, Leiden, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Psychology, Faculty of Social and Behavioral Sciences, Leiden University, Wassenaarseweg 52, Leiden, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>van der Veek</LastName><ForeName>Shelley</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Education and Child Studies, Faculty of Social and Behavioral Sciences, Leiden University, Wassenaarseweg 52, Leiden, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alink</LastName><ForeName>Lenneke</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Education and Child Studies, Faculty of Social and Behavioral Sciences, Leiden University, Wassenaarseweg 52, Leiden, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>van der Voort</LastName><ForeName>Anja</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Education and Child Studies, Faculty of Social and Behavioral Sciences, Leiden University, Wassenaarseweg 52, Leiden, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>72200400</GrantID><Agency>Agencia Nacional de Investigación y Desarrollo</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>W222161-5-1</GrantID><Agency>Leiden University Fund (LUF)</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Child Adolesc Psychiatry Ment Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101297974</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1753-2000</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescent</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Chile</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Coronavirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Lockdown</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mental health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Qualitative</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">School closure</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Wellbeing</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39443979</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13034-024-00808-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s13034-024-00808-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11515594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Bower M, Smout S, Donohoe-Bales A, O’Dean S, Teesson L, Boyle J, et al. A hidden pandemic? An umbrella review of global evidence on mental health in the time of COVID-19. Front Psychiatry. 2023;14:1107560.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10032377</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36970258</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aknin LB, Andretti B, Goldszmidt R, Helliwell JF, Petherick A, De Neve JE, et al. Policy stringency and mental health during the COVID-19 pandemic: a longitudinal analysis of data from 15 countries. Lancet Public Health. 2022;7(5):e417–26.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9023007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35461592</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barendse MEA, Flannery J, Cavanagh C, Aristizabal M, Becker SP, Berger E, et al. Longitudinal change in adolescent depression and anxiety symptoms from before to during the COVID -19 pandemic. J Res Adolesc. 2023;33(1):74–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9349954</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35799311</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Botha F, Morris RW, Butterworth P, Glozier N. Trajectories of psychological distress over multiple COVID-19 lockdowns in Australia. SSM - Popul Health. 2023;21:101315.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9742066</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36530365</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kessler RC, Petukhova M, Sampson NA, Zaslavsky AM, Wittchen H. Twelve-month and lifetime prevalence and lifetime morbid risk of anxiety and mood disorders in the United States. Int J Methods Psychiatr Res. 2012;21(3):169–84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4005415</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22865617</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Green KH, Van De Groep S, Sweijen SW, Becht AI, Buijzen M, De Leeuw RNH, et al. Mood and emotional reactivity of adolescents during the COVID-19 pandemic: short-term and long-term effects and the impact of social and socioeconomic stressors. Sci Rep. 2021;11(1):11563.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8172919</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34078968</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gotlib IH, Miller JG, Borchers LR, Coury SM, Costello LA, Garcia JM, et al. Effects of the COVID-19 pandemic on Mental Health and Brain Maturation in adolescents: implications for analyzing Longitudinal Data. Biol Psychiatry Glob Open Sci. 2023;3(4):912–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Drunen L, Toenders YJ, Wierenga LM, Crone EA. Effects of COVID-19 pandemic on structural brain development in early adolescence. Sci Rep. 2023;13(1):5600.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10075168</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37019914</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Harmelen AL, Kievit RA, Ioannidis K, Neufeld S, Jones PB, Bullmore E, et al. Adolescent friendships predict later resilient functioning across psychosocial domains in a healthy community cohort. Psychol Med. 2017;47(13):2312–22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5820532</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28397612</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nelson EE, Jarcho JM, Guyer AE. Social re-orientation and brain development: an expanded and updated view. Dev Cogn Neurosci. 2016;17:118–27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6990069</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26777136</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Towner E, Chierchia G, Blakemore SJ. Sensitivity and specificity in affective and social learning in adolescence. Trends Cogn Sci. 2023;27(7):642–55.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37198089</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sahi RS, Eisenberger NI, Silvers JA. Peer facilitation of emotion regulation in adolescence. Dev Cogn Neurosci. 2023;62:101262.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10276262</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37302349</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pfeifer JH, Berkman ET. The development of self and identity in adolescence: neural evidence and implications for a value-based choice perspective on motivated behavior. Child Dev Perspect. 2018;12(3):158–64.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6667174</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31363361</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raccanello D, Rocca E, Vicentini G, Brondino M. Eighteen months of COVID-19 pandemic through the lenses of self or others: a Meta-analysis on children and adolescents’ Mental Health. Child Youth Care Forum. 2023;52(4):737–60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9421638</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36059590</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kauhanen L, Wan Mohd Yunus WMA, Lempinen L, Peltonen K, Gyllenberg D, Mishina K, et al. A systematic review of the mental health changes of children and young people before and during the COVID-19 pandemic. Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2023;32(6):995–1013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9373888</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35962147</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orban E, Li LY, Gilbert M, Napp AK, Kaman A, Topf S, et al. Mental health and quality of life in children and adolescents during the COVID-19 pandemic: a systematic review of longitudinal studies. Front Public Health. 2024;11:1275917.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10800626</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38259801</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferro V, Averna R, Murciano M, Raucci U, Cristaldi S, Musolino AMC, et al. Has anything changed in the frequency of emergency department visits and the profile of the adolescent seeking emergency mental care during the COVID-19 pandemic? Children. 2023;10(3):578.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10047842</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36980136</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bera L, Souchon M, Ladsous A, Colin V, Lopez-Castroman J. Emotional and behavioral impact of the COVID-19 epidemic in adolescents. Curr Psychiatry Rep. 2022;24(1):37–46.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8803571</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35102536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosen ML, Rodman AM, Kasparek SW, Mayes M, Freeman MM, Lengua LJ, et al. Promoting youth mental health during the COVID-19 pandemic: a longitudinal study. PLOS ONE. 2021;16(8):e0255294.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8357139</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34379656</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pfefferbaum B. Challenges for child mental health raised by school closure and home confinement during the COVID-19 pandemic. Curr Psychiatry Rep. 2021;23(10):65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8366164</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34398310</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scheiner C, Seis C, Kleindienst N, Buerger A, Psychopathology. Protective factors, and COVID-19 among adolescents: a structural equation Model. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2023;20(3):2493.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9915090</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36767859</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Montreuil M, Camden C, Genest C, Gilbert E, Laberge-Perrault E, Piché G, et al. Children and adolescents’ mental health in pandemics and confinement: a scoping review of vulnerability factors and repercussions. J Child Health Care. 2023;136749352311655.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Magson NR, Freeman JYA, Rapee RM, Richardson CE, Oar EL, Fardouly J. Risk and protective factors for prospective changes in adolescent mental health during the COVID-19 pandemic. J Youth Adolesc. 2021;50(1):44–57.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7590912</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33108542</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benítez MA, Velasco C, Sequeira AR, Henríquez J, Menezes FM, Paolucci F. Responses to COVID-19 in five Latin American countries. Health Policy Technol. 2020;9(4):525–59.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7451099</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32874863</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garrido Contreras MD. Educar en tiempos de pandemia: acentuación de las desigualdades en El sistema educativo chileno. CAMINHOS Educ Diálogos Cult E Divers. 2020;2(2):43–68.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bellei C, Contreras M, Ponce T, Yañez I, Díaz R, Vielma C. The fragility of the school-in-pandemic in Chile. In: Reimers FM (eds) Primary and secondary education during COVID-19. Cham: Springer International Publishing; 2022. pp 79–103. https://link.springer.com/10.1007/978-3-030-81500-4_3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuzmanic D, Valenzuela JP, Claro S, Canales A, Cerda D, Undurraga EA. Socioeconomic disparities in the reopening of schools during the pandemic in Chile. Int J Educ Dev. 2023;100:102805.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10199314</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37235200</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Education of Chile. Lineamientos para el año escolar 2022 [Guidelines for the school year 2022] [Internet]. 2021. https://bibliotecadigital.mineduc.cl/bitstream/handle/20.500.12365/18476/LINEAMIENTOS2022.pdf?sequence=1&amp;isAllowed=y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>OECD, Education at a. Glance 2022: OECD Indicators [Internet]. OECD; 2022 [cited 2024 Jul 17]. (Education at a Glance). https://www.oecd-ilibrary.org/education/education-at-a-glance-2022_3197152b-en</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bellei C, Contreras M. Post-pandemic crisis in Chilean education: The challenge of re-institutionalizing school education. In: Reimers FM (eds) Schools and society during the COVID-19 pandemic [Internet]. Cham: Springer Nature Switzerland; 2024 [cited 2024 Mar 4]. pp 43–62. https://link.springer.com/10.1007/978-3-031-42671-1_3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caqueo-Urízar A, Mena-Chamorro P, Henríquez D, Urzúa A, Irarrázaval M. The effects of social determinants and resilience on the mental health of Chilean adolescents. Children. 2023;10(7):1213.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10378294</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37508710</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mena GE, Martinez PP, Mahmud AS, Marquet PA, Buckee CO, Santillana M. Socioeconomic status determines COVID-19 incidence and related mortality in Santiago, Chile. Science. 2021;372(6545):eabg5298.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8158961</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33906968</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vicente B, Saldivia S, De La Barra F, Melipillán R, Valdivia M, Kohn R. Salud mental infanto-juvenil en Chile Y brechas de atención sanitarias. Rev Médica Chile. 2012;140(4):447–57.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caqueo-Urízar A, Flores J, Escobar C, Urzúa A, Irarrázaval M. Psychiatric disorders in children and adolescents in a middle-income Latin American country. BMC Psychiatry. 2020;20(1):104.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7059272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32138703</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caqueo-Urízar A, Atencio-Quevedo D, Ponce-Correa F, Mena-Chamorro P, Urzúa A, Flores J. Pre and post pandemic depressive and anxious symptoms in children and adolescents in Northern Chile. J Clin Med. 2023;12(4):1601.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9964894</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36836135</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tamarit A, Schoeps K, Del Rosario C, Amador Esparza NA, Montoya-Castilla I. Estado de salud en adolescentes de España, México y Chile durante la COVID-19: un estudio transcultural. Acción Psicológica [Internet]. 2021;18(1). http://revistas.uned.es/index.php/accionpsicologica/article/view/29018</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schoeps K, Tamarit A, De La Barrera U, Lacomba-Trejo L, Montoya-Castilla I, Del Rosario C, et al. Social and Psychological effects of COVID-19 pandemic on adolescents’ and young adults’ mental health: a cross-cultural mediation study. Psychol Rep. 2023;126(6):2729–56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9098395</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35531784</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang Y, Sun L, Tan X. Mental health research during the COVID-19 pandemic: focuses and trends. Front Public Health. 2022;10:895121.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9360762</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35958839</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang SX, Chen J. Scientific evidence on mental health in key regions under the COVID-19 pandemic: meta-analytical evidence from Africa, Asia, China, Eastern Europe, Latin America, South Asia, Southeast Asia, and Spain. Eur J Psychotraumatol. 2021;12(1):2001192.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8654399</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34900123</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang SX, Batra K, Xu W, Liu T, Dong RK, Yin A, et al. Mental disorder symptoms during the COVID-19 pandemic in Latin America– a systematic review and meta-analysis. Epidemiol Psychiatr Sci. 2022;31:e23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9069590</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35438066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashworth E, Hunt A, Chopra J, Eames C, Putwain DW, Duffy K, et al. Adolescents’ lockdown-induced coping experiences (ALICE) study: a qualitative exploration of early adolescents’ experiences of lockdown and reintegration. J Early Adolesc. 2022;42(4):514–41.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Sullivan K, Clark S, McGrane A, Rock N, Burke L, Boyle N, et al. A qualitative study of child and adolescent mental health during the COVID-19 pandemic in Ireland. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18(3):1062.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7908364</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33504101</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McKinlay AR, May T, Dawes J, Fancourt D, Burton A. You’re just there, alone in your room with your thoughts’: a qualitative study about the psychosocial impact of the COVID-19 pandemic among young people living in the UK. BMJ Open. 2022;12(2):e053676.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8829834</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35140155</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tong A, Sainsbury P, Craig J. Consolidated criteria for reporting qualitative research (COREQ): a 32-item checklist for interviews and focus groups. Int J Qual Health Care. 2007;19(6):349–57.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17872937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fryer T. A critical realist approach to thematic analysis: producing causal explanations. J Crit Realism. 2022;21(4):365–84.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braun V, Clarke V. Using thematic analysis in psychology. Qual Res Psychol. 2006;3(2):77–101.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hennink MM, Hutter I, Bailey A. Qualitative research methods, second edition. Los Angeles: SAGE; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ATLAS.ti Scientific Software Development Gmb. Atlas.ti [Internet]. 2023. Available from: https://atlasti.com.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Panchal U, Salazar De Pablo G, Franco M, Moreno C, Parellada M, Arango C, et al. The impact of COVID-19 lockdown on child and adolescent mental health: systematic review. Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2023;32(7):1151–77.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8371430</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34406494</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spiekerman AM, Guo Y, Payton J, Campione-Barr N, Killoren SE, Rote WM, et al. Adolescents’ online connections with friends during COVID-19: an assessment of the forms of communication and their association with emotional adjustment. Children. 2023;10(8):1281.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10453441</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37628280</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marciano L, Ostroumova M, Schulz PJ, Camerini AL. Digital media use and adolescents’ mental health during the COVID-19 pandemic: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Front Public Health. 2022;9:793868.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8848548</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35186872</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pandya A, Lodha P. Social connectedness, excessive screen time during COVID-19 and Mental Health: a review of current evidence. Front Hum Dyn. 2021;3:684137.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamilton JL, Dreier MJ, Boyd SI. Social media as a bridge and a window: the changing relationship of adolescents with social media and digital platforms. Curr Opin Psychol. 2023;52:101633.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10526977</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37454640</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Butler N, Quigg Z, Bates R, Jones L, Ashworth E, Gowland S, et al. The contributing role of family, school, and peer supportive relationships in protecting the mental wellbeing of children and adolescents. School Ment Health. 2022;14(3):776–88.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8818094</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35154501</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gelber D, Castillo C, Alarcón L, Treviño E, Escribano R. COVID-19 and the right to education in Chile: an opportunity to revisit our social contract. Int Rev Educ. 2021;67(1–2):79–101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7898249</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33642612</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yates A, Starkey L, Egerton B, Flueggen F. High school students’ experience of online learning during COVID-19: the influence of technology and pedagogy. Technol Pedagog Educ. 2021;30(1):59–73.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bagnall CL, Skipper Y, Fox CL. Primary-secondary school transition under COVID‐19: exploring the perceptions and experiences of children, parents/guardians, and teachers. Br J Educ Psychol. 2022;92(3):1011–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9111429</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35132610</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferguson S, Brass NR, Medina MA, Ryan AM. The role of school friendship stability, instability, and network size in early adolescents’ social adjustment. Dev Psychol. 2022;58(5):950–62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35311307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramirez S, Aldunate MP, Arriagada C, Bueno M, Cuevas F, González X, et al. Brief research report: the association between educational experiences and COVID-19 pandemic-related variables, and mental health among children and adolescents. Front Psychiatry. 2021;12:647456.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8116561</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33995147</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frankel L, Sampige R. Supporting families: lessons learned from the COVID-19 pandemic. Hum Dev. 2022;66(3):163–6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruiz-Tagle J, Urria I. Household overcrowding trajectories and mental well-being. Soc Sci Med. 2022;296:114051.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35131615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duarte F, Jiménez-Molina Á. A longitudinal nationwide study of psychological distress during the COVID-19 pandemic in Chile. Front Psychiatry. 2022;13:744204.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8907540</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35280180</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orben A, Tomova L, Blakemore SJ. The effects of social deprivation on adolescent development and mental health. 2020;4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Witt A, Sachser C, Fegert JM. Scoping review on trauma and recovery in youth after natural disasters: what Europe can learn from natural disasters around the world. Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2024;33(3):651–65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10894166</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35426528</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schäfer SK, Kunzler AM, Kalisch R, Tüscher O, Lieb K. Trajectories of resilience and mental distress to global major disruptions. Trends Cogn Sci. 2022;26(12):1171–89.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9595401</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36302711</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCrory E, Foulkes L, Viding E. Social thinning and stress generation after childhood maltreatment: a neurocognitive social transactional model of psychiatric vulnerability. Lancet Psychiatry. 2022;9(10):828–37.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35926524</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caqueo-Urízar A, Urzúa A, Aragón-Caqueo D, Charles CH, El-Khatib Z, Otu A, et al. Mental health and the COVID-19 pandemic in Chile. Psychol Trauma Theory Res Pract Policy. 2020;12(5):521–3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reuben A, Moffitt TE, Caspi A, Belsky DW, Harrington H, Schroeder F, et al. Lest we forget: comparing retrospective and prospective assessments of adverse childhood experiences in the prediction of adult health. J Child Psychol Psychiatry. 2016;57(10):1103–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5234278</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27647050</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bronfenbrenner U. The ecology of human development: experiments by nature and design. Cambridge, Mass: Harvard University Press; 1996. p. 330.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Masten A, Barnes A. Resilience in children: developmental perspectives. Children. 2018;5(7):98.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6069421</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30018217</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fegert JM, Ludwig-Walz H, Witt A, Bujard M. Children’s rights and restrictive measures during the COVID-19 pandemic: implications for politicians, mental health experts and society. Child Adolesc Psychiatry Ment Health. 2023;17(1):75. s13034-023-00617–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10286328</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37344880</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Irarrazaval M, Norambuena P, Montenegro C, Toro-Devia O, Vargas B, Caqueo-Urízar A. Public policy responses to address the mental health consequences of the COVID-19 pandemic: evidence from Chile. Front Public Health. 2021;9:590335.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8511669</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34660500</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>