<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39449011</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1472-6920</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>24</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC medical education</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Med Educ</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Prevalence of Dunning-Kruger effect in first semester medical students: a correlational study of self-assessment and actual academic performance.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1210</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1210</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1210</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12909-024-06121-7</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The ability to self-assess is a crucial skill in identifying one's own strengths and weaknesses and in coordinating self-directed learning. The Dunning-Kruger effect occurs when limited knowledge causes individuals to overestimate their competence and underestimate others', leading to poor self-assessment and unrecognized incompetence. To serve as a foundation for developing strategies to improve self-assessment, the self-assessment abilities of first-semester students were assessed.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">In the final weeks of the summer 2021, winter 2021/22, and summer 2022 semesters, the academic performance (oral anatomy exam) of first semester students was assessed (0-15 points). Before the exam results were announced, students were asked to self-assess their performance.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Exam scores (M = 10.64, SD = 2.95) and self-assessed scores (M = 10.38, SD = 2.54) were comparable. The absolute difference between them, as a measure of self-assessment ability ranged from - 9 to + 9 points (M = -0.26, SD = 2.59). Among participants (N = 426), 18.5% assessed themselves accurately, 35.5% overestimated, and 46.0% underestimated their performance. The correlation between actual score and self-assessment was ρ = -0.590 (p &lt; 0.001), reflecting the Dunning-Kruger effect. When separated by gender, correlation for females was ρ = -0.591 (p &lt; 0.001), and for males ρ = -0.580 (p &lt; 0.001).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Realistic self-assessment is a challenge for first-semester students. The data indicate that females tend to overestimate their performance while males underestimate theirs. A pronounced Dunning-Kruger effect is evident in both genders, with significant negative correlations between self-assessment and actual performance. There are several reasons for the occurrence of the Dunning-Kruger effect. Considering that the COVID-19 pandemic influenced learning environments, collaborative learning was significantly restricted. The lack of opportunities for comparison could potentially lead to unrealistic self-assessment.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Knof</LastName><ForeName>Harald</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0942-653X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Anatomy, Institute of Clinical Anatomy and Cell Analysis, Faculty of Medicine, Eberhard Karls University of Tuebingen, Elfriede-Aulhorn- Straße 8, 72076, Tuebingen, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Berndt</LastName><ForeName>Markus</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4467-5355</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Medical Education, LMU University Hospital, LMU Munich, Pettenkoferstraße 8a, 80336, Munich, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shiozawa</LastName><ForeName>Thomas</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7112-1016</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Anatomy, Institute of Clinical Anatomy and Cell Analysis, Faculty of Medicine, Eberhard Karls University of Tuebingen, Elfriede-Aulhorn- Straße 8, 72076, Tuebingen, Germany. thomas.shiozawa@uni-tuebingen.de.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Med Educ</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101088679</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1472-6920</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012647" MajorTopicYN="Y">Self-Assessment</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000073978" MajorTopicYN="Y">Academic Performance</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013337" MajorTopicYN="Y">Students, Medical</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004504" MajorTopicYN="Y">Education, Medical, Undergraduate</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004521" MajorTopicYN="N">Educational Measurement</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055815" MajorTopicYN="N">Young Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Dunning-Kruger effect</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Educational Measurement</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Health professions education</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Medical education</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Medical student</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Self-assessment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Self-regulation</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>6</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39449011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12909-024-06121-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12909-024-06121-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11515314</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Tang Z, Shikama Y, Otani K. Comparison of student self-assessment and teacher assessment of medical interview performance during bedside learning. Fukushima J Med Sci. 2023;69(1):21–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10122972</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36990787</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evans AW, McKenna C, Oliver M. Self-assessment in medical practice. J R Soc Med. 2002;95(10):511–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1279183</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12356978</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antonelli MA. Accuracy of second-year medical students’ self-assessment of clinical skills. Acad Med. 1997;72(10 Suppl 1):S63–65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9347742</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fitzgerald JT, Gruppen LD, White CB. The influence of task formats on the accuracy of medical students’ self-assessments. Acad Med. 2000;75(7):737–41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10926026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arnold L, Willoughby TL, Calkins EV. Self-evaluation in undergraduate medical education: a longitudinal perspective. J Med Educ. 1985;60(1):21–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3965720</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gordon MJ. A review of the validity and accuracy of self-assessments in health professions training. Acad Med. 1991;66(12):762–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1750956</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boud D. Avoiding the traps: seeking good practice in the use of self assessment and reflection in professional courses. Social Work Educ. 1999;18(2):121–32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eva KW, Regehr G. Self-assessment in the health professions: a reformulation and research agenda. Acad Med. 2005;80(10 Suppl):S46–54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16199457</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bussenius L, Harendza S. Development of an instrument for medical students’ self-assessment of facets of competence for patient-centred care. Patient Educ Couns. 2023;115:107926.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37536112</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blanch-Hartigan D. Medical students’ self-assessment of performance: results from three meta-analyses. Patient Educ Couns. 2011;84(1):3–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20708898</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lindsey BA, Nagel ML. Do students know what they know? Exploring the accuracy of students’ self-assessments. Phys Rev Spec Top Phys Educ Res 2015, 11(2).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahmani M. Medical trainees and the Dunning-Kruger Effect: when they don’t know what they don’t know. J Grad Med Educ. 2020;12(5):532–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7594774</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33149817</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deb N, Roy P. Prevalence of Dunning Kruger effect in first year medical students in a tertiary care hospital. Int J Community Med Public Health. 2021;8(11):5283.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Surdilovic D, Adtani P, Fuoad SA, Abdelaal HM, D’Souza J. Evaluation of the Dunning-Kruger effects among Dental students at an academic training Institution in UAE. Acta Stomatol Croat. 2022;56(3):299–310.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9635497</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36382209</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kruger J, Dunning D. Unskilled and unaware of it: how difficulties in recognizing one’s own incompetence lead to inflated self-assessments. J Pers Soc Psychol. 1999;77(6):1121–34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10626367</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meeran S, Goodwin P, Yalabik B. A parsimonious explanation of observed biases when forecasting one’s own performance. Int J Forecast. 2016;32:112–20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davis DA, Mazmanian PE, Fordis M, Van Harrison R, Thorpe KE, Perrier L. Accuracy of physician self-assessment compared with observed measures of competence: a systematic review. JAMA. 2006;296(9):1094–102.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16954489</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coutinho MVC, Thomas J, Fredricks-Lowman I, Alkaabi S, Couchman JJ. Unskilled and unaware: second-order judgments increase with miscalibration for low performers. Front Psychol. 2024;15:1252520.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11215559</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38952836</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clayson DE. Performance overconfidence: Metacognitive effects or Misplaced Student expectations? J Mark Educ. 2005;27(2):122–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kennedy E, Lawton L, Plumlee E. Blissful ignorance: the Problem of unrecognized incompetence and academic performance. J Mark Educ - J Market Educ. 2002;24:243–52.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miller T, Geraci L. Unskilled but aware: reinterpreting overconfidence in low-performing students. J Experimental Psychol Learn Memory Cognition. 2011;37:502–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21261428</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burson KA, Larrick RP, Klayman J. Skilled or unskilled, but still unaware of it: how perceptions of difficulty drive miscalibration in relative comparisons. J Pers Soc Psychol. 2006;90(1):60–77.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16448310</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krueger J, Mueller RA. Unskilled, unaware, or both? The better-than-average heuristic and statistical regression predict errors in estimates of own performance. J Pers Soc Psychol. 2002;82(2):180–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11831408</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoegh-Larsen AM, Gonzalez MT, Reierson IA, Husebo SIE, Hofoss D, Ravik M. Nursing students’ clinical judgment skills in simulation and clinical placement: a comparison of student self-assessment and evaluator assessment. BMC Nurs. 2023;22(1):64.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9996978</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36894974</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kun A, Juhász C, Farkas J. The Dunning–Kruger Effect in Knowledge Management examination of BSc Level Business Students. Int J Eng Manage Sci. 2023;8:14–21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zawadka M, Graczyńska A, Janiszewska A, Ostrowski A, Michałowski M, Rykowski M, Andruszkiewicz P. Lessons learned from a study of the integration of a point-of-care Ultrasound Course into the Undergraduate Medical School Curriculum. Med Sci Monit. 2019;25:4104–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6561147</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31154454</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bell P, Volckmann D. Knowledge surveys in General Chemistry: confidence, overconfidence, and performance. J Chem Educ 2011, 88.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pavel S, Robertson M, Harrison B. The Dunning-Kruger Effect and SIUC University’s Aviation Students. J Aviat Technol Eng 2012, 2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ehrlinger J, Dunning D. How chronic self-views influence (and potentially mislead) estimates of performance. J Pers Soc Psychol. 2003;84:5–17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12518967</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marottoli RA, Richardson ED. Confidence in, and self-rating of, driving ability among older drivers. Accid Anal Prev. 1998;30(3):331–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9663292</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ehrlinger J, Johnson K, Banner M, Dunning D, Kruger J. Why the unskilled are unaware: further explorations of (absent) self-insight among the Incompetent. Organ Behav Hum Decis Process. 2008;105(1):98–121.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2702783</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19568317</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maki RH, Jonas D, Kallod M. The relationship between comprehension and metacomprehension ability. Psychon Bull Rev. 1994;1(1):126–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24203422</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sullivan PJ, Ragogna M, Dithurbide L. An investigation into the Dunning–Kruger effect in sport coaching. Int J Sport Exerc Psychol. 2019;17(6):591–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tzamaras H, Sinz E, Yang M, Ng P, Moore J, Miller S. Competence over confidence: uncovering lower self-efficacy for women residents during central venous catheterization training. BMC Med Educ. 2024;24(1):923.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11348568</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39187825</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barnsley L, Lyon PM, Ralston SJ, Hibbert EJ, Cunningham I, Gordon FC, Field MJ. Clinical skills in junior medical officers: a comparison of self-reported confidence and observed competence. Med Educ. 2004;38(4):358–67.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15025637</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lerner BS, Kalish V, Ledford CJW. Exploring residents’ skills in diagnosing dementia: the unexpected dissonance between ability and confidence. Fam Med. 2017;49(6):460–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28633173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah D, Haisch CE, Noland SL. Case Reporting, competence, and confidence: a discrepancy in the numbers. J Surg Educ. 2018;75(2):304–12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29396274</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu X, Ruan X, Yu C, Yu X, Quan X, Li X, Yuan T, Xia D, Zhang Y, Pei L. Differences between resident self-assessments and faculty- assessments on Anesthesiology milestones and associated factors: a cross-sectional study. BMC Med Educ. 2024;24(1):551.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11100080</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38760807</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Athy S, Talmon G, Samson K, Martin K, Nelson K. Faculty Versus Resident Self-Assessment using Pathology milestones: how aligned are we? Acad Pathol. 2021;8:23742895211060526.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8679011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34926794</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krajc M, Ortmann A. Are the unskilled really that unaware? An alternative explanation. J Econ Psychol. 2008;29(5):724–38.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schlösser T, Dunning D, Johnson KL, Kruger J. How unaware are the unskilled? Empirical tests of the signal extraction counterexplanation for the Dunning–Kruger effect in self-evaluation of performance. J Econ Psychol. 2013;39:85–100.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Magnus JR, Peresetsky AA. A statistical explanation of the Dunning-Kruger Effect. Front Psychol. 2022;13:840180.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8992690</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35401341</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McIntosh RD, Moore AB, Liu Y, Della Sala S. Skill and self-knowledge: empirical refutation of the dual-burden account of the Dunning-Kruger effect. R Soc Open Sci. 2022;9(12):191727.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9727674</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36483762</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feld J, Sauermann J, de Grip A. Estimating the relationship between skill and overconfidence. J Behav Experimental Econ. 2017;68:18–24.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lichtenstein S, Fischhoff B. Do those who know more also know more about how much they know? Organizational Behav Hum Perform. 1977;20:159–83.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Juslin P, Winman A, Olsson H. Naive empiricism and dogmatism in confidence research: a critical examination of the hard–easy Effect. Psychol Rev. 2000;107:384–96.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10789203</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larrick RP, Burson KA, Soll JB. Social comparison and confidence: when thinking you’re better than average predicts overconfidence (and when it does not). Organ Behav Hum Decis Process. 2007;102(1):76–94.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gignac GE, Zajenkowski M. The Dunning-Kruger effect is (mostly) a statistical artefact: valid approaches to testing the hypothesis with individual differences data. Intelligence. 2020;80:101449.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gold B, Kuhn J-T. A longitudinal study on the stability of self-estimated intelligence and its relationship to personality traits. Pers Individ Dif. 2017;106:292–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shepperd JA. Student Derogation of the Scholastic aptitude test: biases in perceptions and presentations of College Board scores. Basic Appl Soc Psych. 1993;14(4):455–73.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dufner M, Denissen JJ, van Zalk M, Matthes B, Meeus WH, van Aken MA, Sedikides C. Positive intelligence illusions: on the relation between intellectual self-enhancement and psychological adjustment. J Pers. 2012;80(3):537–71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22091488</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zajenkowski M, Czarna AZ, Szymaniak K, Dufner M. What do highly narcissistic people think and feel about (their). Intelligence? J Pers. 2020;88(4):703–18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31654584</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jansen R, Rafferty A, Griffiths T. A rational model of the Dunning–Kruger effect supports insensitivity to evidence in low performers. Nat Hum Behav. 2021;5:1–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33633375</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woolliscroft JO, TenHaken J, Smith J, Calhoun JG. Medical students’ clinical self-assessments: comparisons with external measures of performance and the students’ self-assessments of overall performance and effort. Acad Med. 1993;68(4):285–94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8466612</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hacker D, Bol L, Horgan D, Rakow E. Test prediction and performance in a Classroom Context. J Educ Psychol. 2000;92:160–70.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knof H, Berndt M, Shiozawa T. The influence of collaborative learning and self-organisation on medical students’ academic performance in anatomy. Ann Anat. 2024;251:152182.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37879501</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abuzied AIH, Nabag WOM. Structured viva validity, reliability, and acceptability as an assessment tool in health professions education: a systematic review and meta-analysis. BMC Med Educ. 2023;23(1):531.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10369684</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37491301</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boud D, THE ROLE OF SELF-ASSESSMENT IN STUDENT GRADING. Assess Evaluation High Educ. 1989;14(1):20–30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sullivan K, Hall C. Introducing students to self-assessment. Assess Evaluation High Educ. 1997;22(3):289–305.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar VD. Beyond Dunning-Kruger Effect: undermining the biases which would lead to flawed self-assessment among students. Med Sci Educ. 2019;29(4):1155–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8368289</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34457595</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor SE, Brown JD. Illusion and well-being: a social psychological perspective on mental health. Psychol Bull. 1988;103(2):193–210.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3283814</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Epley N, Dunning D. Feeling holier than thou: are self-serving assessments produced by errors in self- or social prediction? J Pers Soc Psychol. 2000;79(6):861–75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11138757</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Molloy E, Boud D, Henderson M. Developing a learning-centred framework for feedback literacy. Assess Evaluation High Educ. 2019;45(4):527–40.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bradley CS, Dreifuerst KT, Johnson BK, Loomis A. More than a Meme: the Dunning-Kruger Effect as an opportunity for positive change in nursing education. Clin Simul Nurs. 2022;66:58–65.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanchez C, Dunning D. Overconfidence among beginners: is a little learning a dangerous thing? J Pers Soc Psychol. 2018;114(1):10–28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29094960</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Traus A, Höffken K, Thomas S, Mangold K, Schröer W. Stu.diCo. – Studieren digital in Zeiten Von Corona. Hildesheim: UVH - Universitätsverlag Hildesheim; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braun T, Qekaj A, Rapp S, König S, Loewe S, Boehringer D. Anregungen für eine Gestaltung Des Studieneinstiegs Unter Pandemiebedingung: Blaupausen für das digitale Wintersemester 2020/21. Stuttgart: Verlag Stuttgart - Universität Stuttgart, Zentrum für Lehre und Weiterbildung;; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andresen S, Lips A, Möller R, Rusack T, Schröer W, Thomas S, Wilmes J. Erfahrungen Und Perspektiven Von Jungen Menschen während Der Corona-Maßnahmen: Erste Ergebnisse Der Bundesweiten Studie JuCo. UVH - Universitätsverlag Hildesheim; 2020.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>