<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39457247</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1660-4601</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>21</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>25</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>International journal of environmental research and public health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Int J Environ Res Public Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Compound Crises: The Impact of Emergencies and Disasters on Mental Health Services in Puerto Rico.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1273</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3390/ijerph21101273</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Mental health in Puerto Rico is a complex and multifaceted issue that has been shaped by the island's unique history, culture, and political status. Recent challenges, including disasters, economic hardships, and political turmoil, have significantly affected the mental well-being of the population, coupled with the limitations in the accessibility of mental health services. Thus, Puerto Rico has fewer mental health professionals per capita than any other state or territory in the United States.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">This comprehensive review examines the impact of disasters on mental health and mental health services in Puerto Rico. Given the exodus of Puerto Ricans from the island, this review also provides an overview of mental health resources available on the island, as well as in the continental United States. This review identifies efforts to address mental health issues, with the intent of gaining a proper understanding of the available mental health services, key trends, as well as observable challenges and achievements within the mental health landscape of the Puerto Rican population.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DESIGN" NlmCategory="METHODS">A comprehensive search using the PRIMO database of the University of Central Florida (UCF) library database was conducted, focusing on key terms related to disasters and mental healthcare and services in Puerto Rico. The inclusion criteria encompassed studies on Puerto Rican individuals, both those who remained on the island and those who migrated post-disaster, addressing the mental health outcomes and services for adults and children. We included peer-reviewed articles published from 2005 onwards in English and/or Spanish, examining the impact of disasters on mental health, accessibility of services, and/or trauma-related consequences.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">In this scoping review, we identified 39 studies addressing the mental health profile of Puerto Ricans, identifying significant gaps in service availability and accessibility and the impact of environmental disasters on mental health. The findings indicate a severe shortage of mental health services in Puerto Rico, exacerbated by disasters such as Hurricanes Irma and Maria, the earthquakes of late 2019 and early 2020 that followed, and the COVID-19 pandemic, resulting in substantial delays in accessing care, and limited insurance coverage, particularly in rural regions. Despite these challenges, efforts to improve mental health services have included substantial federal funding and community initiative aimed at enhancing care availability and infrastructure. Limitations include the use of a single database, language restrictions, and potential variability in data extraction and synthesis.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">This scoping review highlights the significant impact of disasters on mental health in Puerto Rico and the challenges in accessing mental health services exacerbated by disasters. Despite efforts, significant gaps in mental healthcare and services persist, emphasizing the need for more rigorous research and improvements in infrastructure and workforce to enhance mental health outcomes for Puerto Ricans both on the island and in the continental United States.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rivera</LastName><ForeName>Fernando I</ForeName><Initials>FI</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Puerto Rico Research Hub, University of Central Florida, Orlando, FL 32816, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Belligoni</LastName><ForeName>Sara</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-7563-3043</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Puerto Rico Research Hub, University of Central Florida, Orlando, FL 32816, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Arroyo Rodriguez</LastName><ForeName>Veronica</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Medicine, University of Connecticut, Storrs, CT 06269, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chapdelaine</LastName><ForeName>Sophia</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Psychology, Appalachian State University, Boone, NC 28608, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nannuri</LastName><ForeName>Varun</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0002-2945-2126</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Medicine, University of Central Florida, Orlando, FL 32816, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Steen Burgos</LastName><ForeName>Ashley</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Behavioral and Brain Sciences, Ponce Health Sciences University, Ponce, PR 00716, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Int J Environ Res Public Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101238455</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1660-4601</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011647" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Puerto Rico</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008605" MajorTopicYN="Y">Mental Health Services</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000458" MajorTopicYN="N">organization &amp; administration</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004190" MajorTopicYN="Y">Disasters</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004630" MajorTopicYN="N">Emergencies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006297" MajorTopicYN="N">Health Services Accessibility</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008603" MajorTopicYN="N">Mental Health</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Puerto Ricans</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Puerto Rico</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">disasters</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">emergencies</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mental health services</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mental healthcare</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>8</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39457247</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11507531</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph21101273</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">ijerph21101273</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Perreira K., Lallemand N., Napoles A., Zuckerman S. Environmental Scan of Puerto Rico’s Health Care Infrastructure. Urban Institute; Washington, DC, USA: 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Canino G.M., Vila D., Santiago-Batista K., Garcia P., Velez-Baez G., Moreda-Alegria A. Need Assessment Study of Mental Health and Substance Use Disorders and Service Utilization among Adult Population in Puerto Rico—Final Report. Behavioral Sciences Research Institute, University of Puerto Rico, Medical Science Campus, ASSMCA; Bayamón, Puerto Rico: 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hobfoll S.E., Watson P., Bell C.C., Bryant R.A., Brymer M.J., Friedman M.J., Friedman M., Gersons B.P.R., de Jong J.T.V.M., Layne C.M., et al. Five essential elements of immediate and mid–term mass trauma intervention: Empirical evidence. Psychiatry Interpers. Biol. Process. 2007;70:283–315. doi: 10.1521/psyc.2007.70.4.283.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1521/psyc.2007.70.4.283</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18181708</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Canino G., Shrout P.E., NeMoyer A., Vila D., Santiago K.M., Garcia P., Quiñones A., Cruz V., Alegria V. A comparison of the prevalence of psychiatric disorders in Puerto Rico with the United States and the Puerto Rican population of the United States. Soc. Psychiatry Psychiatr. Epidemiol. 2019;54:369–378. doi: 10.1007/s00127-019-01653-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00127-019-01653-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6440857</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30649577</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Junod A., Rivera F., Rogin A., Morales-Burnett J. Climate Migration and Receiving Community Institutional Capacity in the US Gulf Coast. Urban Institute; Washington, DC, USA: 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chapdelaine S. Bachelor’s Thesis. University of Central Florida; Orlando, FL, USA: 2022. Mental Health of Puerto Ricans Who Stayed in Puerto Rico Compared to Those Who Migrated to Florida after Hurricane Maria.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Purtle J., Rivera-González A.C., Mercado D.L., Barajas C.B., Chavez L., Canino G., Ortega A.N. Growing inequities in mental health crisis services offered to indigent patients in Puerto Rico versus the US states before and after Hurricanes Maria and Irma. Health Serv. Res. 2023;58:325–331. doi: 10.1111/1475-6773.14092.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1475-6773.14092</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10012226</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36310433</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jervis R. ‘I Sit and Cry All Day’: Suicide Hotline Calls Double in Puerto Rico 6 Months after Hurricane Maria. USA Today; McLean, VA, USA: 2018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palinkas L.A., Wong M. Global climate change and mental health. Curr. Opin. Psychol. 2020;32:12–16. doi: 10.1016/j.copsyc.2019.06.023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.copsyc.2019.06.023</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31349129</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orengo-Aguayo R., Stewart R.W., de Arellano M.A., Suárez-Kindy J.L., Young J. Disaster exposure and mental health among Puerto Rican youths after Hurricane Maria. JAMA Netw. Open. 2019;2:e192619. doi: 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.2619.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.2619</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6487632</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31026024</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perreira K., Peters R., Lallemand N., Zuckerman S. Puerto Rico Health Care Infrastructure Assessment. Urban Institute; Washington, DC, USA: 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Belligoni S. Held in the grip: Political status, governing institutions, and emergency management procedural arrangements in the cases of Florida and Puerto Rico. Politics Policy. 2024;52:349–364. doi: 10.1111/polp.12581.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/polp.12581</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aponte J. Hurricanes and Mental Health. Hisp. Health Care Int. 2018;16:110–111. doi: 10.1177/1540415318804290.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1540415318804290</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30309247</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halpern J., Vermeulen K. Disaster Mental Health Interventions: Core Principles and Practices. Routledge; Oxfordshire, UK: 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Department of Health of the Government of Puerto Rico . Estadisticas Preliminares de Casos de Suicidios in Puerto Rico. Department of Health of the Government of Puerto Rico; San Juan, Puerto Rico: 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santiago D., Labandera E., Arroyo C. Institutional Resilience in Puerto Rico: A First Look at Efforts by Puerto Rican HSIs. Excelencia in Education; Washington, DC, USA: 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Norris F.H., Friedman M.J., Watson P.J. Summary and Implications of the Disaster Mental Health Research. National Emergency Training Center; Emmitsburg, MD, USA: 2002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12405080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Health Resources and Services Administration (HRSA)  Health Professional Shortage Area (HPSA)  [(accessed on 15 September 2024)]; Available online:  https://data.hrsa.gov/tools/shortage-area/hpsa-find.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eftychiou L., El Morr C. The Digitization of Healthcare: New Challenges and Opportunities. Springer; Berlin/Heidelberg, Germany: 2017. Mobile mental health virtual communities: Challenges and opportunities; pp. 257–275.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Negroni L.K., Medina C.K., Rivera Díaz M., Paniccia M. Perceptions of mental health and utilization of mental health services in Puerto Rico. Soc. Work Ment. Health. 2020;18:149–169. doi: 10.1080/15332985.2019.1700582.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/15332985.2019.1700582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scaramutti C., Salas-Wright C.P., Vos S.R., Schwartz S.J. The Mental Health Impact of Hurricane Maria on Puerto Ricans in Puerto Rico and Florida. Disaster Med. Public Health Prep. 2019;13:24–27. doi: 10.1017/dmp.2018.151.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/dmp.2018.151</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30696508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jimenez D.E., Bartels S.J., Cardenas V., Alegria M. Stigmatizing attitudes toward mental illness among racial/ethnic older adults in primary care. Int. J. Geriatr. Psychiatry. 2013;28:1061–1068. doi: 10.1002/gps.3928.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/gps.3928</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3672370</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23361866</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rivera F.I., Burgos G. The health status of Puerto Ricans in Florida. Centro. J. 2010;22:199–217.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Acevedo-Garcia D., Bates L.M. Latinas/os in the United States: Changing the Face of America. Springer; New York, NY, USA: 2008. Latino health paradoxes: Empirical evidence, explanations, future research, and implications; pp. 101–113.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morales D.A., Barksdale C.L., Beckel-Mitchener A.C. A call to action to address rural mental health disparities. J. Clin. Transl. Sci. 2020;4:463–467. doi: 10.1017/cts.2020.42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/cts.2020.42</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7681156</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33244437</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rivera-Hernandez M., Leyva B., Keohane L.M., Trivedi A.N. Quality of care for white and Hispanic Medicare Advantage enrollees in the United States and Puerto Rico. JAMA Intern. Med. 2016;176:787–794. doi: 10.1001/jamainternmed.2016.0267.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2016.0267</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4934661</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27111865</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Llibre-Guerra J.J., Jimenez-Velazquez I.Z., Llibre-Rodriguez J.J., Acosta D. The impact of COVID-19 on mental health in the Hispanic Caribbean region. Int. Psychogeriatr. 2020;32:1143–1146. doi: 10.1017/S1041610220000848.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S1041610220000848</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7267095</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32383637</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goebert D. Social Support, Mental Health, Minorities, and Acculturative Stress. In: Vega A.M., Miranda K.F., editors. Determinants of Minority Mental Health and Wellness. Springer; New York, NY, USA: 2008. pp. 1–24.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aranda E., Blackwell R., Escue M., Rosa A. Cascading disasters: The impact of hurricane Maria and COVID-19 on post-disaster Puerto Rican migrants’ adaptation and integration in Florida. Lat. Stud. 2023;21:138–161. doi: 10.1057/s41276-022-00390-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1057/s41276-022-00390-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9753070</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36536946</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Federal Emergency Management Agency (FEMA)  Nearly $80 Million from FEMA to Address Mental Health in Puerto Rico. 21 May 2023.  [(accessed on 20 September 2024)]; Available online:  https://www.fema.gov/press-release/20230521/nearly-80-million-fema-address-mental-health-puerto-rico.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Financial Oversight and Management Board for Puerto Rico . Media Release: Oversight Board Certifies $31 Billion Fiscal Year 2024 Budget. Financial Oversight and Management Board for Puerto Rico; San Juan, Puerto Rico: Jun 30, 2023.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>