<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39450522</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1360-0443</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>25</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Addiction (Abingdon, England)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Addiction</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Improving racial/ethnic health equity and naloxone access among people at risk for opioid overdose: A simulation modeling analysis of community-based naloxone distribution strategies in Massachusetts, United States.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/add.16691</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND AND AIMS" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">During the COVID-19 pandemic, there was a surge in opioid overdose deaths (OODs) in Massachusetts, USA, particularly among Black and Hispanic/Latinx populations. Despite the increasing racial and ethnic disparities in OODs, there was no compensatory increase in naloxone distributed to these groups. We aimed to evaluate two community-based naloxone expansion strategies, with the objective of identifying approaches that could mitigate mortality and racial and ethnic disparities in OODs.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DESIGN" NlmCategory="METHODS">Individual-based simulation model. We measured naloxone availability using naloxone kits per OOD and evaluated scenarios of achieving higher benchmarks for naloxone availability (i.e. 40, 60 and 80 kits per OOD) from 2022 levels (overall: 26.0, White: 28.8, Black: 17.3, Hispanic/Latinx: 18.9). We compared two naloxone distribution strategies: (1) proportional distribution: achieving the benchmark ratio at the overall population level while distributing additional kits proportional to the 2022 level for each racial/ethnic group (at 40 kits per OOD benchmark: overall: 40, White: 44.3, Black: 26.6, Hispanic/Latinx: 29.1), and (2) equity-focused distribution: achieving the benchmark ratio among each racial/ethnic group (at 40 kits per OOD benchmark: 40 for all groups).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="SETTING" NlmCategory="METHODS">Massachusetts, United States.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="PARTICIPANTS" NlmCategory="METHODS">People at risk of OOD.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MEASUREMENTS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Annual number and rate of OODs, total healthcare costs of increasing naloxone availability.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="FINDINGS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Both naloxone distribution strategies yielded comparable predicted reductions in total OODs in 2025 and incurred similar incremental costs. However, the relative reduction in the rate of OODs differed across groups. For achieving an 80 kits per OOD benchmark, proportional distribution resulted in a projected 6.7%, 6.5% and 7.1% reduction in annual OODs in 2025 among White, Black and Hispanic/Latinx populations, respectively. In contrast, equity-focused distribution achieved a reduction of 5.7%, 11.3% and 10.2% in the respective groups. In all scenarios, the cost per OOD averted was lower than the generally accepted thresholds for cost per life saved.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">An equity-focused naloxone distribution strategy designed to reduce racial and ethnic disparities in naloxone availability could improve health equity among racial and ethnic groups while potentially improving overall population health at lower healthcare costs per opioid overdose death averted than a proportional distribution strategy.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Addiction published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Society for the Study of Addiction.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zang</LastName><ForeName>Xiao</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5722-8255</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Health Policy and Management, School of Public Health, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Skinner</LastName><ForeName>Alexandra</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, School of Public Health, Brown University, Providence, RI, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Zongbo</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5470-866X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Health Policy and Management, School of Public Health, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shaw</LastName><ForeName>Leah C</ForeName><Initials>LC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, School of Public Health, Brown University, Providence, RI, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Behrends</LastName><ForeName>Czarina N</ForeName><Initials>CN</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3885-088X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Population Health Sciences, Weill Cornell Medical College, New York, NY, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chatterjee</LastName><ForeName>Avik</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, Section of General Internal Medicine, Boston Medical Center and Boston University School of Medicine, Boston, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jalali</LastName><ForeName>Ali</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4349-1519</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Population Health Sciences, Weill Cornell Medical College, New York, NY, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jordan</LastName><ForeName>Ashly E</ForeName><Initials>AE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Drug Use and HIV/HCV Research, New York, NY, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Morgan</LastName><ForeName>Jake R</ForeName><Initials>JR</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1559-3983</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Law, Policy and Management, Boston University School of Public Health, Boston, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nolen</LastName><ForeName>Shayla</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, School of Public Health, Brown University, Providence, RI, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Schackman</LastName><ForeName>Bruce R</ForeName><Initials>BR</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1132-2932</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Population Health Sciences, Weill Cornell Medical College, New York, NY, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Marshall</LastName><ForeName>Brandon D L</ForeName><Initials>BDL</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0134-7052</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, School of Public Health, Brown University, Providence, RI, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Walley</LastName><ForeName>Alexander Y</ForeName><Initials>AY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Massachusetts Department of Public Health, Bureau of Substance Addiction Services and Grayken Center for Addiction, Section of General Internal Medicine, Boston Medical Center and Boston University Chobanian and Avedisian School of Medicine, Boston, MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>P30 DA040500</GrantID><Acronym>DA</Acronym><Agency>NIDA NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>U01 DA047408</GrantID><Acronym>DA</Acronym><Agency>NIDA NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>U01DA047408</GrantID><Agency>National Institutes on Drug Abuse</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>P30DA040500</GrantID><Agency>National Institutes on Drug Abuse</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Addiction</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9304118</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0965-2140</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">community‐based interventions</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cost</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">naloxone distribution</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">opioid overdose death prevention</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">racial/ethnic equity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">simulation modeling</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39450522</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/add.16691</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Mattson CL, Tanz LJ, Quinn K, Kariisa M, Patel P, Davis NL. Trends and geographic patterns in drug and synthetic opioid overdose deaths—United States, 2013–2019. Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2021;70(6):202–207. https://doi.org/10.15585/mmwr.mm7006a4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuehn BM. Accelerated overdose deaths linked with COVID‐19. JAMA. 2021;325(6):523. https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2021.0074</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kariisa M, Davis NL, Kumar S, Seth P, Mattson CL, Chowdhury F, et al. Vital signs: drug overdose deaths, by selected sociodemographic and social determinants of health characteristics—25 states and the District of Columbia, 2019–2020. Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2022;71(29):940–947. https://doi.org/10.15585/mmwr.mm7129e2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Institute on Drug Abuse. Drug overdose death rates; 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>KFF. Opioid overdose death rates and all drug overdose death rates per 100,000 population (age‐adjusted).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Massachusetts Department of Public Health. Current opioid statistics.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bailey ZD, Krieger N, Agénor M, Graves J, Linos N, Bassett MT. Structural racism and health inequities in the USA: evidence and interventions. Lancet. 2017;389(10077):1453–1463. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(17)30569-X</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pamplin JR, Rouhani S, Davis CS, King C, Townsend TN. Persistent criminalization and structural racism in US drug policy: the case of overdose good Samaritan Laws. Am J Public Health. 2023;113(S1):S43–S48. https://doi.org/10.2105/AJPH.2022.307037</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Friedman JR, Hansen H. Evaluation of increases in drug overdose mortality rates in the US by race and ethnicity before and during the COVID‐19 pandemic. JAMA Psychiatry. 2022;79(4):379–381. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2022.0004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han B, Einstein EB, Jones CM, Cotto J, Compton WM, Volkow ND. Racial and ethnic disparities in drug overdose deaths in the US during the COVID‐19 pandemic. JAMA Netw Open. 2022;5(9):e2232314. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.32314</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Irvine MA, Oller D, Boggis J, Bishop B, Coombs D, Wheeler E, et al. Estimating naloxone need in the USA across fentanyl, heroin, and prescription opioid epidemics: a modelling study. Lancet Public Health. 2022;7(3):e210–e218. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2468-2667(21)00304-2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zang X, Bessey SE, Krieger MS, Hallowell BD, Koziol JA, Nolen S, et al. Comparing projected fatal overdose outcomes and costs of strategies to expand community‐based distribution of naloxone in Rhode Island. JAMA Netw Open. 2022;5(11):e2241174. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.41174</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fairbairn N, Coffin PO, Walley AY. Naloxone for heroin, prescription opioid, and illicitly made fentanyl overdoses: challenges and innovations responding to a dynamic epidemic. Int J Drug Policy. 2017;46:172–179. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.drugpo.2017.06.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weiner J, Murphy SM, Behrends C. Expanding access to naloxone: a review of distribution strategies 23 Penn LDIIssue Brief; 2019. p. 132.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Owczarzak J, Weicker N, Urquhart G, Morris M, Park JN, Sherman SG. “We know the streets:” race, place, and the politics of harm reduction. Health Place. 2020;64:102376. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.healthplace.2020.102376</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lopez AM, Thomann M, Dhatt Z, Ferrera J, Al‐Nassir M, Ambrose M, et al. Understanding racial inequities in the implementation of harm reduction initiatives. Am J Public Health. 2022;112(S2):S173–S181. https://doi.org/10.2105/AJPH.2022.306767</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan MR, Hoff L, Elliott L, Scheidell JD, Pamplin JR, Townsend TN, et al. Racial/ethnic disparities in opioid overdose prevention: comparison of the naloxone care cascade in White, Latinx, and black people who use opioids in new York City. Harm Reduct J. 2023;20(1):24. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12954-023-00736-7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nolen S, Zang X, Chatterjee A, Behrends CN, Green TC, Kumar A, et al. Community‐based naloxone coverage equity for the prevention of opioid overdose fatalities in racial/ethnic minority communities in Massachusetts and Rhode Island. Addiction. 2022;117(5):1372–1381. https://doi.org/10.1111/add.15759</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nolen S, Zang X, Chatterjee A, Behrends CN, Green TC, Linas BP, et al. Evaluating equity in community‐based naloxone access among racial/ethnic groups in Massachusetts. Drug Alcohol Depend. 2022;241:109668. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2022.109668</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zang X, Walley AY, Chatterjee A, Kimmel SD, Morgan JR, Murphy SM, et al. Changes to opioid overdose deaths and community naloxone access among black, Hispanic and White people from 2016 to 2021 with the onset of the COVID‐19 pandemic: an interrupted time‐series analysis in Massachusetts, USA. Addiction. 2023;118(12):2413–2423. https://doi.org/10.1111/add.16324</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration State Opioid Response Grants; 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sugarman OK, Hulsey EG, Heller D. Achieving the potential of naloxone saturation by measuring distribution. JAMA Health Forum: Am Med Assoc. 2023;4(10):e233338. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamahealthforum.2023.3338</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Massachusetts behavioral health partnership MBHP Massachusetts Emergency Services Program Overview Presentation; 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Merrall EL, Kariminia A, Binswanger IA, Hobbs MS, Farrell M, Marsden J, et al. Meta‐analysis of drug‐related deaths soon after release from prison. Addiction. 2010;105(9):1545–1554. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1360-0443.2010.02990.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kerr T, Fairbairn N, Tyndall M, Marsh D, Li K, Montaner J, et al. Predictors of non‐fatal overdose among a cohort of polysubstance‐using injection drug users. Drug Alcohol Depend. 2007;87(1):39–45. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2006.07.009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brugal MT, Barrio G, Fuente LDL, Regidor E, Royuela L, Suelves JM. Factors associated with non‐fatal heroin overdose: assessing the effect of frequency and route of heroin administration. Addiction. 2002;97(3):319–327. https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1360-0443.2002.00058.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Darke S, Williamson A, Ross J, Mills KL, Havard A, Teesson M. Patterns of nonfatal heroin overdose over a 3‐year period: findings from the Australian treatment outcome study. J Urban Health. 2007;84(2):283–291. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11524-006-9156-0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Helton JC, Davis FJ. Latin hypercube sampling and the propagation of uncertainty in analyses of complex systems. Reliabil Eng Syst Saf. 2003;81(1):23–69. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0951-8320(03)00058-9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bird SM, Parmar MK, Strang J. Take‐home naloxone to prevent fatalities from opiate‐overdose: protocol for Scotland's public health policy evaluation, and a new measure to assess impact. Drugs: Educ Prev pol. 2015;22(1):66–76. https://doi.org/10.3109/09687637.2014.981509</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zang X, Macmadu A, Krieger MS, Behrends CN, Green TC, Morgan JR, et al. Targeting community‐based naloxone distribution using opioid overdose death rates: a descriptive analysis of naloxone rescue kits and opioid overdose deaths in Massachusetts and Rhode Island. Int J Drug Policy. 2021;98:103435. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.drugpo.2021.103435</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moustaqim‐Barrette A, Papamihali K, Mamdani Z, Williams S, Buxton JA. Accessing take‐home naloxone in British Columbia and the role of community pharmacies: results from the analysis of administrative data. PLoS ONE. 2020;15(9):e0238618. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0238618</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Social Explorer Tables (SE). Census Census Bureau; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration. National Survey on drug use and health: 2‐year RDSA (2018‐2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barocas JA, White LF, Wang J, Walley AY, LaRochelle MR, Bernson D, et al. Estimated prevalence of opioid use disorder in Massachusetts, 2011–2015: a capture–recapture analysis. Am J Public Health. 2018;108(12):1675–1681. https://doi.org/10.2105/AJPH.2018.304673</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Behrends CN, Gutkind S, Winkelstein E, Wright M, Dolatshahi J, Welch A, et al. Costs of opioid overdose education and naloxone distribution in new York City. Subst Abus. 2021;43(1):1–7. https://doi.org/10.1080/08897077.2021.1986877</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Behrends CN, Paone D, Nolan ML, Tuazon E, Murphy SM, Kapadia SN, et al. Estimated impact of supervised injection facilities on overdose fatalities and healthcare costs in new York City. J Subst Abuse Treat. 2019;106:79–88. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jsat.2019.08.010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Savinkina A, Madushani RW, Eftekhari YG, Wang J, Barocas JA, Morgan JR, et al. Population‐level impact of initiating pharmacotherapy and linking to care people with opioid use disorder at inpatient medically managed withdrawal programs: an effectiveness and cost‐effectiveness analysis. Addiction. 2022;117(9):2450–2461. https://doi.org/10.1111/add.15879</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murphy SM, McCollister KE, Leff JA, Yang X, Jeng PJ, Lee JD, et al. Cost‐effectiveness of buprenorphine–naloxone versus extended‐release naltrexone to prevent opioid relapse. Ann Intern Med. 2019;170(2):90–98. https://doi.org/10.7326/M18-0227</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The White House. Circular no. A‐4, regulatory analysis; 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Friedman J, Shover CL. Charting the fourth wave: Geographic, temporal, race/ethnicity and demographic trends in polysubstance fentanyl overdose deaths in the United States, 2010–2021. Addiction. 2023;118(12):2477–2485.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehra R, Franck LS. Structural racism and social distancing: implications for COVID‐19. EClinicalMedicine. 2021;35:100869. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eclinm.2021.100869</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Massachusetts Department of Public Health. Massachusetts opioid‐related overdose deaths rose 2.5 percent in 2022; 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosales R, Janssen T, Yermash J, Yap KR, Ball EL, Hartzler B, et al. Persons from racial and ethnic minority groups receiving medication for opioid use disorder experienced increased difficulty accessing harm reduction services during COVID‐19. J Subst Abuse Treat. 2022;132:108648.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dayton L, Tobin K, Falade‐Nwulia O, Davey‐Rothwell M, Al‐Tayyib A, Saleem H, et al. Racial disparities in overdose prevention among people who inject drugs. J Urban Health. 2020;97(6):823–830. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11524-020-00439-5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Massachusetts Bureau of Substance Addiction Services. Naloxone distribution program locator.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Volkow ND, Chandler RK, Villani J. Need for comprehensive and timely data to address the opioid overdose epidemic without a blindfold. Wiley Online Library. 2022;117(8):2132–2134. https://doi.org/10.1111/add.15957</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mistler CB, Sullivan MC, Copenhaver MM, Meyer JP, Roth AM, Shenoi SV, et al. Differential impacts of COVID‐19 across racial‐ethnic identities in persons with opioid use disorder. J Subst Abuse Treat. 2021;129:108387. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jsat.2021.108387</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schneider KE, Allen ST, Rouhani S, Morris M, Haney K, Saloner B, et al. Increased solitary drug use during COVID‐19: an unintended consequence of social distancing. Int J Drug Policy. 2023;111:103923. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.drugpo.2022.103923</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simha S, Ahmed Y, Brummett CM, Waljee JF, Englesbe MJ, Bicket MC. Impact of the COVID‐19 pandemic on opioid overdose and other adverse events in the USA and Canada: a systematic review. Reg Anesth Pain Med. 2023;48(1):37–43. https://doi.org/10.1136/rapm-2022-103591</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jalali A, Tamimi RM, McPherson SM, Murphy SM. Econometric issues in prospective economic evaluations alongside clinical trials: combining the nonparametric bootstrap with methods that address missing data. Epidemiol Rev. 2022;44(1):67–77. https://doi.org/10.1093/epirev/mxac006</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>