<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39451514</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1471-1788</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>25</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>International journal of psychiatry in clinical practice</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Int J Psychiatry Clin Pract</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Relationship between coping strategies and change in symptom severity in contamination-focused OCD patients during the COVID-19: a one-year follow-up.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1</StartPage><EndPage>7</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1-7</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1080/13651501.2024.2420641</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">To examine the relationship between coping strategies and the change in symptom severity in contamination-focused OCD patients during the COVID-19 pandemic over a one-year follow-up.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">In March 2020, a one-year follow-up study was initiated with 56 contamination-focused OCD patients in Turkey. Coping strategies were evaluated using the COPE scale. OCD symptom severity was assessed using the Yale-Brown Obsessive-Compulsive Scale (Y-BOCS) at the beginning and end of the year. The Fear of COVID-19 Scale was administered mid-year.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">One year post the onset of COVID-19, 68% of patients showed increased OCD symptom severity, while 32% displayed a decrease. Higher scores on the fear of COVID-19 scale and lower acceptance scores from COPE subscales were correlated with increased OCD symptom severity.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The COVID-19 pandemic has intensified OCD symptoms in a substantial proportion of patients, particularly those with heightened fears related to the pandemic, and reduced acceptance-based coping strategies. Tailored interventions emphasising adaptive coping mechanisms may benefit OCD patients in managing their symptoms during external stressors like pandemics.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cengiz Cavusoglu</LastName><ForeName>Emine</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9333-6715</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, Basaksehir Cam and Sakura City Hospital, Istanbul, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Demirkan</LastName><ForeName>Arda Kazim</ForeName><Initials>AK</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1982-5569</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, Samsun LIV Hospital, Samsun, Turkey.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Int J Psychiatry Clin Pract</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9709509</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1365-1501</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><OtherAbstract Type="plain-language-summary" Language="eng"><AbstractText>The COVID-19 pandemic led to significant variations in OCD symptom severity among individuals with contamination-focused OCD.Sixty-eight percent of patients showed an increase in OCD symptom severity (ISS group), while 32% displayed a decrease (DSS group) over a year after the pandemic’s onset.Fear of COVID-19 was significantly higher among those with increased OCD symptoms, highlighting a link between external stressors and OCD exacerbation.Acceptance as a coping mechanism correlated with reduced OCD symptoms. Patients displaying increased OCD symptoms demonstrated lower acceptance scores.External factors, such as global pandemics, can have profound effects on existing mental health conditions. The correlation between fear of COVID-19 and OCD symptom progression confirms this.Acceptance-based therapeutic interventions might be effective for OCD patients facing significant stressors.</AbstractText></OtherAbstract><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Obsessive-compulsive disorder</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">acceptance</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">contamination-focused obsessions</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">coping strategies</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>54</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39451514</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/13651501.2024.2420641</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>