<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39455941</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1471-2458</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>24</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>25</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC public health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Public Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A tale of two times: an exploration of healthcare utilization patterns before and during COVID-19 in Iran.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>2961</StartPage><MedlinePgn>2961</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">2961</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12889-024-20452-6</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The COVID-19 pandemic has impacted global healthcare utilization patterns. This study aimed to examine the impact of COVID-19 pandemic on utilization rate of healthcare services in Iran.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHOD" NlmCategory="METHODS">In this quasi-experimental study, data on the utilization rates of laboratory services, sonography exams, CT scans, MRIs, and EKGs was collected from the Social Security Organization (SSO)'s insurance information system. This data, covering 47 months prior to the pandemic and 25 months during it, was analyzed to assess the pandemic's impact on healthcare utilization among insured individuals in Iran. The data was categorized into direct, indirect, and total sectors, and an Interrupted Time Series Analysis (ITSA) model was employed for data analysis, examining both total and sector-specific utilization rates.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="FINDINGS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The study for single group indicated that in the total sector, Utilization rate per 1000 insured significantly decreased by 25.25 for laboratory services, decreased by 3.99 for sonography, decreased by 1.08 for MRIs and decreased by 1.01 for EKGs, but increased by 2.28 for CT scans in the first pandemic month. Over following months, monthly utilization trends per 1000 insured increased significantly- laboratory services + 1.08, sonography + 0.11, CT scans + 0.12, MRIs + 0.06, and EKGs + 0.05. Pre-pandemic, monthly utilization per 1000 insured was 62.68 labs, 14.47 sonography, 0.72 CT scans, 2.06 MRIs, with all significantly higher in the indirect over direct sector except EKGs which were 2.08 higher in the direct sector. In the first pandemic month, there were significant between-sector differences per 1000 of -4.4 for sonography, + 1.89 CT scans, -1.01 MRIs and + 1.29 EKGs.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The COVID-19 pandemic led to a significant decline in healthcare service utilization, particularly in total and direct sectors, while CT scans remained unaffected. To address these challenges and meet patient needs, Iran's health system should adopt alternative delivery methods like telemedicine.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rezaei</LastName><ForeName>Satar</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6194-6057</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Center for Environmental Determinants of Health, Health Institute, Kermanshah University of Medical Sciences, Kermanshah, Iran. satarrezaei@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mohammadnezhad</LastName><ForeName>Masoud</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Health, Education and Life Sciences, School of Nursing and Midwifery, Birmingham City University, Birmingham, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Education and Behavioral Sciences, Faculty of Public Health, Mahidol University, Nakhon Pathom, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health, Daffodil International University (DIU), Daffodil Smart City (DSC), Birulia, Savar, Dhaka, 1216, Bangladesh.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Public Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100968562</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1471-2458</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007492" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Iran</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010342" MajorTopicYN="Y">Patient Acceptance of Health Care</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D065186" MajorTopicYN="N">Interrupted Time Series Analysis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19 pandemic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Health services utilization</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Social security organization</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Time series analysis</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>25</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>55</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39455941</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12889-024-20452-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12889-024-20452-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11515307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Lassi ZS, Naseem R, Salam RA, Siddiqui F, Das JK. The impact of the COVID-19 Pandemic on Immunization campaigns and programs: a systematic review. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18(3).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7908591</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33499422</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kotiso M, Qirbi N, Al-Shabi K, Vuolo E, Al-Waleedi A, Naiene J, et al. Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on the utilisation of health services at public hospitals in Yemen: a retrospective comparative study. BMJ Open. 2022;12(1):e047868.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8724586</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34980605</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amsah N, Md Isa Z, Ahmad N, Abdul Manaf MR. Impact of COVID-19 pandemic on Healthcare Utilization among patients with type 2 diabetes Mellitus: a systematic review. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2023;20(5).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10002238</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36901588</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahubessy FF, Darmawan ES. Financial performance of hospital during pandemic Covid 19. Budapest International Research and critics Institute-Journal (BIRCI-Journal). 2022;5(1):2230–48.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Filippo O, D’Ascenzo F, Angelini F, Bocchino PP, Conrotto F, Saglietto A, et al. Reduced rate of hospital admissions for ACS during Covid-19 outbreak in Northern Italy. N Engl J Med. 2020;383(1):88–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7224608</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32343497</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahmoodpour-Azari M, Rezaei S, Badiee N, Hajizadeh M, Mohammadi A, Kazemi-Karyani A, et al. The COVID-19 pandemic and healthcare utilization in Iran: evidence from an interrupted time series analysis. Osong Public Health and Research Perspectives; 2023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10522821</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37415435</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Howarth A, Munro M, Theodorou A, Mills PR. Trends in healthcare utilisation during COVID-19: a longitudinal study from the UK. BMJ open. 2021;11(7):e048151.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8327639</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34330859</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cassell K, Zipfel CM, Bansal S, Weinberger DM. Trends in non-COVID-19 hospitalizations prior to and during the COVID-19 pandemic period, United States, 2017–2021. Nat Commun. 2022;13(1):5930.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9546751</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36209210</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choi SE, Simon L, Basu S, Barrow JR. Changes in dental care use patterns due to COVID-19 among insured patients in the United States. J Am Dent Association. 2021;152(12):1033–43. e3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8444228</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34656295</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karande S, Chong GTF, Megally H, Parmar D, Taylor GW, Obadan-Udoh EM, et al. Changes in dental and medical visits before and during the COVID‐19 pandemic among US children aged 1–17 years. Commun Dent Oral Epidemiol. 2023;51(3):483–93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9877772</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36326121</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rezaei Z, Lotfi F, Bayati M, Kavosi Z. The effect of Covid-19 pandemic on healthcare utilization in public vs private centers in Iran: a multiple group interrupted time-series analysis. BMC Health Serv Res. 2023;23(1):822.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10394764</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37528374</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pour-Azari MM, Badiee N, Karyani AK, Soltani S, Rezaei S. The Effect of COVID-19 pandemic on using CTS and MRI in Iran: evidence from an interrupted Time Series Analysis. J Health Rep Technol. 2023;9(4).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10522821</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37415435</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salimi R, Gomar R, Heshmati B. The COVID-19 outbreak in Iran. J Glob Health. 2020;10(1):010365.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7296218</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32566156</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lazzerini M, Barbi E, Apicella A, Marchetti F, Cardinale F, Trobia G. Delayed access or provision of care in Italy resulting from fear of COVID-19. Lancet Child Adolesc Health. 2020;4(5):e10–1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7146704</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32278365</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mantica G, Riccardi N, Terrone C, Gratarola A. Non-COVID-19 visits to emergency departments during the pandemic: the impact of fear. Public Health. 2020;183:40–1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7203034</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32417567</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmadi S, Kazemi-Karyani A, Badiee N, Byford S, Mohammadi A, Piroozi B, et al. The impact of COVID-19 pandemic on hospital admissions for nine diseases in Iran: insight from an interrupted time series analysis. Cost Eff Resource Allocation. 2022;20(1):58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9628075</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36319966</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>https://landinfo.no/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/Report-Iran-Welfare-system-12082020.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doshmangir L, Bazyar M, Rashidian A, Gordeev VS. Iran health insurance system in transition: equity concerns and steps to achieve universal health coverage. Int J Equity Health. 2021;20(1):37.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7807408</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33446202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davari M, Haycox A, Walley T. The Iranian health insurance system; past experiences, present challenges and future strategies. Iran J Public Health. 2012;41(9):1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3494208</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23193499</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soleymani F, Godman B, Yarimanesh P, Kebriaeezadeh A. Prescribing patterns of physicians working in both the direct and indirect treatment sectors in Iran; findings and implications. J Pharm Health Serv Res. 2019;10(4):407–13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salimi R, Gomar R, Heshmati B. The COVID-19 outbreak in Iran. J Global Health. 2020;10(1).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7296218</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32566156</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bernal JL, Cummins S, Gasparrini A. Interrupted time series regression for the evaluation of public health interventions: a tutorial. Int J Epidemiol. 2017;46(1):348–55.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5407170</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27283160</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang H, Feng X, Lange S, Tran A, Manthey J, Rehm J. Estimating effects of health policy interventions using interrupted time-series analyses: a simulation study. BMC Med Res Methodol. 2022;22(1):235.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9429656</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36045338</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heydarian M, Behzadifar M, Chalitsios CV, Keshvari M, Omidifar R, Ghanbari MK, et al. Effect of COVID-19 on the number of CT-scans and MRI Services of Public Hospitals in Iran: an interrupted Time Series Analysis. Ethiop J Health Sci. 2021;31(6):1109–14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8968382</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35392347</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park K, Byeon J, Yang Y, Cho H. Healthcare utilisation for elderly people at the onset of the COVID-19 pandemic in South Korea. BMC Geriatr. 2022;22(1):395.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9072758</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35524173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ishikawa T, Sato J, Hattori J, Goda K, Kitsuregawa M, Mitsutake N. The association between telehealth utilization and policy responses on COVID-19 in Japan: interrupted time-series analysis. Interact J Med Res. 2022;11(2):e39181.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9278403</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35752952</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karami Matin B, Hajizadeh M, Najafi F, Homaie Rad E, Piroozi B, Rezaei S. The impact of health sector evolution plan on hospitalization and cesarean section rates in Iran: an interrupted time series analysis. Int J Qual Health Care. 2018;30(1):75–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29272503</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J, Spencer A, Hulme C, Corbett A, Khan Z, Da Silva MV, et al. Healthcare utilisation, physical activity and mental health during COVID-19 lockdown: an interrupted time-series analysis of older adults in England. Eur J Ageing. 2022;19(4):1617–30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9702630</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36467547</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Linden A. Conducting interrupted time-series analysis for single-and multiple-group comparisons. Stata J. 2015;15(2):480–500.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yucel M, Avsar C. The effect of COVID-19 pandemic on biochemistry laboratory test consumption numbers and variety. De Gruyter; 2020. pp. 339–41.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lerner EB, Newgard CD, Mann NC. Effect of the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic on the US emergency medical services system: a preliminary report. Acad Emerg Med. 2020;27(8):693–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7323429</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32557999</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luxenburg O, Saban M, Myers V, Vaknin S, Boldor N, Wilf-Miron R. National and regional trends in MRI utilization in the face of the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic. Isr J Health Policy Res. 2021;10(1):1–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8280577</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34266476</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubin GD, Ryerson CJ, Haramati LB, Sverzellati N, Kanne JP, Raoof S, et al. The role of chest imaging in patient management during the COVID-19 pandemic: a multinational consensus statement from the Fleischner Society. Radiology. 2020;296(1):172–80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7233395</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32255413</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loftus TM, Wessling EG, Cruz DS, Schmidt MJ, Kim HS, McCarthy DM, et al. Impact of the COVID pandemic on emergency department CT utilization: where do we go from here? Emerg Radiol. 2022;29(5):879–85.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9212207</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35729442</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stamenova V, Chu C, Pang A, Fang J, Shakeri A, Cram P, et al. Virtual care use during the COVID-19 pandemic and its impact on healthcare utilization in patients with chronic disease: a population-based repeated cross-sectional study. PLoS ONE. 2022;17(4):e0267218.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9037937</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35468168</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koonin LM, Hoots B, Tsang CA, Leroy Z, Farris K, Jolly T, et al. Trends in the Use of Telehealth during the emergence of the COVID-19 pandemic - United States, January-March 2020. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2020;69(43):1595–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7641006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33119561</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>