<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39450012</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2156-8650</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>34</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Medical science educator</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Med Sci Educ</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Using Disruptive Technologies in the Anatomy Discipline After the COVID-19 Pandemic: A Scoping Review.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1215</StartPage><EndPage>1229</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1215-1229</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s40670-024-02080-2</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>COVID-19 pandemic health restrictions affected the theoretical and practical teaching of anatomy. This review aims to analyze studies about teaching anatomy in this period. A search through the PubMed/Medline, Scopus, Lilacs, Web of Science, and Google Scholar databases found 1607 articles. After removing duplicates and excluding articles by reading the title/abstract, and then after full reading, 43 articles were included. The remote synchronous and asynchronous active methodologies employ virtual reality, 3D models, and web conferencing platforms to enable audio-visual interaction. While synchronous remote teaching emerged as an important opportunity, its efficacy in imparting knowledge and practical skills remains under scrutiny.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s) under exclusive licence to International Association of Medical Science Educators 2024. Springer Nature or its licensor (e.g. a society or other partner) holds exclusive rights to this article under a publishing agreement with the author(s) or other rightsholder(s); author self-archiving of the accepted manuscript version of this article is solely governed by the terms of such publishing agreement and applicable law.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>de Oliveira</LastName><ForeName>Leandro Ferreira</ForeName><Initials>LF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Ribeirão Preto School of Dentistry, Café Avenue, s / n - Campus of USP, Ribeirão Preto, 14040-904 SP Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ribeiro</LastName><ForeName>Aline Barbosa</ForeName><Initials>AB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medicine Faculty, Barão of Mauá University Center, Ribeirão Preto, SP Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Colombo</LastName><ForeName>Pedro Bortoleto</ForeName><Initials>PB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medicine, Barão of Mauá University Center, Ribeirão Preto, SP Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Makrakis</LastName><ForeName>Laís Ranieri</ForeName><Initials>LR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Ribeirão Preto School of Dentistry, Café Avenue, s / n - Campus of USP, Ribeirão Preto, 14040-904 SP Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Silva-Lovato</LastName><ForeName>Cláudia Helena</ForeName><Initials>CH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Ribeirão Preto School of Dentistry, Café Avenue, s / n - Campus of USP, Ribeirão Preto, 14040-904 SP Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ribeiro</LastName><ForeName>Adriana Barbosa</ForeName><Initials>AB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Ribeirão Preto School of Dentistry, Café Avenue, s / n - Campus of USP, Ribeirão Preto, 14040-904 SP Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>31</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Med Sci Educ</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101625548</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2156-8650</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Anatomy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Teaching methodologies</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflict of InterestThe authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39450012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11496419</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40670-024-02080-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">2080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Woolsey G. Applied surgical anatomy. New York: Lea Brothers. 1902:405–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rafai N, Lemos M, Kennes LN, Hawari A, Gerhardt-Szép S, Classen-Linke I. Anatomy meets dentistry! Linking anatomy and clinical practice in the preclinical dental curriculum. BMC Med Educ. 2016;16(1):305. 10.1186/s12909-016-0825-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5123369</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27887620</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu A, Xiao QY, McWatt S, Utomo R, Talis A, Saraci K, Brassett C, Sagoo MG, Wingate R, Chien CL, Traxler H, Waschke J, Vielmuth F, Yamada Y, Sakurai T, Zeroual M, Olsen J, El-Batti S, Viranta-Kovanen S, Keay K, Stewart W, Kunzel C, Bernd P, Kielstein H, Noël GPJC. The anatomy course during COVID-19: the impact of cadaver-based learning on the initiation of reflection on death. Med Sci Educ. 2022;32(5):1033–44. 10.1007/s40670-022-01609-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9453724</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36097588</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Co M, Cheung KYC, Cheung WS, et al. Distance education for anatomy and surgical training - a systematic review. Surgeon: J Royal Colleges Surg Edinb Irel. 2022;20(5):e195-205. 10.1016/j.surge.2021.08.001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8514899</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34483055</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almarzooq ZI, Lopes M, Kochar A. Virtual learning during the COVID-19 pandemic: a disruptive technology in graduate medical education. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2020;75(20):2635–8. 10.1016/j.jacc.2020.04.015.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7159871</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32304797</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turney BW. Anatomy in a modern medical curriculum. Ann R Coll Surg Engl. 2007;89(2):104–7. 10.1308/003588407X168244.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1964553</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17346399</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sugand K, Abrahams P, Khurana A. The anatomy of anatomy: a review for its modernization. Anat Sci Educ. 2010;3(2):83–93. 10.1002/ase.139.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20205265</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naidoo N, Akhras A, Banerjee Y. Confronting the challenges of anatomy education in a competency-based medical curriculum during normal and unprecedented times (COVID-19 pandemic): pedagogical framework development and implementation. JMIR Med Educ. 2020;6(2):e21701. 10.2196/21701.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7546732</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32873536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alsoufi A, Alsuyihili A, Msherghi A, Elhadi A, Atiyah H, Ashini A, Ashwieb A, Ghula M, Ben Hasan H, Abudabuos S, Alameen H, Abokhdhir T, Anaiba M, Nagib T, Shuwayyah A, Benothman R, Arrefae G, Alkhwayildi A, Alhadi A, Zaid A, Elhadi M. Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on medical education: medical students’ knowledge, attitudes, and practices regarding electronic learning. PLoS ONE. 2020;15(11):e0242905. 10.1371/journal.pone.0242905.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7688124</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33237962</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li J, Nie L, Li Z, Lin L, Tang L, Ouyang J. Maximizing modern distribution of complex anatomical spatial information: 3D reconstruction and rapid prototype production of anatomical corrosion casts of human specimens. Anat Sci Educ. 2012;5(6):330–9. 10.1002/ase.1287.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22653786</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng X, Chan LK, Pan SQ, Cai H, Li YQ, Yang X. Gross anatomy education in China during the COVID-19 pandemic: a national survey. Anat Sci Educ. 2021;14(1):8–18. 10.1002/ase.2036.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33217164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Nuland SE, Eagleson R, Rogers KA. Educational software usability: artifact or design? Anat Sci Educ. 2017;10(2):190–9. 10.1002/ase.1636.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27472554</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nicholson DT, Chalk C, Funnell WR, Daniel SJ. Can virtual reality improve anatomy education? A randomised controlled study of a computer-generated three-dimensional anatomical ear model. Med Educ. 2006;40(11):1081–7. 10.1111/j.1365-2929.2006.02611.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17054617</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Darras KE, Spouge R, Hatala R, Nicolaou S, Hu J, Worthington A, Krebs C, Forster BB. Integrated virtual and cadaveric dissection laboratories enhance first year medical students’ anatomy experience: a pilot study. BMC Med Educ. 2019;19(1):366. 10.1186/s12909-019-1806-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6781397</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31590672</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hanaei S, Takian A, Majdzadeh R, Maboloc CR, Grossmann I, Gomes O, Milosevic M, Gupta M, Shamshirsaz AA, Harbi A, Burhan AM, Uddin LQ, Kulasinghe A, Lam CM, Ramakrishna S, Alavi A, Nouwen JL, Dorigo T, Schreiber M, Abraham A, Shelkovaya N, Krysztofiak W, Ebrahimi Warkiani M, Sellke F, Ogino S, Barba FJ, Brand S, Vasconcelos C, Salunke DB, Rezaei N. Emerging standards and the hybrid model for organizing scientific events during and after the COVID-19 pandemic. Disaster Med Public Health Prep. 2022;16(3):1172–7. 10.1017/dmp.2020.406.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8129682</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33100253</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tricco AC, Lillie E, Zarin W, O’Brien KK, Colquhoun H, Levac D, Moher D, Peters MDJ, Horsley T, Weeks L, Hempel S, Akl EA, Chang C, McGowan J, Stewart L, Hartling L, Aldcroft A, Wilson MG, Garritty C, Lewin S, Godfrey CM, Macdonald MT, Langlois EV, Soares-Weiser K, Moriarty J, Clifford T, Tunçalp Ö, Straus SE. PRISMA extension for scoping reviews (PRISMA-ScR): checklist and explanation. Ann Intern Med. 2018;169(7):467–73. 10.7326/M18-0850.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30178033</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Page MJ, McKenzie JE, Bossuyt PM, Boutron I, Hoffmann TC, Mulrow CD, Shamseer L, Tetzlaff JM, Moher D. Updating guidance for reporting systematic reviews: development of the PRISMA 2020 statement. J Clin Epidemiol. 2021;134:103–12. 10.1016/j.jclinepi.2021.02.003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33577987</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Longhurst GJ, Stone DM, Dulohery K, Scully D, Campbell T, Smith CF, Strength. Weakness, opportunity, threat (SWOT) analysis of the adaptations to anatomical education in the United Kingdom and Republic of Ireland in response to the Covid-19 pandemic. Anat Sci Educ. 2020;13(3):301–11. 10.1002/ase.1967.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7264742</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32306550</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pather N, Blyth P, Chapman JA, Dayal MR, Flack NAMS, Fogg QA, Green RA, Hulme AK, Johnson IP, Meyer AJ, Morley JW, Shortland PJ, Štrkalj G, Štrkalj M, Valter K, Webb AL, Woodley SJ, Lazarus MD. Forced disruption of anatomy education in Australia and New Zealand: an acute response to the Covid-19 pandemic. Anat Sci Educ. 2020;13(3):284–300. 10.1002/ase.1968.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7264523</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32306555</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shin M, Prasad A, Sabo G, Macnow ASR, Sheth NP, Cross MB, Premkumar A. Anatomy education in US medical schools: before, during, and beyond COVID-19. BMC Med Educ. 2022;22(1):103. 10.1186/s12909-022-03177-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8851737</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35172819</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harmon DJ, Attardi SM, Barremkala M, Bentley DC, Brown KM, Dennis JF, Goldman HM, Harrell KM, Klein BA, Ramnanan CJ, Richtsmeier JT, Farkas GJ. An analysis of anatomy education before and during COVID-19: May-August. Anat Sci Educ. 2021;14(2):132–47. 10.1002/ase.2051.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33387389</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iwanaga J, Kamura Y, Nishimura Y, Terada S, Kishimoto N, Tanaka T, Tubbs RS. A new option for education during surgical procedures and related clinical anatomy in a virtual reality workspace. Clin Anat. 2021;34(3):496–503. 10.1002/ca.23724.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33502787</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flynn W, Kumar N, Donovan R, Jones M, Vickerton P. Delivering online alternatives to the anatomy laboratory: early experience during the COVID-19 pandemic. Clin Anat. 2021;34(5):757–65. 10.1002/ca.23722.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8014296</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33470455</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iravani M, Nasab MB, Bahmaei H, Ghanbari S, Mohaghegh Z, Siahkal SF. The level of satisfaction and quality of e-learning in medical universities of Iran during the epidemic of COVID-19. J Educ Health Promot. 2022;11:9. 10.4103/jehp.jehp_1555_20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8893104</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35281399</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singal A, Bansal A, Chaudhary P, Singh H, Patra A. Anatomy education of medical and dental students during COVID-19 pandemic: a reality check. Surg Radiol Anat. 2021;43(4):515–21. 10.1007/s00276-020-02615-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7672260</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33206209</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thom ML, Kimble BA, Qua K, Wish-Baratz S. Is remote near-peer anatomy teaching an effective teaching strategy? Lessons learned from the transition to online learning during the Covid-19 pandemic. Anat Sci Educ. 2021;14(5):552–61. 10.1002/ase.2122.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8426839</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34268899</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lisiecki JL, Johnson SP, Grant D, Chung KC. Learners’ responses to a virtual cadaver dissection nerve course in the COVID era: a survey study. Arch Plast Surg. 2022;49(5):676–82. 10.1055/s-0042-1756351.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9507583</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36159381</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uzuner MB, Nalbant A, Geneci F, Turhan E. Thought, attitudes, and practices of the anatomy departments on receiving and embalming cadavers during the pandemic process. Int J Morphol [online]. 2022;40(3):801–7. 10.4067/S0717-95022022000300801.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shojaei A, Feili A, Kojuri J, Norafshan A, Bazrafkan L. The blacksmith approach: a strategy for teaching and learning in the medical anatomy course (a qualitative study). BMC Med Educ. 2022;22(1):728. 10.1186/s12909-022-03800-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9584281</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36266705</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown KE, Heise N, Eitel CM, Nelson J, Garbe BA, Meyer CA, Ivie KR Jr, Clapp TR. A large-scale, multiplayer virtual reality deployment: a novel approach to distance education in human anatomy. Med Sci Educ. 2023;33(2):409–21. 10.1007/s40670-023-01751-w.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9933027</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36820280</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stone D, Longhurst GJ, Dulohery K, Campbell T, Richards A, O’Brien D, Franchi T, Hall S, Border S. A multicentre analysis of approaches to learning and student experiences of learning anatomy online. Med Sci Educ. 2022;32(5):1117–30. 10.1007/s40670-022-01633-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9483883</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36160292</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hatcher AR, Pearson AS, Platt KM. A quality improvement apprenticeship: gross anatomy in the time of COVID-19. Anat Sci Educ. 2022;15(5):970–9. 10.1002/ase.2212.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9353286</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35892188</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jumaa MI, Hanafy SM, Arafa MA. With the new challenges of COVID- 19, can we depend entirely on online learning for higher education in the medical schools? Adv Med Educ Pract. 2022;13:829–37. 10.2147/AMEP.S368438.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9373998</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35968537</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim CY, Park JS, Lee JH, Ha HM, Chung BS. Effects of open board lecture videos on anatomy. Int J Morphol. 2022;40(4):1117–22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McNamara JP, Nolan MF. COVID-19 modifications to a first year medical human anatomy course: effects on student performance on summative examinations. Clin Anat. 2023;36(1):83–91. 10.1002/ca.23965.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9874716</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36216782</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salman A, Qureshi AS, Umar Z, Riaz M, Usman M, Zulfiqar S, Ali U, Saeed H. Effects of COVID-19 pandemic on anatomy education of medical and dental students of Pakistan; a reality check. Surg Radiol Anat. 2022;44(11):1495–500. 10.1007/s00276-022-03034-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9580425</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36260136</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fisher D, Solomons D, Makhathini KB. Face-to-face versus online-based lectures: a COVID-19 induced study on assessments. Front Educ. 2022;7:1–17. 10.3389/feduc.2022.1045311.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pręgowska A, Osial M, Dolega-Dolegowski D, Kolecki R, Proniewska K. Information and communication technologies combined with mixed reality as supporting tools in medical education. Electronics. 2022;11(22):3778. 10.3390/electronics11223778.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang CW, Mullen CR, Johnson SP, Grant DW, Lisiecki JL, Chung KC. Innovation in delivering a live, virtual cadaver dissection course. Plast Reconstr Surg. 2022;150(4):e909-12. 10.1097/PRS.0000000000009563.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35939640</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chimmalgi M, Rajesh S, Kumar KVA, Asha UV, Jose JE, Chandrakumari K. Problem-based learning using online platforms: an interactive alternative to mandatory e-learning during the COVID-19 pandemic. J Anat Soc India. 2022;71(3):178–85. 10.4103/jasi.jasi_13_22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohamed R, Benjamin LA, Sahu PK. Online anatomy teaching during the COVID-19 pandemic: assessing the perceptions of undergraduate veterinary medical students. J Adv Vet Anim Res. 2022;9(3):453–62. 10.5455/javar.2022.i614.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9597925</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36382038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kochhar S, Tasnim T, Gupta A. Is cadaveric dissection essential in medical education? A qualitative survey comparing pre-and post-COVID-19 anatomy courses. J Osteopath Med. 2022;123(1):19–26. 10.1515/jom-2022-0016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36039567</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vedi N, Dulloo P, Singh P. Digital technology for facilitating inquiry-based learning during the COVID pandemic for human anatomy course. J Educ Health Promot. 2022;11:344. 10.4103/jehp.jehp_38_22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9768716</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36567995</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bayazit A, Apaydin N, Gonullu I. Predicting at-risk students in an online flipped anatomy course using learning analytics. Educ Sci. 2022;12(9):581. 10.3390/educsci12090581.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khojasteh L, Zahra K, Elham N, Sedigheh S, Majidreza F. E-learning-based medical education during COVID19 pandemic from medical students’ viewpoints. 2021;1–25. 10.21203/rs.3.rs-234844/v1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kazoka D, Pilmane M. Remote practical anatomy classes: new challenges and directions for tutors. Society. Integration.Education. Proceedings of the International Scientific Conference. Proc Int Scientific Conf. 2021;I:247–258. 10.17770/sie2021vol1.6195.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stunden C, Zakani S, Martin A, Moodley S, Jacob J. Replicating anatomical teaching specimens using 3D modeling embedded within a multimodal e-learning course: pre-post study exploring the impact on medical education during COVID-19. JMIR Med Educ. 2021;7(4):e30533. 10.2196/30533.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8663546</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34787589</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pollock NB. Student performance and perceptions of anatomy and physiology across face-to-face, hybrid, and online teaching lab styles. Adv Physiol Educ. 2022;46(3):453–60. 10.1152/advan.00074.2022.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35759525</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hadžiomerović N, Hadžiomerović AI, Avdić R, Muminović A, Tandir F, Bejdić P, Pandžić A. Students’ performance in teaching neuroanatomy using traditional and technology-based methods. Anat Histol Embryol. 2023;52(1):115–22. 10.1111/ahe.12876.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36259629</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Albalushi H, Al Mushaiqri M, Sirasanagandla SR, Das S. Students’ performance in face-to-face, online, and hybrid methods of teaching and assessment in anatomy. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19(20):13318. 10.3390/ijerph192013318.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9602488</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36293903</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schulte H, Schmiedl A, Mühlfeld C, Knudsen L. Teaching gross anatomy during the COVID-19 pandemic: effects on medical students’ gain of knowledge, confidence levels and pandemic-related concerns. Ann Anat. 2022;244:151986. 10.1016/j.aanat.2022.151986.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9334863</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35914632</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sánchez-Ramírez C, Alarcón E, Bravo L, Paredes P, Nova P, Iturra-González A, Valdés I, Ortiz A. How were modified the human anatomy study habits during and after confinement by the COVID-19 pandemic? Int J Morphology. 2022;40(6):1484–9. 10.4067/S0717-95022022000601484.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fox AL, Dallaghan GLB, Gilliland KO. The effectiveness of a virtual anatomy curriculum versus traditional cadaveric dissection in UNC SOM’s first-year class. Med Sci Educ. 2022;32(6):1319–21. 10.1007/s40670-022-01646-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9517981</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36193110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hortsch M. The Michigan Histology website as an example of a free anatomical resource serving learners and educators worldwide. Anat Sci Educ. 2023;16(3):363–71. 10.1002/ase.2239.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36453096</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chisci E, Parlani G, Gatta E, Isernia G, de Donato G, Antonello M, Simonte G, Kölbel T, Bertoglio L, Yeung KK, Donas K, Fazzini S, Dias N, Michelagnoli S, Televascolare Games Group. The new educational project televascular games during the coronavirus disease 2019 pandemic. J Vasc Surg Cases Innov Tech. 2022;8(4):638–45. 10.1016/j.jvscit.2022.05.019.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9296369</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35873717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cardoso-Júnior A, Faria RMD. Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on students’ motivation in relation to asynchronous anatomy video lectures. Med Sci Educ. 2022;33(1):119–28. 10.1007/s40670-022-01714-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9753862</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36536828</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banovac I, Kovačić N, Hladnik A, Blažević A, Bičanić I, Petanjek Z, Katavić V. In the eye of the beholder - how course delivery affects anatomy education. Ann Anat. 2023;246:152043. 10.1016/j.aanat.2022.152043.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9762916</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36549401</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ouzzani M, Hammady H, Fedorowicz Z, Elmagarmid A. Rayyan-a web and mobile app for systematic reviews. Syst Rev. 2016;5(1):210. 10.1186/s13643-016-0384-4. PMID: 27919275; PMCID: PMC5139140.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5139140</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27919275</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ratinaud P, Marchand P. Application De La méthode ALCESTE à de gros corpus et stabilité des mondes lexicaux: analyse Du CableGate avec IraMuTeQ. In: Actes des 11eme Journées internationales d’Analyse statistique des Données textuelles. Belgique: JADT, Liège; 2012. p. 835–44.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steil AV, Dias NM, Lopes FM, Silva MLBD, Bousfield ABDS, De Luca Canto G. Reporting characteristics of systematic reviews in psychology: a scoping review. J Health Psychol. 2022;27(13):2964–81. 10.1177/13591053221074592.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35148652</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Onigbinde OA, Ajagbe AO, Oyeniran OI, Chia T. Post-COVID-19 pandemic: standard operating procedures for gross anatomy laboratory in the new standard. Morphologie. 2021;105(350):196–203. 10.1016/j.morpho.2020.10.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7572044</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33268295</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Attardi SM, Harmon DJ, Barremkala M, Bentley DC, Brown KM, Dennis JF, Goldman HM, Harrell KM, Klein BA, Ramnanan CJ, Farkas GJ. An analysis of anatomy education before and during COVID-19: August-December 2020. Anat Sci Educ. 2022;15(1):5–26. 10.1002/ase.2152.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8653345</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34758206</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>