<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39458123</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2077-0383</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><Issue>20</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>17</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of clinical medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Clin Med</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Impact of Comorbidities and Skin Diseases on Post-Vaccination Reactions: A Study on COVID-19 Vaccinations in Poland.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">6173</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3390/jcm13206173</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText><b>Background:</b> The COVID-19 pandemic necessitated rapid and widespread vaccination efforts, which proved critical in reducing the severity and mortality of the virus. However, the interplay between vaccinations, pre-existing skin conditions, and other comorbidities still needs to be explored. This study investigated the occurrence and severity of adverse events following immunization (AEFIs) with COVID-19 vaccines in individuals with chronic skin diseases and comorbidities within a Central European cohort. <b>Methods:</b> An anonymous online survey was conducted between May 2022 and February 2023, targeting students and employees of universities in Wrocław, Poland. A total of 513 respondents were analyzed, focusing on AEFIs following the first, second, and third doses of COVID-19 vaccines and the effects of COVID-19 on conditions such as atopic dermatitis, psoriasis, vitiligo, acne vulgaris, rosacea, and various comorbidities. <b>Results:</b> COVID-19 vaccination effectively protected against severe disease across all doses. The analysis revealed no significant impact of either COVID-19 infection or vaccination on the course of selected skin diseases and comorbidities. The reporting of AEFIs to the Sanitary Inspection was notably low. The Moderna and Pfizer mRNA-based vaccines were associated with a higher reported number of AEFIs, particularly after the second and third doses, compared to AstraZeneca, which exhibited fewer adverse events after subsequent doses. <b>Conclusions:</b> COVID-19 vaccination is both safe and effective, even in patients with pre-existing skin conditions and comorbidities. Vaccine selection may benefit from considering individual health profiles, and better reporting of AEFIs is needed to enhance vaccine safety monitoring.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jęśkowiak-Kossakowska</LastName><ForeName>Izabela</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8829-4482</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacology, Faculty of Medicine, Wroclaw Medical University, Mikulicza-Radeckiego 2, 50-345 Wroclaw, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nowotarska</LastName><ForeName>Paulina</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biostructure and Animal Physiology, Wroclaw University of Environmental and Life Sciences, Norwida 25/27, 50-375 Wroclaw, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Grosman-Dziewiszek</LastName><ForeName>Patrycja</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7362-6571</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacology, Faculty of Medicine, Wroclaw Medical University, Mikulicza-Radeckiego 2, 50-345 Wroclaw, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Szeląg</LastName><ForeName>Adam</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8104-5267</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacology, Faculty of Medicine, Wroclaw Medical University, Mikulicza-Radeckiego 2, 50-345 Wroclaw, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wiatrak</LastName><ForeName>Benita</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1404-2274</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacology, Faculty of Medicine, Wroclaw Medical University, Mikulicza-Radeckiego 2, 50-345 Wroclaw, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>J Clin Med</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101606588</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2077-0383</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19 vaccination</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Poland</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">adverse events</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">comorbidities</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">skin diseases</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vaccine safety</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39458123</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11508506</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/jcm13206173</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">jcm13206173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Awan M.H., Samreen S., Salim B., Gul H., Perveen S., Nasim A. Corona Virus Disease-19 Vaccine-Associated Autoimmune Disorders. Rheumatol. Immunol. Res. 2022;3:111–119. doi: 10.2478/rir-2022-0019.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2478/rir-2022-0019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9895874</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36788969</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fadlyana E., Rusmil K., Tarigan R., Rahmadi A.R., Prodjosoewojo S., Sofiatin Y., Khrisna C.V., Sari R.M., Setyaningsih L., Surachman F., et al. A Phase III, Observer-Blind, Randomized, Placebo-Controlled Study of the Efficacy, Safety, and Immunogenicity of SARS-CoV-2 Inactivated Vaccine in Healthy Adults Aged 18–59 Years: An Interim Analysis in Indonesia. Vaccine. 2021;39:6520–6528. doi: 10.1016/j.vaccine.2021.09.052.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2021.09.052</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8461222</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34620531</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fang X., Qiao S., Zhang R., Yang T., Wang Z., Kong Q., Sun M., Geng J., Fang C., Chen Y., et al. Effects of Coronavirus Disease 2019 Vaccination on Seizures in Patients with Epilepsy. Chin. Med. J. 2023;136:571–577. doi: 10.1097/CM9.0000000000002558.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/CM9.0000000000002558</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10106124</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36848187</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uwamino Y., Kurafuji T., Sato Y., Tomita Y., Shibata A., Tanabe A., Yatabe Y., Noguchi M., Arai T., Ohno A., et al. Young Age, Female Sex, and Presence of Systemic Adverse Reactions Are Associated with High Post-Vaccination Antibody Titer after Two Doses of BNT162b2 MRNA SARS-CoV-2 Vaccination: An Observational Study of 646 Japanese Healthcare Workers and University Staff. Vaccine. 2022;40:1019–1025. doi: 10.1016/j.vaccine.2022.01.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2022.01.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8739021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35033389</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niebel D., Wenzel J., Wilsmann-Theis D., Ziob J., Wilhelmi J., Braegelmann C. Single-Center Clinico-Pathological Case Study of 19 Patients with Cutaneous Adverse Reactions Following COVID-19 Vaccines. Dermatopathology. 2021;8:463–476. doi: 10.3390/dermatopathology8040049.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/dermatopathology8040049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8544472</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34698094</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Shitany N.A., Bagher A.M., Binmahfouz L.S., Eid B.G., Almukadi H., Badr-Eldin S.M., El-Hamamsy M., Mohammedsaleh Z.M., Saleh F.M., Almuhayawi M.S., et al. The Adverse Reactions of Pfizer BioNTech COVID-19 Vaccine Booster Dose Are Mild and Similar to the Second Dose Responses: A Retrospective Cross-Sectional Study. Int. J. Gen. Med. 2022;15:6821–6836. doi: 10.2147/IJGM.S376316.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/IJGM.S376316</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9426871</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36051568</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cantisani C., Chello C., Grieco T., Ambrosio L., Kiss N., Tammaro A., Tosti G., Paolino G., Pellacani G. Cutaneous Reactions to COVID-19 Vaccines in a Monocentric Study: A Case Series. J. Clin. Med. 2022;11:3811. doi: 10.3390/jcm11133811.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/jcm11133811</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9267144</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35807096</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sampath V., Rabinowitz G., Shah M., Jain S., Diamant Z., Jesenak M., Rabin R., Vieths S., Agache I., Akdis M., et al. Vaccines and Allergic Reactions: The Past, the Current COVID-19 Pandemic, and Future Perspectives. Allergy Eur. J. Allergy Clin. Immunol. 2021;76:1640–1660. doi: 10.1111/all.14840.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/all.14840</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8251022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33811364</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rogers A., Rooke E., Morant S., Guthrie G., Doney A., Duncan A., MacKenzie I., Barr R., Pigazzani F., Zutis K., et al. Adverse Events and Overall Health and Well-Being after COVID-19 Vaccination: Interim Results from the VAC4COVID Cohort Safety Study. BMJ Open. 2022;12:e060583. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2021-060583.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2021-060583</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9160588</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35649591</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cai C., Peng Y., Shen E., Huang Q., Chen Y., Liu P., Guo C., Feng Z., Gao L., Zhang X., et al. A Comprehensive Analysis of the Efficacy and Safety of COVID-19 Vaccines. Mol. Ther. 2021;29:2794–2805. doi: 10.1016/j.ymthe.2021.08.001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ymthe.2021.08.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8342868</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34365034</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim M.A., Lee Y.W., Kim S.R., Kim J.H., Min T.K., Park H.S., Shin M., Ye Y.M., Lee S., Lee J., et al. COVID-19 Vaccine-Associated Anaphylaxis and Allergic Reactions: Consensus Statements of the KAAACI Urticaria/Angioedema/Anaphylaxis Working Group. Allergy Asthma Immunol. Res. 2021;13:526–544. doi: 10.4168/aair.2021.13.4.526.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4168/aair.2021.13.4.526</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8255352</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34212542</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Romantowski J., Kruszewski J., Solarski O., Bant A., Chciałowski A., Pietrzyk I., Sańpruch P., Górska A., Chełmińska M., Knurowska A., et al. Protocol of Safe Vaccination against COVID-19 in Patients with High Risk of Allergic Reactions. Clin. Transl. Allergy. 2022;12:e12152. doi: 10.1002/clt2.12152.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/clt2.12152</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9112196</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35601631</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jęśkowiak I., Wiatrak B., Grosman-Dziewiszek P., Szeląg A. The Incidence and Severity of Post-Vaccination Reactions after Vaccination against COVID-19. Vaccines. 2021;9:502. doi: 10.3390/vaccines9050502.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/vaccines9050502</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8152224</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34067955</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu K., Wang Z., Qin M., Gao Y., Luo N., Xie W., Zou Y., Wang J., Ma X. A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis of the Effectiveness and Safety of COVID-19 Vaccination in Older Adults. Front. Immunol. 2023;14:1113156. doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2023.1113156.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2023.1113156</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10020204</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36936964</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du Y., Chen L., Shi Y. Safety, Immunogenicity, and Efficacy of COVID-19 Vaccines in Adolescents, Children, and Infants: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. Front. Public Health. 2022;10:829176. doi: 10.3389/fpubh.2022.829176.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2022.829176</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9046659</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35493393</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y., Zhang Y., Zhang M., Zhang X., Li H., Wang Y., Wang W., Ji J., Wu L., Zheng D. The Prevalence of Adverse Reactions among Individuals with Three-Dose COVID-19 Vaccination. J. Infect. Public Health. 2023;16:125–132. doi: 10.1016/j.jiph.2022.12.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jiph.2022.12.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9724502</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36516647</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang Y., Chen H., Lv J., Huang T., Zhang R., Zhang D., Luo L., Wei S., Liu X., Zhang S., et al. Evaluation of Immunogenicity and Safety of Vero Cell-Derived Inactivated COVID-19 Vaccine in Older Patients with Hypertension and Diabetes Mellitus. Vaccines. 2022;10:1020. doi: 10.3390/vaccines10071020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/vaccines10071020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9315836</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35891184</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoffmann M.A., Wieler H.J., Enders P., Buchholz H.G., Plachter B. Age- and Sex-Graded Data Evaluation of Vaccination Reactions after Initial Injection of the Bnt162b2 Mrna Vaccine in a Local Vaccination Center in Germany. Vaccines. 2021;9:911. doi: 10.3390/vaccines9080911.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/vaccines9080911</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8402474</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34452036</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Granados Villalpando J.M., de Romero Tapia S.J., del Baeza Flores G.C., Ble Castillo J.L., Juarez Rojop I.E., Lopez Junco F.I., Olvera Hernández V., Quiroz Gomez S., Ruiz Quiñones J.A., Guzmán Priego C.G. Prevalence and Risk Factors of Adverse Effects and Allergic Reactions after COVID-19 Vaccines in a Mexican Population: An Analytical Cross-Sectional Study. Vaccines. 2022;10:2012. doi: 10.3390/vaccines10122012.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/vaccines10122012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9781330</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36560422</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gianfredi V., Minerva M., Casu G., Capraro M., Chiecca G., Gaetti G., Mazzocchi R.M., Musarò P., Basteri P., Bertini B., et al. Immediate Adverse Events Following COVID-19 Immunization. A Cross-Sectional Study of 314,664 Italian Subjects. Acta Biomed. 2021;92:e2021487. doi: 10.23750/abm.v92iS6.12365.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.23750/abm.v92iS6.12365</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8851022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34739452</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duijster J.W., Lieber T., Pacelli S., Van Balveren L., Ruijs L.S., Raethke M., Kant A., Van Hunsel F. Sex-Disaggregated Outcomes of Adverse Events after COVID-19 Vaccination: A Dutch Cohort Study and Review of the Literature. Front. Immunol. 2023;14:1078736. doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2023.1078736.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2023.1078736</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9922710</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36793715</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sánchez-Saez F., Peiró S., Cuenca L., Vanaclocha H., Limón R., Salas D., Burgos J.S., Sánchez-Payá J., Meneu R., Díez J., et al. Side Effects during the Week after First Dose Vaccination with Four COVID-19 Vaccines. Results of the ProVaVac Survey Study with 13,837 People in Spain. Vaccine. 2022;40:5942–5949. doi: 10.1016/j.vaccine.2022.08.028.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2022.08.028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9420721</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36068110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loosen S.H., Bohlken J., Weber K., Konrad M., Luedde T., Roderburg C., Kostev K. Factors Associated with Non-Severe Adverse Reactions after Vaccination against SARS-CoV-2: A Cohort Study of 908,869 Outpatient Vaccinations in Germany. Vaccines. 2022;10:566. doi: 10.3390/vaccines10040566.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/vaccines10040566</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9032707</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35455315</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watanabe M., Balena A., Tuccinardi D., Tozzi R., Risi R., Masi D., Caputi A., Rossetti R., Spoltore M.E., Filippi V., et al. Central Obesity, Smoking Habit, and Hypertension Are Associated with Lower Antibody Titres in Response to COVID-19 MRNA Vaccine. Diabetes Metab. Res. Rev. 2022;38:e3465. doi: 10.1002/dmrr.3465.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/dmrr.3465</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8209952</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33955644</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chenchula S., Vidyasagar K., Pathan S., Sharma S., Chavan M.R., Bhagavathula A.S., Padmavathi R., Manjula M., Chhabra M., Gupta R., et al. Global Prevalence and Effect of Comorbidities and Smoking Status on Severity and Mortality of COVID-19 in Association with Age and Gender: A Systematic Review, Meta-Analysis and Meta-Regression. Sci. Rep. 2023;13:6415. doi: 10.1038/s41598-023-33314-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-023-33314-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10115382</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37076543</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bots S.H., Riera-Arnau J., Belitser S.V., Messina D., Aragón M., Alsina E., Douglas I.J., Durán C.E., García-Poza P., Gini R., et al. Myocarditis and Pericarditis Associated with SARS-CoV-2 Vaccines: A Population-Based Descriptive Cohort and a Nested Self-Controlled Risk Interval Study Using Electronic Health Care Data from Four European Countries. Front. Pharmacol. 2022;13:1038043. doi: 10.3389/fphar.2022.1038043.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fphar.2022.1038043</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9730238</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36506571</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Couderc A.L., Ninove L., Nouguerède E., Rey D., Rebroin M., Daumas A., Tomasini P., Greillier L., Salas S., Duffaud F., et al. Acceptance, Efficacy, and Safety of COVID-19 Vaccination in Older Patients with Cancer. J. Geriatr. Oncol. 2022;13:850–855. doi: 10.1016/j.jgo.2022.05.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jgo.2022.05.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9108027</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35589542</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shulman R.M., Weinberg D.S., Ross E.A., Ruth K., Rall G.F., Olszanski A.J., Helstrom J., Hall M.J., Judd J., Chen D.Y.T., et al. Adverse Events Reported by Patients With Cancer After Administration of a 2-Dose MRNA COVID-19 Vaccine. JNCCN J. Natl. Compr. Cancer Netw. 2022;20:160–166. doi: 10.6004/jnccn.2021.7113.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.6004/jnccn.2021.7113</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9664486</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35130494</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weaver K.N., Zhang X., Dai X., Watkins R., Adler J., Dubinsky M.C., Kastl A., Bousvaros A., Strople J.A., Cross R.K., et al. Impact of SARS-CoV-2 Vaccination on Inflammatory Bowel Disease Activity and Development of Vaccine-Related Adverse Events: Results From PREVENT-COVID. Inflamm. Bowel Dis. 2022;28:1497–1505. doi: 10.1093/ibd/izab302.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ibd/izab302</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8822409</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34871388</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miyazaki H., Watanabe D., Ito Y., Ikeda S., Okamoto N., Tokunaga E., Ku Y., Ooi M., Hoshi N., Kodama Y. Differences in Coronavirus Disease—19 Vaccination Related Side Effects in Patients with Ulcerative Colitis and Crohn’s Disease in Japan. Indian J. Gastroenterol. 2023;42:701–707. doi: 10.1007/s12664-023-01386-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12664-023-01386-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37505394</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wasserbauer M., Hlava S., Trojanek M., Stovicek J., Milota T., Drabek J., Koptová P., Cupkova A., Pichlerová D., Kucerova B., et al. Efficacy and Safety of SARS-CoV-2 Vaccination in Patients with Inflammatory Bowel Disease on Immunosuppressive and Biological Therapy: Prospective Observational Study. PLoS ONE. 2022;17:e0273612. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0273612.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0273612</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9439210</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36054100</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>An Z., Figueroa-Parra G., Zhou X., Li Y., Jaquith J., McCarthy-Fruin K., Sletten J., Warrington K.J., Weyand C., Crowson C.S., et al. Immune Responses and Disease Biomarker Long-Term Changes Following COVID-19 MRNA Vaccination in a Cohort of Rheumatic Disease Patients. Front. Immunol. 2023;14:1224702. doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2023.1224702.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2023.1224702</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10424846</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37583697</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y.K., Lui M.P.K., Yam L.L., Cheng C.S., Tsang T.H.T., Kwok W.S., Chung H.Y. COVID-19 Vaccination in Patients with Rheumatic Diseases: Vaccination Rates, Patient Perspectives, and Side Effects. Immun. Inflamm. Dis. 2022;10:e589. doi: 10.1002/iid3.589.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/iid3.589</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8926511</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35099852</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeng H., Liu H., Liu Z., Zhou X., Lu X., Yan Z., Zhou Y., Dai L., Chen Y., Yang T., et al. Safety and Immunogenicity of Inactivated COVID-19 Vaccination in Adult Rheumatic Patients in South China: A Prospective Study. Hum. Vaccin Immunother. 2022;18:2090176. doi: 10.1080/21645515.2022.2090176.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/21645515.2022.2090176</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9621074</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35878733</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen C., Huang S., Geng L., Lai P., Dou H., Zhang H., Chen H., Liang J., Sun L. COVID-19 Vaccination and Infection Status: A Cross-Sectional Survey of Patients with Rheumatic Diseases in China. Rheumatol. Int. 2024;44:703–713. doi: 10.1007/s00296-023-05438-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00296-023-05438-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37897662</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kridin K., Schonmann Y., Onn E., Bitan D.T., Weinstein O., Cohen A.D. Determinants and Effectiveness of BNT162b2 MRNA Vaccination Among Patients with Atopic Dermatitis: A Population-Based Study. Am. J. Clin. Dermatol. 2022;23:385–392. doi: 10.1007/s40257-022-00672-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40257-022-00672-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8924351</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35294720</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoon D., Jeon H.L., Noh Y., Choe Y.J., Choe S.A., Jung J., Shin J.Y. A Nationwide Survey of MRNA COVID-19 Vaccinee’s Experiences on Adverse Events and Its Associated Factors. J. Korean Med. Sci. 2023;38:e170. doi: 10.3346/jkms.2023.38.e170.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3346/jkms.2023.38.e170</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10244024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37272559</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Català A., Muñoz-Santos C., Galván-Casas C., Roncero Riesco M., Revilla Nebreda D., Solá-Truyols A., Giavedoni P., Llamas-Velasco M., González-Cruz C., Cubiró X., et al. Cutaneous Reactions after SARS-CoV-2 Vaccination: A Cross-Sectional Spanish Nationwide Study of 405 Cases*. Br. J. Dermatol. 2022;186:142–152. doi: 10.1111/bjd.20639.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/bjd.20639</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8444756</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34254291</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morimoto H., Hayano S., Ozawa N., Ogura Y., Usui H., Usami T., Ohse A., Otsuka M., Miyachi M., Tokura Y. Questionnaire Survey of Possible Association of Allergic Diseases with Adverse Reactions to Sars-Cov-2 Vaccination. Vaccines. 2021;9:1421. doi: 10.3390/vaccines9121421.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/vaccines9121421</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8708946</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34960167</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang H., Lin J., Wu J., Zhang J., Zhang L., Yuan S., Chen J., Tang Q., Zhang A., Cui Y., et al. Allergic Diseases Aggravate the Symptoms of SARS-CoV-2 Infection in China. Front. Immunol. 2023;14:1284047. doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2023.1284047.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2023.1284047</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10777727</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38204754</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen C., Song X., Murdock D.J., Marcus A., Hussein M., Jalbert J.J., Geba G.P. Association between Allergic Conditions and COVID-19 Susceptibility and Outcomes. Ann. Allergy Asthma Immunol. 2024;132:637–645.e7. doi: 10.1016/j.anai.2024.01.011.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.anai.2024.01.011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38242353</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chirasuthat S., Ratanapokasatit Y., Thadanipon K., Chanprapaph K. Immunogenicity, Effectiveness, and Safety of COVID-19 Vaccines among Patients with Immune-Mediated Dermatological Diseases: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. Acta Derm. Venereol. 2024;104:adv40009. doi: 10.2340/actadv.v104.40009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2340/actadv.v104.40009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11094464</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38698654</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hren M.G., Khattri S. Low Rates of Vaccination among Atopic Dermatitis, Alopecia Areata, Psoriasis, and Psoriatic Arthritis Patients on Biologics. Arch. Dermatol. Res. 2024;316:285. doi: 10.1007/s00403-024-03037-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00403-024-03037-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38796548</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Q., Lv C., Han X., Shen M., Kuang Y. A Web-Based Survey on Factors for Unvaccination and Adverse Reactions of SARS-CoV-2 Vaccines in Chinese Patients with Psoriasis. J. Inflamm. Res. 2021;14:6265–6273. doi: 10.2147/JIR.S341429.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/JIR.S341429</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8636842</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34866925</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Genovese G., Puig L., Di Lernia V., Graceea D., Bella D.O. Immunogenicity of Three Doses of Anti-SARS-CoV-2 BNT162b2 Vaccine in Psoriasis Patients Treated with Biologics. Front. Med. 2022;9:961904</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9485492</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36148445</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaya O., Keskinkaya Z., Mermutlu S.I., Oguz-Kilic S., Cakir H. COVID-19 Among Patients with Psoriasis: A Single-Center Retrospective Cross-Sectional Study. Infect. Dis. Clin. Microbiol. 2023;5:127–135. doi: 10.36519/idcm.2023.192.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.36519/idcm.2023.192</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10986702</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38633013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi X., Sun Y., Ding X. Impact of COVID-19 Vaccine and COVID-19 Infection on Vitiligo Activity and Progression. Clin. Cosmet. Investig. Dermatol. 2023;16:3581–3587. doi: 10.2147/CCID.S439045.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/CCID.S439045</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10729677</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38116145</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsai T.F., Ng C.Y. COVID-19 Vaccine–Associated Vitiligo: A Cross-Sectional Study in a Tertiary Referral Center and Systematic Review. J. Dermatol. 2023;50:982–989. doi: 10.1111/1346-8138.16799.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1346-8138.16799</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37186102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hou X., Wu N., Xu M., Kharel P., Wu F., Wu Y., Wang R., Chen J. Demographic and Clinical Feature Disparity between Progress and Non-Progress Patients with Vitiligo after COVID-19 Vaccination: A Cross-Sectional Study. Exp. Dermatol. 2023;32:1344–1349. doi: 10.1111/exd.14825.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/exd.14825</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37140178</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siewert B., Szabat A., Chądzińska-Cebula M., Purpurowicz-Miękus N., Sujkowski P., Spachacz R., Dworacki G., Wysocki J., Januszkiewicz-Lewandowska D., Gowin E. To vaccinate or not to vaccinate—bnt162b2 seroconversion rate and side effects among polish healthcare workers. Int. J. Occup. Med. Environ. Health. 2022;35:761–766. doi: 10.13075/ijomeh.1896.01887.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.13075/ijomeh.1896.01887</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10464737</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36052946</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fasano G., Bennardo L., Ruffolo S., Passante M., Ambrosio A.G., Napolitano M., Provenzano E., Nisticò S.P., Patruno C. Erythema Migrans-like COVID Vaccine Arm: A Literature Review. J. Clin. Med. 2022;11:797. doi: 10.3390/jcm11030797.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/jcm11030797</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8836892</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35160249</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Picone V., Martora F., Fabbrocini G., Marano L. “Covid Arm”: Abnormal Side Effect after Moderna COVID-19 Vaccine. Dermatol. Ther. 2022;35:e15197. doi: 10.1111/dth.15197.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/dth.15197</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8646724</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34750923</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lindgren A.L., Austin A.H., Welsh K.M. COVID Arm: Delayed Hypersensitivity Reactions to SARS-CoV-2 Vaccines Misdiagnosed as Cellulitis. J. Prim. Care Community Health. 2021;12:21501327211024431. doi: 10.1177/21501327211024431.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/21501327211024431</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8202256</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34120504</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramos C.L., Kelso J.M. “COVID Arm”: Very Delayed Large Injection Site Reactions to MRNA COVID-19 Vaccines. J. Allergy Clin. Immunol. Pract. 2021;9:2480–2481. doi: 10.1016/j.jaip.2021.03.055.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jaip.2021.03.055</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8056968</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33864927</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valera-Rubio M., Sierra-Torres M.I., Castillejo García R., Cordero-Ramos J., López-Márquez M.R., Cruz-Salgado Ó., Calleja-Hernández M.Á. Adverse Events Reported after Administration of BNT162b2 and MRNA-1273 COVID-19 Vaccines among Hospital Workers: A Cross-Sectional Survey-Based Study in a Spanish Hospital. Expert Rev. Vaccines. 2022;21:533–540. doi: 10.1080/14760584.2022.2022478.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/14760584.2022.2022478</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8787836</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34986076</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maruyama A., Sawa T., Teramukai S., Katoh N. Adverse Reactions to the First and Second Doses of Pfizer-BioNTech COVID-19 Vaccine among Healthcare Workers. J. Infect. Chemother. 2022;28:934–942. doi: 10.1016/j.jiac.2022.03.015.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jiac.2022.03.015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8947941</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35361536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bian S., Li L., Wang Z., Cui L., Xu Y., Guan K., Zhao B. Allergic Reactions After the Administration of COVID-19 Vaccines. Front. Public Health. 2022;10:878081. doi: 10.3389/fpubh.2022.878081.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2022.878081</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9152252</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35655467</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nassar R.I., Alnatour D., Thiab S., Nassar A., El-Hajji F., Basheti I.A. Short-Term Side Effects of COVID-19 Vaccines: A Cross-Sectional Study in Jordan. Hum. Vaccin Immunother. 2022;18:2082792. doi: 10.1080/21645515.2022.2082792.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/21645515.2022.2082792</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9621041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35759219</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>