<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39454233</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1476-5616</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>237</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>24</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Public health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Public Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Key stakeholders' perspectives of public health emergency preparedness in Palestine: A qualitative exploratory study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>232</StartPage><EndPage>237</EndPage><MedlinePgn>232-237</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.puhe.2024.10.013</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0033-3506(24)00424-4</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">Palestine continues to face emergencies and a series of humanitarian crises. This study aims to comprehend emergency planning and response including the recent COVID-19 pandemic. Comprehending and recording these experiences will facilitate on-going improvement of Palestine's Public Health Emergency Preparedness (PHEP).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="STUDY DESIGN" NlmCategory="METHODS">A qualitative exploratory study.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Fifteen semi-structured interviews were conducted with key informant decision-makers representing various sectors of the Palestinian health system. The data collection period took place from April 2022-December 2022. A convenient purposive sample was chosen based on identifying important stakeholders in the West Bank's health sector. Every interview was transcribed. Major themes and subthemes were identified using content thematic analysis.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The study demonstrates Palestine's inadequate preparation for emergencies, instead there is a focus on response once a crisis has occurred. No national entity or mechanism is leading the collective preparedness efforts, which might ultimately result in a stronger emergency response. Instead, the efforts are dispersed across several entities, and decisions are not made cooperatively. As for resources, the study indicates that an emergency budget has not been allocated. The study showed a good degree of multi-sectoral collaboration with some reservations regarding the creation of various committees and their efficacy in handling crises.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The findings made it abundantly evident that significant efforts are needed to improve Palestine's level of preparedness and planning. One of the study's primary conclusions is that the health sector must shift from a reactionary to a preparedness-oriented mindset. Additionally, it is necessary to keep an eye on any changes in the nation's health and analysis must take place to strengthen the health system's response plans. Moreover, the activation of the emergency operation center in Palestine is one of the key advancements of the preparedness system.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd.. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Miqdadi</LastName><ForeName>Reem</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Al-Quds University, School of Public Health, Jerusalem, Palestine. Electronic address: reem.mekdade@students.alquds.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hamdan</LastName><ForeName>Motasem</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Health Policy &amp; Management, School of Public Health, Al-Quds University, Jerusalem, Palestine. Electronic address: mhamdan@staff.alquds.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Public Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0376507</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0033-3506</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Emergency preparedness</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Ministry of health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Palestine</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39454233</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.puhe.2024.10.013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0033-3506(24)00424-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>