<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39454249</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1879-1360</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>187</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>21</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of psychosomatic research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Psychosom Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Unlike other medical conditions, type 2 diabetes is a risk factor for new-onset major depression after COVID-19.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>111963</StartPage><MedlinePgn>111963</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.jpsychores.2024.111963</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0022-3999(24)00375-1</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">It is unclear whether pre-COVID medical conditions are risk factors for post-COVID major depressive episode (MDE). We aimed to determine which pre-COVID medical conditions are risk factors for post-COVID MDE after a hospitalization for COVID-19.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">We conducted a nested retrospective case-cohort study within a cohort of 650 patients evaluated six months after hospitalization for COVID-19 at Bicêtre hospital, France. Nine medical conditions present before COVID-19 (High blood pressure, obesity, type 2 diabetes, cardiac, respiratory and renal disease, immune deficiency, neoplasia and liver disease) were extracted from medical records. MDE was assessed using the Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-5 Disorders-Clinician Version (SCID-5-CV). Bivariate and multivariable analyses were performed to determine which pre-COVID medical conditions are independent risk factors for post-COVID new-onset MDE.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Patients mean age was 62.8 (15.8), 258 (39.7 %) were women; 301 (46.3 %) had high blood pressure, 205 (32.4 %) had obesity, and 186 (28.6 %) had type 2 diabetes. Thirty-six (5.5 %) patients were diagnosed with a new-onset MDE. In contrast to other medical conditions, type 2 diabetes was significantly associated with new-onset MDE (OR = 2.51 [1.19-5.29]).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Unlike other pre-COVID medical conditions, type 2 diabetes is a risk factor for post-COVID MDE. Patients with type 2 diabetes should be screened for MDE after a hospitalization for COVID-19.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gasnier</LastName><ForeName>Matthieu</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Service Hospitalo-Universitaire de Psychiatrie de Bicêtre, Mood Center Paris Saclay, Assistance Publique-Hôpitaux de Paris, Hôpitaux Universitaires Paris-Saclay, Hôpital de Bicêtre, Le Kremlin Bicêtre F-94275, France; MOODS Team, INSERM 1018, CESP (Centre de Recherche en Epidémiologie et Santé des Populations), Université Paris-Saclay, Faculté de Médecine Paris-Saclay, Le Kremlin Bicêtre F-94275, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lecoq</LastName><ForeName>Anne-Lise</ForeName><Initials>AL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Centre de Recherche Clinique, Hôpitaux Universitaires Paris-Saclay, Assistance Publique-Hôpitaux de Paris, Hôpital de Bicêtre, Le Kremlin Bicêtre F-94275, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pham</LastName><ForeName>Tài</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de médecine intensive-réanimation, hôpital de Bicêtre, Inserm UMR_S999, FHU SEPSIS, Le Kremlin-Bicêtre F-94275, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Morin</LastName><ForeName>Luc</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de réanimation pédiatrique et médecine néonatale, Hôpital de Bicêtre, Le Kremlin-Bicêtre F-94275, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Radiguer</LastName><ForeName>François</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de réanimation chirurgicale, Hôpital de Bicêtre, DMU 12 Anesthésie, réanimation, douleur, Le Kremlin-Bicêtre, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gosset-Grainville</LastName><ForeName>Eugénie</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Service Hospitalo-Universitaire de Psychiatrie de Bicêtre, Mood Center Paris Saclay, Assistance Publique-Hôpitaux de Paris, Hôpitaux Universitaires Paris-Saclay, Hôpital de Bicêtre, Le Kremlin Bicêtre F-94275, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Quinque</LastName><ForeName>Marie</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Service Hospitalo-Universitaire de Psychiatrie de Bicêtre, Mood Center Paris Saclay, Assistance Publique-Hôpitaux de Paris, Hôpitaux Universitaires Paris-Saclay, Hôpital de Bicêtre, Le Kremlin Bicêtre F-94275, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alaoui</LastName><ForeName>Wassim Najib</ForeName><Initials>WN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Service Hospitalo-Universitaire de Psychiatrie de Bicêtre, Mood Center Paris Saclay, Assistance Publique-Hôpitaux de Paris, Hôpitaux Universitaires Paris-Saclay, Hôpital de Bicêtre, Le Kremlin Bicêtre F-94275, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Deflesselle</LastName><ForeName>Eric</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MOODS Team, INSERM 1018, CESP (Centre de Recherche en Epidémiologie et Santé des Populations), Université Paris-Saclay, Faculté de Médecine Paris-Saclay, Le Kremlin Bicêtre F-94275, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Choucha</LastName><ForeName>Walid</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Service Hospitalo-Universitaire de Psychiatrie de Bicêtre, Mood Center Paris Saclay, Assistance Publique-Hôpitaux de Paris, Hôpitaux Universitaires Paris-Saclay, Hôpital de Bicêtre, Le Kremlin Bicêtre F-94275, France; MOODS Team, INSERM 1018, CESP (Centre de Recherche en Epidémiologie et Santé des Populations), Université Paris-Saclay, Faculté de Médecine Paris-Saclay, Le Kremlin Bicêtre F-94275, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Figueiredo</LastName><ForeName>Samy</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de réanimation chirurgicale, Hôpital de Bicêtre, DMU 12 Anesthésie, réanimation, douleur, Le Kremlin-Bicêtre, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zaidan</LastName><ForeName>Mohamad</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de néphrologie transplantation, Hôpital de Bicêtre, Maladies du cœur et des vaisseaux, Le Kremlin-Bicêtre, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Savale</LastName><ForeName>Laurent</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de pneumologie et soins intensifs respiratoires, Hôpital de Bicêtre, Inserm UMR_S999, Le Kremlin-Bicêtre F-94275, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Montani</LastName><ForeName>David</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de pneumologie et soins intensifs respiratoires, Hôpital de Bicêtre, Inserm UMR_S999, Le Kremlin-Bicêtre F-94275, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Monnet</LastName><ForeName>Xavier</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de médecine intensive-réanimation, hôpital de Bicêtre, Inserm UMR_S999, FHU SEPSIS, Le Kremlin-Bicêtre F-94275, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Becquemont</LastName><ForeName>Laurent</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MOODS Team, INSERM 1018, CESP (Centre de Recherche en Epidémiologie et Santé des Populations), Université Paris-Saclay, Faculté de Médecine Paris-Saclay, Le Kremlin Bicêtre F-94275, France; Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Centre de Recherche Clinique, Hôpitaux Universitaires Paris-Saclay, Assistance Publique-Hôpitaux de Paris, Hôpital de Bicêtre, Le Kremlin Bicêtre F-94275, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Corruble</LastName><ForeName>Emmanuelle</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Service Hospitalo-Universitaire de Psychiatrie de Bicêtre, Mood Center Paris Saclay, Assistance Publique-Hôpitaux de Paris, Hôpitaux Universitaires Paris-Saclay, Hôpital de Bicêtre, Le Kremlin Bicêtre F-94275, France; MOODS Team, INSERM 1018, CESP (Centre de Recherche en Epidémiologie et Santé des Populations), Université Paris-Saclay, Faculté de Médecine Paris-Saclay, Le Kremlin Bicêtre F-94275, France. Electronic address: emmanuelle.corruble@aphp.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Colle</LastName><ForeName>Romain</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Service Hospitalo-Universitaire de Psychiatrie de Bicêtre, Mood Center Paris Saclay, Assistance Publique-Hôpitaux de Paris, Hôpitaux Universitaires Paris-Saclay, Hôpital de Bicêtre, Le Kremlin Bicêtre F-94275, France; MOODS Team, INSERM 1018, CESP (Centre de Recherche en Epidémiologie et Santé des Populations), Université Paris-Saclay, Faculté de Médecine Paris-Saclay, Le Kremlin Bicêtre F-94275, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><CollectiveName>COMEBAC study group</CollectiveName></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Psychosom Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0376333</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-3999</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Major depressive episode</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Type 2 diabetes</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest All authors have completed the ICMJE uniform disclosure form at http://www.icmje.org/disclosure-of-interest/ and declare: no support from any organisation for the submitted work; no financial relationships with any organisations that might have an interest in the submitted work in the previous three years; no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work. Dr. Montani reported personal fees from Actelion, GSK, Pfizer, MSD, Chiesi, Boehringer, and Incyte Biosciences France, grants from Bayer and MSD, and nonfinancial support from Acceleron outside the submitted work. Dr. Monnet reported personal fees from Getinge Pulsion Medical and Baxter outside the submitted work. Dr. Becquemont reported grants from Sanofi Genzyme for a presentation concerning Gaucher disease, and pharmacogenetics and drug interactions with Eliglustat outside the submitted work. No other disclosures were reported.</CoiStatement><InvestigatorList><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Morin</LastName><ForeName>Luc</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de réanimation pédiatrique et médecine néonatale, Hôpital de Bicêtre, DMU 3 Santé de l'enfant et de l'adolescent, Le Kremlin-Bicêtre, France. Electronic address: luc.morin@aphp.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Savale</LastName><ForeName>Laurent</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de pneumologie et soins intensifs respiratoires, Hôpital de Bicêtre, DMU 5 Thorinno, Inserm UMR_S999, Le Kremlin-Bicêtre, France. Electronic address: laurent.savale@aphp.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pham</LastName><ForeName>Tài</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de médecine intensive-réanimation, hôpital de Bicêtre, DMU 4 CORREVE Maladies du cœur et des vaisseaux, Inserm UMR_S999, Le Kremlin-Bicêtre, France. Electronic address: tai.pham@aphp.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Colle</LastName><ForeName>Romain</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de psychiatrie, Hôpital de Bicêtre, DMU 11, équipe MOODS, INSERM U1178, CESP (Centre de Recherche en Epidémiologie et Santé des Populations), Le Kremlin-Bicêtre, France. Electronic address: romain.colle@aphp.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Figueiredo</LastName><ForeName>Samy</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de réanimation chirurgicale, Hôpital de Bicêtre, DMU 12 Anesthésie, réanimation, douleur, Le Kremlin-Bicêtre, France. Electronic address: samy.figueiredo@aphp.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Harrois</LastName><ForeName>Anatole</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de réanimation chirurgicale, Hôpital de Bicêtre, DMU 12 Anesthésie, réanimation, douleur, Le Kremlin-Bicêtre, France. Electronic address: anatole.harrois@aphp.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gasnier</LastName><ForeName>Matthieu</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de psychiatrie, Hôpital de Bicêtre, DMU 11, équipe MOODS, INSERM U1178, CESP (Centre de Recherche en Epidémiologie et Santé des Populations), Le Kremlin-Bicêtre, France. Electronic address: matthieu.gasnier@aphp.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lecoq</LastName><ForeName>Anne-Lise</ForeName><Initials>AL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Centre de recherche Clinique Paris-Saclay, DMU 13 Santé publique, Information médicale, Appui à la recherche clinique, INSERM U1018, CESP (Centre de Recherche en Epidémiologie et Santé des Populations). Electronic address: anne-lise.lecoq@aphp.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Meyrignac</LastName><ForeName>Olivier</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de radiologie diagnostique et interventionnelle, Hôpital de Bicêtre, DMU 14 Smart Imaging, BioMaps, Le Kremlin-Bicêtre, France. Electronic address: olivier.meyrignac@aphp.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Noel</LastName><ForeName>Nicolas</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de médecine interne et immunologie clinique, Hôpital de Bicêtre, DMU 7 Endocrinologie-immunités-inflammations-cancer-urgences, Le Kremlin-Bicêtre, France. Electronic address: nicolas.noel@aphp.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Baudry</LastName><ForeName>Elodie</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de gériatrie aiguë, Hôpital de Bicêtre, DMU 1 Médecine territoire gériatrie, Le Kremlin-Bicêtre, France. Electronic address: elodie.baudry@aphp.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bellin</LastName><ForeName>Marie-France</ForeName><Initials>MF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de radiologie diagnostique et interventionnelle, Hôpital de Bicêtre, DMU 14 Smart Imaging, BioMaps, Le Kremlin-Bicêtre, France. Electronic address: marie-france.bellin@aphp.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Beurnier</LastName><ForeName>Antoine</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de physiologie et d'explorations fonctionnelles respiratoires, Hôpital de Bicêtre, DMU 5 Thorinno, Inserm UMR_S999, Le Kremlin-Bicêtre, France. Electronic address: antoine.beurnier@aphp.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Choucha</LastName><ForeName>Walid</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de psychiatrie, Hôpital de Bicêtre, DMU 11, équipe MOODS, INSERM U1178, CESP (Centre de Recherche en Epidémiologie et Santé des Populations), Le Kremlin-Bicêtre, France. Electronic address: walid.choucha@aphp.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Corruble</LastName><ForeName>Emmanuelle</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de psychiatrie, Hôpital de Bicêtre, DMU 11, équipe MOODS, INSERM U1178, CESP (Centre de Recherche en Epidémiologie et Santé des Populations), Le Kremlin-Bicêtre, France. Electronic address: emmanuelle.corruble@aphp.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dortet</LastName><ForeName>Laurent</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de microbiologie, Hôpital de Bicêtre, DMU 15 Biologie-Génétique-PUI, INSERM 1193, Le Kremlin-Bicêtre, France. Electronic address: laurent.dortet@aphp.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hardy-Leger</LastName><ForeName>Isabelle</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de médecine interne et immunologie clinique, Hôpital de Bicêtre, DMU 7 Endocrinologie-immunités-inflammations-cancer-urgences, Le Kremlin-Bicêtre, France. Electronic address: isabelle.hardy-leger@aphp.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Radiguer</LastName><ForeName>François</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de réanimation chirurgicale, Hôpital de Bicêtre, DMU 12 Anesthésie, réanimation, douleur, Le Kremlin-Bicêtre, France. Electronic address: francois.radiguer@aphp.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sportouch</LastName><ForeName>Sabine</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de médecine intensive-réanimation, hôpital de Bicêtre, DMU 4 CORREVE Maladies du cœur et des vaisseaux, Inserm UMR_S999, Le Kremlin-Bicêtre, France. Electronic address: sabine.sportouch@aphp.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Verny</LastName><ForeName>Christiane</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de gériatrie aiguë, Hôpital de Bicêtre, DMU 1 Médecine territoire gériatrie, Le Kremlin-Bicêtre, France. Electronic address: christiane.verny@aphp.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wyplosz</LastName><ForeName>Benjamin</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service des maladies infectieuses et tropicales, Hôpital de Bicêtre, DMU 7 Endocrinologie-immunités-inflammations-cancer-urgences, INSERM U1018, CESP (Centre de Recherche en Epidémiologie et Santé des Populations), Le Kremlin-Bicêtre, France. Electronic address: benjamin.wyplosz@aphp.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zaidan</LastName><ForeName>Mohamad</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de néphrologie transplantation, Hôpital de Bicêtre, DMU 4 CORREVE Maladies du cœur et des vaisseaux, Le Kremlin-Bicêtre, France. Electronic address: mohamad.zaidan@aphp.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Becquemont</LastName><ForeName>Laurent</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Centre de recherche Clinique Paris-Saclay, DMU 13 Santé publique, Information médicale, Appui à la recherche clinique, INSERM U1018, CESP (Centre de Recherche en Epidémiologie et Santé des Populations). Electronic address: laurent.becquemont@aphp.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Montani</LastName><ForeName>David</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de pneumologie et soins intensifs respiratoires, Hôpital de Bicêtre, DMU 5 Thorinno, Inserm UMR_S999, Le Kremlin-Bicêtre, France. Electronic address: david.montani@aphp.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Monnet</LastName><ForeName>Xavier</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Université Paris-Saclay, AP-HP, Service de médecine intensive-réanimation, hôpital de Bicêtre, DMU 4 CORREVE Maladies du cœur et des vaisseaux, Inserm UMR_S999, Le Kremlin-Bicêtre, France. Electronic address: xavier.monnet@aphp.fr.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Investigator></InvestigatorList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39454249</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychores.2024.111963</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0022-3999(24)00375-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>