<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39451456</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2227-9032</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>12</Volume><Issue>20</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>15</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Healthcare (Basel, Switzerland)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Healthcare (Basel)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Progress Achieved, Landmarks, and Future Concerns in Biomedical and Health Informatics.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">2041</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3390/healthcare12202041</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The biomedical and health informatics (BMHI) fields have been advancing rapidly, a trend particularly emphasised during the recent COVID-19 pandemic, introducing innovations in BMHI. Over nearly 50 years since its establishment as a scientific discipline, BMHI has encountered several challenges, such as mishaps, delays, failures, and moments of enthusiastic expectations and notable successes. This paper focuses on reviewing the progress made in the BMHI discipline, evaluating key milestones, and discussing future challenges.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">To, Structured, step-by-step qualitative methodology was developed and applied, centred on gathering expert opinions and analysing trends from the literature to provide a comprehensive assessment. Experts and pioneers in the BMHI field were assigned thematic tasks based on the research question, providing critical inputs for the thematic analysis. This led to the identification of five key dimensions used to present the findings in the paper: informatics in biomedicine and healthcare, health data in Informatics, nurses in informatics, education and accreditation in health informatics, and ethical, legal, social, and security issues.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Each dimension is examined through recently emerging innovations, linking them directly to the future of healthcare, like the role of artificial intelligence, innovative digital health tools, the expansion of telemedicine, and the use of mobile health apps and wearable devices. The new approach of BMHI covers newly introduced clinical needs and approaches like patient-centric, remote monitoring, and precision medicine clinical approaches.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">These insights offer clear recommendations for improving education and developing experts to advance future innovations. Notably, this narrative review presents a body of knowledge essential for a deep understanding of the BMHI field from a human-centric perspective and, as such, could serve as a reference point for prospective analysis and innovation development.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ognjanović</LastName><ForeName>Ivana</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty for Information Systems and Technologies, University of Donja Gorica, 81000 Podgorica, Montenegro.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>European Federation for Medical Informatics, CH-1052 Le Mont-sur-Lausanne, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zoulias</LastName><ForeName>Emmanouil</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1953-3267</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Health Informatics Lab, Department of Nursing, National and Kapodistrian University of Athens, 11527 Athens, Greece.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mantas</LastName><ForeName>John</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3051-1819</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Health Informatics Lab, Department of Nursing, National and Kapodistrian University of Athens, 11527 Athens, Greece.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Healthcare (Basel)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101666525</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2227-9032</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">accreditation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">biomedical informatics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">digital health innovations</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">education</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ethics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">health informatics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">health informatics data</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">medical informatics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nursing informatics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">security</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>25</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>54</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39451456</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11506887</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/healthcare12202041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">healthcare12202041</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Haux R. On Determining Factors for Good Research in Biomedical and Health Informatics. Some Lessons Learned. Yearb. Med. Inform. 2014;9:255–264. doi: 10.15265/IY-2014-0025.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15265/IY-2014-0025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4287077</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24853031</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haux R., Kulikowski C.A., Bakken S., de Lusignan S., Kimura M., Koch S., Mantas J., Maojo V., Marschollek M., Martin-Sanchez F., et al. Research Strategies for Biomedical and Health Informatics: Some Thought-Provoking and Critical Proposals to Encourage Scientific Debate on the Nature of Good Research in Medical Informatics. Methods Inf. Med. 2017;56:e1–e10. doi: 10.3414/ME16-01-0125.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3414/ME16-01-0125</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5388922</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28119991</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mantas J., Hasman A., Haux R., editors. Achievements, Milestones and Challenges in Biomedical and Health Informatics. Volume 300 IOS Press; Amsterdam, The Netherlands: 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knaup P., Ammenwerth E., Dujat C., Grant A., Hasman A., Hein A., Hochlehnert A., Kulikowski C., Mantas J., Maojo V., et al. Assessing the Prognoses on Health Care in the Information Society 2013—Thirteen Years After. J. Med. Syst. 2014;38:73. doi: 10.1007/s10916-014-0073-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10916-014-0073-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24952606</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haux R., Ammenwerth E., Herzog W., Knaup P. Health Care in the Information Society. A Prognosis for the Year 2013. Int. J. Med. Inform. 2002;66:3–21. doi: 10.1016/S1386-5056(02)00030-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1386-5056(02)00030-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12453552</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ückert F., Ammenwerth E., Dujat C., Grant A., Haux R., Hein A., Hochlehnert A., Knaup-Gregori P., Kulikowski C., Mantas J., et al. Past and next 10 Years of Medical Informatics Special Issue: Health Care in the Information Society—A Prognosis for the Year 2013. J. Med. Syst. 2014;38:74. doi: 10.1007/s10916-014-0074-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10916-014-0074-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24952607</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haux R., Knaup P. Recommendations of the International Medical Informatics Association (IMIA) on Education in Health and Medical Informatics. Methods Inf. Med. 2000;39:267–277. doi: 10.1055/s-0038-1634340.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1055/s-0038-1634340</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10992757</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mantas J., Ammenwerth E., Demiris G., Hasman A., Haux R., Hersh W., Hovenga E., Lun K.C., Marin H., Martin-Sanchez F., et al. Recommendations of the International Medical Informatics Association (IMIA) on Education in Biomedical and Health Informatics. Methods Inf. Med. 2010;49:105–120. doi: 10.24105/ejbi.2011.07.2.2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.24105/ejbi.2011.07.2.2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20054502</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bichel-Findlay J., Koch S., Mantas J., Abdul S.S., Al-Shorbaji N., Ammenwerth E., Baum A., Borycki E.M., Demiris G., Hasman A., et al. Recommendations of the International Medical Informatics Association (IMIA) on Education in Biomedical and Health Informatics: Second Revision. Int. J. Med. Inform. 2023;170:104908. doi: 10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2022.104908.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2022.104908</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36502741</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stern C., Lizarondo L., Carrier J., Godfrey C., Rieger K., Salmond S., Apóstolo J., Kirkpatrick P., Loveday H. Methodological Guidance for the Conduct of Mixed Methods Systematic Reviews. JBI Evid. Synth. 2020;18:2108–2118. doi: 10.11124/JBISRIR-D-19-00169.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.11124/JBISRIR-D-19-00169</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32813460</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sukhera J. Narrative Reviews: Flexible, Rigorous, and Practical. J. Grad. Med. Educ. 2022;14:414–417. doi: 10.4300/JGME-D-22-00480.1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4300/JGME-D-22-00480.1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9380636</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35991099</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hasman A., Ammenwerth E., Dickhaus H., Knaup P., Lovis C., Mantas J., Maojo V., Martin-Sanchez F.J., Musen M., Patel V.L., et al. Biomedical Informatics—A Confluence of Disciplines? Methods Inf. Med. 2011;50:508–524. doi: 10.3414/ME11-06-0003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3414/ME11-06-0003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22146914</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nightingale A. A Guide to Systematic Literature Reviews. Surgery. 2009;27:381–384. doi: 10.1016/j.mpsur.2009.07.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.mpsur.2009.07.005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lovis C. Achievements, Milestones and Challenges in Biomedical and Health Informatics. Volume 300. IOS Press; Amsterdam, The Netherlands: 2022. Health, Digital Health and Decision Support: Sisyphus and Pandora; pp. 180–189.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36300411</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahimi B., Nadri H., Lotfnezhad Afshar H., Timpka T. A Systematic Review of the Technology Acceptance Model in Health Informatics. Appl. Clin. Inform. 2018;9:604–634. doi: 10.1055/s-0038-1668091.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1055/s-0038-1668091</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6094026</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30112741</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Melton B.L. Systematic Review of Medical Informatics–Supported Medication Decision Making. Biomed. Inform. Insights. 2017;9:117822261769797. doi: 10.1177/1178222617697975.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1178222617697975</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5391194</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28469432</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Protti D.J., Van Bemmel J.H., Gunzenhauser R., Haux R., Warner H., Douglas J.V., Lang E. Can Health/Medical Informatics Be Regarded as a Separate Discipline? Methods Inf. Med. 1994;33:318–326. doi: 10.1055/s-0038-1635017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1055/s-0038-1635017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8072425</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mantas J. Achievements, Milestones and Challenges in Biomedical and Health Informatics. Volume 300. IOS Press; Amsterdam, The Netherlands: 2022. A Personal Odyssey in Health Informatics: The Journey to Ithaca; pp. 203–219.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36300413</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agrawal J.P., Erickson B.J., Kahn C.E. Imaging Informatics: 25 Years of Progress. Yearb. Med. Inform. 2016;25:S23–S31. doi: 10.15265/IYS-2016-s004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15265/IYS-2016-s004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5171495</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27362590</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mantas J., Heaton A.G. Handwritten Character Recognition by Parallel Labelling and Shape Analysis. Pattern Recognit. Lett. 1983;1:465–468. doi: 10.1016/0167-8655(83)90087-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0167-8655(83)90087-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Govindan V.K., Shivaprasad A.P. Character Recognition—A Review. Pattern Recognit. 1990;23:671–683. doi: 10.1016/0031-3203(90)90091-X.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0031-3203(90)90091-X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pal N.R., Pal S.K. A Review on Image Segmentation Techniques. Pattern Recognit. 1993;26:1277–1294. doi: 10.1016/0031-3203(93)90135-J.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0031-3203(93)90135-J</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hasman A., Mantas J., Zarubina T. An Abridged History of Medical Informatics Education in Europe. Acta Inform. Medica. 2014;22:25–36. doi: 10.5455/aim.2014.22.25-36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5455/aim.2014.22.25-36</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3947951</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24648617</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chennubhotla C., Clarke L.P., Fedorov A., Foran D., Harris G., Helton E., Nordstrom R., Prior F., Rubin D., Saltz J.H., et al. An Assessment of Imaging Informatics for Precision Medicine in Cancer. Yearb. Med. Inform. 2017;26:110–119. doi: 10.15265/IY-2017-041.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15265/IY-2017-041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6250996</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29063549</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Novak J., Zarinabad N., Rose H., Arvanitis T., MacPherson L., Pinkey B., Oates A., Hales P., Grundy R., Auer D., et al. Classification of Paediatric Brain Tumours by Diffusion Weighted Imaging and Machine Learning. Sci. Rep. 2021;11:2987. doi: 10.1038/s41598-021-82214-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-82214-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7862387</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33542327</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grist J.T., Withey S., Bennett C., Rose H.E.L., MacPherson L., Oates A., Powell S., Novak J., Abernethy L., Pizer B., et al. Combining Multi-Site Magnetic Resonance Imaging with Machine Learning Predicts Survival in Pediatric Brain Tumors. Sci. Rep. 2021;11:18897. doi: 10.1038/s41598-021-96189-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-96189-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8460620</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34556677</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao D., Grist J.T., Rose H.E.L., Davies N.P., Wilson M., MacPherson L., Abernethy L.J., Avula S., Pizer B., Gutierrez D.R., et al. Metabolite Selection for Machine Learning in Childhood Brain Tumour Classification. NMR Biomed. 2022;35:e4673. doi: 10.1002/nbm.4673.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/nbm.4673</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35088473</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>González-Vélez H., Mier M., Julià-Sapé M., Arvanitis T.N., García-Gómez J.M., Robles M., Lewis P.H., Dasmahapatra S., Dupplaw D., Peet A., et al. HealthAgents: Distributed Multi-Agent Brain Tumor Diagnosis and Prognosis. Appl. Intell. 2009;30:191–202. doi: 10.1007/s10489-007-0085-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10489-007-0085-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gibb A., Easton J., Davies N., Sun Y., Macpherson L., Natarajan K., Arvanitis T., Peet A. The Development of a Graphical User Interface, Functional Elements and Classifiers for the Non-Invasive Characterization of Childhood Brain Tumours Using Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy. Knowl. Eng. Rev. 2011;26:353–363. doi: 10.1017/S0269888911000154.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0269888911000154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guiot J., Vaidyanathan A., Deprez L., Zerka F., Danthine D., Frix A.-N., Lambin P., Bottari F., Tsoutzidis N., Miraglio B., et al. A Review in Radiomics: Making Personalized Medicine a Reality via Routine Imaging. Med. Res. Rev. 2021;42:426–440. doi: 10.1002/med.21846.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/med.21846</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34309893</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arvanitis T.N. Achievements, Milestones and Challenges in Biomedical and Health. Volume 300. IOS Press BV; Amsterdam, The Netherlands: 2022. Informatics Opportunities and Challenges in Medical Imaging: A Journey; pp. 19–29.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36300399</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mantas J. Biomedical and Health Informatics Education—The IMIA Years. Yearb. Med. Inform. 2016;25:S92–S102. doi: 10.15265/IY-2016-032.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15265/IY-2016-032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5171512</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27488405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y.C.J. Achievements, Milestones and Challenges in Biomedical and Health Informatics. Volume 300. IOS Press BV; Amsterdam, The Netherlands: 2022. Temporal Phenomics—A Powerful Approach Using AI to Achieve “Earlier Medicine”; pp. 177–179.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36300410</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Solomonoff R.J. The Time Scale of Artificial Intelligence: Reflections on Social Effects. Hum. Syst. Manag. 1985;5:149–153. doi: 10.3233/HSM-1985-5207.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3233/HSM-1985-5207</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turing A.M. Computing Machinery and Intelligence. In: Epstein R., Roberts G., Beber G., editors. Parsing the Turing Test. Springer; Dordrecht, The Netherlands: 2009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-1-4020-6710-5_3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ishihara K. Artificial Intelligence and Medicine. Dokkyo J. Med. Sci. 2023;50:2–8. doi: 10.15354/si.22.re068.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15354/si.22.re068</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muhiyaddin R., Elfadl A., Mohamed E., Shah Z., Alam T., Abd-Alrazaq A., Househ M. Informatics and Technology in Clinical Care and Public Health. Volume 289. IOS Press BV; Amsterdam, The Netherlands: 2022. Electronic Health Records and Physician Burnout: A Scoping Review; pp. 481–484.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35062195</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnson K.B., Neuss M.J., Detmer D.E. Electronic Health Records and Clinician Burnout: A Story of Three Eras. J. Am. Med. Inform. Assoc. 2021;28:967–973. doi: 10.1093/jamia/ocaa274.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jamia/ocaa274</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8068425</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33367815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McPeek-Hinz E., Boazak M., Sexton J.B., Adair K.C., West V., Goldstein B.A., Alphin R.S., Idris S., Hammond W.E., Hwang S.E., et al. Clinician Burnout Associated With Sex, Clinician Type, Work Culture, and Use of Electronic Health Records. JAMA Netw. Open. 2021;4:E215686. doi: 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.5686.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.5686</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8058638</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33877310</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adler-Milstein J., Zhao W., Willard-Grace R., Knox M., Grumbach K. Electronic Health Records and Burnout: Time Spent on the Electronic Health Record after Hours and Message Volume Associated with Exhaustion but Not with Cynicism among Primary Care Clinicians. J. Am. Med. Inform. Assoc. 2020;27:531–538. doi: 10.1093/jamia/ocz220.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jamia/ocz220</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7647261</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32016375</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gardner R.L., Cooper E., Haskell J., Harris D.A., Poplau S., Kroth P.J., Linzer M. Physician Stress and Burnout: The Impact of Health Information Technology. J. Am. Med. Inform. Assoc. 2019;26:106–114. doi: 10.1093/jamia/ocy145.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jamia/ocy145</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7647171</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30517663</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moy A.J., Schwartz J.M., Chen R.J., Sadri S., Lucas E., Cato K.D., Rossetti S.C. Measurement of Clinical Documentation Burden among Physicians and Nurses Using Electronic Health Records: A Scoping Review. J. Am. Med. Inform. Assoc. 2021;28:998–1008. doi: 10.1093/jamia/ocaa325.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jamia/ocaa325</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8068426</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33434273</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Electronic Health Records National Symposium | EHR National Symposium | Stanford Medicine.  [(accessed on 16 March 2024)].  Available online:  https://med.stanford.edu/ehr.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hermann G. Karl Popper: Logik Der Forschung. Zur Erkenntnistheorie Der Modernen Naturwissenschaft, Vi+248 Pp. Springer: Berlin 1935. J. Gen. Philos. Sci. 2020;51:621–623. doi: 10.1007/s10838-020-09531-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10838-020-09531-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erasmus A., Brunet T.D.P., Fisher E. What Is Interpretability? Philos. Technol. 2021;34:833–862. doi: 10.1007/s13347-020-00435-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13347-020-00435-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8654716</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34966640</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holzinger A., Langs G., Denk H., Zatloukal K., Müller H. Causability and Explainability of Artificial Intelligence in Medicine. Wiley Interdiscip. Rev. Data Min. Knowl. Discov. 2019;9:e1312. doi: 10.1002/widm.1312.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/widm.1312</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7017860</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32089788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McDermid J.A., Jia Y., Porter Z., Habli I. Artificial Intelligence Explainability: The Technical and Ethical Dimensions. Philos. Trans. R. Soc. A Math. Phys. Eng. Sci. 2021:379. doi: 10.1098/rsta.2020.0363.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1098/rsta.2020.0363</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8366909</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34398656</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farris A.B., Vizcarra J., Amgad M., Cooper L.A.D., Gutman D., Hogan J. Artificial Intelligence and Algorithmic Computational Pathology: An Introduction with Renal Allograft Examples. Histopathology. 2021;78:791–804. doi: 10.1111/his.14304.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/his.14304</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8715391</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33211332</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Slabaugh G., Beltran L., Rizvi H., Deloukas P., Marouli E. Applications of Machine and Deep Learning to Thyroid Cytology and Histopathology: A Review. Front. Oncol. 2023;13:958310. doi: 10.3389/fonc.2023.958310.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fonc.2023.958310</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10661921</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38023130</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Collins F.S., Varmus H. A New Initiative on Precision Medicine. N. Engl. J. Med. 2015;372:793–795. doi: 10.1056/NEJMp1500523.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMp1500523</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5101938</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25635347</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chatzimina M.E., Papadaki H.A., Pontikoglou C., Tsiknakis M. A Comparative Sentiment Analysis of Greek Clinical Conversations Using BERT, RoBERTa, GPT-2, and XLNet. Bioengineering. 2024;11:521. doi: 10.3390/bioengineering11060521.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/bioengineering11060521</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11200492</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38927757</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang L.W.Y., Ng W.Y., Lei X., Tan S.C.Y., Wang Z., Yan M., Pargi M.K., Zhang X., Lim J.S., Gunasekeran D.V., et al. Development and Testing of a Multi-Lingual Natural Language Processing-Based Deep Learning System in 10 Languages for COVID-19 Pandemic Crisis: A Multi-Center Study. Front. Public Health. 2023;11:1063466. doi: 10.3389/fpubh.2023.1063466.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2023.1063466</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9968846</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36860378</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ndwabe H., Basu A., Mohammed J. Post Pandemic Analysis on Comprehensive Utilization of Telehealth and Telemedicine. Clin. eHealth. 2024;7:5–14. doi: 10.1016/j.ceh.2023.12.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ceh.2023.12.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zinzuwadia A., Goldberg J.M., Hanson M.A., Wessler J.D. Emerging Practices in Telehealth. Academic Press; Cambridge, MA, USA: 2023. Continuous cardiology: The intersection of telehealth and remote patient monitoring; pp. 97–115.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/B978-0-443-15980-0.00004-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu J.-C., Cheng C.-Y., Cheng T.-H., Liu C.-N., Chen J.-J., Hao W.-R., Liu J.-C., Cheng C.-Y., Cheng T.-H., Liu C.-N., et al. Unveiling the Potential: Remote Monitoring and Telemedicine in Shaping the Future of Heart Failure Management. Life. 2024;14:936. doi: 10.3390/life14080936.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/life14080936</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11355081</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39202678</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maroongroge S., De B., Woodhouse K.D., Bassett R.L., Lee P., Bloom E.S., Smith G.L., Frank S.J., Li J., Perkins G., et al. Physician Perspectives on Telemedicine in Radiation Oncology. Adv. Radiat. Oncol. 2023;8:101005. doi: 10.1016/j.adro.2022.101005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.adro.2022.101005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9598490</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36311822</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sauerbrei A., Kerasidou A., Lucivero F., Hallowell N. The Impact of Artificial Intelligence on the Person-Centred, Doctor-Patient Relationship: Some Problems and Solutions. BMC Med. Inform. Decis. Mak. 2023;23:73. doi: 10.1186/s12911-023-02162-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12911-023-02162-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10116477</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37081503</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Padhan S., Mohapatra A., Ramasamy S.K., Agrawal S. Artificial Intelligence (AI) and Robotics in Elderly Healthcare: Enabling Independence and Quality of Life. Cureus. 2023;15:e42905. doi: 10.7759/cureus.42905.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.42905</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10474924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37664381</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alowais S.A., Alghamdi S.S., Alsuhebany N., Alqahtani T., Alshaya A.I., Almohareb S.N., Aldairem A., Alrashed M., Bin Saleh K., Badreldin H.A., et al. Revolutionizing Healthcare: The Role of Artificial Intelligence in Clinical Practice. BMC Med. Educ. 2023;23:689. doi: 10.1186/s12909-023-04698-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12909-023-04698-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10517477</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37740191</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghaffar Nia N., Kaplanoglu E., Nasab A. Evaluation of Artificial Intelligence Techniques in Disease Diagnosis and Prediction. Discov. Artif. Intell. 2023;3:5. doi: 10.1007/s44163-023-00049-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s44163-023-00049-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta A., Singh A. Healthcare 4.0: Recent Advancements and Futuristic Research Directions. Wirel. Pers. Commun. 2023;129:933–952. doi: 10.1007/s11277-022-10164-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11277-022-10164-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9795952</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36594000</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dagliati A., Malovini A., Tibollo V., Bellazzi R. Health Informatics and EHR to Support Clinical Research in the COVID-19 Pandemic: An Overview. Brief. Bioinform. 2021;22:812–822. doi: 10.1093/bib/bbaa418.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/bib/bbaa418</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7929411</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33454728</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knaup P., Benning N.H., Seitz M.W., Eisenmann U. EHealth and Clinical Documentation Systems. Stud. Health Technol. Inform. 2020;274:174–188. doi: 10.3233/SHTI200676.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3233/SHTI200676</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32990673</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ehrenstein V., Kharrazi H., Lehmann H., Taylor C.O. Tools and Technologies for Registry Interoperability, Registries for Evaluating Patient Outcomes: A User’s Guide. 3rd ed. Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (US); Rockville, MD, USA: 2019. Obtaining Data from Electronic Health Records; pp. 1–92. Addendum 2 [Internet]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaipio J., Kuusisto A., Hyppönen H., Heponiemi T., Lääveri T. Physicians’ and Nurses’ Experiences on EHR Usability: Comparison between the Professional Groups by Employment Sector and System Brand. Int. J. Med. Inform. 2020;134:104018. doi: 10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2019.104018.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2019.104018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31835158</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rudin R.S., Friedberg M.W., Shekelle P., Shah N., Bates D.W. Getting Value from Electronic Health Records: Research Needed to Improve Practice. Ann. Intern. Med. 2020;172:S130–S136. doi: 10.7326/M19-0878.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7326/M19-0878</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32479182</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Friedberg M.W., Chen P.G., Van Busum K.R., Aunon F., Pham C., Caloyeras J., Mattke S., Pitchforth E., Quigley D.D., Brook R.H., et al. Factors Affecting Physician Professional Satisfaction and Their Implications for Patient Care, Health Systems, and Health Policy. Rand Health Q. 2014;3:1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5051918</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28083306</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moore J.H., Barnett I., Boland M.R., Chen Y., Demiris G., Gonzalez-Hernandez G., Herman D.S., Himes B.E., Hubbard R.A., Kim D., et al. Ideas for How Informaticians Can Get Involved with COVID-19 Research. BioData Min. 2020;13:3. doi: 10.1186/s13040-020-00213-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13040-020-00213-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7216865</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32419848</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akhlaq A., McKinstry B., Sheikh A. The Characteristics and Capabilities of the Available Open Source Health Information Technologies Supporting Healthcare: A Scoping Review Protocol. J. Innov. Health Inform. 2018;25:230–238. doi: 10.14236/jhi.v25i4.1022.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.14236/jhi.v25i4.1022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30672406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fechner M., Brix T.J., Hardt T., Oehm J., Dugas M., Storck M. Digital Personalized Health and Medicine. Volume 270. IOS Press; Amsterdam, The Netherlands: 2020. Evaluation of OpenEHR Repositories Regarding Standard Compliance; pp. 592–596.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3233/SHTI200229</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32570452</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koppel R., Lehmann C.U. Implications of an Emerging EHR Monoculture for Hospitals and Healthcare Systems. J. Am. Med. Inform. Assoc. 2015;22:465–471. doi: 10.1136/amiajnl-2014-003023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/amiajnl-2014-003023</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25342181</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salahuddin L., Ismail Z. Classification of Antecedents towards Safety Use of Health Information Technology: A Systematic Review. Int. J. Med. Inform. 2015;84:877–891. doi: 10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2015.07.004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2015.07.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26238706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Viitanen J., Hyppönen H., Lääveri T., Vänskä J., Reponen J., Winblad I. National Questionnaire Study on Clinical ICT Systems Proofs: Physicians Suffer from Poor Usability. Int. J. Med. Inform. 2011;80:708–725. doi: 10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2011.06.010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2011.06.010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21784701</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaipio J., Lääveri T., Hyppönen H., Vainiomäki S., Reponen J., Kushniruk A., Borycki E., Vänskä J. Usability Problems Do Not Heal by Themselves: National Survey on Physicians’ Experiences with EHRs in Finland. Int. J. Med. Inform. 2017;97:266–281. doi: 10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2016.10.010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2016.10.010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27919385</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Esmaeilzadeh P., Mirzaei T. Using Electronic Health Records to Mitigate Workplace Burnout Among Clinicians During the COVID-19 Pandemic: Field Study in Iran. JMIR Med. Inform. 2021;9:e28497. doi: 10.2196/28497.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/28497</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8176947</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34033578</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pereira R., Duarte J., Salazar M., Santos M., Abelha A., Machado J. Usability of an Electronic Health Record; Proceedings of the 2012 IEEE International Conference on Industrial Engineering and Engineering Management; Hong Kong, China. 10–13 December 2012; pp. 1568–1572.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Topaz M., Ronquillo C., Peltonen L.M., Pruinelli L., Sarmiento R.F., Badger M.K., Ali S., Lewis A., Georgsson M., Jeon E., et al. Nurse Informaticians Report Low Satisfaction and Multi-Level Concerns with Electronic Health Records: Results from an International Survey. AMIA Annu Symp Proc. 2016;2016:2016–2025.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5333337</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28269961</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moghaddasi H., Rabiei R., Asadi F., Ostvan N. Evaluation of Nursing Information Systems: Application of Usability Aspects in the Development of Systems. Healthc. Inform. Res. 2017;23:101–108. doi: 10.4258/hir.2017.23.2.101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4258/hir.2017.23.2.101</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5435582</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28523208</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ludwig M., Ludwig B., Mikuła A., Biernat S., Rudnicki J., Kaliszewski K. The Use of Artificial Intelligence in the Diagnosis and Classification of Thyroid Nodules: An Update. Cancers. 2023;15:708. doi: 10.3390/cancers15030708.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/cancers15030708</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9913834</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36765671</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shilo S., Rossman H., Segal E., Shilo S., Rossman H., Segal E. Axes of a Revolution: Challenges and Promises of Big Data in Healthcare. Nat. Med. 2020;26:29–38. doi: 10.1038/s41591-019-0727-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41591-019-0727-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31932803</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Si Y., Du J., Li Z., Jiang X., Miller T., Wang F., Jim Zheng W., Roberts K. Deep Representation Learning of Patient Data from Electronic Health Records (EHR): A Systematic Review. J. Biomed. Inform. 2021;115:103671. doi: 10.1016/j.jbi.2020.103671.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jbi.2020.103671</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11290708</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33387683</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bengio Y., Courville A., Vincent P. Representation Learning: A Review and New Perspectives. IEEE Trans. Pattern Anal. Mach. Intell. 2013;35:1798–1828. doi: 10.1109/TPAMI.2013.50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/TPAMI.2013.50</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23787338</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsu W., El-Saden S., Taira R.K. Medical Imaging Informatics. Adv. Exp. Med. Biol. 2016;939:167–224. doi: 10.1007/978-981-10-1503-8_8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-981-10-1503-8_8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27807748</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Obermeyer Z., Emanuel E.J. Predicting the Future—Big Data, Machine Learning, and Clinical Medicine. N. Engl. J. Med. 2016;375:1216–1219. doi: 10.1056/NEJMp1606181.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMp1606181</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5070532</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27682033</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benke K., Benke G. Artificial Intelligence and Big Data in Public Health. Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health. 2018;15:2796. doi: 10.3390/ijerph15122796.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph15122796</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6313588</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30544648</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aekanth S.G., Tillinghast D.J. Human-Automation Interaction. Springer; Berlin/Heidelberg, Germany: 2023. The Emergence of Wearable Technologies in Healthcare: A Systematic Review; pp. 43–59.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-3-031-10788-7_3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tao Q., Liu S., Zhang J., Jiang J., Jin Z., Huang Y., Liu X., Lin S., Zeng X., Li X., et al. Clinical Applications of Smart Wearable Sensors. iScience. 2023;26:107485. doi: 10.1016/j.isci.2023.107485.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.isci.2023.107485</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10448028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37636055</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ju J., Wearable B.-K., Moon J., Ju B.-K. Wearable Sensors for Healthcare of Industrial Workers: A Scoping Review. Electronics. 2024;13:3849. doi: 10.3390/electronics13193849.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/electronics13193849</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Furstenau L.B., Leivas P., Sott M.K., Dohan M.S., López-Robles J.R., Cobo M.J., Bragazzi N.L., Choo K.K.R. Big Data in Healthcare: Conceptual Network Structure, Key Challenges and Opportunities. Digit. Commun. Netw. 2023;9:856–868. doi: 10.1016/j.dcan.2023.03.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.dcan.2023.03.005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guevara M., Chen S., Thomas S., Chaunzwa T.L., Franco I., Kann B.H., Moningi S., Qian J.M., Goldstein M., Harper S., et al. Large Language Models to Identify Social Determinants of Health in Electronic Health Records. Npj Digit. Med. 2024;7:6. doi: 10.1038/s41746-023-00970-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41746-023-00970-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10781957</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38200151</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Šajnović U., Vošner H.B., Završnik J., Žlahtič B., Kokol P. Internet of Things and Big Data Analytics in Preventive Healthcare: A Synthetic Review. Electronics. 2024;13:3642. doi: 10.3390/electronics13183642.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/electronics13183642</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herland M., Khoshgoftaar T.M., Wald R. A Review of Data Mining Using Big Data in Health Informatics. J. Big Data. 2014;1:2. doi: 10.1186/2196-1115-1-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/2196-1115-1-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Donelle L., Comer L., Hiebert B., Hall J., Shelley J.J., Smith M.J., Kothari A., Burkell J., Stranges S., Cooke T., et al. Use of Digital Technologies for Public Health Surveillance during the COVID-19 Pandemic: A Scoping Review. Digit. Health. 2023;9:20552076231173220. doi: 10.1177/20552076231173220.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/20552076231173220</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10196539</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37214658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raza S., Dolatabadi E., Ondrusek N., Rosella L., Schwartz B. Discovering Social Determinants of Health from Case Reports Using Natural Language Processing: Algorithmic Development and Validation. BMC Digit. Health. 2023;1:35. doi: 10.1186/s44247-023-00035-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s44247-023-00035-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghebrehiwet I., Zaki N., Damseh R., Mohamad M.S. Revolutionizing Personalized Medicine with Generative AI: A Systematic Review. Artif. Intell. Rev. 2024;57:128. doi: 10.1007/s10462-024-10768-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10462-024-10768-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee H.Y., Lee K.H., Lee K.H., Erdenbayar U., Hwang S., Lee E.Y., Lee J.H., Kim H.J., Park S.B., Park J.W., et al. Internet of Medical Things-Based Real-Time Digital Health Service for Precision Medicine: Empirical Studies Using MEDBIZ Platform. Digit. Health. 2023;9:20552076221149659. doi: 10.1177/20552076221149659.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/20552076221149659</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9834931</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36644659</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pankiw M., Brezden-Masley C., Charames G.S. Comprehensive Genomic Profiling for Oncological Advancements by Precision Medicine. Med. Oncol. 2024;41:1. doi: 10.1007/s12032-023-02228-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12032-023-02228-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37993657</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gyrard A., Mohammadi S., Gaur M., Kung A. IoT-Based Preventive Mental Health Using Knowledge Graphs and Standards for Better Well-Being. arXiv. 20242406.13791</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Canfell O.J., Davidson K., Woods L., Sullivan C., Cocoros N.M., Klompas M., Zambarano B., Eakin E., Littlewood R., Burton-Jones A. Precision Public Health for Non-Communicable Diseases: An Emerging Strategic Roadmap and Multinational Use Cases. Front. Public Health. 2022;10:854525. doi: 10.3389/fpubh.2022.854525.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2022.854525</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9024120</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35462850</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weber P., Peltonen L.-M., Junger A. Achievements, Milestones and Challenges in Biomedical and Health. Volume 300. IOS Press BV; Amsterdam, The Netherlands: 2022. The Essence and Role of Nurses in the Future of Biomedical and Health Informatics; pp. 164–176.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36300409</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Statistics 2022: Monitoring Health for the SDGs, Sustainable Development Goals.  [(accessed on 16 March 2024)].  Available online:  https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240051157.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Myers C.R. Promoting Population Health: Nurse Advocacy, Policy Making, and Use of Media. Nurs. Clin. N. Am. 2020;55:11–20. doi: 10.1016/j.cnur.2019.11.001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cnur.2019.11.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32005360</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>State of the World’s Nursing 2020: Investing in Education, Jobs and Leadership.  [(accessed on 16 March 2024)].  Available online:  https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240003279.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosseter R. Fact Sheet: Nursing Shortage. 2017.  [(accessed on 1 July 2024)].  Available online:  https://www.aacnnursing.org/news-data/fact-sheets/nursing-shortage.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ozbolt J.G., Saba V.K. A Brief History of Nursing Informatics in the United States of America. Nurs. Outlook. 2008;56:199–205. doi: 10.1016/j.outlook.2008.06.008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.outlook.2008.06.008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18922268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nagle L.M., Sermeus W., Junger A. Evolving Role of the Nursing Informatics Specialist. Stud. Health Technol. Inform. 2017;232:212–221. doi: 10.3233/978-1-61499-738-2-212.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3233/978-1-61499-738-2-212</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28106600</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kulikowski C.A. Achievements, Milestones and Challenges in Biomedical and Health Informatics. Volume 300. IOS Press BV; Amsterdam, The Netherlands: Oct 26, 2022. 50 Years of Achievements and Persistent Challenges for Biomedical and Health Informatics and John Mantas’ Educational and Nursing Informatics Contributions; pp. 1–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36300397</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palenski T., Hills L., Unnikrishnan S., Eynon R. How AI Works: Reconfiguring Lifelong Learning. Postdigital Sci. Educ. 2024 doi: 10.1007/s42438-024-00496-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s42438-024-00496-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park E., Kim H., Steinhoff A. Health-Related Internet Use by Informal Caregivers of Children and Adolescents: An Integrative Literature Review. J. Med. Internet Res. 2016;18:e4124. doi: 10.2196/jmir.4124.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/jmir.4124</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4796403</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26940750</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vargas H., Donabedian A. The Methods and Findings of Quality Assessment and Monitoring: An Illustrated Analysis. J. Public Health Policy. 1986;7:134. doi: 10.2307/3342133.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2307/3342133</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tourangeau A.E., Cranley L.A., Jeffs L. Impact of Nursing on Hospital Patient Mortality: A Focused Review and Related Policy Implications. Qual. Saf. Health Care. 2006;15:4–8. doi: 10.1136/qshc.2005.014514.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/qshc.2005.014514</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2563988</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16456202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gibbons M.C., Wilson R.F., Samal L., Lehmann C.U., Dickersin K., Lehmann H.P., Aboumatar H., Finkelstein J., Shelton E., Sharma R., et al. Consumer Health Informatics: Results of a Systematic Evidence Review and Evidence Based Recommendations. Transl. Behav. Med. 2011;1:72–82. doi: 10.1007/s13142-011-0016-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13142-011-0016-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3717687</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24073033</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Demiris G. Achievements, Milestones and Challenges in Biomedical and Health. Volume 300. IOS Press BV; Amsterdam, The Netherlands: 2022. Personal Health Informatics: New Tools and Roles for Health Care; pp. 53–63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36300402</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Onnela J.P., Rauch S.L. Harnessing Smartphone-Based Digital Phenotyping to Enhance Behavioral and Mental Health. Neuropsychopharmacology. 2016;41:1691–1696. doi: 10.1038/npp.2016.7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/npp.2016.7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4869063</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26818126</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carreiro S., Wittbold K., Indic P., Fang H., Zhang J., Boyer E.W. Wearable Biosensors to Detect Physiologic Change During Opioid Use. J. Med. Toxicol. 2016;12:255–262. doi: 10.1007/s13181-016-0557-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13181-016-0557-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4996791</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27334894</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fletcher R.R., Tam S., Omojola O., Redemske R., Kwan J. Wearable Sensor Platform and Mobile Application for Use in Cognitive Behavioral Therapy for Drug Addiction and PTSD; Proceedings of the 2011 Annual International Conference of the IEEE Engineering in Medicine and Biology Society; EMBS, Boston, MA, USA. 30 August 2011–3 September 2011; pp. 1802–1805.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22254678</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pappadà A., Chattat R., Chirico I., Valente M., Ottoboni G. Assistive Technologies in Dementia Care: An Updated Analysis of the Literature. Front. Psychol. 2021;12:644587. doi: 10.3389/fpsyg.2021.644587.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2021.644587</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8024695</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33841281</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan M., Bocquet H., Campo E., Val T., Pous J. Alarm Communication Network to Help Carers of the Elderly for Safety Purposes: A Survey of a Project. Int. J. Rehabil. Res. 1999;22:131–136. doi: 10.1097/00004356-199906000-00008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/00004356-199906000-00008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10448625</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chung J., Demiris G., Thompson H.J. Ethical Considerations Regarding the Use of Smart Home Technologies for Older Adults: An Integrative Review. Annu. Rev. Nurs. Res. 2016;34:155–181. doi: 10.1891/0739-6686.34.155.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1891/0739-6686.34.155</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26673381</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaugler J.E., McCarron H.R., Mitchell L.L. Perceptions of Precision Medicine among Diverse Dementia Caregivers and Professional Providers. Alzheimer’s Dement. Transl. Res. Clin. Interv. 2019;5:468–474. doi: 10.1016/j.trci.2019.07.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.trci.2019.07.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6744595</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31535000</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choi Y.K., Thompson H.J., Demiris G. Internet-of-Things Smart Home Technology to Support Aging-in-Place: Older Adults’ Perceptions and Attitudes. J. Gerontol. Nurs. 2021;47:15–21. doi: 10.3928/00989134-20210310-03.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3928/00989134-20210310-03</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34038251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ventura-Silva J., Martins M.M., Trindade L.d.L., Faria A.d.C.A., Pereira S., Zuge S.S., Ribeiro O.M.P.L. Artificial Intelligence in the Organization of Nursing Care: A Scoping Review. Nurs. Rep. 2024;14:2733–2745. doi: 10.3390/nursrep14040202.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nursrep14040202</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11503362</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39449439</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuznetsova M., Kim A.Y., Scully D.A., Wolski P., Syrowatka A., Bates D.W., Dykes P.C. Implementation of a Continuous Patient Monitoring System in the Hospital Setting: A Qualitative Study. Jt. Comm. J. Qual. Patient Saf. 2024;50:235–246. doi: 10.1016/j.jcjq.2023.10.017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jcjq.2023.10.017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38101994</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olesen M.L., Rossen S., Jørgensen R., Udbjørg L.L., Hansson H. Usefulness of a Digitally Assisted Person-Centered Care Intervention: Qualitative Study of Patients’ and Nurses’ Experiences in a Long-Term Perspective. JMIR Nurs. 2023;6:e46673. doi: 10.2196/46673.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/46673</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10236280</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37200076</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hakami A., Hussain F., Bakheet A., Alghamdi K., AlAtrash K. Nursing Research Priorities Based on the Nurse-Sensitive Indicators: Scoping Review. Open Nurs. J. 2023;17:e187443462301270. doi: 10.2174/18744346-v17-e230508-2023-29.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2174/18744346-v17-e230508-2023-29</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yadav S. Embracing Artificial Intelligence: Revolutionizing Nursing Documentation for a Better Future. Cureus. 2024;16:e57725. doi: 10.7759/cureus.57725.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.57725</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11073762</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38711689</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Labrague L.J., Aguilar-Rosales R., Yboa B.C., Sabio J.B., de Los Santos J.A. Student nurses’ attitudes, perceived utilization, and intention to adopt artificial intelligence (AI) technology in nursing practice: A cross-sectional study. Nurse Educ. Pract. 2023;73:103815. doi: 10.1016/j.nepr.2023.103815.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.nepr.2023.103815</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37922736</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baixinho C.L., Costa A., Nascimento T., Loura D., Henriques A. World Conference on Qualitative Research. Springer Nature Switzerland; Cham, Switzerland: 2024. Preparing for a Digital Future: Student Perceptions of Innovation and Technology in Nursing; pp. 245–256.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-3-031-65735-1_15</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hersh W. A Stimulus to Define Informatics and Health Information Technology. BMC Med. Inform. Decis. Mak. 2009;9:24. doi: 10.1186/1472-6947-9-24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1472-6947-9-24</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2695439</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19445665</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hersh W. Achievements, Milestones and Challenges in Biomedical and Health Informatics. Volume 300. IOS Press BV; Amsterdam, The Netherlands: Oct 26, 2022. Competencies and Curricula Across the Spectrum of Learners for Biomedical and Health Informatics; pp. 93–107.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36300405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moen A., Antypas K. Achievements, Milestones and Challenges in Biomedical and Health Informatics. Volume 300. IOS Press BV; Amsterdam, The Netherlands: Oct 26, 2022. Capacity Development to Leverage Advances in Health Informatics for All; pp. 12–18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36300398</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saranto K., Kinnunen U.M. Achievements, Milestones and Challenges in Biomedical and Health Informatics. Volume 300. IOS Press; Amsterdam, The Netherlands: 2022. Milestones and Outcomes in Health and Human Services Informatics Education Programmes; pp. 77–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36300404</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jimenez G., Spinazze P., Matchar D., Koh Choon Huat G., van der Kleij R.M.J.J., Chavannes N.H., Car J. Digital Health Competencies for Primary Healthcare Professionals: A Scoping Review. Int. J. Med. Inform. 2020;143:104260. doi: 10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2020.104260.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2020.104260</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32919345</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee K.H., Kim M.G., Lee J.H., Lee J., Cho I., Choi M., Han H.W., Park M. Empowering Healthcare through Comprehensive Informatics Education: The Status and Future of Biomedical and Health Informatics Education. Healthc. Inform. Res. 2024;30:113–126. doi: 10.4258/hir.2024.30.2.113.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4258/hir.2024.30.2.113</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11098769</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38755102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu Z., Meng Z. Characteristics and Enlightenment of Health Informatics Education in American Universities. Rev. Educ. Theory. 2020;3:49. doi: 10.30564/ret.v3i4.2398.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.30564/ret.v3i4.2398</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wright G. Achievements, Milestones and Challenges in Biomedical and Health Informatics. Volume 300. IOS Press BV; Amsterdam, The Netherlands: Oct 26, 2022. Organisational Change: Using Health Informatics Education as a Change Agent; pp. 64–76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36300403</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davies A., Mueller J., Moulton G. Core Competencies for Clinical Informaticians: A Systematic Review. Int. J. Med. Inform. 2020;141:104237. doi: 10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2020.104237.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2020.104237</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32771960</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Macassa G., McGrath C. Common Problems! And Common Solutions?—Teaching at the Intersection Between Public Health and Criminology: A Public Health Perspective. Ann. Glob. Health. 2024;90:12. doi: 10.5334/aogh.4375.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5334/aogh.4375</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10870948</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38370862</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sponselee A.-M.A.G., Van Hoof J. Higher Education Beyond Faculties: Interdisciplinary Education in Care and Technology. Stud. Health Technol. Inform. 2017;242:1024–1029.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28873922</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kampov-Polevoi J., Hemminger B.M. A Curricula-Based Comparison of Biomedical and Health Informatics Programs in the USA. J. Am. Med. Inform. Assoc. 2011;18:195–202. doi: 10.1136/jamia.2010.004259.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/jamia.2010.004259</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3116256</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21292707</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hovenga E.J. Global Health Informatics Education. Stud. Health Technol. Inform. 2000;57:3–14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10947666</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diomidus M., Mantas J. Assessing the Progress of the M.Sc. Course in Health Informatics under the ERASMUS Programme. Int. J. Med. Inform. 1998;50:159–163. doi: 10.1016/S1386-5056(98)00063-X.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1386-5056(98)00063-X</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9726507</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ognjanović I., Šendelj R., Ammenwerth E. The Importance of Health Informatics in Public Health during a Pandemic. Volume 272. IOS Press; Amsterdam, The Netherlands: 2020. Multidisciplinary Approach for Education in Healthcare Management: Case Study from Montenegro; pp. 330–333.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32604669</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valenta A.L., Berner E.S., Boren S.A., Deckard G.J., Eldredge C., Fridsma D.B., Gadd C., Gong Y., Johnson T., Jones J., et al. AMIA Board White Paper: AMIA 2017 Core Competencies for Applied Health Informatics Education at the Master’s Degree Level. J. Am. Med. Inform. Assoc. 2018;25:1657–1668. doi: 10.1093/jamia/ocy132.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jamia/ocy132</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7647152</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30371862</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO . Digital Education for Building Health Workforce Capacity. World Health Organization; Geneva, Switzerland: 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization . Global Strategy on Human Resources for Health: Workforce 2030. Volumn 64 World Health Organization; Geneva, Switzerland: 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dorsey A.D., Clements K., Garrie R.L., Houser S.H., Berner E.S. Bridging the Gap: A Collaborative Approach to Health Information Management and Informatics Education. Appl. Clin. Inform. 2015;6:211–223. doi: 10.4338/ACI-2014-09-RA-0083.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4338/ACI-2014-09-RA-0083</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4493326</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26171071</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hasman A. IMIA Accreditation of Health Informatics Programs. Yearb. Med. Inform. 2012;7:139–143. doi: 10.1055/s-0038-1639445.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1055/s-0038-1639445</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22890356</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mantas J. Informatics Empowers Healthcare Transformation. Volume 238. IOS Press; Amsterdam, The Netherlands: 2017. Accreditation and Certification in Health Informatics: Principles and Procedures; pp. 272–275.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28679942</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jung S. Challenges for Future Directions for Artificial Intelligence Integrated Nursing Simulation Education. Korean J. Women Health Nurs. 2023;29:239. doi: 10.4069/kjwhn.2023.09.06.1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4069/kjwhn.2023.09.06.1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10565529</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37813667</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kretzschmar V., Sailer A., Wertenauer M., Seitz J. Enhanced Educational Experiences through Personalized and AI-Based Learning. Int. J. Stud. Educ. 2024;6:191–209. doi: 10.46328/ijonse.206.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.46328/ijonse.206</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Narayanan S., Ramakrishnan R., Durairaj E., Das A. Artificial Intelligence Revolutionizing the Field of Medical Education. Cureus. 2023;15:e49604. doi: 10.7759/cureus.49604.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.49604</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10755136</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38161821</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buabbas A.J., Miskin B., Alnaqi A.A., Ayed A.K., Shehab A.A., Syed-Abdul S., Uddin M. Investigating Students’ Perceptions towards Artificial Intelligence in Medical Education. Healthcare. 2023;11:1298. doi: 10.3390/healthcare11091298.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/healthcare11091298</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10178742</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37174840</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tolentino R., Baradaran A., Gore G., Pluye P., Abbasgholizadeh-Rahimi S. Curriculum Frameworks and Educational Programs in AI for Medical Students, Residents, and Practicing Physicians: Scoping Review. JMIR Med. Educ. 2024;10:e54793. doi: 10.2196/54793.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/54793</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11294785</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39023999</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giebel G.D., Speckemeier C., Abels C., Plescher F., Börchers K., Wasem J., Blase N., Neusser S. Problems and Barriers Related to the Use of Digital Health Applications: Scoping Review. J. Med. Internet Res. 2023;25:e43808. doi: 10.2196/43808.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/43808</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10221513</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37171838</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Computer and Internet Use in the United States.  [(accessed on 16 March 2024)];2018  Available online:  https://www.census.gov/library/publications/2021/acs/acs-49.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spanakis E.G., Bonomi S., Sfakianakis S., Santucci G., Lenti S., Sorella M., Tanasache F.D., Palleschi A., Ciccotelli C., Sakkalis V., et al. Cyber-Attacks and Threats for Healthcare—A Multi-Layer Thread Analysis; Proceedings of the 2020 42nd Annual International Conference of the IEEE Engineering in Medicine &amp; Biology Society (EMBC); Montreal, QC, Canada. 20–24 July 2020; Piscataway, NJ, USA: IEEE; Jul, 2020. pp. 5705–5708.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33019270</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He Y., Aliyu A., Evans M., Luo C. Health Care Cybersecurity Challenges and Solutions Under the Climate of COVID-19: Scoping Review. J. Med. Internet Res. 2021;23:e21747. doi: 10.2196/21747.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/21747</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8059789</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33764885</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>2021 Data Breach Trend Report.  [(accessed on 16 March 2024)].  Available online:  https://protectedharbor.com/healthcare-data-trend-report/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Symantec Corporation Cyber Security and Healthcare: An Evolving Understanding of Risk Healthcare Organizations and Their Supply Chains Are under Attack—A Review of 2017 and a Look Ahead. Cyber Security and Healthcare (Executive Summary) 2018.  [(accessed on 16 March 2024)].  Available online:  https://docs.broadcom.com/doc/2018-istr-executive-summary-for-healthcare-professionals-en.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jalali M.S., Kaiser J.P. Cybersecurity in Hospitals: A Systematic, Organizational Perspective. J. Med. Internet Res. 2018;20:e10059. doi: 10.2196/10059.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/10059</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5996174</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29807882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nifakos S., Chandramouli K., Nikolaou C.K., Papachristou P., Koch S., Panaousis E., Bonacina S. Influence of Human Factors on Cyber Security within Healthcare Organisations: A Systematic Review. Sensors. 2021;21:5119. doi: 10.3390/s21155119.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/s21155119</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8348467</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34372354</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Department of Health a Human Services  Health Industry Cybersecurity Practices: Managing Threats and Protecting Patients; Healthcare and Public Health Sector Coordinating Council: 2023.  [(accessed on 16 March 2024)]; Available online:  https://405d.hhs.gov/Documents/HICP-Main-508.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Largent E.A., Karlawish J., Wexler A. From an Idea to the Marketplace: Identifying and Addressing Ethical and Regulatory Considerations across the Digital Health Product-Development Lifecycle. BMC Digit. Health. 2024;2:41. doi: 10.1186/s44247-024-00098-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s44247-024-00098-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11308106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39130168</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bente B.E., Van Dongen A., Verdaasdonk R., van Gemert-Pijnen L. EHealth Implementation in Europe: A Scoping Review on Legal, Ethical, Financial, and Technological Aspects. Front. Digit. Health. 2024;6:1332707. doi: 10.3389/fdgth.2024.1332707.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fdgth.2024.1332707</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10957613</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38524249</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Landers C., Vayena E., Amann J., Blasimme A. Stuck in Translation: Stakeholder Perspectives on Impediments to Responsible Digital Health. Front. Digit. Health. 2023;5:1069410. doi: 10.3389/fdgth.2023.1069410.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fdgth.2023.1069410</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9939685</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36815171</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nickel P.J., Loosman I., Frank L., Vinnikova A. Justice and Empowerment Through Digital Health: Ethical Challenges and Opportunities. Digit. Soc. 2023;2:42. doi: 10.1007/s44206-023-00075-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s44206-023-00075-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Access O., Cuff A. The Evolution of Digital Health and Its Continuing Challenges. BMC Digit. Health. 2023;1:3. doi: 10.1186/S44247-022-00004-X.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/S44247-022-00004-X</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9872053</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38014367</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pool J., Akhlaghpour S., Fatehi F., Burton-Jones A. A Systematic Analysis of Failures in Protecting Personal Health Data: A Scoping Review. Int. J. Inf. Manag. 2024;74:102719. doi: 10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2023.102719.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2023.102719</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar A., Chatterjee K. Securing Internet of Medical Devices Using Energy Efficient Blockchain for Healthcare 4.0. Cluster Comput. 2024;27:8333–8348. doi: 10.1007/s10586-024-04437-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10586-024-04437-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gkontra P., Quaglio G., Garmendia A.T., Lekadir K. Clinical Applications of Artificial Intelligence in Real-World Data. Springer International Publishing; Cham, Switzerland: 2023. Challenges of Machine Learning and AI (What Is Next?), Responsible and Ethical AI; pp. 263–285.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-3-031-36678-9_17</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>