<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39455044</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-0953</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Environmental research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Environ Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Construction of a New Emergency Management System for Potentially Viral/Viral Municipal Solid Waste in China: Based on the "Beam-Column Structure" Framework Model.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>120158</StartPage><MedlinePgn>120158</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.envres.2024.120158</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0013-9351(24)02065-6</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Emergency management of municipal solid waste during public health emergencies is crucial for curbing the spread of viruses and controlling environmental pollution. Most existing solid waste management systems, are designed with a top-down approach, covering multiple industries and sectors. However, these systems often fail to effectively manage potentially viral solid waste in household waste, which impedes effective solid waste management during public health emergencies and increases the risk of viral outbreaks. For example, during the COVID-19 outbreak, negligent management of potentially viral solid waste may result in the formation of a potential transmission chain of COVID-19 virus. Improper waste management may contaminate natural vectors such as water, soil and air, thereby increasing the pathways of human contact with infected vectors and promoting the risk of transmission of viral diseases such as dengue, Zika and hepatitis A. In this study, the applicability and limitations of the Chinese public emergency management system in the disposal of Potentially Viral/Viral Municipal Solid Waste (PVMSW) were analyzed in the breakout of public health crises. To address the need for precise risk control, efficient collaboration among key stakeholders, functional integration crossing multiple management organizations and flexible responses to complex situations, we proposed a PVMSW emergency management system based on a "Beam-Column Structure" model. This system consists of four modules: main traction, organizational leadership, functional articulation and demand matching. Each module is supported by the corresponding safeguards, including multi-level subject responsibilities, multi-scenario organization and implementation, multi-chain process connection and multi-demand control methods. The PVMSW emergency management system proposed in this study contributes to extending the framework of existing waste management protocols and enhancing the timely collection, transportation and disposal of PVMSW in public health crises. It offers valuable insights and guidance on the practices for improving risk awareness and management capacity in China's solid waste emergency response.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024. Published by Elsevier Inc.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Ying</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Environment and Energy Engineering, Beijing University of Civil Engineering and Architecture, Beijing 102616, China; Beijing Energy Conservation &amp; Sustainable Urban and Rural Development Provincial and Ministry Co-construction Collaboration Innovation Center, Beijing University of Civil Engineering and Architecture, Beijing 102616, China; Climate Change Research and Talent Training Base in Beijing, Beijing University of Civil Engineering and Architecture, Beijing 100044, China. Electronic address: liy@bucea.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>XueRui</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Environment and Energy Engineering, Beijing University of Civil Engineering and Architecture, Beijing 102616, China. Electronic address: 18272821915@163.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Qu</LastName><ForeName>Yao</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of Science and Technology &amp; Industrialization Development,Ministry of Housing Urban-Rural Development of People's Republic of China, BeiJing 100044, , China; CUCDE Environmental Technology CO.,LTD, BeiJing 100032, China. Electronic address: quyao701@163.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Haoxiang</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Civil and Transportation Engineering, Beijing University of Civil Engineering and Architecture, Beijing 102616, China. Electronic address: chenhaoxiang@bucea.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Xiaojing</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Science, Beijing University of Civil Engineering and Architecture, Beijing 102616, China. Electronic address: xjwang@bucea.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Environ Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0147621</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0013-9351</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Emergency Incident</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Emergency Management System</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Potentially Viral/Viral Municipal Solid Waste</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Public Safety</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of Competing Interest ☐ The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper. ☒ The authors declare the following financial interests/personal relationships which may be considered as potential competing interests: Ying Li reports financial support was provided by The Cultivation project Funds for Beijing University of Civil Engineering and Architecture. Ying Li reports financial support was provided by Beijing Municipal Education Commission. If there are other authors, they declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>25</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>25</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39455044</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2024.120158</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0013-9351(24)02065-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>