<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39455516</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1614-7499</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>26</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Environmental science and pollution research international</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The impact of COVID-19 restrictions on road traffic and noise pollution of the urban street, a case study from Krakow, Poland.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s11356-024-35365-5</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The study determined the impact of restrictions introduced by the Ministry of Health in connection with the COVID-19 pandemic on traffic and sound pressure levels in the university building and its immediate vicinity. Mickiewicza Street was selected for the study. It is one of the city's busiest streets, located relatively close to the old historic center, and is the main artery connecting the north and south of the city. There are residential buildings on this street, but primarily offices and institutions, as well as schools and universities. Noise near the street and in buildings located relatively close to the road can be a serious problem in places where peace is required (e.g., libraries, reading rooms, university halls). Therefore, the acoustic comfort needed in these places may be disturbed, and the perception of knowledge acquisition may be limited. The aim of the work was achieved through measurements and analysis of street traffic intensity and sound pressure levels, taking into account pandemic restrictions. Then, statistical analyses were performed, which showed significant variability in traffic intensity and sound pressure values in individual periods of the pandemic. The pandemic's beginning was mainly characterized by a significant decrease in the above data, deviating from the norm. In the pre-pandemic period, an average of 47,733 vehicles passed through the street daily, and the median sound pressure was L<sub>eq.OUT</sub> = 62.0 dBA outside the building and L<sub>eq.INS</sub> = 44.0 dBA inside. During the greatest restrictions, a period called "lockdown," the number of cars driving decreased a little to an average of 44,153 per day, but there were days with 10,000-20,000 cars passing. In turn, noise decreased to 59.9 dBA for L<sub>eq.OUT</sub> and 43.2 dBA for L<sub>eq.INS</sub>. Between the first and second waves of infections, traffic was comparable to the post-pandemic period (an average of 69,027 cars per day), and noise also increased to L<sub>eq.OUT</sub> = 64-65 dBA and close to L<sub>eq.INS</sub> = 47.5 dBA. Studies have shown that noise on Mickiewicza Street is mainly caused by traffic (correlation coefficient: r = 0.92 for L<sub>eq.OUT</sub> and r = 0.86 for L<sub>eq.INS</sub>). The sound pressure level is high outside (L<sub>eq.OUT</sub> = 63.9 dBA) but relatively low inside the building (L<sub>eq.INS</sub> = 47.0 dBA) and should not negatively affect university staff and students (L<sub>eq.WH</sub> &lt; L<sub>WH.acc</sub>). Based on the analyses, three stages show society's approach to the COVID-19 pandemic: (1) fear of the COVID-19 pandemic; (2) relaxation after restrictions; (3) getting used to the COVID-19 pandemic. These periods did not correlate with the development of the pandemic or the number of people infected and dead.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Plesiński</LastName><ForeName>Karol</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2157-2502</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Environmental Engineering and Geodesy, Department of Hydraulic Engineering and Geotechnics, University of Agriculture in Krakow, Mickiewicza Street 24/28, 30-059, Kraków, Poland. karol.plesinski@urk.edu.pl.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cholewa</LastName><ForeName>Mariusz</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Environmental Engineering and Geodesy, Department of Hydraulic Engineering and Geotechnics, University of Agriculture in Krakow, Mickiewicza Street 24/28, 30-059, Kraków, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9441769</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0944-1344</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Acoustic parameters</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19 pandemic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19 restrictions</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Main urban street</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Noise pollution</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2 coronavirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Street traffic</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39455516</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-024-35365-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s11356-024-35365-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Abbaspour M, Golmohammadi R, Nassiri P, Mahjub H (2006) An investigation on time-interval optimisation of traffic noise measurement. J Low Freq Noise Vib Act Control 25:267–273. https://doi.org/10.1260/026309206779884883</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1260/026309206779884883</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdmouleh MA, Dahech S (2024) Spatio-temporal variation of noise pollution in South Paris during and outside the COVID-19 lockdowns. Sci Rep 14:1487. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-51305-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-51305-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akhtar N, Kafeel A, Gangopadhyay S (2012) Road traffic noise mapping and a case study for Delhi region. Int J Appl Eng Technol 2(4):39–45</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aletta F, Oberman T, Mitchell A, Tong H, Kang J (2020) Assessing the changing urban sound environment during the COVID-19 lockdown period using short-term acoustic measurements. Noise Mapp 7(1):123–134. https://doi.org/10.1515/noise-2020-0011</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1515/noise-2020-0011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alías-Pujol F, Angelini F, Alsina-Pagès RM, Zambon G, Benocci R (2024) A long-term global and clustering analysis of the COVID-19 pandemic effects on the sound environment of Milan, Italy: road traffic and other noise sources. Appl Acoust 221:110036</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.apacoust.2024.110036</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alsina-Pagès RM, Alías F, Bellucci P, Cartolano PP, Coppa I, Peruzzi L, Bisceglie A, Zambon G (2020) Noise at the time of COVID 19: the impact in some areas in Rome and Milan. Italy Noise Mapp 7(1):248–264. https://doi.org/10.1515/noise-2020-0021</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1515/noise-2020-0021</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alsina-Pagès RM, Bergadà P, Martínez-Suquía C (2021) Changes in the soundscape of Girona during the COVID lockdown. J Acoust Soc Am 149:3416–3423. https://doi.org/10.1121/10.0004986</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1121/10.0004986</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alvares-Sanches T, Osborne PE, White PR (2023) Impacts of the COVID lockdown on the soundscape of an urban area: noise, psychoacoustic metrics and ecoacoustic indices. Inter-Noise Noise-Con Congress Conf Proceed Jpn Chiba 9:5700–5708. https://doi.org/10.3397/IN_2023_0812</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3397/IN_2023_0812</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amoatey P, Al-Harthy I, Al-Jabri K et al (2022) Impact of COVID-19 pandemic on aircraft noise levels, annoyance, and health effects in an urban area in Oman. Environ Sci Pollut Res 29:23407–23418. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11356-021-17514-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-021-17514-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amoatey P, Al-Harthy I, Amankona D, Douban S, Izady A, Chen M, Al-Jabri K, Al-Alawi M (2023) Contribution of outdoor noise-induced health risk in schools located in urbanized arid country. Environ Sci Pollut Res 30(16):48107–48119. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11356-023-25643-z</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-023-25643-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Announcement (2014) Announcement of the Minister of the Environment of 22 January 2014 regarding the publication of the uniform text of the regulation of the Minister of the Environment on permissible environmental noise levels. Dziennik Ustaw 112:1–6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asensio C, Pavón I, de Arcas G (2020) Changes in noise levels in the city of Madrid during COVID-19 lockdown in 2020. J Acoust Soc Am 148:1748–1755. https://doi.org/10.1121/10.0002008</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1121/10.0002008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Audrin T, Apparicio P, Ségui A-M (2022) Aircraft noise and environmental equity in Montréal: a comparison of noise indicators and an analysis of the impacts of COVID-19. Transp Res D Transp Environ 106:103274. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.trd.2022.103274</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.trd.2022.103274</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aumond P, Can A, Lagrange M, Gontier F, Lavandier C (2022) Multidimensional analyses of the noise impacts of COVID-19 lockdown. J Acoust Soc Am 151:911–923. https://doi.org/10.1121/10.0009324</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1121/10.0009324</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ayush G, Elizabeth AJ, Patil VV, Herlekar M (2022) Noise levels in urban and rural settlements of Bhubaneswar: a case study. Nat Environ Pollut Technol 21(2):231–239. https://doi.org/10.46488/NEPT.2022.v21i01.026</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.46488/NEPT.2022.v21i01.026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bazaras J, Jablonskytė J, Jotautienė E (2010) Interdependence of noise and traffic flow. Transport 23:67–72. https://doi.org/10.3846/1648-4142.2008.23.67-72</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3846/1648-4142.2008.23.67-72</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berglund B, Lindvall T, Schwela DH (1999) Guidelines for community noise. World Health Organization. Geneva, p 141</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boczkowska K, Frątczak M, Nowacka A (2014) Koncepcja metodyki oceny ryzyka w narażeniu na hałas. Zeszyty Naukowe Politechniki Łódzkiej, Organizacja i Zarządzanie 1193(53):5–26</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bohatkiewicz J, Czarnecka W, Jamrozik K, Biernacki S, Hałucha M (2014) Impact of traffic calming on acoustic climate in street surrounding. Budownictwo i Architektura 13(1):235–252</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.35784/bud-arch.1943</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bouzir TAK, Zemmouri N, Berkouk D (2017) Assessment of noise pollution in the city of Biskra, Algeria. Int J Environ Ecol Eng 11(12):486–491</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown MB, Forsythe AB (1974) Robust tests for the equality of variances. J Am Stat Assoc 69(346):364–367. https://doi.org/10.2307/2285659</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2307/2285659</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caraka RE, Yusra Y, Toharudin T, Chen R-C, Basyuni M, Juned V, Gio PU, Pardamean B (2021) Did noise pollution really improve during COVID-19? Evid Taiwan Sustain 13:5946. https://doi.org/10.3390/su13115946</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/su13115946</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Casla-Herguedas B, Romero-Fernández A, Carrascal T, Navas-Martín MÁ, Cuerdo-Vilches T (2023) Noise perception and health effects on population: a cross-sectional study on COVID-19 lockdown by noise sources For Spanish dwellings. Buildings 13(9):2224. https://doi.org/10.3390/buildings13092224</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/buildings13092224</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choi J, Utembe S, Fisher G, Torre P (2021) Air pollution impacts in Melbourne, Victoria associated with COVID-19 measures in 2020. Air Quality and Climate Change 55(1):16–32</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chowdhury A, Debsarkar A, Chakraborty S (2015) Critical assessment of day time traffic noise level at curbside open-air microenvironment of Kolkata City. India J Environ Health Sci Eng 13:1–6. https://doi.org/10.1186/s40201-015-0219-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40201-015-0219-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chowdhury A, Debsarkar A, Chakraborty S (2016) Assessment of seasonal variations of average traffic pollution levels in curbside open-air microenvironments in Kolkata India. Health Scope 5(2):33081. https://doi.org/10.17795/jhealthscope-33081</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.17795/jhealthscope-33081</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Čurović L, Jeram S, Murovec J, Novaković T, Rupnik K, Prezelj J (2021) Impact of COVID-19 on environmental noise emitted from the port. Sci Total Environ 756:144–147. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.144147</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.144147</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Directive 2002/49/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 25 June 2002 relating to the assessment and management of environmental noise – Official Journal of the European Communities L 189 of 18 July 2002.  https://data.europa.eu/eli/dir/2002/49/oj . Accessed 16 Oct 2024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dodge Y (2008) The concise encyclopedia of statistics. Springer-Verlag, New York</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Draft Regulation (2012) Draft Regulation of the Minister of the Environment of 6 September 2012 amending the regulation on permissible environmental noise levels. Ministry of the Environment, Warsaw, pp 1–11</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Draft Regulation (2012) Draft Regulation of the Minister of the Environment of 20 September 2012 amending the regulation on permissible environmental noise levels. Ministry of the Environment, Warsaw, pp 1–15</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duszyński J, Afelt A, Kossowska M, Ochab-Marcinek A, Owczuk R, Paczos W, Plater-Zyberk A, Pyrć K, Rosińska M, Rychard A, Smiatacz T (2021) Kroniki pandemii. Lata 2020-2021. Magazyn Polskiej Akademii Nauk 4(68):1–120</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EEA Report (2014) Noise in Europe 2014. 10, European environment agency, Copenhagen</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ewens WJ, Grant GR (2001) Statistical methods in bioinformatics. Springer-Verlag, Berlin</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-1-4757-3247-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fisher RA (1935) The Design of Experiments. Oliver &amp; Boyd, Edinburgh</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freitas EF, Martins FF, Oliveira A, Segundo IR, Torres H (2018) Traffic noise and pavement distresses: modelling and assessment of in- put parameters influence through data mining techniques. Appl Acoust 138:147–155. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apacoust.2018.03.019</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.apacoust.2018.03.019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gardziejczyk W (2018) Hałaśliwość nawierzchni drogowych. Oficyna Wydawnicza Politechniki Białostockiej, Białystok</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gevú N, Carvalho B, Fagerlande GC, Niemeyer ML, Medeiros Cortês M, Boscher Torres JC (2021) Rio de Janeiro noise mapping during the COVID-19 pandemic period. Noise Mapp 8:162–171. https://doi.org/10.1515/noise-2021-0012</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1515/noise-2021-0012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gierasimiuk P, Motylewicz M (2014) Traffic noise in the vicinity of roads and streets - assessment problems and protective actions. In: Skoczko I, Piekutin J, Zarzecka A, Gregorczuk-Petersons E (eds) Inżynieria Środowiska - Młodym Okiem. Oficyna Wydawnicza Politechniki Białostockiej, Białystok, pp 1–33</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>IEC 61672–1 standard (2013) Electroacoustics - sound level meters - part 1: specifications. Inte Electrotech Commission, Edition 2:15</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ISO 1996–1:2016. Acoustic – description, measurement and assessment of environmental noise. Part 1: basic quantities and assessment procedures. International Standard, 3<sup>rd</sup> edition, Geneva, Switzerland, 6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jensen P (1973) Control of environmental noise. J Air Pollut Control Assoc 23(12):1028–1034. https://doi.org/10.1080/00022470.1973.10469874</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/00022470.1973.10469874</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jóźwiak Z (2014) Analiza porównawcza poziomu hałasu w wybranych punktach Szczecina. Logistyka 6:13420–13426</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khomenko S, Cirach M, Barrera-Gómez J, Pereira-Barboza E, Iungman T, Mueller N, Foraster M, Tonne C, Thondoo M, Jephcote C, Gulliver J, Woodcock J, Nieuwenhuijsen M (2022) Impact of road traffic noise on annoyance and preventable mortality in European cities: a health impact assessment. Environ Int. 162:107160. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2022.107160</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2022.107160</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kraszewski M, Kucharski RJ, Kurpiewski A (1996) Metody pomiaru hałasu zewnętrznego w środowisku. Warszawa, Państwowa Inspekcja Ochrony Środowiska, Biblioteka Monitoringu Środowiska, p 76</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kruskal WH (1952) A nonparametric test for the several sample problem. Ann Math Stat 23(4):525–540. https://doi.org/10.1214/aoms/1177729332</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1214/aoms/1177729332</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kruskal WH, Wallis WA (1952) Use of ranks in one-criterion variance analysis. J Am Stat Assoc 47(260):583–621. https://doi.org/10.2307/2280779</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2307/2280779</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar P, Nigam SP, Kumar N (2014) Vehicular traffic noise modeling using artificial neural network approach. Transp Res c: Emerg Technol 40:111–122. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.trc.2014.01.006</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.trc.2014.01.006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Licitra G, Teti L, Cerchiai M, Bianco F (2017) The influence of tyres on the use of the CPX method for evaluating the effectiveness of a noise mitigation action based on low-noise road surfaces. Transp Res d: Transp Environ 55:217–226</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.trd.2017.07.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maggi AL, Muratore J, Gaetán S, Zalazar-Jaime MF, Evin D, Villalobo JP, Hinalaf M (2021) Perception of the acoustic environment during COVID-19 lockdown in Argentina. J. Acoust. Soc. Am. 149:3902–3909. https://doi.org/10.1121/10.0005131</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1121/10.0005131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mamun MMA., Shil A, Paul A Paul P (2017) Analysis of noise pollution impacting educational institutes near busy traffic nodes in Chittagong City. 1st International Conference on Green Architecture (ICGrA 2017), 127–133</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maranda K (2008) Mapy Akustyczne Dróg Krajowych. Magazyn Autostrady 1–2:37–41</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mimani A, Singh R (2021) Anthropogenic noise variation in Indian cities due to the COVID-19 lockdown during March-to-May 2020. J Acoust Soc Am 150:3216–3227. https://doi.org/10.1121/10.0006966</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1121/10.0006966</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Health (2024) https://www.gov.pl/web/koronawirus . Accessed 16 Oct 2024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitchell A, Oberman T, Aletta F, Kachlicka M, Lionello M, Erfanian M, Kang J (2021) Investigating urban soundscapes of the COVID-19 lockdown: a predictive soundscape modeling approach. J Acoust Soc Am 150:4474–4488. https://doi.org/10.1121/10.0008928</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1121/10.0008928</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mrčelić GJ, Vukić L, Jambrošić K (2023) Multi-faceted analysis of airborne noise impact in the Port of Split (II). J Mar Sci Eng 11:1189. https://doi.org/10.3390/jmse11061189</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/jmse11061189</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munir S, Khan S, Nazneen S, Ahmad SS (2021) Temporal and seasonal variations of noise pollution in urban zones: a case study in Pakistan. Environ Sci Pollut Res 28:29581–29589. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11356-021-12738-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-021-12738-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Münzel T, Kröller-Schön S, Oelze M, Gori T, Schmidt FP, Steven S, Hahad O, Röösli M, Wunderli JM, Daiber A, Sørensen M (2020) Adverse cardiovascular effects of traffic noise with a focus on nighttime noise and the new WHO noise guidelines. Annu Rev Public Health 41:310–322. https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-publhealth-081519-062400</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1146/annurev-publhealth-081519-062400</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ohaeri EC, Obafemi AA (2024) Impact analysis of noise pollution on human-health: a case study of southern region of Nigeria. J Energy Res Rev 16(2):1–8. https://doi.org/10.9734/jenrr/2024/v16i2332</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.9734/jenrr/2024/v16i2332</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>OSHA (2022) Technical manual (OTM) Section III: chapter 5, Table G-16 permissible noise exposure. https://www.osha.gov/otm/section-3-health-hazards/chapter-5#standards . Accessed 16 Oct 2024</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poniatowski P (2022) Permissible levels of road traffic noise – a few remarks on illusory acoustic protection. Palestra 6:67–86. https://doi.org/10.54383/0031-0344.2022.6.5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.54383/0031-0344.2022.6.5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rącka I, Szopińska K (2017) Investment decisions on the local housing market vs. road noise. Wydawnictwo Uniwersytetu Ekonomicznego we Wrocławiu. 483:100–117. https://doi.org/10.15611/pn.2017.483.09</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15611/pn.2017.483.09</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ranpise R, Tandel B (2022) Urban road traffic noise monitoring, mapping, modelling, and mitigation: a thematic review. Noise Mapp 9(1):48–66. https://doi.org/10.1515/noise-2022-0004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1515/noise-2022-0004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Regulation (1980) Regulation of the Council of Ministers of 30 September 1980 on environmental protection against noise and vibration. Dziennik Ustaw 24(90):257–259</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Regulation (1998) Regulation of the Minister of Environmental Protection, Natural Resources and Forestry of 13 May 1998 on permissible noise levels in the environment. Dziennik Ustaw 66(436):2558–2560</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Regulation (2004) Regulation of the Minister of the Environment of 29 July 2004 on permissible noise levels in the environment. Dziennik Ustaw 178(1841):12482–12484</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Regulation (2007) Regulation of the Minister of the Environment of 14 June 2007 on permissible noise levels in the environment. Dziennik Ustaw 120(826):8276–8280</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Regulation, (2011) Regulation of the minister of the environment of 16 June 20011 on requirements for conducting measurements of substance or energy levels in the environment by the manager of a road, railway line, tram line, airport or port. Dziennik Ustaw 140(824):8505–8532</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Regulation (2012) Regulation of the Minister of the Environment of 8 October 2012 on permissible noise levels in the environment. Dziennik Ustaw 1109:1–3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodríguez R, Machimbarrena M, Tarrero AI (2022) Environmental noise evolution during COVID-19 state of emergency: evidence of Peru’s need for action plans. Acoustics 4(2):479–491. https://doi.org/10.3390/acoustics4020030</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/acoustics4020030</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rumpler R, Venkataraman S, Goransson P (2020) An observation of the impact of CoViD-19 recommendation measures monitored through urban noise levels in central Stockholm. Sweden Sustainable Cities Soc 63(102469):1–8. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scs.2020.102469</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scs.2020.102469</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Said G, Arias A, Carilli L, Stasi A (2020) Urban noise measurements in the city of Buenos Aires during the mandatory quarantine. J Acoust Soc Am 148:3149–3152. https://doi.org/10.1121/10.0002423</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1121/10.0002423</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sburlati D, Miller A, Williams A (2019) Nambucca heads to Urunga low noise diamond grinding pavement noise monitoring. Roads and Maritime Services, SLR Consulting Australia, Lane Cove NSW</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shapiro SS, Wilk MB (1965) An analysis of variance test for normality (complete samples). Biometrika 52(3–4):591–611. https://doi.org/10.2307/2333709</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2307/2333709</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh D, Kumari N, Sharma P (2018) A review of adverse effects of road traffic noise on human health. FNL 17(1):1830001–1831332. https://doi.org/10.1142/S021947751830001X</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1142/S021947751830001X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh N, Tiwari M, Manar M, Shukla SP, Mohan D (2023) Statistical and spatio-temporal analyses of noise pollution level and its health impact. Environ Sci Pollut Res 30:82951–82963. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11356-023-28264-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-023-28264-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spennemann DH, Parker M (2020) Hitting the ‘pause’ button: what does COVID-19 tell us about the future of heritage sounds? Noise Mapp 7(1):265–275. https://doi.org/10.1515/noise-2020-0022</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1515/noise-2020-0022</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Szopińska K (2015) Traffic noise as factor affecting the attractiveness of the city’s recreation and relaxation areas. Logistyka 3:4740–4749</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Staiano MA (2018) Tire–pavement noise and pavement texture. J Transp Eng B Pavements 144(3):04018034. https://doi.org/10.1061/JPEODX.0000047</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1061/JPEODX.0000047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stansfeld SA, Matheson MP (2003) Noise pollution: non-auditory effects on health. Br. Med. Bull. 68(1):243–257</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/bmb/ldg033</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Supranowicz E (1995) Nazwy ulic Krakowa. Institute of Polish Language. Polish Academy of Science, Kraków</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tandel BN, Macwan JE (2013) Assessment and MLR modelling of urban traffic noise at major arterial roads of an Indian city. J Environ Res Dev (JERAD) 7:1703–1709</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tandel BN, Macwan JE (2017) Road traffic noise exposure and hearing impairment among traffic policemen in Surat. Western India. J Inst Eng (India) A 98(1):101–5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40030-017-0210-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tian B, Liu Y, Niu K, Li S, Xie J, Li X (2014) Reduction of tire-pavement noise by porous concrete pavement. J Mater Civ Eng 26(2):233–239. https://doi.org/10.1061/(ASCE)MT.1943-5533.0000809</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1061/(ASCE)MT.1943-5533.0000809</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tobías A, Recio A, Díaz J, Linares C (2015) Health impact assessment of traffic noise in Madrid (Spain). Environ Res 137:136–140. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envres.2014.12.011</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2014.12.011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trudeau C, Tarlao C, Guastavino C (2023) Montreal soundscapes during the COVID-19 pandemic: a spatial analysis of noise complaints and residents’ surveys. Noise Mapp 10(1):20220169. https://doi.org/10.1515/noise-2022-0169</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1515/noise-2022-0169</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vida Manzano J, Almagro Pastor JA, García Quesada R, Aletta F, Oberman T, Mitchell A, Kang JEE (2021) The “sound of silence” in Granada during the COVID-19 lockdown. Noise Mapp 8:16–31. https://doi.org/10.1515/noise-2021-0002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1515/noise-2021-0002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vílchez-Gómez R, BarrigónMorillas JM, Montes González D, Rey-Gozalo G (2023) Drastic mobility restrictions during SARS-CoV-2 pandemic: an opportunity to learn about constraints on the way to a pollution-free city. Environ Sci Pollut Res Int 30(58):122182–122199. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11356-023-30631-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-023-30631-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yildirim Y, Keshavarzi G, Arefi M (2023) Noise complaints, the COVID-19 pandemic, and compact developments: evidence from five American cities. Environ Sci Pollut Res 30(14):40724–40736. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11356-023-25133-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11356-023-25133-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zambon G, Confalonieri C, Benocci AF, R, (2021) Effects of COVID-19 outbreak on the sound environment of the city of Milan. Italy Noise Mapp 8(1):116–128. https://doi.org/10.1515/noise-2021-0009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1515/noise-2021-0009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zijadić N (2021) Impact of COVID-19 in 2020 on the operation of Sarajevo airport. In: 22nd International Symposium on Quality “Quality – Yesterday, today, tomorrow”, Poreč, 9–11 June 2021, pp 139–155.  https://doi.org/10.52730/izbg5486</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>