<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39455623</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2045-2322</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>14</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>25</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Scientific reports</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Sci Rep</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Novel metal-organic framework biosensing platform for detection of COVID-19 RNA.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>25437</StartPage><MedlinePgn>25437</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">25437</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1038/s41598-024-75668-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The latest pandemic resulting from the novel SARS-CoV-2 coronavirus has significantly affected public health, the worldwide economy, and social life. Metal organic frameworks (MOFs) are currently being implemented in biosensors for rapid and accurate detection of viruses thanks to their exceptional properties. This research aims to develop a Zeolitic Imidazolate Framework-8 (ZIF-8) based fluorescent biosensor for facile and rapid COVID-19 RNA sequence detection. ZIF-8 was characterized using several tests, such as FT-IR, TGA, and PXRD, to examine the MOF's crystalline structure and thermal stability. The results demonstrated high crystallinity and thermal stability up to a temperature of 550 °C. The experimental study showed that ZIF-8 is an excellent fluorescence quencher, with 78.39% quenching efficiency. Analyzing the adsorption mechanism of probe DNA into ZIF-8 revealed that they can form electrostatic and π-π stacking interactions, forming a P-DNA@ZIF-8 complex and that PET is more dominant than FRET in the quenching mechanism. This ZIF-8 biosensing platform showed high sensitivity towards COVID-19 RNA with an ultra-low limit of detection of 6.24 pM, a rapid detection time of 8 min, and high selectivity to COVID-19 RNA. Indeed, ZIF-8 experienced much lower fluorescence recovery when tested on two mismatched RNAs. The experimental results show the potential use of ZIF-8 as a novel biosensor for a rapid and sensitive COVID-19 diagnosis.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Elgazar</LastName><ForeName>Aya</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Chemical and Biological Engineering, American University of Sharjah, 26666, Sharjah, United Arab Emirates.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sabouni</LastName><ForeName>Rana</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Chemical and Biological Engineering, American University of Sharjah, 26666, Sharjah, United Arab Emirates. rsabouni@aus.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ghommem</LastName><ForeName>Mehdi</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Mechanical Engineering, American University of Sharjah, 26666, Sharjah, United Arab Emirates.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Majdalawieh</LastName><ForeName>Amin F</ForeName><Initials>AF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biology, Chemistry, and Environmental Sciences, College of Arts and Sciences, American University of Sharjah, 26666, Sharjah, United Arab Emirates.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>FRG22-C-E27</GrantID><Agency>American University of Sharjah (AUS)</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>OAPCEN-1410-E00 308</GrantID><Agency>American University of Sharjah (AUS)</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Sci Rep</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101563288</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2045-2322</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000073396">Metal-Organic Frameworks</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D012367">RNA, Viral</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>1318-02-1</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D017641">Zeolites</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="C000715613">ZIF-8 metal-organic framework</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D007093">Imidazoles</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000073396" MajorTopicYN="Y">Metal-Organic Frameworks</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015374" MajorTopicYN="Y">Biosensing Techniques</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012367" MajorTopicYN="Y">RNA, Viral</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000032" MajorTopicYN="N">analysis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="Y">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="N">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D057230" MajorTopicYN="N">Limit of Detection</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017641" MajorTopicYN="N">Zeolites</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007093" MajorTopicYN="N">Imidazoles</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="N">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Biosensor</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19 RNA sequence</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Detection limit</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Metal–organic frameworks</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Probe DNA</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ZIF-8</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39455623</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11511930</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-75668-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1038/s41598-024-75668-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. WHO Coronavirus (COVID-19) Dashboard | WHO Coronavirus (COVID-19) Dashboard With Vaccination Data. https://covid19.who.int/ (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheikh Ismail, L. et al. Impact of the coronavirus pandemic (COVID-19) lockdown on mental health and well-being in the United Arab Emirates. Front. Psychiatry12, 265 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8007782</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33796033</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bedford, J. et al. COVID-19: Towards controlling of a pandemic. The Lancet395, 1015–1018 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7270596</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32197103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quraishi, M., Upadhyay, S. K. &amp; Nigam, A. COVID-19 diagnostics: A panoramic view on its present scenario, challenges and solutions. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. India Section B Biol. Sci.92, 709–721 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9137266</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35669849</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan, A. S. et al. The virological, immunological, and imaging approaches for COVID-19 diagnosis and research. SLAS Technol.25, 522–544 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7435207</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32808850</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carter, L. J. et al. Assay techniques and test development for COVID-19 diagnosis. ACS Cent. Sci.6, 591–605 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7197457</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32382657</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tahamtan, A. &amp; Ardebili, A. Real-time RT-PCR in COVID-19 detection: Issues affecting the results. 10.1080/14737159.2020.175743720, 453–454 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7189409</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32297805</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orooji, Y. et al. An overview on SARS-CoV-2 (COVID-19) and other human coronaviruses and their detection capability via amplification assay, chemical sensing, biosensing, immunosensing, and clinical assays. Nano-Micro Lett.13, 1–30 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7604542</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33163530</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Purohit, S., Rao, P. K. &amp; Rawtani, D. Sampling and analytical techniques for COVID-19. in COVID-19 in the Environment 75–94 (Elsevier, 2022). 10.1016/B978-0-323-90272-4.00008-7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Narwade, M., Shaikh, A., Gajbhiye, K. R., Kesharwani, P. &amp; Gajbhiye, V. Advanced cancer targeting using aptamer functionalized nanocarriers for site-specific cargo delivery. Biomater. Res.27, 42 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10164340</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37149607</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharabati, A. et al. Biomedical applications of metal−organic frameworks for disease diagnosis and drug delivery: A review. Nanomaterials12, 277 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8780624</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35055294</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao, Y. et al. Two-dimensional porphyrin-Co9S8 nanocomposites with synergistic peroxidase-like catalysis: Synthesis and application toward colorimetric biosensing of H2O2 and glutathione. Colloids Surf. A Physicochem. Eng. Asp.568, 248–258 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Y. et al. Metal-organic frameworks for virus detection. Biosens. Bioelectron.169, 112604 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7489328</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32980805</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdel-Magied, A. F., Abdelhamid, H. N., Ashour, R. M., Zou, X. &amp; Forsberg, K. Hierarchical porous zeolitic imidazolate frameworks nanoparticles for efficient adsorption of rare-earth elements. Microporous Mesoporous Mater.278, 175–184 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Q. et al. Fabrication of polyphenol-etched amino acid-modified ZIF-8 and their carbonic anhydrase-like catalytic activity. Colloids Surf. A Physicochem. Eng. Asp.682, 132882 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Q., Sun, Y., Li, S., Zhang, P. &amp; Yao, Q. Synthesis and modification of ZIF-8 and its application in drug delivery and tumor therapy. RSC Adv.10, 37600–37620 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9057214</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35515141</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park, K. S. et al. Exceptional chemical and thermal stability of zeolitic imidazolate frameworks. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.103, 10186–10191 (2006).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1502432</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16798880</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trino, L. D. et al. ZIF-8 metal-organic framework electrochemical biosensor for the detection of protein-protein interaction. Chem. Mater.33, 1293–1306 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdelhamid, H. N. Zeolitic imidazolate frameworks (ZIF-8) for biomedical applications: A review. Curr. Med. Chem.28, 7023–7075 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34102965</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan, Y., Zhan, S. &amp; Xia, F. Zeolitic imidazolate framework-based biosensor for detection of HIV-1 DNA. Anal. Biochem.546, 5–9 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29382468</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, J., Yang, K., Wu, Z., Li, X. &amp; Duan, Q. Nitrogen-doped porous carbon-based fluorescence sensor for the detection of ZIKV RNA sequences: Fluorescence image analysis. Talanta205, 120091 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31450455</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehmandoust, M., Gumus, Z. P., Soylak, M. &amp; Erk, N. Electrochemical immunosensor for rapid and highly sensitive detection of SARS-CoV-2 antigen in the nasal sample. Talanta240, 123211 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8730781</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34999319</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang, Z. W., Zhao, T. T., Li, C. M., Li, Y. F. &amp; Huang, C. Z. 2D MOF-based photoelectrochemical aptasensor for SARS-CoV-2 spike glycoprotein detection. ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces13, 49754–49761 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34657424</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palanisamy, S. et al. One-step-one-pot hydrothermally derived metal-organic-framework-nanohybrids for integrated point-of-care diagnostics of SARS-CoV-2 viral antigen/pseudovirus utilizing electrochemical biosensor chip. Sens. Actuators B Chem.390, 133960 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10170875</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37193120</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, X. et al. MIL-101(CuFe) Nanozymes with excellent peroxidase-like activity for simple, accurate, and visual naked-eye detection of SARS-CoV-2. Anal. Chem.95, 1731–1738 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36576944</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rabiee, N. et al. Bioactive hybrid metal-organic framework (MOF)-based nanosensors for optical detection of recombinant SARS-CoV-2 spike antigen. Sci. Total Environ.825, 153902 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8849853</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35182622</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rabiee, N. et al. Porphyrin molecules decorated on metal–organic frameworks for multi-functional biomedical applications. Biomolecules11, 1714 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8615380</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34827712</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gumilar, G. et al. Rapid and label-free screening of SARS-CoV-2 virus in the infected human nasopharyngeal swab samples using UiO-66-modified SPR chip. J. Ind. Eng. Chem.127, 467–475 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reyes, S. et al. Metal organic framework encapsulated tamavidin-Gluc reporter: Application in COVID-19 spike antigen bioluminescent immunoassay. Sens. Diagn.1, 1198–1208 (2022).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9662597</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36561132</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alkhodairy, H., Naeem, M., Helal, A., Khalil, A. B. &amp; Bajis, A. Development of Metal organic Framework Based Biosensor to Detect the Coronavirus (Covid-19). bioRxiv 2022.08.20.504642 (2022) 10.1101/2022.08.20.504642.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodrigues, M. G. F., Barbosa, T. L. A. &amp; Rodrigues, D. P. A. Zinc imidazolate framework-8 nanoparticle application in oil removal from oil/water emulsion and reuse. J. Nanopart. Res.22, 1–15 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma, R. et al. Metal-organic framework ZIF-8 for exceptional HCl removal from Hydrogen gas by reaction. Int. J. Hydrog. Energy47, 20556–20560 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie, Y. et al. Application of a novel Au@ZIF-8 composite in the detection of bisphenol a by surface-enhanced Raman spectroscopy. Foods12, 813 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9956950</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36832886</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen, T. M. T. et al. A high-performance ZIF-8 membrane for gas separation applications: Synthesis and characterization. Environ. Technol. Innov.31, 103169 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaur, H., Mohanta, G. C., Gupta, V., Kukkar, D. &amp; Tyagi, S. Synthesis and characterization of ZIF-8 nanoparticles for controlled release of 6-mercaptopurine drug. J. Drug Deliv. Sci. Technol.41, 106–112 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bustamante, E. L., Fernández, J. L. &amp; Zamaro, J. M. Influence of the solvent in the synthesis of zeolitic imidazolate framework-8 (ZIF-8) nanocrystals at room temperature. J. Colloid Interface Sci.424, 37–43 (2014).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24767495</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nasrollahzadeh, M., Atarod, M., Sajjadi, M., Sajadi, S. M. &amp; Issaabadi, Z. Plant-mediated green synthesis of nanostructures: Mechanisms, characterization, and applications. Interface Sci. Technol.28, 199–322 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan, X. et al. Highly porous ZIF-8 nanocrystals prepared by a surfactant mediated method in aqueous solution with enhanced adsorption kinetics. ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces6, 14994–14999 (2014).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25109746</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taheri, M. et al. Stability of ZIF-8 nanopowders in bacterial culture media and its implication for antibacterial properties. Chem. Eng. J.413, 127511 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pinto, M. del C., Duque, A. L. &amp; Macías, P. Fluorescence spectroscopic study on the interaction of resveratrol with lipoxygenase. J. Mol. Struct.980, 143–148 (2010).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui, Y., Yue, Y., Qian, G. &amp; Chen, B. Luminescent functional metal-organic frameworks. Chem. Rev.112, 1126–1162 (2012).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21688849</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao, H. Q. et al. A zinc(II)-based two-dimensional MOF for sensitive and selective sensing of HIV-1 ds-DNA sequences. Anal. Chim. Acta922, 55–63 (2016).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27154832</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, L., Liu, Y. L., Liu, C. G., Ye, F. &amp; Fu, Y. A luminescent sensor based on a new Cd-MOF for nitro explosives and organophosphorus pesticides detection. Inorg. Chem. Commun.122, 108272 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asad, M. et al. Hydrazone connected stable luminescent covalent–organic polymer for ultrafast detection of nitro-explosives. RSC Adv.11, 39270–39277 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9044423</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35492474</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie, B.-P. et al. Simultaneous detection of Dengue and Zika virus RNA sequences with a three-dimensional Cu-based zwitterionic metal–organic framework, comparison of single and synchronous fluorescence analysis. Sens. Actuators B Chem.254, 1133–1140 (2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qin, L. et al. A water-stable metal–organic framework of a zwitterionic carboxylate with dysprosium: A sensing platform for Ebolavirus RNA sequences. Chem. Commun.52, 132–135 (2016).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26502791</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, G. et al. High-efficiency aluminum-metal organic framework/HEPES electrochemiluminescence system for ultrasensitive detection of HBV DNA. Anal. Chem.95, 7030–7035 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37074993</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Y. W. et al. Metal-organic gel and metal-organic framework based switchable electrochemiluminescence RNA sensing platform for Zika virus. Sens. Actuators B Chem.321, 128456 (2020).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>