<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39455424</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1478-5153</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>25</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Nursing in critical care</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Nurs Crit Care</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Exploring the experience of cardiothoracic ICU clinicians during the COVID-19 pandemic: A grounded theory study.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/nicc.13186</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Prior to the COVID-19 pandemic a flexible approach to visiting was adopted by many Intensive Care Units in the United Kingdom. Due to the rapid spread globally of COVID-19, significant policy changes were put in place, including the restriction on visitors to patients in hospital. Evidence has emerged demonstrating the negative impact of these restrictions on patients with COVID-19, their families and the staff caring for them. However, there is limited data about the impact of these restrictions in the non-COVID ICU environment.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="AIM" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">This study aimed to explore the experiences of staff caring for non-COVID-19 patients in a cardiothoracic critical care unit during the COVID-19 pandemic.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="STUDY DESIGN" NlmCategory="METHODS">This qualitative research study adopted a grounded theory methodological approach. This methodology was used due to the unique situation, with no prior research available. We recruited healthcare staff that worked in a cardiothoracic critical care unit during the COVID-19 pandemic. Semi structured interviews were carried out, transcribed, and analysed. Using the data collected, a theory was constructed.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Interviews were carried out with 20 healthcare staff from a range of professions including nurses, doctors, and allied health professionals. Following data analysis four main categories emerged from the data: impact and implementation of visiting restrictions; the dehumanisation of patients; end-of-life care and witnessing distress. From these four categories, a theory has emerged suggesting that healthcare staff in a non-covid ICU were regularly exposed to potentially moral injurious events, despite being shielded from caring for patients with COVID-19.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">This study provides a theory that healthcare staff caring for non-COVID-19 critical care patients during the period of visiting restrictions were exposed to potentially morally injurious events.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RELEVANCE TO CLINICAL PRACTICE" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Repeated exposure to potentially morally injurious events can lead to the development of moral injury and its adverse consequences. This study highlights the need to support all staff in the post COVID era, including those who worked in a non-COVID environment.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Nursing in Critical Care published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of British Association of Critical Care Nurses.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hughes</LastName><ForeName>Leah</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>NHS Ayrshire and Arran, Ayr, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shelley</LastName><ForeName>Benjamin</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Golden Jubilee National Hospital, Glasgow, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Medicine, Dentistry and Nursing, University of Glasgow, Glasgow, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>McPeake</LastName><ForeName>Joanne</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Healthcare Improvement Studies Institute, University of Cambridge, Cambridge, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Royal College of Nursing Foundation</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>PD-2019-02-16</GrantID><Agency>THIS Institute, University of Cambridge</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Nurs Crit Care</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9808649</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1362-1017</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cardiothoracic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">health care staff</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">moral injury</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">visiting</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39455424</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/nicc.13186</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. WHO Director‐General's opening remarks at the media briefing on COVID‐19 – 11. 2020. Accessed January 31, 2022. https://www.who.int/director-general/speeches/detail/who-director-general-s-opening-remarks-at-the-media-briefing-on-covid-19---11-march-2020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hugelius K, Harada N, Marutani M. Consequences of visiting restrictions during the COVID‐19 pandemic: an integrative review. Int J Nurs Stud. 2021;121:104000. doi:10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2021.104000</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dos Santos SS, Nassar Junior AP. An outbreak of restrictive intensive care unit visiting policies. Intens Crit Care Nurs. 2022;68:103140. doi:10.1016/j.iccn.2021.103140</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McQueen F, Leitch J. Updated principles for restricting visitors to patients in NHS Scotland during Covid‐19 outbreak. [Letter to healthboards re: visiting]. 2020. Accessed May 24, 2020. http://www.healthliteracyplace.org.uk/media/1568/24-03-2020-updated-principles-for-restricting-visitors-to-patients-in-nhs-scotland-during-covid-19-outbreak.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gibson V, Plowright C, Collins T, et al. Position statement on visiting in adult critical care units in the United Kingdom. Nurs Crit Care. 2012;17(4):213‐218. doi: 10.1111/j.1478‐5153.2012.00513.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hunter JD, Goddard C, Rothwell M, Ketharaju S, Cooper H. A survey of intensive care unit visiting policies in the United Kingdom. Anaesthesia. 2010;65(11):1101‐1105. doi:10.1111/j.1365‐2044.2010.06506.x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosa RG, Falavigna M, da Silva DB, et al. Effect of flexible family visitation on delirium among patients in the intensive care unit: the ICU visits randomized clinical trial. JAMA. 2019;322(3):216‐228. doi:10.1001/jama.2019.8766</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ning J, Cope V. Open visiting in adult intensive care units – a structured literature review. Intensive Crit Care Nurs. 2020;56:102763. doi:10.1016/j.iccn.2019.102763</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McPeake J, Kentish‐Barnes N, Banse E, et al. Clinician perceptions of the impact of ICU family visiting restrictions during the COVID‐19 pandemic: an international investigation. Crit Care. 2023;27(1):33. doi:10.1186/s13054‐023‐04318‐8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kentish‐Barnes N, Morin L, Cohen‐Solal Z, Cariou A, Demoule A, Azoulay E. The lived experience of ICU clinicians during the coronavirus disease 2019 outbreak: a qualitative study. Crit Care Med. 2021;49(6):e585‐e597. doi:10.1097/CCM.0000000000004939</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bryman A. Social Research Methods. 5th ed. Oxford University Press; 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Charmaz K. Constructing Grounded Theory. 2nd ed. SAGE Publications; 2014.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCrae N, Purssell E. Is it really theoretical? A review of sampling in grounded theory studies in nursing journals. J Adv Nurs. 2016;72(10):2284‐2293. doi:10.1111/jan.12986</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noble H, Mitchell G. What is grounded theory? Evid Based Nurs. 2016;19(2):34‐35. doi:10.1136/eb‐2016‐102306</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chun Tie Y, Birks M, Francis K. Grounded theory research: a design framework for novice researchers. SAGE Open Med. 2019;7:7. doi:10.1177/2050312118822927</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Denton G, Davies V, Whyman E, Arora N. A narrative review of the training structure, role, and safety profile of advanced critical care practitioners in adult intensive services in the United Kingdom. Aust Crit Care. 2023;36(1):145‐150. doi:10.1016/j.aucc.2022.12.005</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Litz BT, Kerig PK. Introduction to the special issue on moral injury: conceptual challenges, methodological issues, and clinical applications. J Trauma Stress. 2019;32(3):341‐349. doi:10.1002/jts.22405</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Čartolovni A, Stolt M, Scott PA, Suhonen R. Moral injury in healthcare professionals: a scoping review and discussion. Nurs Ethics. 2021;28(5):590‐602. doi:10.1177/0969733020966776</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williamson V, Stevelink SAM, Greenberg N. Occupational moral injury and mental health: systematic review and meta‐analysis. Br J Psychiatry. 2018;212(6):339‐346. doi:10.1192/bjp.2018.55</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barnes HA, Hurley RA, Taber KH. Moral injury and PTSD: often co‐occurring yet mechanistically different. J Neuropsychiatry Clin Neurosci. 2019;31(2):A4‐A103. doi:10.1176/appi.neuropsych.19020036</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kopacz MS, Ames D, Koenig HG. It's time to talk about physician burnout and moral injury. Lancet Psychiatry. 2019;6(11):e28. doi:10.1016/S2215‐0366(19)30385‐2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosen A, Cahill JM, Dugdale LS. Moral injury in health care: identification and repair in the COVID‐19 era. J Gen Intern Med. 2022;37(14):3739‐3743. doi:10.1007/s11606‐022‐07761‐5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dean W, Talbot S, Dean A. Reframing clinician distress: moral injury not burnout. Federal Practit. 2019;36(9):400‐402.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song YK, Mantri S, Lawson JM, Berger EJ, Koenig HG. Morally injurious experiences and emotions of health care professionals during the COVID‐19 pandemic before vaccine availability. JAMA Netw Open. 2021;4(11):e2136150. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.36150</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Romero‐García M, Delgado‐Hito P, Gálvez‐Herrer M, et al. Moral distress, emotional impact and coping in intensive care unit staff during the outbreak of COVID‐19. Intens Crit Care Nurs. 2022;70:103206. doi:10.1016/j.iccn.2022.103206</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>British Medical Association. Moral Distress and Moral Injury: Recognising and Tackling it for UK Doctors. British Medical Association; 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moss M, Good VS, Gozal D, Kleinpell R, Sessler CN. An official critical care societies collaborative statement‐burnout syndrome in critical care health‐care professionals: a call for action. Chest. 2016;150(1):17‐26. doi:10.1016/j.chest.2016.02.649</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boulton AJ, Slowther AM, Yeung J, Bassford C. Moral distress among intensive care unit professions in the UK: a mixed methods study. BMJ Open. 2023;3:e068918. doi:10.1136/bmjopen‐2022‐068918</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>