<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39453864</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1537-7385</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>103</Volume><Issue>11S Suppl 3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>American journal of physical medicine &amp; rehabilitation</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Am J Phys Med Rehabil</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Respiratory Vaccination Rates in People Living With Spinal Cord Injury/Disorder in Switzerland: A Descriptive Analysis of Coverage and Vaccine Hesitancy.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>S333</StartPage><EndPage>S340</EndPage><MedlinePgn>S333-S340</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/PHM.0000000000002562</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">The aim of the study is to provide a population-based evaluation of vaccination coverage to prevent respiratory complications from SARS-COV-2, influenza, and pneumococcus, among community-dwelling persons with spinal cord injury/disease.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DESIGN" NlmCategory="METHODS">This is a cross-sectional survey conducted in 2022, utilizing questionnaires administered to persons with spinal cord injury/disease living in Switzerland. Main outcomes were ever-vaccination rates for SARS-COV-2, influenza, and pneumococcus. Secondary outcomes included demographics, lesion and education levels, as well as respiratory and cardiovascular conditions. Vaccine hesitancy was additionally assessed for all three vaccines in nonvaccinated persons through questions on reasons for not getting vaccinated.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">A total of 1158 persons participated in this survey. Overall vaccination rates were highest for SARS-COV-2 86.5% (95% CI = 84.4-88.3), followed by influenza 44.6 (41.7-47.6) and pneumococcus: 7.5% (6.0-9.3). The most prominent reasons for not being vaccinated were doubt on effectiveness (72.7%) and potential side effects (60%) for SARS-COV-2, patients did not feel at risk for influenza (57%) and insufficient information from the physician (52.4%) for pneumococcus vaccination.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">In individuals with spinal cord injury/disease, vaccination coverage is notably low for influenza and especially pneumococcus. Vaccine hesitancy varies between vaccination types and is associated with vaccine-specific reasons. These findings underscore the imperative for updated clinical vaccination guidelines, improved public health information, and targeted intervention programs for specific patient groups.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mueller</LastName><ForeName>Gabi</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6391-3737</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Swiss Paraplegic Research, Nottwil, Switzerland (GM, MWGB); Faculty of Health Sciences and Medicine, University of Lucerne, Lucerne, Switzerland (GM, IE-H, MWGB); Swiss Paraplegic Centre, Nottwil, Switzerland (IE-H); REHAB Basel, Basel, Switzerland (MH-G); Clinique Romande de Réadaptation, Sion, Switzerland (XJ); Spinal Cord Injury Center, Balgrist University Hospital, Zurich, Switzerland (MS); and Corporate Health Consulting, Düdingen, Switzerland (SB); and General practitioner practice, Schenkon, Switzerland (CW).</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Eriks-Hoogland</LastName><ForeName>Inge</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7388-6656</Identifier></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hund-Georgiadis</LastName><ForeName>Margret</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4415-2888</Identifier></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jordan</LastName><ForeName>Xavier</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3389-0057</Identifier></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Schubert</LastName><ForeName>Martin</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bertschy</LastName><ForeName>Sue</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9620-6852</Identifier></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wenk</LastName><ForeName>Christian</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Brinkhof</LastName><ForeName>Martin Wg</ForeName><Initials>MW</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9319-665</Identifier></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Am J Phys Med Rehabil</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8803677</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0894-9115</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D007252">Influenza Vaccines</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000086663">COVID-19 Vaccines</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D022242">Pneumococcal Vaccines</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013557" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Switzerland</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013119" MajorTopicYN="Y">Spinal Cord Injuries</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003430" MajorTopicYN="N">Cross-Sectional Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007252" MajorTopicYN="Y">Influenza Vaccines</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000008" MajorTopicYN="N">administration &amp; dosage</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000088823" MajorTopicYN="Y">Vaccination Hesitancy</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000368" MajorTopicYN="N">Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086663" MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19 Vaccines</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000073887" MajorTopicYN="N">Vaccination Coverage</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D022242" MajorTopicYN="N">Pneumococcal Vaccines</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000008" MajorTopicYN="N">administration &amp; dosage</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007251" MajorTopicYN="N">Influenza, Human</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011795" MajorTopicYN="N">Surveys and Questionnaires</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014611" MajorTopicYN="N">Vaccination</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>Financial disclosure statements have been obtained, and no conflicts of interest have been reported by the authors or by any individuals in control of the content of this article.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>28</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39453864</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/PHM.0000000000002562</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00002060-202411003-00013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Restivo V, Costantino C, Bono S, et al.: Influenza vaccine effectiveness among high-risk groups: a systematic literature review and meta-analysis of case-control and cohort studies. Hum Vaccin Immunother 2018;14:724–35</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wyplosz B, Fernandes J, Sultan A, et al.: Pneumococcal and influenza vaccination coverage among at-risk adults: a 5-year French national observational study. Vaccine 2022;40:4911–21</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grana C, Ghosn L, Evrenoglou T, et al.: Efficacy and safety of COVID-19 vaccines. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 2022;12:CD015477</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chamberlain JD, Buzzell A, Gmunder HP, et al.: Comparison of all-cause and cause-specific mortality of persons with traumatic spinal cord injuries to the general Swiss population: results from a national cohort study. Neuroepidemiology 2019;52(3–4):205–13</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fujiwara T, Hara Y, Chino N: Expiratory function in complete tetraplegics: study of spirometry, maximal expiratory pressure, and muscle activity of pectoralis major and latissimus dorsi muscles. Am J Phys Med Rehabil 1999;78:464–9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wan D, Krassioukov AV: Life-threatening outcomes associated with autonomic dysreflexia: a clinical review. J Spinal Cord Med 2014;37:2–10</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raab AM, Mueller G, Elsig S, et al.: Systematic review of incidence studies of pneumonia in persons with spinal cord injury. J Clin Med 2021;11:211</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barman A, Roy SS, Sasidharan SK, et al.: Clinical features and prognosis of COVID-19/SARS-CoV-2 infections in persons with spinal cord injury: a review of current literature. Spinal Cord Ser Cases 2021;7:58</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trautner BW, Atmar RL, Hulstrom A, et al.: Inactivated influenza vaccination for people with spinal cord injury. Arch Phys Med Rehabil 2004;85:1886–9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grohskopf LA, Alyanak E, Ferdinands JM, et al.: Prevention and control of seasonal influenza with vaccines: recommendations of the advisory committee on immunization practices, United States, 2021-22 influenza season. MMWR Recomm Rep 2021;70:1–28</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weaver FM, Hatzakis M, Evans CT, et al.: A comparison of multiple data sources to identify vaccinations for veterans with spinal cord injuries and disorders. J Am Med Inform Assoc 2004;11:377–9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>MacDonald NE: Hesitancy SWGoV: vaccine hesitancy: definition, scope and determinants. Vaccine 2015;33:4161–4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goldstein S, MacDonald NE, Guirguis S: Hesitancy SWGoV: health communication and vaccine hesitancy. Vaccine 2015;33:4212–4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stucki G, Bickenbach J: The international spinal cord injury survey and the learning health system for spinal cord injury. Am J Phys Med Rehabil 2017;96(2 Suppl 1):S2–4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gross-Hemmi MH, Gemperli A, Fekete C, et al.: Methodology and study population of the second Swiss national community survey of functioning after spinal cord injury. Spinal Cord 2021;59:363–72</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brinkhof MW, Fekete C, Chamberlain JD, et al.: Swiss national community survey on functioning after spinal cord injury: protocol, characteristics of participants and determinants of non-response. J Rehabil Med 2016;48:120–30</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brommer B, Engel O, Kopp MA, et al.: Spinal cord injury-induced immune deficiency syndrome enhances infection susceptibility dependent on lesion level. Brain 2016;139(Pt 3):692–707</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>DeVivo MJ, Black KJ, Stover SL: Causes of death during the first 12 years after spinal cord injury. Arch Phys Med Rehabil 1993;74:248–54</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chotiyarnwong C, Pattanakuhar S, Srisuppaphon D, et al.: COVID-19 vaccination status in people with spinal cord injury: results from a cross-sectional study in Thailand. J Spinal Cord Med 2024;47:573–83</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kricorian K, Civen R, Equils O: COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy: misinformation and perceptions of vaccine safety. Hum Vaccin Immunother 2022;18:1950504</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Majid U, Ahmad M, Zain S, et al.: COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy and acceptance: a comprehensive scoping review of global literature. Health Promot Int 2022;37:daac078</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leuchter RK, Jackson NJ, Mafi JN, et al.: Association between Covid-19 vaccination and influenza vaccination rates. N Engl J Med 2022;386:2531–2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garbinsky D, Hunter S, La EM, et al.: State-level variations and factors associated with adult vaccination coverage: a multilevel modeling approach. Pharmacoecon Open 2021;5:411–23</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nowak GJ, Gellin BG, MacDonald NE, et al.: Hesitancy SWGoV: addressing vaccine hesitancy: the potential value of commercial and social marketing principles and practices. Vaccine 2015;33:4204–11</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waites KB, Canupp KC, Chen YY, et al.: Revaccination of adults with spinal cord injury using the 23-valent pneumococcal polysaccharide vaccine. J Spinal Cord Med 2008;31:53–9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waites KB, Canupp KC, Edwards K, et al.: Immunogenicity of pneumococcal vaccine in persons with spinal cord injury. Arch Phys Med Rehabil 1998;79:1504–9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goldstein B, Weaver FM, Hammond MC: New CDC recommendations: annual influenza vaccination recommended for individuals with spinal cord injuries. J Spinal Cord Med 2005;28:383–4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evans CT, Weaver FM, Rogers TJ, et al.: Guideline-recommended management of community-acquired pneumonia in veterans with spinal cord injury. Top Spinal Cord Inj Rehabil 2012;18:300–5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kothari A, McCutcheon C, Graham ID: Defining integrated knowledge translation and moving forward: a response to recent commentaries. Int J Health Policy Manag 2017;6:299–300</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jull J, Giles A, Graham ID: Community-based participatory research and integrated knowledge translation: advancing the co-creation of knowledge. Implement Sci 2017;12:150</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>