<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39453446</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1433-8491</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>25</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>European archives of psychiatry and clinical neuroscience</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Eur Arch Psychiatry Clin Neurosci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Silexan in anxiety, depression, and related disorders: pharmacological background and clinical data.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s00406-024-01923-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>We present a narrative review of clinical trials investigating the anxiolytic and antidepressant effects of silexan, an active substance derived from lavender oil and summarize nonclinical findings from pharmacological studies supporting its therapeutic use. Six studies investigated the efficacy of the lavender oil in patients with subthreshold and generalized anxiety disorders as well as in mixed anxiety and depressive disorder (MADD). Furthermore, we present data indicating that silexan may influence sleep quality as well as anxiety or depressive disorders in individuals with post-COVID-19. Silexan taken orally at a daily dose of 80 mg for 10 weeks was significantly superior to placebo in reducing psychic and somatic symptoms of anxiety and was as effective as 0.5 mg/d lorazepam and 20 mg/d paroxetine. In patients with mild or moderate major depression, silexan was superior to placebo and comparably effective to 50 mg/d sertraline. Significant antidepressant effects were also observed in MADD and depression co-morbid with anxiety. The herbal product had a beneficial effect on activities of daily living and health-related quality of life. Adverse events associated with silexan in clinical trials were limited to eructation and mild, transient gastrointestinal complaints. The herbal product was not associated with drug interactions, sedation, sleep disturbance, dependence and abuse potential, sexual dysfunction, weight gain or withdrawal symptoms. Silexan was therefore safe and effective in subthreshold and syndromal anxiety disorders and in major depression.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kasper</LastName><ForeName>Siegfried</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8278-191X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Molecular Neuroscience, Center of Brain Research, Medical University of Vienna, Spitalgasse 4, Vienna, A-1090, Austria. siegfried.kasper@meduniwien.ac.at.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Eckert</LastName><ForeName>Anne</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Neurobiology Laboratory for Brain Aging and Mental Health, Psychiatric University Clinics Basel, Basel, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Platform Molecular and Cognitive Neurosciences, University of Basel, Basel, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Eur Arch Psychiatry Clin Neurosci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9103030</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0940-1334</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Anxiety disorder</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Depression</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Lavender oil</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pharmacology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Review</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Silexan</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">post-COVID-19</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>12</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39453446</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00406-024-01923-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s00406-024-01923-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Wittchen HU, Jacobi F, Rehm J, Gustavsson A, Svensson M, Jönsson B, Olesen J, Allgulander C, Alonso J, Faravelli C, Fratiglioni L, Jennum P, Lieb R, Maercker A, van Os J, Preisig M, Salvador-Carulla L, Simon R, Steinhausen H-C (2011) The size and burden of mental disorders and other disorders of the brain in Europe 2010. Eur Neuropsychopharmacol 21(9):655–679. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.euroneuro.2011.07.018</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.euroneuro.2011.07.018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21896369</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>GBD 2019 Mental Disorders Collaborators (2022) Global, regional, and national burden of 12 mental disorders in 204 countries and territories, 1990–2019: a systematic analysis for the global burden of Disease Study 2019. Lancet Psychiatry 9(2):137–150. https://doi.org/10.1016/s2215-0366(21)00395-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s2215-0366(21)00395-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8776563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bui E, Fava M (2017) From depression to anxiety, and back. Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica 136(4):341–342. https://doi.org/10.1111/acps.12801</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/acps.12801</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28865404</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saha S, Lim CCW, Cannon DL, Burton L, Bremner M, Cosgrove P, Huo Y, J. MJ (2021) Co-morbidity between mood and anxiety disorders: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Depress Anxiety 38:286–306. https://doi.org/10.1002/da.23113</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/da.23113</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33225514</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carter RM, Wittchen HU, Pfister H, Kessler RC (2001) One-year prevalence of subthreshold and threshold DSM-IV generalized anxiety disorder in a nationally representative sample. Depress Anxiety 13(2):78–88. https://doi.org/10.1002/da.1020</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/da.1020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11301924</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lyndon GJ, Prieto R, Wajsbrot DB, Allgulander C, Bandelow B (2019) Efficacy of venlafaxine extended release in major depressive disorder patients: effect of baseline anxiety symptom severity. Int Clin Psychopharmacol 34(3):110–118. https://doi.org/10.1097/yic.0000000000000256</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/yic.0000000000000256</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30870236</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6445597</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kircanski K, LeMoult J, Ordaz S, Gotlib IH (2017) Investigating the nature of co-occurring depression and anxiety: comparing diagnostic and dimensional research approaches. J Affect Disord 216:123–135. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jad.2016.08.006</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2016.08.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27554605</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braam AW, Copeland JR, Delespaul PA, Beekman AT, Como A, Dewey M, Fichter M, Holwerda TJ, Lawlor BA, Lobo A, Magnusson H, Prince MJ, Reischies F, Wilson KC, Skoog I (2014) Depression, subthreshold depression and comorbid anxiety symptoms in older europeans: results from the EURODEP concerted action. J Affect Disord 155:266–272. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jad.2013.11.011</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2013.11.011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24355647</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y, Tang M, Yuan S, Fu S, Li Y, Li Y, Wang Q, Cao Y, Liu L, Zhang Q (2022) Rhodiola rosea: a therapeutic candidate on cardiovascular diseases. Oxid Med Cell Longev 2022:1348795. https://doi.org/10.1155/2022/1348795</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2022/1348795</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35265260</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8898776</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beard C, Millner AJ, Forgeard MJ, Fried EI, Hsu KJ, Treadway MT, Leonard CV, Kertz SJ, Björgvinsson T (2016) Network analysis of depression and anxiety symptom relationships in a psychiatric sample. Psychol Med 46(16):3359–3369. https://doi.org/10.1017/s0033291716002300</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/s0033291716002300</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27623748</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5430082</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zbozinek TD, Rose RD, Wolitzky-Taylor KB, Sherbourne C, Sullivan G, Stein MB, Roy-Byrne PP, Craske MG (2012) Diagnostic overlap of generalized anxiety disorder and major depressive disorder in a primary care sample. Depress Anxiety 29(12):1065–1071. https://doi.org/10.1002/da.22026</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/da.22026</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23184657</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3629816</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maj M (2005) Psychiatric comorbidity: an artefact of current diagnostic systems? Br J Psychiatry 186:182–184. https://doi.org/10.1192/bjp.186.3.182</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1192/bjp.186.3.182</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15738496</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>American Psychiatric Association (2013) Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-5). In: American Psychiatric A, American Psychiatric Association DSMTF (eds) Neurocognitive disorders. vol Accessed from https://nla.gov.au/nla.cat-vn6261708 , 5th edn. American Psychiatric Association, Arlington, V.A</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (2019) ICD-11: International classification of diseases (11th revision)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eysenck MW, Fajkowska M (2018) Anxiety and depression: toward overlapping and distinctive features. Cogn Emot 32(7):1391–1400. https://doi.org/10.1080/02699931.2017.1330255</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/02699931.2017.1330255</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28608767</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jacobson NC, Newman MG (2017) Anxiety and depression as bidirectional risk factors for one another: a meta-analysis of longitudinal studies. Psychol Bull 143(11):1155–1200. https://doi.org/10.1037/bul0000111</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/bul0000111</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28805400</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hirschfeld RM (2001) The comorbidity of major depression and anxiety disorders: Recognition and Management in Primary Care. Prim Care Companion J Clin Psychiatry 3(6):244–254. https://doi.org/10.4088/pcc.v03n0609</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4088/pcc.v03n0609</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15014592</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">181193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buntrock C, Ebert DD, Lehr D, Smit F, Riper H, Berking M, Cuijpers P (2016) Effect of a web-based guided self-help intervention for Prevention of Major Depression in adults with Subthreshold Depression. JAMA 315(17). https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2016.4326</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Volz H-P, Saliger J, Kasper S, Möller H-J, Seifritz E (2021) Subsyndromal generalised anxiety disorder: operationalisation and epidemiology - a systematic literature survey. Int J Psychiatry Clin Pract 1–10. https://doi.org/10.1080/13651501.2021.1941120</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bandelow B, Zohar J, Hollander E, Kasper S, Moller HJ, World Federation of Societies of Biological Psychiatry Task Force on Treatment Guidelines for Anxiety O-C, Posttraumatic Stress D (2002) World Federation of Societies of Biological Psychiatry (WFSBP) guidelines for the pharmacological treatment of anxiety, obsessive-compulsive and posttraumatic stress disorders. World J Biol Psychiatry 3(4):171–199. https://doi.org/10.3109/15622970209150621</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3109/15622970209150621</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12516310</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santarsieri D, Schwartz TL (2015) Antidepressant efficacy and side-effect burden: a quick guide for clinicians. Drugs Context 4:212290. https://doi.org/10.7573/dic.212290</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7573/dic.212290</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26576188</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4630974</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Longo LP, Johnson B (2000) Addiction: part I. benzodiazepines–side effects, abuse risk and alternatives. Am Family Phys 61(7):2121–2128</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baldwin DS, Montgomery SA, Nil R, Lader M (2007) Discontinuation symptoms in depression and anxiety disorders. Int J Neuropsychopharmacol 10(1):73–84. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1461145705006358</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S1461145705006358</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16359583</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tamam L, Ozpoyraz N (2002) Selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor discontinuation syndrome: a review. Adv Ther 19(1):17–26. https://doi.org/10.1007/BF02850015</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/BF02850015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12008858</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simms BA, Zamponi GW (2014) Neuronal voltage-gated calcium channels: structure, function, and dysfunction. Neuron 82(1):24–45. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2014.03.016</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2014.03.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24698266</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schuwald AM, Nöldner M, Wilmes T, Klugbauer N, Leuner K, Müller WE (2013) Lavender oil-potent anxiolytic properties via modulating voltage dependent calcium channels. PLoS ONE 8(4):e59998. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0059998</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0059998</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23637742</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3639265</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mueller WE, Schuwald A, Noeldner M, Kasper S, Friedland K (2015) Pharmakologische Grundlagen Der Therapeutischen Anwendung Von Silexan (Lasea<sup>®</sup>). [Pharmacological basis of the therapeutic use of Silexan (Lasea<sup>®</sup>)]. Psychopharmakotherapie 22:3–14</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seifritz E, Möller H-J, Volz H-P, Müller WE, Hopyan T, Wacker A, Schläfke S, Kasper S (2021) No abuse potential of Silexan in healthy recreational drug users: a randomized controlled trial. Int J Neuropsychopharmacol 24(3):171–180. https://doi.org/10.1093/ijnp/pyaa064</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ijnp/pyaa064</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33300578</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schjerning O, Rosenzweig M, Pottegard A, Damkier P, Nielsen J (2016) Abuse potential of Pregabalin: a systematic review. CNS Drugs 30(1):9–25. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40263-015-0303-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40263-015-0303-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26767525</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kehr J, Yoshitake T, Koch E, Noeldner M (2010) Effects of intraperitoneal administration of Silexan, an essential oil from flowers of Lavandula angustifolia on extracellular levels of noradrenaline, dopamine and serotonin in the prefrontal cortex of freely moving rats. Planta Med 76(12):P654. https://doi.org/10.1055/s-0030-1264952</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1055/s-0030-1264952</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baldinger P, Höflich AS, Mitterhauser M, Hahn A, Rami-Mark C, Spies M, Wadsak W, Lanzenberger R, Kasper S (2015) Effects of Silexan on the serotonin-1A receptor and microstructure of the human brain: a randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind, cross-over study with molecular and structural neuroimaging. Int J Neuropsychopharmacol 18(4):1–9. https://doi.org/10.1093/ijnp/pyu063</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ijnp/pyu063</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spindelegger C, Lanzenberger R, Wadsak W, Mien LK, Stein P, Mitterhauser M, Moser U, Holik A, Pezawas L, Kletter K, Kasper S (2009) Influence of escitalopram treatment on 5-HT 1A receptor binding in limbic regions in patients with anxiety disorders. Mol Psychiatry 14(11):1040–1050. https://doi.org/10.1038/mp.2008.35</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/mp.2008.35</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18362913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fonseca ECM, Ferreira LR, Figueiredo PLB, Maia C, Setzer WN, Da Silva JKR (2023) Antidepressant effects of essential oils: a review of the past Decade (2012–2022) and Molecular Docking Study of their Major Chemical Components. Int J Mol Sci 24(11). https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms24119244</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Somrudee S, Dawrung S, Chantana M (2017) Subchronic Administration of Linalool decreases depressive-like Behaviour in restrained rats. J Pharm Pharmacol 5(7). https://doi.org/10.17265/2328-2150/2017.07.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duman RS, Heninger GR, Nestler EJ (1997) A molecular and cellular theory of depression. Arch Gen Psychiatry 54(7):597–606. https://doi.org/10.1001/archpsyc.1997.01830190015002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/archpsyc.1997.01830190015002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9236543</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Price RB, Duman R (2020) Neuroplasticity in cognitive and psychological mechanisms of depression: an integrative model. Mol Psychiatry 25(3):530–543. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41380-019-0615-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41380-019-0615-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31801966</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Friedland K, Silani G, Schuwald A, Stockburger C, Koch E, Nöldner M, Müller WE (2021) Neurotrophic properties of Silexan, an essential oil from the flowers of lavender-preclinical evidence for antidepressant-like properties. Pharmacopsychiatry 54(1):37–46. https://doi.org/10.1055/a-1293-8585</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1055/a-1293-8585</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33254260</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Müller WE, Sillani G, Schuwald A, Friedland K (2021) Pharmacological basis of the anxiolytic and antidepressant properties of Silexan<sup>®</sup>, an essential oil from the flowers of lavender. Neurochem Int 143:104899. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuint.2020.104899</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.neuint.2020.104899</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33181239</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dwivedi Y, Pandey GN (2008) Adenylyl cyclase-cyclicAMP signaling in mood disorders: role of the crucial phosphorylating enzyme protein kinase A. Neuropsychiatr Dis Treat 4(1):161–176. https://doi.org/10.2147/ndt.s2380</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/ndt.s2380</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18728821</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2515915</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanchez-Vidana DI, Po KK, Fung TK, Chow JK, Lau WK, So PK, Lau BW, Tsang HW (2019) Lavender essential oil ameliorates depression-like behavior and increases neurogenesis and dendritic complexity in rats. Neurosci Lett 701:180–192. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neulet.2019.02.042</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.neulet.2019.02.042</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30825591</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kasper S, Gastpar M, Müller WE, Volz HP, Möller HJ, Dienel A, Schläfke S (2010) Silexan, an orally administered Lavandula oil preparation, is effective in the treatment of ‘subsyndromal’ anxiety disorder: a randomized, double-blind, placebo controlled trial. Int Clin Psychopharmacol 25(6):277–287. https://doi.org/10.1097/YIC.0b013e32833b3242</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/YIC.0b013e32833b3242</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20512042</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kasper S, Anghelescu I, Dienel A (2015) Efficacy of orally administered Silexan in patients with anxiety-related restlessness and disturbed sleep - A randomized, placebo-controlled trial. Eur Neuropsychopharmacol 25(11):1960–1967. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.euroneuro.2015.07.024</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.euroneuro.2015.07.024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26293583</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kasper S, Volz HP, Dienel A, Schlafke S (2016) Efficacy of Silexan in mixed anxiety-depression - A randomized, placebo-controlled trial. Eur Neuropsychopharmacol 26(2):331–340. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.euroneuro.2015.12.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.euroneuro.2015.12.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26718792</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woelk H, Schläfke S (2010) A multi-center, double-blind, randomised study of the lavender oil preparation silexan in comparison to Lorazepam for generalized anxiety disorder. Phytomedicine 17(2):94–99. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phymed.2009.10.006</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.phymed.2009.10.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19962288</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kasper S, Gastpar M, Müller WE, Volz H-P, Möller H-J, Schläfke S, Dienel A (2014) Lavender oil preparation silexan is effective in generalized anxiety disorder – a randomized, double-blind comparison to placebo and paroxetine. Int J Neuropsychopharmacol 17(06):859–869. https://doi.org/10.1017/s1461145714000017</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/s1461145714000017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24456909</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kasper S, Möller HJ, Volz HP, Schläfke S, Dienel A (2017) Silexan in generalized anxiety disorder: investigation of the therapeutic dosage range in a pooled data set. Int Clin Psychopharmacol 32(4):195–204. https://doi.org/10.1097/YIC.0000000000000176</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/YIC.0000000000000176</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28379882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamilton M (1959) The assessment of anxiety states by rating. Br J Med Psychol 32:50–55</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.2044-8341.1959.tb00467.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">13638508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dold M, Bartova L, Volz HP, Seifritz E, Möller HJ, Schläfke S, Kasper S (2023) Efficacy of Silexan in patients with anxiety disorders: a meta-analysis of randomized, placebo-controlled trials. Eur Arch Psychiatry Clin Neurosci. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00406-022-01547-w</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00406-022-01547-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36717399</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10465640</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zung WW (1971) A rating instrument for anxiety disorders. Psychosomatics 12(6):371–379</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0033-3182(71)71479-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">5172928</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Covi L, Rickels K, Lipman RS, McNair DM, Smith VK, Downing R, Kahn R, Fisher S (1981) Effects of psychotropic agents on primary depression. Psychopharmacol Bull 17:100–103</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zigmond AS, Snaith RP (1983) The hospital anxiety and depression scale. Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica 67(6):361–370</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0447.1983.tb09716.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6880820</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Institute of Mental Health (1970) 12 - CGI. Clinical global impressions. In: Guy W (ed) EDCEU Assessment in Psychopharmacology. U.S. National Institute of Mental Health, Psychopharmacology Research Branch, Rockville, Md., pp 217–222</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>von Känel R, Kasper S, Bondolfi G, Holsboer-Trachsler E, Hättenschwiler J, Hatzinger M, Imboden C, Heitlinger E, Seifritz E (2021) Therapeutic effects of Silexan on somatic symptoms and physical health in patients with anxiety disorders: a meta-analysis. Brain Behav 11(4):e01997. https://doi.org/10.1002/brb3.1997</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/brb3.1997</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ware JE Jr., Sherbourne CD (1992) The MOS 36-item short-form health survey (SF-36). I. conceptual framework and item selection. Med Care 30(6):473–483</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/00005650-199206000-00002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1593914</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kasper S, Volz HP, Moller HJ, Schlafke S, Klement S, Anghelescu IG, Seifritz E (2024) Lavender oil preparation silexan is effective in mild-to-moderate major depression: a randomized, placebo- and reference-controlled trial. Eur Arch Psychiatry Clin Neurosci. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00406-024-01783-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00406-024-01783-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38558147</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Montgomery SA, Åsberg M (1979) A new depression scale designed to be sensitive to change. Br J Psychiatry 134:382–389</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1192/bjp.134.4.382</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">444788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheehan DV, Harnett-Sheehan K, Raj BA (1996) The measurement of disability. Int Clin Psychopharmacol 11 Suppl 3:89–95. https://doi.org/10.1097/00004850-199606003-00015</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/00004850-199606003-00015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamilton M (1967) Development of a rating scale for primary depressive illness. Br J Soc Clin Psychol 6(4):278–296</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.2044-8260.1967.tb00530.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6080235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bartova L, Dold M, Volz HP, Seifritz E, Moller HJ, Kasper S (2023) Beneficial effects of Silexan on co-occurring depressive symptoms in patients with subthreshold anxiety and anxiety disorders: randomized, placebo-controlled trials revisited. Eur Arch Psychiatry Clin Neurosci 273(1):51–63. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00406-022-01390-z</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00406-022-01390-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35262795</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bélanger L, Morin CM, Langlois F, Ladouceur R (2004) Insomnia and generalized anxiety disorder: effects of cognitive behavior therapy for gad on insomnia symptoms. J Anxiety Disord 18(4):561–571. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0887-6185(03)00031-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s0887-6185(03)00031-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15149714</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta R, Zalai D, Spence DW, BaHammam AS, Ramasubramanian C, Monti JM, Pandi-Perumal SR (2014) When insomnia is not just insomnia: the deeper correlates of disturbed sleep with reference to DSM-5. Asian J Psychiatr 12:23–30. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajp.2014.09.003</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ajp.2014.09.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25441304</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holsboer-Trachsler E, Prieto R (2013) Effects of Pregabalin on sleep in generalized anxiety disorder. Int J Neuropsychopharmacol 16(4):925–936. https://doi.org/10.1017/s1461145712000922</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/s1461145712000922</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23009881</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seifritz E, Kasper S, Möller HJ, Volz HP, Müller WE, Eckert A, Hatzinger M (2022) Effect of anxiolytic drug silexan on sleep - a narrative review. World J Biol Psychiatry 23(7):493–500. https://doi.org/10.1080/15622975.2021.2013092</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/15622975.2021.2013092</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36259937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seifritz E, Schläfke S, Holsboer-Trachsler E (2019) Beneficial effects of Silexan on sleep are mediated by its anxiolytic effect. J Psychiatr Res 115::69–74. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpsychires.2019.04.013</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2019.04.013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31121394</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krüger T, Becker EM, Kostev K (2022) Prescription of Silexan is Associated with less frequent general practitioner repeat consultations due to disturbed sleep compared to benzodiazepine receptor agonists: a retrospective database analysis. Healthc (Basel) 11(1). https://doi.org/10.3390/healthcare11010077</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paez AF, Nicolalde B, Esquetini-Vernon C, Lara-Taranchenko Y, Zambrano K, Ocampo J, Fusaro S, Capa G, Caicedo A (2022) Psychiatric disorders in Post-acute COVID-syndrome (PDPACS): recommendations for health care professionals. Eur Neuropsychopharmacol 58:100–102. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.euroneuro.2022.03.003</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.euroneuro.2022.03.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35349906</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8956896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bartova L, Dold M, Fugger G, Weidenauer A, Rujescu D, Kasper S (2023) Silexan for treatment of anxiety and depression in the context of COVID-19. Eur Neuropsychopharmacol 70:47–48. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.euroneuro.2023.02.015</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.euroneuro.2023.02.015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36867894</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9946880</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kasper S, Eckert A, Moller HJ, Volz HP, Seifritz E (2023) Psychiatric manifestations of post-COVID-19 syndrome: the potential benefit of Silexan. Int J Psychiatry Clin Pract 1–7. https://doi.org/10.1080/13651501.2023.2187308</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yap WS, Dolzhenko AV, Jalal Z, Hadi MA, Khan TM (2019) Efficacy and safety of lavender essential oil (Silexan) capsules among patients suffering from anxiety disorders: a network meta-analysis. Sci Rep 9(1):18042. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-019-54529-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-54529-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31792285</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6889391</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Möller HJ, Volz HP, Seifritz E, Müller H, Kenntner-Mabiala R, Kaussner Y, Schoch S, Kasper S (2021) Silexan does not affect driving performance after single and multiple dose applications: results from a double-blind, placebo and reference-controlled study in healthy volunteers. J Psychiatr Res 136:543–551. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpsychires.2020.10.028</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2020.10.028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33221027</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gastpar M, Müller WE, Volz HP, Möller HJ, Schläfke S, Dienel A, Kasper S (2017) Silexan does not cause withdrawal symptoms even when abruptly discontinued. Int J Psychiatry Clin Pract 21(3):177–180. https://doi.org/10.1080/13651501.2017.1301488</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/13651501.2017.1301488</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28319423</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doroshyenko O, Rokitta D, Zadoyan G, Klement S, Schläfke S, Dienel A, Gramatté T, Lück H, Fuhr U (2013) Drug cocktail interaction study on the effect of the orally administered lavender oil preparation silexan on cytochrome P-450 enzymes in healthy volunteers. Drug Metab Dispos 41(5):987–993. https://doi.org/10.1124/dmd.112.050203</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1124/dmd.112.050203</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23401474</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heger-Mahn D, Pabst G, Dienel A, Schlafke S, Klipping C (2014) No interacting influence of lavender oil preparation silexan on oral contraception using an ethinyl estradiol/levonorgestrel combination. Drugs R D 14(4):265–272. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40268-014-0065-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40268-014-0065-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25319228</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4269819</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li S, Zhang X, Cai Y, Zheng L, Pang H, Lou L (2023) Sex difference in incidence of major depressive disorder: an analysis from the global burden of Disease Study 2019. Ann Gen Psychiatry 22(1):53. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12991-023-00486-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12991-023-00486-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38087353</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10714584</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Mey C, Dienel A (2013) Silexan ist sicher bei eingeschränkter Nierenfunktion. [Silexan is safe in patients with impaired renal function.] English translation of Original publication provided by Dr. Willmar Schwabe. NeuroGeriatrie 10</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarris J, Ravindran A, Yatham LN, Marx W, Rucklidge JJ, McIntyre RS, Akhondzadeh S, Benedetti F, Caneo C, Cramer H, Cribb L, de Manincor M, Dean O, Deslandes AC, Freeman MP, Gangadhar B, Harvey BH, Kasper S, Lake J, Lopresti A, Lu L, Metri NJ, Mischoulon D, Ng CH, Nishi D, Rahimi R, Seedat S, Sinclair J, Su KP, Zhang ZJ, Berk M (2022) Clinician guidelines for the treatment of psychiatric disorders with nutraceuticals and phytoceuticals: the World Federation of Societies of Biological Psychiatry (WFSBP) and Canadian Network for Mood and anxiety treatments (CANMAT) taskforce. World J Biol Psychiatry 23(6):424–455. https://doi.org/10.1080/15622975.2021.2013041</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/15622975.2021.2013041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35311615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Möller HJ, Volz HP, Dienel A, Schläfke S, Kasper S (2019) Efficacy of Silexan in subthreshold anxiety: meta-analysis of randomised, placebo-controlled trials. Eur Arch Psychiatry Clin Neurosci 269(2):183–193. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00406-017-0852-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00406-017-0852-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29150713</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kasper S, Müller WE, Volz HP, Möller HJ, Koch E, Dienel A (2018) Silexan in anxiety disorders: clinical data and pharmacological background. World J Biol Psychiatry 19(6):412–420. https://doi.org/10.1080/15622975.2017.1331046</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/15622975.2017.1331046</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28511598</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Müller WE, Sillani G, Schuwald A, Friedland K (2021) Pharmacological basis of the anxiolytic and antidepressant properties of Silexan(R), an essential oil from the flowers of lavender. Neurochem Int 143:104899. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuint.2020.104899</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.neuint.2020.104899</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33181239</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Volz HP, Stirnweiss J, Kasper S, Moller HJ, Seifritz E (2023) Subthreshold depression - concept, operationalisation and epidemiological data. A scoping review. Int J Psychiatry Clin Pract 27(1):92–106. https://doi.org/10.1080/13651501.2022.2087530</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/13651501.2022.2087530</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35736807</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haller H, Cramer H, Lauche R, Gass F, Dobos GJ (2014) The prevalence and burden of subthreshold generalized anxiety disorder: a systematic review. BMC Psychiatry 14:128. https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-244X-14-128</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1471-244X-14-128</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24886240</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4048364</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodríguez MR, Nuevo R, Chatterji S, Ayuso-Mateos JL (2012) Definitions and factors associated with subthreshold depressive conditions: a systematic review. BMC Psychiatry 12:181. https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-244x-12-181</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1471-244x-12-181</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23110575</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3539957</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andrews G, Carter GL (2001) What people say about their general practitioners’ treatment of anxiety and depression. Med J Aust 175(S1):S48–51. https://doi.org/10.5694/j.1326-5377.2002.tb04287.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5694/j.1326-5377.2002.tb04287.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11556437</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kessler RC, Berglund P, Demler O, Jin R, Merikangas KR, Walters EE (2005) Lifetime prevalence and age-of-onset distributions of DSM-IV disorders in the National Comorbidity Survey Replication. Arch Gen Psychiatry 62(6):593–602. https://doi.org/10.1001/archpsyc.62.6.593</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/archpsyc.62.6.593</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15939837</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bekker MH, van Mens-Verhulst J (2007) Anxiety disorders: sex differences in prevalence, degree, and background, but gender-neutral treatment. Gend Med 4 Suppl B:S 178–193. https://doi.org/10.1016/s1550-8579(07)80057-x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farhane-Medina NZ, Luque B, Tabernero C, Castillo-Mayen R (2022) Factors associated with gender and sex differences in anxiety prevalence and comorbidity: a systematic review. Sci Prog 105(4):368504221135469. https://doi.org/10.1177/00368504221135469</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/00368504221135469</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36373774</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu L, Shen H, Tan L, Huang Q, Chen Q, Liang M, He L, Zhou Y (2023) Prevalence and factors associated with anxiety and depression among community-dwelling older adults in Hunan, China: a cross-sectional study. BMC Psychiatry 23(1):107. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12888-023-04583-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12888-023-04583-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36793025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9930706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferguson JM (2001) SSRI antidepressant medications: adverse effects and Tolerability. Prim Care Companion J Clin Psychiatry 3(1):22–27. https://doi.org/10.4088/pcc.v03n0105</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4088/pcc.v03n0105</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15014625</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">181155</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kasper S (2015) Phytopharmaceutical treatment of anxiety, depression, and dementia in the elderly: evidence from randomized, controlled clinical trials. Wien Med Wochenschr 165(11–12):217–228. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10354-015-0360-y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10354-015-0360-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26092515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar V (2013) Characterization of anxiolytic and neuropharmacological activities of Silexan. Wien Med Wochenschr 163(3–4):89–94. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10354-012-0164-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10354-012-0164-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23361848</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>