<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39463801</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1178-6329</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>17</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Health services insights</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Health Serv Insights</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Procedure Prioritization During a Nationwide Ban on Non-Urgent Healthcare: A Quasi-Experimental Retrospective Study of Hospital Data in Switzerland.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>11786329241293534</StartPage><MedlinePgn>11786329241293534</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">11786329241293534</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1177/11786329241293534</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">During the COVID-19 lockdown in spring 2020, Switzerland restricted non-urgent healthcare services to safeguard capacity. While prioritization of care was supposed to be driven by medical urgency, demographic factors or economic incentives might have influenced the hospitals' resource allocation decisions.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This study investigates potential determinants of procedure prioritization in hospitalized patients during the lockdown period.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DESIGN" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Quasi-experimental retrospective study of hospital data in Switzerland.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">We analyzed 496 456 adult patients with known insurance status and a recorded procedure, admitted for cardiovascular, orthopedic/musculoskeletal or oncological reasons from January 2017 (3 years before the COVID-19 outbreak) to mid-April 2020 (in the first year of the COVID-19 pandemic), to obtain admission rate ratios (ARRs, "lockdown" admission rates divided by "normal" rates) from negative binomial regression analysis of fortnightly admissions for frequent procedure-diagnosis combinations. Quade and Wilcoxon signed-rank tests compared ARRs between sex×age, insurance and comorbidity strata.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Admission rates showed significant reductions for 29 of 53 procedure-diagnosis combinations. Reductions varied strongly by emergency, with largest decreases in orthopedic procedures for arthrosis (osteoarthritis) and non-arthritic joint disorders, and the smallest in cerebral imaging for stroke patients and surgical procedures for malignant neoplasms. The only difference in ARRs between strata was a stronger decrease in admission rates for cardiovascular combinations for patients with private versus basic health insurance.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">While medical procedures were affected to varying degrees by the ban on non-urgent healthcare during the COVID-19 lockdown, we found no robust evidence that factors other than medical urgency influenced healthcare prioritization.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s) 2024.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Grischott</LastName><ForeName>Thomas</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1564-5296</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Primary Care, University Hospital Zurich, University of Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mehra</LastName><ForeName>Tarun</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Oncology and Hematology, University Hospital Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Meyer</LastName><ForeName>Matthias R</ForeName><Initials>MR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Primary Care, University Hospital Zurich, University of Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Cardiology, Cantonal Hospital Graubünden, Chur, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Senn</LastName><ForeName>Oliver</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Primary Care, University Hospital Zurich, University of Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rachamin</LastName><ForeName>Yael</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Primary Care, University Hospital Zurich, University of Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Health Serv Insights</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101624726</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1178-6329</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Switzerland</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Treatment prioritization</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">capacity planning</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">health equity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">healthcare access</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39463801</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11503697</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/11786329241293534</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1177_11786329241293534</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>
OECD. Health for Everyone? Social Inequalities in Health and Health Systems. OECD Health Policy Studies. 2019. Accessed September 6, 2024. https://www.oecd-ilibrary.org/content/publication/3c8385d0-en</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rachamin Y, Meyer MR, Rosemann T, Grischott T. Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on elective and emergency inpatient procedure volumes in Switzerland - a retrospective study based on insurance claims data. Int J Health Policy Manag. 2023;12:6932.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10125178</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36243943</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Zentrale Ethikkommission der SAMW. Ausserordentliche Ressourcenknappheit in der stationären Versorgung: Ethische Grundsätze und prozedurale Kriterien für die Verschiebung von Behandlungen. Stellungnahme der Zentralen Ethikkommission (ZEK) der SAMW. Published February 7, 2022. Accessed September 6, 2024. https://www.samw.ch/dam/jcr:9326a1db-ded2-4d98-8dcb-91e6099f0004/stellungnahme_zek_samw_posteriorisierungen_20220207.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Peters O, Vuffray C, Haslebacher K.
Überhang in der stationären Leistungserbringung zu Gunsten der Zusatzversicherten. Published June 10, 2016. Accessed September 6, 2024. https://www.bag.admin.ch/dam/bag/de/dokumente/kuv-aufsicht/stat/articles-et-analyses-aos/stationaere-leistung-zusatzversicherte.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Engelberger K.
Akutstationäre Spitaltarife im Zusatzversicherungsbereich - Ein nationaler Tarif- und Kostenvergleich. Published October 2021. Accessed September 6, 2024. https://www.bag.admin.ch/dam/bag/de/dokumente/kuv-aufsicht/stat/articles-et-analyses-aos/stationaere-leistung-zusatzversicherte.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Eidgenössische Finanzmarktaufsicht FINMA. Krankenzusatzversicherer: FINMA sieht umfassenden Handlungsbedarf bei Leistungsabrechnungen. Published December 17, 2020. Accessed September 6, 2024. https://www.finma.ch/de/~/media/finma/dokumente/dokumentencenter/8news/medienmitteilungen/2020/12/20201217-mm-leistungsabrechung-krankenzusatzversicherer.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehra T, Moos RM, Seifert B, et al.. Impact of structural and economic factors on hospitalization costs, inpatient mortality, and treatment type of traumatic hip fractures in Switzerland. Arch Osteoporos. 2017;12:7-11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28013447</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hochfelder JP, Khatib ON, Glait SA, Slover JD. Femoral neck fractures in New York State. Is the rate of THA increasing, and do race or payer influence decision making? J Orthop Trauma. 2014;28:422-426.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24343251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muheim LLS, Senn O, Früh M, et al.. Inappropriate use of arthroscopic meniscal surgery in degenerative knee disease. Acta Orthop. 2017;88:550-555.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5560220</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28665174</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Bundesamt für Statistik BFS. Die Bevölkerung der Schweiz im Jahr 2020. Statistik der Schweiz. Published December 23, 2021. Accessed September 6, 2024. https://dam-api.bfs.admin.ch/hub/api/dam/assets/19964430/master</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Bundesamt für Statistik BFS. Medizinische Statistik der Krankenhäuser und Statistik der stationären Betriebe des Gesundheitwesens: Detailkonzept. Published October 10, 2014. Accessed September 6, 2024. https://dam-api.bfs.admin.ch/hub/api/dam/assets/230430/master</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Bundesamt für Statistik BFS. Medizinische Statistik der Krankenhäuser - Variablen der Medizinischen Statistik. Spezifikationen gültig ab 1.1.2020. Published March 5, 2020. Accessed September 6, 2024. https://dam-api.bfs.admin.ch/hub/api/dam/assets/12167417/master</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Bundesamt für Statistik BFS. Schweizerische Operationsklassifikation (CHOP): Systematisches Verzeichnis – Version 2020. Statistik der Schweiz. Published July 31, 2019. Accessed September 6, 2024. https://dam-api.bfs.admin.ch/hub/api/dam/assets/9286150/master</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Bundesinstitut für Arzneimittel und Medizinprodukte BfArM. Internationale statistische Klassifikation der Krankheiten und verwandter Gesundheitsprobleme - 10. Revision - German Modification - Version 2018. Accessed September 6, 2024. https://klassifikationen.bfarm.de/icd-10-gm/kode-suche/htmlgm2018/index.htm</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma N, Schwendimann R, Endrich O, Ausserhofer D, Simon M. Comparing Charlson and Elixhauser comorbidity indices with different weightings to predict in-hospital mortality: an analysis of national inpatient data. BMC Health Serv Res. 2021;21:13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7786470</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33407455</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elixhauser A, Steiner C, Harris DR, Coffey RM. Comorbidity measures for use with administrative data. Med Care. 1998;36:8-27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9431328</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Walraven C, Austin PC, Jennings A, Quan H, Forster AJ. A modification of the Elixhauser comorbidity measures into a point system for hospital death using administrative data. Med Care. 2009;47:626-633.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19433995</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gasparini A. Comorbidity: an R package for computing comorbidity scores. J Open Source Softw. 2018;3:648.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hothorn T, Bretz F, Westfall P. Simultaneous inference in general parametric models. Biom J. 2008;50:346-363.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18481363</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
R Core Team. R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing; 2023. https://www.R-project.org</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fahrner R, Bähler S, Lindner G. COVID-19 lock-down significantly reduced number of surgical presentations in an emergency department. Wien Klin Wochenschr. 2021;133:399-402.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7841980</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33507348</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hübner M, Zingg T, Martin D, Eckert P, Demartines N. Surgery for non-Covid-19 patients during the pandemic. PLoS One. 2020;15:e0241331.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7584248</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33095834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wiefels MD, Gmunder KN, Ruiz JW. Patient income level and health insurance correlate with differences in health care utilization during the COVID-19 pandemic. J Public Health Res. 2023;12:1-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9998417</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36911537</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krishnamoorthy Y, Kuberan D, Krishnan M, et al.. Impact of health insurance coverage on health care utilization during COVID-19 pandemic: a propensity score matched survey analysis in a target region in India. Int J Health Plann Manage. 2023;38:723-734.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36788661</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y, Bai G, Anderson G. COVID-19 and hospital financial viability in the US. JAMA Health Forum. 2022;3:e221018.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9107033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35977260</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Struja T, Suter F, Rohrmann S, et al.. Comparison of cardiovascular procedure rates in patients with supplementary vs basic insurance in Switzerland. JAMA Netw Open. 2023;6:e2251965.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9860525</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36662521</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adhikari S, Titus AR, Baum A, et al.. Disparities in routine healthcare utilization disruptions during COVID-19 pandemic among veterans with type 2 diabetes. BMC Health Serv Res. 2023;23:41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9842402</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36647113</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Altwicker-Hámori S, Stucki M. Factors associated with the choice of supplementary hospital insurance in Switzerland - an analysis of the Swiss Health Survey. BMC Health Serv Res. 2023;23:264.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10018950</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36927575</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davillas A, Jones AM. Unmet health care need and income-related horizontal equity in use of health care during the COVID-19 pandemic. Health Econ. 2021;30:1711-1716.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8250305</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33890334</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vestesson EM, De Corte KLA, Crellin E, et al.. Consultation rate and mode by deprivation in English general practice from 2018 to 2022: population-based study. JMIR Public Health Surveill. 2023;9:e44944.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10189615</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37129943</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>González-Touya M, Stoyanova A, Urbanos-Garrido RM. COVID-19 and unmet healthcare needs of older people: did inequity arise in Europe? Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18:9177.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8431067</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34501767</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Wirth B, Stucki M, Thommen C, Höglinger M.
Auswirkungen der Covid-19-bedingten Einschränkungen auf die stationäre Gesundheitsversorgung im Kanton Zürich. Published July 2022. Accessed September 6, 2024. https://www.zh.ch/content/dam/zhweb/bilder-dokumente/themen/gesundheit/gesundheitsversorgung/spitaeler_kliniken/zhaw_auswirkungen_der_covid_19_bedingten_einschränkungen.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simpson EH. The interpretation of interaction in contingency tables. J R Stat Soc Series B Stat Methodol. 1951;13:238-241.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonovas S, Piovani D. Simpson’s paradox in clinical research: a cautionary tale. J Clin Med. 2023;12:1633.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9960320</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36836181</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>