<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39468612</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1475-9276</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>23</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>28</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>International journal for equity in health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Int J Equity Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Determinants of COVID-19 vaccination acceptance based on the novel Omale INDEPT FORCIS Framework and recommendations for subsequent pandemics: a qualitative study among community members in Ebonyi state, Nigeria.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>223</StartPage><MedlinePgn>223</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12939-024-02284-3</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The unprecedented COVID-19 pandemic has become an endemic disease of global public health importance. Mass COVID-19 vaccination has been an essential global control strategy amidst challenges of limited acceptance. Because of globalization, COVID-19/similar diseases vaccination acceptance and the determinants in any particular setting are important global public health issues. Using a novel and pragmatic framework, this study explored determinants of COVID-19 vaccination acceptance among community members during the pandemic in Ebonyi state, Nigeria, and made policy-relevant recommendations on how to increase vaccination acceptance in subsequent outbreaks/pandemics.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">This qualitative study was based on the novel and pragmatic Individual Experiences and Perceptions and Complacency, Confidence, Convenience, and Compulsion (Four 'Cis') Determinants of Vaccination Acceptance Conceptual Framework - Omale INDEPT FORCIS Framework. On April 26 and 27, 2022, 20 semi-structured face-to-face focus group discussions were conducted in local language and pidgin English with 100 purposively selected consenting/assenting community members aged 15 years and above who had resided in the community for at least one year. Data was analysed using deductive (with some inductive) thematic analytic approach.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The many, diverse, and significant determinants of COVID-19 vaccination acceptance found were factors that were individual-related (individual experiences and perceptions and knowledge about COVID-19, COVID-19 vaccine/vaccination, and the vaccination process/system, sociodemographic, individual's condition (e.g. pregnancy)); COVID-19-related (factuality, transmissibility, frequency, severity, fatality); COVID-19 vaccine/vaccination-related (safety/side-effects, effectiveness, speedy production); COVID-19 vaccination process/system-related (real availability/accessibility); family, group, and other individual-related (experiences and perceptions and actions); and broader local, national, international, and global (LONING) context-related (socio-political, economic, historic, health system factors). The broader LONING contextual factors included the unprecedented disinformation/conspiracy theories, non-sustained COVID-19 risk/behaviour change communication, enforcement and non-enforcement or termination of peculiar control policies/measures (lockdowns, social/physical distancing, use of face mask etc.), mandatory COVID-19 vaccination policies, provision of incentives, past experiences regarding the Ebola viral disease outbreak, (un)trustworthiness of the Nigerian health system and her international/global partners, and the (un)trustworthiness of the governments in Nigeria and bad/good governance, inclusive of the failure of the Ebonyi state government to distribute the COVID-19 palliatives to the people during the lockdowns.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The evidence illuminates complex and interrelated, specific underlying, and peculiar policy-relevant LONING determinants of COVID-19 vaccination acceptance and emphasizes the need for concerted and comprehensive LONING strategies (involving all the relevant LONING stakeholders/policy makers) in addressing these determinants to increase vaccination acceptance among community members in subsequent outbreaks/pandemics in Ebonyi state/Nigeria and similar settings.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Omale</LastName><ForeName>Ugwu I</ForeName><Initials>UI</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Medicine, Alex Ekwueme Federal University Teaching Hospital Abakaliki (AEFUTHA), Abakaliki, Ebonyi State, Nigeria. omaleiu@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Adeke</LastName><ForeName>Azuka S</ForeName><Initials>AS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Medicine, Alex Ekwueme Federal University Teaching Hospital Abakaliki (AEFUTHA), Abakaliki, Ebonyi State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Oka</LastName><ForeName>Onyinyechukwu U</ForeName><Initials>OU</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Medicine, Alex Ekwueme Federal University Teaching Hospital Abakaliki (AEFUTHA), Abakaliki, Ebonyi State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ikegwuonu</LastName><ForeName>Cordis O</ForeName><Initials>CO</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Medicine, Alex Ekwueme Federal University Teaching Hospital Abakaliki (AEFUTHA), Abakaliki, Ebonyi State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Iyare</LastName><ForeName>Osarhiemen</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Medicine, Alex Ekwueme Federal University Teaching Hospital Abakaliki (AEFUTHA), Abakaliki, Ebonyi State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nnachi</LastName><ForeName>Olaedo O</ForeName><Initials>OO</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Medicine, Alex Ekwueme Federal University Teaching Hospital Abakaliki (AEFUTHA), Abakaliki, Ebonyi State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Uduma</LastName><ForeName>Victor U</ForeName><Initials>VU</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Alex Ekwueme Federal University Teaching Hospital Abakaliki (AEFUTHA), Abakaliki, Ebonyi State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Amuzie</LastName><ForeName>Chidinma I</ForeName><Initials>CI</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Medicine, Federal Medical Centre Umuahia, Umuahia, Abia State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nkwo</LastName><ForeName>Glory E</ForeName><Initials>GE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Medicine, Federal Medical Centre Umuahia, Umuahia, Abia State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nwali</LastName><ForeName>Ugochi I A</ForeName><Initials>UIA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Medicine, Alex Ekwueme Federal University Teaching Hospital Abakaliki (AEFUTHA), Abakaliki, Ebonyi State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ukpabi</LastName><ForeName>Okechukwu O</ForeName><Initials>OO</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Medicine, Alex Ekwueme Federal University Teaching Hospital Abakaliki (AEFUTHA), Abakaliki, Ebonyi State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Okeke</LastName><ForeName>Ifeyinwa M</ForeName><Initials>IM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Medicine, Alex Ekwueme Federal University Teaching Hospital Abakaliki (AEFUTHA), Abakaliki, Ebonyi State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ewah</LastName><ForeName>Richard L</ForeName><Initials>RL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Anaesthesia, Alex Ekwueme Federal University Teaching Hospital Abakaliki (AEFUTHA), Abakaliki, Ebonyi State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Anaesthesia Unit, Department of Surgery, Ebonyi State University, Abakaliki, Ebonyi State, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Int J Equity Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101147692</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1475-9276</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000086663">COVID-19 Vaccines</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009549" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Nigeria</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086663" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19 Vaccines</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000627" MajorTopicYN="N">therapeutic use</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D036301" MajorTopicYN="Y">Qualitative Research</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055815" MajorTopicYN="N">Young Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000293" MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescent</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000088823" MajorTopicYN="N">Vaccination Hesitancy</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010342" MajorTopicYN="N">Patient Acceptance of Health Care</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017144" MajorTopicYN="N">Focus Groups</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000368" MajorTopicYN="N">Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014611" MajorTopicYN="N">Vaccination</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Community members</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Determinants</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">International/global health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Nigeria</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Omale INDEPT FORCIS Framework</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics/outbreaks</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Policy recommendations</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Qualitative study</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Vaccination acceptance (uptake hesitancy intention timeliness)</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39468612</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12939-024-02284-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12939-024-02284-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (WHO). From emergency response to long-term COVID-19 disease management: sustaining gains made during the COVID-19 pandemic. Geneva: WHO; 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. Statement on the fifteenth meeting of the IHR. (2005) Emergency Committee on the COVID-19 pandemic [Internet]. 2023 [cited 2024 Jan 18]. https://www.who.int/news/item/05-05-2023-statement-on-the-fifteenth-meeting-of-the-international-health-regulations-(2005)-emergency-committee-regarding-the-coronavirus-disease-(covid-19)-pandemic</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. COVID-19 epidemiological update: Edition 170. Aug: Geneva; 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Nigeria Centre for Disease Control (NCDC). COVID-19 Nigeria. Accessed 5th May, 2023 from: https://covid19.ncdc.gov.ng</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Omale UI, Iyare O, Ewah RL, Amuzie CI, Oka OU, Uduma VU et al. COVID-19 vaccination acceptance among community members and health workers in Ebonyi state, Nigeria: study protocol for a concurrent-independent mixed method analyses of intention to receive, timeliness of the intention to receive, uptake and hesitancy to COVID-19 vaccination and the determinants. BMJ Open. 2022;12(12).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Primary Health Care Development Agency (NPHCDA). COVID-19 Vaccination Update: 2nd Dose, January 26th, 2022. Accessed 27th January, 2022 from: https://www.facebook.com/photo?fbid=301924068642685&amp;set=pcb.301924321975993</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>NPHCDA. Total Clients Reached with COVID-19 Vaccine. 26th. January, 2022. Accessed 28th January, 2022 from: https://www.facebook.com/photo?fbid=301924015309357&amp;set=pcb.301924321975993</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karashiali C, Konstantinou P, Christodoulou A, Kyprianidou M, Nicolaou C, Karekla M et al. A qualitative study exploring the social contagion of attitudes and uptake of COVID-19 vaccinations. Hum Vaccines Immunotherapeutics. 2023;19(2).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bosankic-Cmajcanin N, Musa S, Draganovic S. In the Face of a pandemic: I Felt the same as when the War Started—A qualitative study on COVID-19 Vaccine Acceptance in Bosnia and Herzegovina. Int J Public Health. 2023;68.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chimatiro CS, Hajison P, Jella CD, Tshotetsi L, Mpachika-Mfipa F. Barriers affecting COVID-19 vaccination in Phalombe District, Malawi: a qualitative study. S Afr Med J. 2023;113(4):e16554.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37283154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herry AM, Greaves D, Smith P, Toledo NA, Wildman A, Wildman T et al. Facilitators of and barriers to COVID-19 vaccination in Grenada: a qualitative study. Revista Panam De Salud Publica/Pan Am J Public Health. 2023;47.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sialubanje C, Mukumbuta N, Ng’andu M, Sumani EM, Nkonkomalimba M, Lyatumba DEM et al. Perspectives on the COVID-19 vaccine uptake: a qualitative study of community members and health workers in Zambia. BMJ Open. 2022;12(11).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Myburgh N, Mulaudzi M, Tshabalala G, Beta N, Gutu K, Vermaak S et al. A qualitative study exploring motivators and barriers to COVID-19 vaccine uptake among adults in South Africa and Zimbabwe. Vaccines (Basel). 2023;11(4).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duong MC, Nguyen HT, Duong M, Evaluating. COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy: a qualitative study from Vietnam. Diabetes Metabolic Syndrome: Clin Res Reviews. 2022;16(1).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashfield S, Donelle L, Uppal G, Bauer MA, Kothari A. Community organization perspectives on COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy and how they increased COVID-19 vaccine confidence: a Canadian Immunization Research Network, social sciences and humanities network study. Front Public Health. 2023;11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alzubaidi H, Samorinha C, Saddik B, Saidawi W, Abduelkarem AR, Abu-Gharbieh E, et al. A mixed-methods study to assess COVID-19 vaccination acceptability among university students in the United Arab Emirates. Hum Vaccin Immunother. 2021;17(11):4074–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/21645515.2021.1969854</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34534052</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8828074</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carlson SJ, Edwards G, Blyth CC, Nattabi B, Attwell K. Corona is coming’: COVID-19 vaccination perspectives and experiences amongst culturally and linguistically diverse West australians. Health Expect. 2022;25(6):3062–72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/hex.13613</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36262050</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9700143</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balasuriya L, Santilli A, Morone J, Ainooson J, Roy B, Njoku A et al. COVID-19 Vaccine Acceptance and Access among Black and Latinx communities. JAMA Netw Open. 2021;4(10).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang W, Dove-Medows E, Shealey J, Sanchez K, Benson L, Seymore DSD et al. COVID-19 vaccine attitudes among a majority black sample in the Southern US: public health implications from a qualitative study. BMC Public Health. 2023;23(1).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eichelberger L, Hansen A, Cochran P, Hahn M, Fried R. COVID-19 vaccine decision-making in remote Alaska between November 2020 and November 2021. Int J Circumpolar Health. 2023;82(1).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khanam M, Sanin KI, Rita RS, Akand F, Rabbi MF, Hasan MK et al. COVID-19 vaccine barriers and perception among rural adults: a qualitative study in Bangladesh. BMJ Open. 2023;13(10).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Denford S, Mowbray F, Towler L, Wehling H, Lasseter G, Amlôt R et al. Exploration of attitudes regarding uptake of COVID-19 vaccines among vaccine hesitant adults in the UK: a qualitative analysis. BMC Infect Dis. 2022;22(1).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luevanich C, Kane R, Naklong A, Surachetkomson P. Perceptions and intentions around Uptake of the COVID-19 vaccination among older people: a mixed-methods study in Phuket Province, Thailand. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2023;20(11).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ingram C, Roe M, Downey V, Phipps L, Perrotta C. Exploring key informants’ perceptions of Covid-19 vaccine hesitancy in a disadvantaged urban community in Ireland: emergence of a ‘4Cs’ model. Vaccine. 2023;41(2):519–31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2022.11.072</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36496286</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naqvi M, Li L, Woodrow M, Yadav P, Kostkova P. Understanding COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy in ethnic minorities groups in the UK. Front Public Health. 2022;10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Skinner NA, Sanders K, Lopez E, Sotz Mux MS, Abascal Miguel L, Vosburg KB et al. Barriers to COVID-19 vaccine acceptance to improve messages for vaccine uptake in indigenous populations in the central highlands of Guatemala: a participatory qualitative study. BMJ Open. 2023;13(1).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim S, Willis E, Wehlage S, Scheffer-Wentz H, Dulitz M. COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy and short-term and long-term intentions among unvaccinated young adults: a mixed-method approach. BMC Public Health. 2022;22(1).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zwawua O, Kor E. Factors Associated with COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy among a rural sample in Benue State, Nigeria: a qualitative study. Nigerian Journal of Health Promotion.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iwuagwu AO, Rayner D, Ngwu CN, Kalu ME. Why I have not taken the COVID-19 vaccine a descriptive qualitative study of older adults’ perceived views of COVID-19 vaccine uptake in Nigeria. J Popul Ageing. 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Omale UI, Ewah RL, Amuzie CI, Ikegwuonu CO, Nkwo GE, Iwegbulam CC et al. Study protocol for a cluster-randomised controlled trial of hybrid parents and health workers adaptive intervention for optimal routine childhood immunisation coverage in the communities of Ebonyi state, Nigeria: the AGINTOPIC trial protocol. BMJ Open. 2023;13(7).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. Immunization agenda 2030: a global strategy to leave no one behind. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>SAGE Working Group. Report of The SAGE Working Group on Vaccine Hesitancy. 2014 Oct.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Brien BC, Harris IB, Beckman TJ, Reed DA, Cook DA. Standards for reporting qualitative research: a synthesis of recommendations. Acad Med. 2014;89(9):1245–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/ACM.0000000000000388</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24979285</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braun V, Clarke V. Using thematic analysis in psychology. Qual Res Psychol. 2006;3(2):77–101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1191/1478088706qp063oa</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gale NK, Heath G, Cameron E, Rashid S, Redwood S. Using the framework method for the analysis of qualitative data in multi-disciplinary health research. BMC Med Res Methodol. 2013;13(1).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Omale UI, Uduma VU, Adeke AS, Ikegwuonu CO, Nkwo GE, Nwali UIA et al. COVID-19 and COVID-19 vaccination experiences and perceptions and their predictors among community members during the COVID-19 pandemic in Ebonyi state, Nigeria: an analytical cross-sectional study. BMC Public Health. 2024;24(1).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Ten threats to global health in 2019. 2019. Accessed August 15, 2021 from: https://www.who.int/news-room/spotlight/ten-threats-to-global-health-in-2019</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stead M, Ford A, Eadie D, Biggs H, Elliott C, Ussher M, et al. A step too far or perfect sense? A qualitative study of British adults’ views on mandating COVID-19 vaccination and vaccine passports. Vaccine. 2022;40(51):7389–96.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2022.05.072</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35773124</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9162982</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sprengholz P, Korn L, Eitze S, Felgendreff L, Siegers R, Goldhahn L, et al. Attitude toward a mandatory COVID-19 vaccination policy and its determinants: evidence from serial cross-sectional surveys conducted throughout the pandemic in Germany. Vaccine. 2022;40(51):7370–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2022.01.065</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35153092</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8830774</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lewandowsky S, Holford D, Schmid P. Public policy and conspiracies: the case of mandates. Curr Opin Psychol. 2022;47.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>OECD. Enhancing public trust in COVID-19 vaccination: The role of governments. 2021 May.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>