<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39460909</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1869-6953</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>26</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Diabetes therapy : research, treatment and education of diabetes and related disorders</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Diabetes Ther</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Current Perspectives in Pre- and Diabetic Peripheral Neuropathy Diagnosis and Management: An Expert Statement for the Gulf Region.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s13300-024-01658-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Peripheral neuropathy (PN) significantly impacts the quality of life, causing substantial morbidity and increased mortality, as well as escalating healthcare costs. While PN can have various causes, the most common form, diabetic peripheral neuropathy, poses considerable risks for potential complications. Diabetic peripheral neuropathy (DPN) affects over 50% of people with prediabetes and diabetes. Despite its prevalence, a global gap in diagnosis and management exists, exacerbated by the COVID-19 pandemic. This expert consensus was formulated through a comprehensive evaluation by a panel of experts, informed by a focused literature review, aiming to establish a clinically robust approach to diagnosing and managing pre- and diabetic PN with the early utilization of neurotropic B vitamins. This document offers a consensus perspective on the existing challenges in diagnosing and managing PN, focusing on DPN. The expert panel proposes measures to address this underdiagnosed burden, highlighting the importance of early intervention through innovative screening methods, integrated care approaches, and therapeutic strategies. The document advocates for increased awareness, targeted campaigns, and proactive care strategies to bridge gaps in the patient care of individuals with diabetes, emphasizing the importance of early detection and timely management to improve overall health outcomes. Specific recommendations include incorporating simplified questionnaires and innovative screening methods into routine care, prioritizing neurotropic B vitamin supplementation, optimizing glucagon-like peptide 1 (GLP-1) receptor agonist treatments, and adopting a holistic approach to neuropathy management. The consensus underscores the urgent need to address the underdiagnosis and undertreatment of PN, offering practical measures to enhance early detection and improve health outcomes for individuals with DPN.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Beshyah</LastName><ForeName>Salem A</ForeName><Initials>SA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3650-9741</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, NMC Royal, MBZ, Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates. beshyah@yahoo.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, College of Medicine and Health Sciences, Khalifa University, Abu Dhabi, UAE. beshyah@yahoo.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, Dubai Medical College, Dubai, United Arab Emirates. beshyah@yahoo.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jayyousi</LastName><ForeName>Amin</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hamad Medical Corporation, Doha, Qatar.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Al-Mamari</LastName><ForeName>Ali Saif</ForeName><Initials>AS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, Sultan Qaboos University Hospital, Muscat, Oman.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shaaban</LastName><ForeName>Ashraf</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Diabetes Control Centre, Ghassan Najib Pharaon Hospital, Jeddah, Kingdom of Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ozairi</LastName><ForeName>Ebaa Al</ForeName><Initials>EA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Clinical Care Research and Clinical Trials Unit, Dasman Diabetes Institute, Dasman, Kuwait.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nafach</LastName><ForeName>Jalal</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Diabetes, Dubai Diabetes Center, Dubai, United Arab Emirates.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jallo</LastName><ForeName>Mahir Khalil Ibrahim</ForeName><Initials>MKI</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine and Endocrinology, Centre of Endocrinology, Gulf Medical University and Thumbay University Hospital, Ajman, United Arab Emirates.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khader</LastName><ForeName>Said</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Diabetes and Endocrinology, Dr. Sulaiman Alhabib Medical Group, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Evans</LastName><ForeName>Marc</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Diabetes Resource Center, University Hospital Llandough, Penarth, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Diabetes Ther</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101539025</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1869-6961</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Diabetes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Early detection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Expert statement</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Neurotropic B vitamins</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Peripheral neuropathy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Prediabetes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Screening</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Vitamin B</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39460909</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13300-024-01658-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s13300-024-01658-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Juster-Switlyk K, Smith AG. Updates in diabetic peripheral neuropathy. F1000Research. 2016;5:F1000 Faculty Rev-738.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.12688/f1000research.7898.1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27158461</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4847561</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miranda-Massari JR, Gonzalez MJ, Jimenez FJ, Allende-Vigo MZ, Duconge J. Metabolic correction in the management of diabetic peripheral neuropathy: improving clinical results beyond symptom control. Curr Clin Pharmacol. 2011;6(4):260–73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2174/157488411798375967</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22082324</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3682498</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Callaghan BC, Cheng HT, Stables CL, Smith AL, Feldman EL. Diabetic neuropathy: clinical manifestations and current treatments. Lancet Neurol. 2012;11(6):521–34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(12)70065-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22608666</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4254767</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marchettini P, Lacerenza M, Mauri E, Marangoni C. Painful peripheral neuropathies. Curr Neuropharmacol. 2006;4(3):175–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2174/157015906778019536</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18615140</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2430688</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Egenolf N, Zu Altenschildesche CM, et al. Diagnosing small fiber neuropathy in clinical practice: a deep phenotyping study. Ther Adv Neurol Disord. 2021;14:17562864211004318.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/17562864211004318</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34335876</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8283814</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berger A, Dukes EM, Oster G. Clinical characteristics and economic costs of patients with painful neuropathic disorders. J Pain. 2004;5(3):143–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jpain.2003.12.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15106126</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>American Diabetes Association. Standards of medical care in diabetes—2021 abridged for primary care providers. Clin Diabetes. 2021;39(1):14–43.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/cd21-as01</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ziegler D, Papanas N, Vinik AI, Shaw JE. Epidemiology of polyneuropathy in diabetes and prediabetes. Handb Clin Neurol. 2014;126:3–22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/B978-0-444-53480-4.00001-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25410210</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>International Diabetes Federation. IDF Diabetes Atlas 2021. https://diabetesatlas.org/atlas/tenth-edition/ . Accessed 2024 Feb 16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar S, Rao K, Maiya AG, Hande HM, Hazari A. Need for early diabetic peripheral neuropathy screening among public transport professionals—a case report. Laser Ther. 2016;25(2):141–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5978/islsm.16-CR-01</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27721566</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4961672</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Armstrong DG, Boulton AJM, Bus SA. Diabetic foot ulcers and their recurrence. N Engl J Med. 2017;376(24):2367–75. https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMra1615439 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Juster-Switlyk K, Smith AG. Updates in diabetic peripheral neuropathy. F1000Res. 2016;5:F1000 Faculty Rev-738. https://doi.org/10.12688/f1000research.7898.1 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh R, Kishore L, Kaur N. Diabetic peripheral neuropathy: current perspective and future directions. Pharmacol Res. 2014;80:21–35. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phrs.2013.12.005 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Algeffari MA. Painful diabetic peripheral neuropathy among Saudi diabetic patients is common but under-recognized: multicenter cross-sectional study at primary health care setting. J Fam Community Med. 2018;25(1):43–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/jfcm.JFCM_145_16</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Armstrong DG, Boulton AJM, Bus SA. Diabetic foot ulcers and their recurrence. N Engl J Med. 2017;376(24):2367–75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMra1615439</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28614678</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh R, Kishore L, Kaur N. Diabetic peripheral neuropathy: current perspective and future directions. Pharmacol Res. 2014;80:21–35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.phrs.2013.12.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24373831</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Armstrong DG, Lavery LA, Vela SA, Quebedeaux TL, Fleischli JG. Choosing a practical screening instrument to identify patients at risk for diabetic foot ulceration. Arch Intern Med. 1998;158(3):289–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/archinte.158.3.289</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9472210</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olaleye D, Perkins BA, Bril V. Evaluation of three screening tests and a risk assessment model for diagnosing peripheral neuropathy in the diabetes clinic. Diabetes Res Clin Pract. 2001;54(2):115–28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0168-8227(01)00278-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11640995</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perkins BA, Olaleye D, Zinman B, Bril V. Simple screening tests for peripheral neuropathy in the diabetes clinic. Diabetes Care. 2001;24(2):250–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/diacare.24.2.250</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11213874</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Breiner A, Lovblom LE, Perkins BA, Bril V. Does the prevailing hypothesis that small-fiber dysfunction precedes large-fiber dysfunction apply to type 1 diabetic patients? Diabetes Care. 2014;37(5):1418–24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/dc13-2005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24574353</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dube S, Hulke SM, Wakode SL, et al. Effectiveness of Semmes Weinstein 10 gm monofilament in diabetic peripheral neuropathy taking nerve conduction and autonomic function study as reference tests. J Fam Med Prim Care. 2022;11(10):6204–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/jfmpc.jfmpc_195_22</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McIllhatton A, Lanting S, Lambkin D, Leigh L, Casey S, Chuter V. Reliability of recommended non-invasive chairside screening tests for diabetes-related peripheral neuropathy: a systematic review with meta-analyses. BMJ Open Diabetes Res Care. 2021;9(2): e002528.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjdrc-2021-002528</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34952841</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8710873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drobek N, Sowa P, Jankowski P, et al. Undiagnosed diabetes and prediabetes in patients with chronic coronary syndromes—an alarming public health issue. J Clin Med. 2021;10(9):1981.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/jcm10091981</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34063006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8124594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ponirakis G, Elhadd T, Chinnaiyan S, et al. Prevalence and risk factors for painful diabetic neuropathy in secondary healthcare in Qatar. J Diabetes Investig. 2019;10(6):1558–64. https://doi.org/10.1111/jdi.13037 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jdi.13037</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30860314</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6825939</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ponirakis G, Abdul-Ghani MA, Jayyousi A, et al. Painful diabetic neuropathy is associated with increased nerve regeneration in patients with type 2 diabetes undergoing intensive glycemic control. J Diabetes Investig. 2021;12(9):1642–50. https://doi.org/10.1111/jdi.13544 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jdi.13544</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33714226</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8409832</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ponirakis G, Elhadd T, Al Ozairi E, et al, Prevalence and risk factors for diabetic peripheral neuropathy, neuropathic pain and foot ulceration in the Arabian Gulf region. J Diabetes Investig. 2022;13(9):1551–59. https://doi.org/10.1111/jdi.13815</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jdi.13815</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35445568</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9434582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang W, Balamurugan A, Biddle J, et al. Diabetic neuropathy status and the concerns in underserved rural communities: challenges and opportunities for diabetes educators. Diabetes Educ. 2011;37(4):536–48. https://doi.org/10.1177/0145721711410717 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0145721711410717</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21750334</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee PY, Hani SS, Cheng YG, et al. The proportion of undiagnosed diabetic peripheral neuropathy and its associated factors among patients with T2DM attending urban health clinics in Selangor. Malays Fam Physician. 2022;17(1):36–43. https://doi.org/10.51866/oa1297 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.51866/oa1297</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35440953</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsuji M, Yasuda T, Kaneto H, et al. Painful diabetic neuropathy in Japanese diabetic patients is common but underrecognized. Pain Res Treat. 2013;2013:318352. https://doi.org/10.1155/2013/318352 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2013/318352</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24377045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herman WH, Kennedy L. Underdiagnosis of peripheral neuropathy in type 2 diabetes. Diabetes Care. 2005;28(6):1480–1. https://doi.org/10.2337/diacare.28.6.1480 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/diacare.28.6.1480</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15920071</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malik RA, Aldinc E, Chan SP, et al. Perceptions of painful diabetic peripheral neuropathy in South-East Asia: Results from patient and physician surveys. Adv Ther. 2017;34(6):1426–37. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12325-017-0536-5 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12325-017-0536-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28502036</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5487881</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daousi C, MacFarlane IA, Woodward A, et al. Chronic painful peripheral neuropathy in an urban community: a controlled comparison of people with and without diabetes. Diabet Med. 2004;21(9):976-82. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1464-5491.2004.01271.x .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1464-5491.2004.01271.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15317601</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bongaerts BWC, Rathmann W, Heier M, et al. Older subjects with diabetes and prediabetes are frequently unaware of having distal sensorimotor polyneuropathy: the KORA F4 study. Diabetes Care. 2013;36(5):1141–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/dc12-0744</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23275355</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3631873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Veresiu AI, Bondor CI, Florea B, Vinik EJ, Vinik AI, Gâvan NA. Detection of undisclosed neuropathy and assessment of its impact on quality of life: a survey in 25,000 Romanian patients with diabetes. J Diabetes Complications. 2015;29(5):644–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jdiacomp.2015.04.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25922309</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gad H, Kalra S, Pinzon R, et al. Earlier diagnosis of peripheral neuropathy in primary care: a call to action. J Peripher Nerv Syst JPNS. 2024;29:28–37.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jns.12613</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38268316</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carmichael J, Fadavi H, Ishibashi F, Shore AC, Tavakoli M. Advances in screening, early diagnosis and accurate staging of diabetic neuropathy. Front Endocrinol. 2021;26(12):671257.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fendo.2021.671257</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karahan AY, Kucuksarac S, Soran N, Ordahan B, Tekin L, Basaran A. Nurse’s knowledge of neuropathic pain. Neurol Int. 2014;6(3):5492. https://doi.org/10.4081/ni.2014.5492 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheng X, Li T, Hu Y, Xiong CS, Hu L. Correlation between blood glucose indexes generated by the flash glucose monitoring system and diabetic vascular complications. Diabetes Metab Syndr Obes. 2023;16:2447–56. https://doi.org/10.2147/DMSO.S418224 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ziegler D, Herder C, Papanas N. Neuropathy in prediabetes. Diabetes Metab Res Rev. 2023;39(8):e3693.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/dmrr.3693</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37470302</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alleman CJM, Westerhout KY, Hensen M, et al. Humanistic and economic burden of painful diabetic peripheral neuropathy in Europe: a review of the literature. Diabetes Res Clin Pract. 2015;109(2):215–25.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.diabres.2015.04.031</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26008721</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diabetes Control and Complications Trial Research Group, Nathan DM, Genuth S, et al. The effect of intensive treatment of diabetes on the development and progression of long-term complications in insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus. N Engl J Med. 1993;329(14):977–86.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJM199309303291401</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Landais A. Neurological complications of bariatric surgery. Obes Surg. 2014;24(10):1800–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11695-014-1376-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25060718</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stabler SP. Clinical practice. Vitamin B12 deficiency. N Engl J Med. 2013;368(2):149–60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMcp1113996</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23301732</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith BH, Torrance N. Epidemiology of neuropathic pain and its impact on quality of life. Curr Pain Headache Rep. 2012;16(3):191–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11916-012-0256-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22395856</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Briani C, Dalla Torre C, Citton V, et al. Cobalamin deficiency: clinical picture and radiological findings. Nutrients. 2013;5(11):4521–39.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/nu5114521</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24248213</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3847746</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>American Diabetes Association. 1. Improving care and promoting health in populations: standards of medical care in diabetes—2020. Diabetes Care. 2019;43(Suppl_1):S7-13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2337/dc19-S001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gad H, Petropoulos IN, Khan A, et al. Corneal confocal microscopy for the diagnosis of diabetic peripheral neuropathy: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Diabetes Investig. 2022;13(1):134–147. https://doi.org/10.1111/jdi.13643 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galiero R, Caturano A, Vetrano E, et al. Peripheral neuropathy in diabetes mellitus: pathogenetic mechanisms and diagnostic options. Int J Mol Sci. 2023 Feb 10;24(4):3554. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms24043554 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alharbi TJ, Tourkmani AM, Abdelhay O, et al. The association of metformin use with vitamin B12 deficiency and peripheral neuropathy in Saudi individuals with type 2 diabetes mellitus. PLoS ONE. 2018;13(10):e0204420.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0204420</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30321183</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6188756</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cavalli E, Mammana S, Nicoletti F, Bramanti P, Mazzon E. The neuropathic pain: an overview of the current treatment and future therapeutic approaches. Int J Immunopathol Pharmacol. 2019;33:2058738419838383. https://doi.org/10.1177/2058738419838383 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fornasari D. Pharmacotherapy for neuropathic pain: a review. Pain Ther. 2017;6(Suppl 1):25–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40122-017-0091-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29178034</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5701897</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nauck MA, Quast DR, Wefers J, Meier JJ. GLP-1 receptor agonists in the treatment of type 2 diabetes—state-of-the-art. Mol Metab. 2021;46:101102. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.molmet.2020.101102 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>García-Casares N, González-González G, de la Cruz-Cosme C, et al. Effects of GLP-1 receptor agonists on neurological complications of diabetes. Rev Endocr Metab Disord. 2023;24(4):655–72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11154-023-09807-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37231200</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10404567</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paez-Hurtado AM, Calderon-Ospina CA, Nava-Mesa MO. Mechanisms of action of vitamin B1 (thiamine), B6 (pyridoxine), and B12 (cobalamin) in pain: a narrative review. Nutr Neurosci. 2023;26(3):235–53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/1028415X.2022.2034242</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35156556</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pinzon RT, Schellack N, Matawaran BJ, et al. Clinical recommendations for the use of neurotropic B vitamins (B1, B6, and B12) for the management of peripheral neuropathy: consensus from a multidisciplinary expert panel. J Assoc Physicians India. 2023;71(7):11–2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37449697</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>