<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39464729</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2347-3584</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>35</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Virusdisease</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Virusdisease</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Molecular characterization, phylogenetic and variation analyses of SARS-CoV-2 strains in India.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>462</StartPage><EndPage>477</EndPage><MedlinePgn>462-477</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s13337-024-00878-7</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="UNLABELLED">In the wake of the havoc caused by the COVID-19 pandemic, it is imperative to use the available genomic sequence data to gain insight into the mutational and genomic diversity of SARS-CoV-2. Here we have performed comparative phylogenetic, mutational and genetic diversity analysis on 1962 SARS-CoV-2 genome sequences from seven worst hit Indian states during the third Covid-19 wave, to determine the SARS-CoV-2 strains and mutations in circulation during the third wave and the transmission pattern and disease epidemiology across the states and gain valuable insight into the viral evolution. 6083 Single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) were discovered in the analysis with 93 SNPs common to all states. The genetic relatedness among the statewise multilocus genotypes was visualized by plotting a minimum spanning tree based on Bruvo's distance framework. The phylogenetic tree based on Nei's genetic distance showed distinct clades. The AMOVA results indicated that large proportion of the total genetic variation is distributed within the samples, rather than between the samples within each population and between the populations. Our findings provide insight into the SARS-CoV-2 variants and mutations which dominated the third COVID-19 wave in India and thus provide a basis to monitor and further assess these variants and their sub lineages and mutations for their clinical impact and reaction to existing and newly designed drugs and vaccines. The genetic diversity analysis helps in comprehending the viral transmission scenarios across the Indian states so as to enable the State government and researchers in developing state specific prevention measures for future.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="SUPPLEMENTARY INFORMATION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1007/s13337-024-00878-7.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Indian Virological Society 2024. Springer Nature or its licensor (e.g. a society or other partner) holds exclusive rights to this article under a publishing agreement with the author(s) or other rightsholder(s); author self-archiving of the accepted manuscript version of this article is solely governed by the terms of such publishing agreement and applicable law.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Banerjee</LastName><ForeName>Meghna</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Bioscience and Biotechnology, Banasthali Vidyapith, Vanasthali, Rajasthan 304022 India.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/05ycegt40</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.440551.1</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0000 8736 7112</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chakraborty</LastName><ForeName>Dipjyoti</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Bioscience and Biotechnology, Banasthali Vidyapith, Vanasthali, Rajasthan 304022 India.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/05ycegt40</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.440551.1</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0000 8736 7112</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chakraborty</LastName><ForeName>Arindom</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0741-8955</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Statistics, Visva-Bharati University, Santiniketan, West Bengal 731235 India.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/02y28sc20</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.440987.6</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 2259 7889</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>09</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>India</Country><MedlineTA>Virusdisease</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101624144</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2347-3584</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Genetic diversity analysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mutational analysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Phylogeny</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP)</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39464729</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11502728</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13337-024-00878-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">878</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Ahmad SU, Kiani BH, Abrar M, Jan Z, Zafar I, Ali Y, Khan AA. A comprehensive genomic study, mutation screening, phylogenetic and statistical analysis of SARS-CoV-2 and its variant omicron among different countries. J Infect Public Health. 2022;15(8):878–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9262654</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35839568</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akkız H. The Biological Functions and Clinical Significance of SARS-CoV-2 Variants of Corcern. Front Med. 2022. 10.3389/fmed.2022.849217.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9163346</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35669924</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alai S, Gujar N, Joshi M, Gautam M, Gairola S. Pan-India novel coronavirus SARS-CoV-2 genomics and global diversity analysis in spike protein. Heliyon. 2021;7(3):6564.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7972664</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33758785</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhattacharya M, Chatterjee S, Sharma AR, Lee SS, Chakraborty C. Delta variant (B. 1.617. 2) of SARS-CoV-2: Current understanding of infection, transmission, immune escape, and mutational landscape. Folia Microbiol. 2023;68(1):17–28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9374302</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35962276</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bruvo R, Michiels NK, D’SOUZA, T. G., &amp; Schulenburg, H. A simple method for the calculation of microsatellite genotype distances irrespective of ploidy level. Mol Ecol. 2004;13(7):2101–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15189230</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Combes P, Bisseux M, Bal A, Marin P, Latour J, Archimbaud C, Mirand A. Evidence of co-infections during Delta and Omicron SARS-CoV-2 variants co-circulation through prospective screening and sequencing. Clin Microbiol Infect. 2022;28(11):1503–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9250411</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35792280</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Focosi D, Maggi F. Neutralising antibody escape of SARS-CoV-2 spike protein: risk assessment for antibody-based Covid-19 therapeutics and vaccines. Rev Med Virol. 2021;31(6): e2231.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8250244</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33724631</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghosh N, Nandi S, Saha I. Phylogenetic analysis of 17271 Indian SARS-CoV-2 genomes to identify temporal and spatial hotspot mutations. PLoS ONE. 2022;17(3): e0265579.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8959188</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35344550</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hadfield J, Megill C, Bell SM, Huddleston J, Potter B, Callender C, Neher RA. Nextstrain: real-time tracking of pathogen evolution. Bioinformatics. 2018;34(23):4121–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6247931</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29790939</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hossain A, Trishna SA, Rashid AA, Khair S, Alam ARU. Unique mutations in SARS-CoV-2 omicron subvariants’ non-spike proteins: potential impact on viral pathogenesis and host immune evasion. Microb Pathogenes. 2022;170:105699.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9356572</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35944840</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamvar ZN, Tabima JF, Grünwald NJ. Poppr: an R package for genetic analysis of populations with clonal, partially clonal, and/or sexual reproduction. PeerJ. 2014;2: e281.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3961149</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24688859</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kannan SR, Spratt AN, Sharma K, Goyal R, Sönnerborg A, Apparsundaram S, Singh K. Complex mutation pattern of Omicron BA. 2: evading antibodies without losing receptor interactions. Int J Mol Sci. 2022;23(10):5534.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9141577</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35628343</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katoh K, Standley DM. MAFFT multiple sequence alignment software version 7: improvements in performance and usability. Mol Biol Evol. 2013;30(4):772–80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3603318</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23329690</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li X, Zhang L, Chen S, Ji W, Li C, Ren L. Recent progress on the mutations of SARS-CoV-2 spike protein and suggestions for prevention and controlling of the pandemic. Infect Genet Evol. 2021;93: 104971.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8213438</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34146731</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu C, Ginn HM, Dejnirattisai W, Supasa P, Wang B, Tuekprakhon A, Screaton GR. Reduced neutralisation of SARS-CoV-2 B. 1.617 by vaccine and convalescent serum. Cell. 2021;184(16):4220–36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8218332</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34242578</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y, Liu J, Plante KS, Plante JA, Xie X, Zhang X, Weaver SC. The N501Y spike substitution enhances SARS-CoV-2 infection and transmission. Nature. 2022;602(7896):294–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8900207</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34818667</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Minh BQ, Schmidt HA, Chernomor O, Schrempf D, Woodhams MD, Von Haeseler A, Lanfear R. IQ-TREE 2: new models and efficient methods for phylogenetic inference in the genomic era. Mol Biol Evol. 2020;37(5):1530–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7182206</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32011700</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohapatra RK, Kandi V, Sarangi AK, Verma S, Tuli HS, Chakraborty S, Dhama K. The recently emerged BA. 4 and BA. 5 lineages of Omicron and their global health concerns amid the ongoing wave of COVID-19 pandemic–Correspondence. Int J Surg (London, England). 2022;103:106698.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9176102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35690362</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muttineni R, RN B, Putty K, Marapakala K, KP S, Panyam J, Kondapi AK. SARS-CoV-2 variants and spike mutations involved in second wave of COVID-19 pandemic in India. Transbound Emerg Dis. 2022;69(5):e1721–e1733.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9115369</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35266305</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nikolaidis M, Papakyriakou A, Chlichlia K, Markoulatos P, Oliver SG, Amoutzias GD. Comparative analysis of SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern, including omicron, highlights their common and distinctive amino acid substitution patterns, especially at the spike ORF. Viruses. 2022;14(4):707.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9025783</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35458441</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Obermeyer F, Jankowiak M, Barkas N, Schaffner SF, Pyle JD, Yurkovetskiy L, Lemieux JE. Analysis of 6.4 million SARS-CoV-2 genomes identifies mutations associated with fitness. Science. 2022;376(6599):1327–32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9161372</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35608456</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ou J, Lan W, Wu X, Zhao T, Duan B, Yang P, Zhang Q. Tracking SARS-CoV-2 Omicron diverse spike gene mutations identifies multiple inter-variant recombination events. Signal Transduct Target Therapy. 2022;7(1):1–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9039610</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35474215</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parasar J, Pandey RK, Patel Y, Singh PP, Srivastava A, Mishra RK, Chaubey G. Genetic diversity and spatiotemporal distribution of SARS-CoV-2 alpha variant in India. COVID. 2023;3(4):472-9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pastorio C, Zech F, Noettger S, Jung C, Jacob T, Sanderson T, Kirchhoff F. Determinants of Spike infectivity, processing, and neutralisation in SARS-CoV-2 Omicron subvariants BA. 1 and BA. 2. Cell Host Microbe. 2022;30(9):1255–68.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9289044</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35931073</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahimi F, Abadi ATB. The Omicron subvariant BA. 2: Birth of a new challenge during the COVID-19 pandemic. Int J Surg. 2022;99:106261.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8837492</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35167986</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rajpal VR, Sharma S, Sehgal D, Singh A, Kumar A, Vaishnavi S, Raina SN. A comprehensive account of SARS-CoV-2 genome structure, incurred mutations, lineages and COVID-19 vaccination program. Futur Virol. 2022;17(9):687–706.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9203033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35747328</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sahni C, Chowdhury PBR, Devadas D, Ashish A, Singh NK, Yadav A, Singh R (2022) Corrected: SARS-CoV-2 Mutations Responsible for Immune Evasion Leading to Breakthrough Infection.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9592688</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36312656</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sassi MB, Ferjani S, Mkada I, Arbi M, Safer M, Elmoussi A, Boubaker IBB. Phylogenetic and amino acid signature analysis of the SARS-CoV-2s lineages circulating in Tunisia. Infect Genet Evolut. 2022;102:105300.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9085353</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35552003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah M, Woo HG. Omicron: a heavily mutated SARS-CoV-2 variant exhibits stronger binding to ACE2 and potently escapes approved COVID-19 therapeutic antibodies. Front immunol. 2022. 10.3389/fimmu.2021.830527.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8819067</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35140714</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shen L, Triche TJ, Bard JD, Biegel JA, Judkins AR, Gai X. Spike Protein NTD mutation G142D in SARS-CoV-2 Delta VOC lineages is associated with frequent back mutations, increased viral loads, and immune evasion. MedRxiv. 2021. 10.1101/2021.09.12.21263475.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shiraz R, Tripathi S (2022) ENHANCED RECOMBINATION AMONG SARS-COV-2 OMICRON VARIANTS CONTRIBUTES TO VIRAL IMMUNE ESCAPE. bioRxiv.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36691935</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shrestha LB, Foster C, Rawlinson W, Tedla N, Bull RA. Evolution of the SARS-CoV-2 omicron variants BA. 1 to BA. 5: Implications for immune escape and transmission. Rev Med Virol. 2022;32(5):2381.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9349777</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35856385</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh P, Negi SS, Bhargava A, Kolla VP, Arora RD. Preliminary genomic analysis of the Omicron Variants of SARS-CoV-2 in central india during the third wave of the COVID-19 pandemic. Arch Med Res. 2022;53(6):574–84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9395282</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36123226</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh J, Rahman SA, Ehtesham NZ, Hira S, Hasnain SE. SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern are emerging in India. Nat Med. 2021;27(7):1131–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34045737</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thakur S, Sasi S, Pillai SG, Nag A, Shukla D, Singhal R, Velu GSK. SARS-CoV-2 mutations and their impact on diagnostics, therapeutics and vaccines. Front Med. 2022. 10.3389/fmed.2022.815389.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8902153</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35273977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Volz E, Hill V, McCrone JT, Price A, Jorgensen D, O’Toole Á, Allan J. Evaluating the effects of SARS-CoV-2 spike mutation D614G on transmissibility and pathogenicity. Cell. 2021;184(1):64–75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7674007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33275900</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu H, Xing N, Meng K, Fu B, Xue W, Dong P, Zhu Z. Nucleocapsid mutations R203K/G204R increase the infectivity, fitness, and virulence of SARS-CoV-2. Cell Host Microbe. 2021;29(12):1788–801.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8590493</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34822776</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yadav PD, Nyayanit DA, Majumdar T, Patil S, Kaur H, Gupta N, Bhargava B. An epidemiological analysis of SARS-CoV-2 genomic sequences from different regions of India. Viruses. 2021;13(5):925.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8156686</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34067745</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>