<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39464406</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2048-6790</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>13</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of nutritional science</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Nutr Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Psychological well-being, food insecurity, academic performance and other risk factors in a sample of university students in Jordan during COVID-19.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e61</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e61</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e61</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1017/jns.2024.67</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>This research validated an Arabic version of the Psychological General Well-being Index-Short version (PGWB-S) and examined the relationship between perceived psychological well-being, and food insecurity, academic achievement, and other risk factors in a sample of university students in Amman, Jordan, during COVID-19. A cross-sectional study was conducted in two phases. Phase 1 translated and validated the Arabic copy of the PGWB-S in 122 students from the University of Jordan. In Phase 2, 414 students completed the demographic questionnaire, Arabic versions of the PGWB-S, the Ryff Psychological Well-being Scale, and the Individual Food Insecurity Experience Scale. The participants had a mean PGWB-S score of 15.82 ± 0.34, and 41.3% had a mean score below 15. Psychological well-being was better in students younger than 21 and/or who had a GPA ≥3.0, were of normal weight or overweight, physically inactive, and food secure, did not drink coffee or smoke, as well as in those whose neighbourhood contained grocery stores and/or public transportation (P &lt; 0.05). In conclusion, during the pandemic, perceived mental well-being was moderate in a Jordanian sample of university students. Perceived psychological well-being was also positively associated with food security and academic performance. These findings suggest that improving food security and academic achievement may contribute to enhanced psychological well-being among university students. Therefore, higher education institutions with the help of the government are encouraged to facilitate the provision of mental health care services to students, mainly post the coronavirus, which according to our knowledge is limited.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s) 2024.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mousa</LastName><ForeName>Tamara Y</ForeName><Initials>TY</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4046-3494</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nutrition and Food Technology, School of Agriculture, The University of Jordan, Amman, Jordan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dardas</LastName><ForeName>Latefa A</ForeName><Initials>LA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Health Nursing, School of Nursing, The University of Jordan, Amman, Jordan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Nutr Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101590587</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2048-6790</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007597" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Jordan</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013334" MajorTopicYN="Y">Students</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014495" MajorTopicYN="N">Universities</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003430" MajorTopicYN="N">Cross-Sectional Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000084884" MajorTopicYN="Y">Food Insecurity</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055815" MajorTopicYN="N">Young Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012307" MajorTopicYN="N">Risk Factors</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008603" MajorTopicYN="Y">Mental Health</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="Y">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011795" MajorTopicYN="N">Surveys and Questionnaires</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000073978" MajorTopicYN="N">Academic Performance</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000293" MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescent</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000092862" MajorTopicYN="N">Psychological Well-Being</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Arabic psychological general well-being index-short version (PGWB-S)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Food insecurity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Jordan</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>There was no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39464406</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11503852</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/jns.2024.67</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2048679024000673</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>
Department of Statistics of Jordan. Published August 1, 2021. Accessed August 22, 2021. http://dosweb.dos.gov.jo/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The World Health Organization. Results of Jordan National STEPwise Survey (STEPs) of Noncommunicable Diseases and their Risk Factors 2019. Amman: WHO; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Massad I, Al-Taher R, Massad F, et al. The impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on mental health: early quarantine-related anxiety and its correlates among Jordanians. EMHJ. 2020;26:1165–1172.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33103743</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malak M, Khalifeh A. Anxiety and depression among school students in Jordan: prevalence, risk factors, and predictors. Perspect Psychiatr Care. 2018;54:242–250.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28617949</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dalky H, Gharaibeh A. Depression, anxiety, and stress among college students in Jordan and their need for mental health services. Nurs Forum 2018;54:1–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30554406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamdan-Mansour A, Marmash L. Psychological well-being and general health of Jordanian university students. J Psychosoc Nurs Ment Health Serv. 2007;45:31–39.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17990739</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huppert F. Psychological well-being: evidence regarding its causes and consequences. Health Well-Being. 2009;1:137–164.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>AlAzzam M, Abuhammad S, Abdalrahim A, et al. Predictors of depression and anxiety among senior high school students during COVID-19 pandemic: the context of home quarantine and online education. J Sch Nurs. 2021;37:241–248.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33563066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al Omari O, Al Sabei S, Al Rawajfah O, et al. Prevalence and predictors of depression, anxiety, and stress among youth at the time of COVID-19: an online cross-sectional multicountry study. Depression Res Treatment. 2020;2020:1–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7537692</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33062331</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olaimat A, Aolymat I, Elsahoryi N, et al. Attitudes, anxiety, and behavioral practices regarding COVID-19 among university students in Jordan: a cross-sectional study. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2022;103:1177–1183.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7470553</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32662398</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Becerra M, Becerra B. Psychological distress among college students: role of food insecurity and other social determinants of mental health. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020;17:4118–4129.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7312727</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32526990</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fang D, Thomsen M, Nayga R. The association between food insecurity and mental health during the COVID-19 pandemic. BMC Public Health. 2021;21:607–614.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8006138</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33781232</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raskind L, Haardorfer R, Berg C. Food insecurity, psychosocial health, and academic performance among college and university students in Georgia, USA. Public Health Nutr. 2019;22:476–485.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6366643</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30724722</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cafiero C, Viviani S, Nord M. Food security measurement in a global context:the food insecurity experience scale. Measurement. 2018;116:146–152.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Global Food Security Index. Explor Countries. Jordan - Middle East and North Africa - Upper Middle Income. NY: GFSI; 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, Office of Disease Prevention and Health Promotion. Dietary Guidelines for Americans 2015–2020. Washington, DC: U.S. Department of Health and Human Services; 2015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wolfson J, Garcia T, Leung C. Food insecurity is associated with depression, anxiety, and stress: evidence from the early days of the COVID-19 pandemic in the United States. Health Equity. 2021;5:64–71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7929913</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33681691</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Collings S, Blakely T, Kruse K, et al. The association of food security with psychological distress in New Zealand and any gender differences. Social Sci Medicine. 2011;30:1–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21481507</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shankar-Krishnan N, Fornieles Deu A, Sánchez-Carracedo D. Associations between food insecurity and psychological wellbeing, body image, disordered eating and dietary habits: evidence from spanish adolescents. Child Ind Res. 2021;14:163–183.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Myers C. Food insecurity and psychological distress: a review of the recent literature. Curr Nutr Rep. 2020;9:107–118.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7282962</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32240534</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galea S, Merchant RM, Lurie N. The mental health consequences of COVID-19 and physical distancing: the need for prevention and early intervention. JAMA Intern Med. 2020;180:817–818.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32275292</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grossi E, Groth N, Mosconi P, et al. Development and validation of the short version of the psychological general well-being index (PGWB-S). Health Qual Life Out. 2006;4:88–95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1647268</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17105655</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dupuy HJ. The psychological general well-being (pgwb) index. In: Wenger NK, Mattson ME, Furberg CD, Elinson J, eds. Assessment of Quality of Life in Clinical Trials of Cardiovascular Therapies. Lyon: Le Jacq Publishing; 1984.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6333175</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grossi E, Mosconi P, Groth N, et al. IL Questionario Psychological General Well Being. QUESTIONARIO per la Valutazione Dello Stato Generale di Benessere Psicologico. Versione Italiana, Milan: Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche “Mario Negri”; 2002.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (WHO). Process of Translation and Adaptation of Instruments. Geneva: WHO; 2005.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen J. A coefficient of agreement for nominal scales. Educ Psychol Meas. 1960;20:37–46.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pereira M, Antunes M, Barroso I, et al. Adaptation and validation of the psychological general well-being index: confirmatory factor analysis of the short version. Rev Enferm Ref. 2018;4:9–18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guidetti M, Averna A, Castellini G, et al. Physical activity during COVID-19 lockdown: data from an Italian survey. Healthcare. 2021;9:513–522.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8146725</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33925257</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Udhayakumar P, Illango P. Psychological wellbeing among college students. J Social Work Educ Practice. 2018;3:79–89.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ballard T, Kepple A, Cafiero C. The Food Insecurity Experience Scale: Development of a Global Standard for Monitoring Hunger Worldwide. Rome: FAO; 2013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tufts University. Data4Diets: Building Blocks for Diet-Related Food Security Analysis. Boston, MA: Tufts University; 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elsahoryi N, Al-Sayyed H, Odeh M, et al. Effect of covid-19 on food security: a cross-sectional survey. Clin Nutr ESPEN. 2020;40:171–178.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7533117</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33183533</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munro B. Statistical Methods for Health Care Research. Philadelphia: Lippincott Williams and Wilkins; 2005.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Husban N, Alkhayat A, Aljweesri M, et al. Effects of COVID-19 pandemic on medical students in Jordanian universities: a multi-center cross-sectional study. Ann Med Surg. 2021;67:1–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8209674</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34168869</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almomani E, Qablan A, Almomany A, et al. The coping strategies followed by university students to mitigatethe COVID-19 quarantine psychological impact. Curr Psychol. 2021;40:5772–5781.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8106545</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33994758</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alqudah A, Al-Smadi A, Oqal M, et al. About anxiety levels and anti-anxiety drugs among quarantined undergraduate Jordanian students during COVID-19 pandemic. Int J Clin Pract. 2021;75:1–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8250113</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33884714</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Basheti I, Mhaidat Q, Mhaidat H. Prevalence of anxiety and depression during COVID-19 pandemic among healthcare students in Jordan and its effect on their learning process: a national survey. PLoS One 2021;16:1–16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8021185</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33819301</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamaideh S, Al-Modallal H, Tanash M, et al. Depression, anxiety and stress among undergraduate students during COVID-19 outbreak and “home-quarantine”. Nursing Open. 2021;8:1–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8242644</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33988913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Ajlouni Z, Park S, Alawa J, et al. Anxiety and depressive symptoms are associated with poor sleep health during a period of COVID-19-induced nationwide lockdown: a cross-sectional analysis of adults in Jordan. BMJ Open. 2020;10:1–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7757395</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33371040</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gasteiger N, Vedhara K, Massey A, et al. Depression, anxiety and stress during the COVID-19 pandemic: results from a New Zealand cohort study on mental well-being. BMJ. 2021;11:1–16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8098295</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33941630</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jia R, Ayling K, Chalder T, et al. Mental health in the UK during the COVID-19 pandemic: cross-sectional analyses from a community cohort study. BMJ. 2020;10:1–14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7493070</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32933965</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarwer D, Polonsky H. The psychosocial burden of obesity. Endocrinol Metab Clin North Am. 2016;45:677–688.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6052856</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27519139</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mousa T, Mashal R, Al-Domi H, et al. Body image dissatisfaction among adolescent schoolgirls in Jordan. Body Image. 2010;7:46–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19910269</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choi D, Ota S, Watanuki S. Does cigarette smoking relieve stress? Evidence from the event-related potential (ERP). Int J Psychophysiol. 2015;98:470–476.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26497442</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haskell C, Kennedy D, Wesnes K, et al. Cognitive and mood improvements of caffeine in habitual consumers and habitual non-consumers of caffeine. Psychopharmacology. 2005;179:813–825.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15678363</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith A. Caffeine, cognitive failures and health in a non-working community sample. Hum Psychopharmacol. 2009;24:29–34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19016251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>