<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39464820</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2052-336X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>22</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Dec</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of environmental health science &amp; engineering</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Environ Health Sci Eng</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Odour and indoor air quality hazards in railway cars: an Australian mixed methods case study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>503</StartPage><EndPage>517</EndPage><MedlinePgn>503-517</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s40201-024-00908-y</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="PURPOSE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This case study aimed to diagnose the cause(s) of a seasonal, and objectionable odour reported by travellers and drivers in the railway cars of Australian passenger trains. The research questions were to: (1) identify whether significant microbial colonisation was present within the air handling system of trains and causing the odours; to (2) identify other potential sources and; (3) remedial options for addressing the issue.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A mixed-methods, action research design was used adopted. Sections of the heating, ventilation, and air conditioning (HVAC) systems from odour-affected trains were swabbed for bacteria and fungi and examined for evidence of wear, fatigue and damage on-site and off-site. Insulation foam material extracted from the walls of affected trains was also subjected to a chemical assessment following exposure to varying humidity and temperature conditions in a climate simulator. This was accompanied by a qualitative sensory characterisation.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Upon exposure to a variety of simulated temperature and humidity combinations to recreate the odour, volatile chemical compounds released from the insulation foam by water were identified as its likely cause. In addition, a range of potentially serious pathogenic and odour-causing microbes were cultured from the HVAC systems, although it is considered unlikely that bacterial colonies were the odour source.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The research has implications for the sanitising and maintenance policies for HVAC systems on public transport, especially when operating in humid environments. The sanitary imposition, especially in the wake of COVID-19 may be required to ensure the safety of the travelling public and drivers.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s) 2024.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chandra</LastName><ForeName>Shaneel</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4257-5860</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Science and Sustainability, School of Health, Medical and Applied Sciences, Central Queensland University, Rockhampton North, QLD 4702 Australia.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/023q4bk22</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.1023.0</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 2193 0854</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bricknell</LastName><ForeName>Lisa</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5072-9030</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Science and Sustainability, School of Health, Medical and Applied Sciences, Central Queensland University, Rockhampton North, QLD 4702 Australia.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/023q4bk22</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.1023.0</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 2193 0854</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Makiela</LastName><ForeName>Sandrine</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Science and Sustainability, School of Health, Medical and Applied Sciences, Central Queensland University, Rockhampton North, QLD 4702 Australia.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/023q4bk22</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.1023.0</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 2193 0854</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bruce</LastName><ForeName>Sherie</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0003-9312-8571</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Science and Sustainability, School of Health, Medical and Applied Sciences, Central Queensland University, Rockhampton North, QLD 4702 Australia.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/023q4bk22</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.1023.0</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 2193 0854</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Naweed</LastName><ForeName>Anjum</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5534-4295</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Appleton Institute for Behavioural Science, Central Queensland University, 44 Greenhill Road, Wayville, SA 5034 Australia.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/023q4bk22</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.1023.0</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 2193 0854</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Environ Health Sci Eng</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101613643</NlmUniqueID></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Indoor air quality</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Odour</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Public health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Railways</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Risk</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Competing interestsThe authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39464820</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11499582</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40201-024-00908-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">908</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Kim KH, Kim SH, Jung YR, Kim MG. Evaluation of malodor for automobile air conditioner evaporator by using laboratory-scale test cooling bench. J Chromatogr A. 2008;1204(1):72–80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18701113</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sakakibara K, Kaitani K, Hamada C, Sato S, Matsuo M. Analysis of odor in car cabin. J Soc Automot Eng Rev. 1999;20(2):237–41.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spengler JD, Samet JM, McCarthy JF. Indoor air quality handbook. New York: McGraw-Hill: McGraw-Hill’s AccessEngineering; 2001.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hugenholtz P, Fuerst JA. Heterotrophic bacteria in an air-handling system. Appl Environ Microbiol. 1992;58:3914–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC183204</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1476435</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ford. Climate Control- musty or mildew type odor from climate control system- escape 2001–2003, in Technical Service Bulletin. Ford Motor Company; 2003.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braithwaite SK. Sensory Analysis and Health Risk Assessment of Environmental Odors. 2019, University of California, Los Angeles: Ann Arbor. p. 217.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dalton P. Odor perception and beliefs about risk. Chem Senses. 1996;21(4):447–58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8866108</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luongo JC, Fennelly KP, Keen JA, Zhai ZJ, Jones BW, Miller SL. Role of mechanical ventilation in the airborne transmission of infectious agents in buildings. Indoor Air. 2016;26(5):666–78.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7165552</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26562748</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lutz BD, Jin J, Rinaldi MG, Wickes BL, Huycke MM. Outbreak of invasive aspergillus infection in Surgical patients, Associated with a Contaminated Air-Handling System. Clin Infect Dis. 2003;37(6):786–93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12955639</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morawska L, Tang JW, Bahnfleth W, Bluyssen PM, Boerstra A, Buonanno G, Cao J, Dancer S, Floto A, Franchimon F, Haworth C, Hogeling J, Isaxon C, Jimenez JL, Kurnitski J, Li Y, Loomans M, Marks G, Marr LC, Mazzarella L, Melikov AK, Miller S, Milton DK, Nazaroff W, Nielsen PV, Noakes C, Peccia J, Querol X, Sekhar C, Seppänen O, Tanabe S-i, Tellier R, Tham KW, Wargocki P, Wierzbicka A, Yao M. How can airborne transmission of COVID-19 indoors be minimised? Environ Int. 2020;142:p105832.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7250761</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32521345</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horve PF, Dietz LG, Fretz M, Constant DA, Wilkes A, Townes JM, Martindale RG, Messer WB, Van Den Wymelenberg KG. Identification of SARS-CoV-2 RNA in healthcare heating, ventilation, and air conditioning units. Indoor Air. 2021;31(6):1826–32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8447041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34189769</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiu Z, Cao H. Commuter exposure to particulate matter in urban public transportation of Xi’an, China. J Environ Health Sci Eng. 2020;18(2):451–62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7721829</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33312574</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Totaro M, Costa AL, Casini B, Profeti S, Gallo A, Frendo L, Porretta A, Valentini P, Privitera G, Baggiani A. Microbiological Air Quality in Heating, Ventilation and Air Conditioning systems of Surgical and Intensive Care areas: the application of a Disinfection Procedure for Dehumidification devices. Pathogens, 2019. 8(1).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6472009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30650590</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ng TW, Chan PY, Chan TT, Wu H, Lai KM. Skin squames contribute to ammonia and volatile fatty acid production from bacteria colonizing in air-cooling units with odor complaints. Indoor Air. 2018;28(2):258–65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29130534</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simmons RB, Noble JA, Rose L, Price DL, Crow SA, Ahearn DG. Fungal colonization of automobile air conditioning systems. J Ind Microbiol Biotechnol. 1997;19(2):150–3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gołofit-Szymczak M, Stobnicka-Kupiec A, Górny RL. Impact of air-conditioning system disinfection on microbial contamination of passenger cars. Air Qual Atmos Health. 2019;12(9):1127–35.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rad RH, Khani MR, Mehdikia H, Shafiei M, Shokri B. Decomposition of high concentration benzene (produced in paper and painting industries) and its byproducts, methane and carbon dioxide, using plate gliding arc. J Environ Health Sci Eng. 2019;17(2):549–60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6985433</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32030133</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yau YH, Poh KS, Badarudin A. An investigation of thermal environment of an existing UFAD system in a high-rise office building in the tropics. J Environ Health Sci Eng. 2018;16(2):313–22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6277336</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30729002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verriele M, Plaisance H, Vandenbilcke V, Locoge N, Jaubert JN, Meunier G. Odor evaluation and discrimination of car cabin and its components: application of the field of odors approach in a sensory descriptive analysis. J Sens Stud. 2012;27(2):102–10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buchecker F, Baum A, Loos HM, Buettner A. Follow your nose - traveling the world of odorants in new cars. Indoor Air. 2022;32(3):e13014–n/a.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35347790</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buchecker F, Loos HM, Buettner A. Smells like new car or rather like an old carriage? - resolution of the decay behavior of odorants in vehicle cabins during usage. Indoor Air. 2022;32(9):e13112–n/a.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36168231</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu B, Chen X, Xiong J. Air quality inside motor vehicles’ cabins: a review. Indoor + Built Environ. 2018;27(4):452–65.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wolkoff P, Wilkins CK, Clausen PA, Nielsen GD. Organic compounds in office environments - sensory irritation, odor, measurements and the role of reactive chemistry. Indoor Air. 2006;16(1):7–19.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16420493</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duffee RA, O’Brien M. Response to odours, in Indoor Air Quality Handbook, J.D. Spengler, J.M. Samet, and J.F. McCarthy, Editors. 2001, McGraw-Hill Education: New York.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Distel H, Ayabe-Kanamura S, Martinez-Gomez M, Schicker I, Kobayakawa T, Saito S, Hudson R. Perception of everyday odors: correlation between intensity, familiarity and strength of hedonic judgement. Chem Senses. 1999;24(2):191–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10321820</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Logan DW. Do you smell what I smell? Genetic variation in olfactory perception. Biochem Soc Trans. 2014;42(4):861–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25109969</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sorokowska A, Sorokowski P, Hummel T. Cross-cultural administration of an odor discrimination test. Chemosens Percept. 2014;7(2):85–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4037584</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24883170</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antrobus B. Train troubles: Silver lining on mould-affected NGR trains, in The Fraser Coast Chronicle. 2020, NewsCorp.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan Y-C, McTainsh G, Leys J, McGowan H, Tews K. Influence of the 23 October 2002 Dust Storm on the Air Quality of four Australian cities. Water Air Soil Pollut. 2005;164(1):329–48.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miranda MT, Romero P, Valero-Amaro V, Arranz JI, Montero I. Ventilation conditions and their influence on thermal comfort in examination classrooms in times of COVID-19. A case study in a Spanish area with Mediterranean climate. Int J Hyg Environ Health. 2022;240:113910.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8695129</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34968975</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akumuntu JB, Wehn U, Mulenga M, Brdjanovic D. Enabling the sustainable Faecal Sludge Management service delivery chain—A case study of dense settlements in Kigali, Rwanda. Int J Hyg Environ Health. 2017;220(6):960–73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28596087</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Selbach C, Soldánová M, Sures B. Estimating the risk of swimmer’s itch in surface waters– a case study from Lake Baldeney, River Ruhr. Int J Hyg Environ Health. 2016;219(7, Part B):693–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25900402</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mandal J, Brandl H. Bioaerosols in indoor environment - A review with special reference to residential and occupational locations. Open Environ Biol Monit J. 2011;4:83–96.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mislivec PBB. Comparison of antibiotic-amended Potato Dextrose Agar and Acidified Potato Dextrose Agar as Growth substrates for Fungi. J Association Official Anal Chem. 1976;59:720–1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">5395</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh S, Beena PM. Comparative study of different microscopic techniques and culture media for the isolation of dermatophytes. Ind J Med Microbiol. 2003;21:21–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17642969</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li J, Zou K, Li W, Wang G, Yang W. Olfactory characterization of typical odorous pollutants part I: Relationship between the hedonic tone and odor concentration. Atmosphere. 2019;10(9):524.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sucker K, Both R, Bischoff M, Guski R, Krämer U, Winneke G. Odor frequency and odor annoyance part II: dose–response associations and their modification by hedonic tone. Int Arch Occup Environ Health. 2008;81(6):683–94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17906873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li R, Zhong Y, Guan L. Research on odor characteristics of typical odorants of railway vehicle products. Environ Sci Pollut Res. 2023;30(32):78216–28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37269517</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greenberg MI, Curtis JA, Vearrier D. The perception of odor is not a surrogate marker for chemical exposure: a review of factors influencing human odor perception. Clin Toxicol (Phila). 2013;51(2):70–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23387344</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brechbühl J, Moine F, Nenniger Tosato M, Sporkert F, Broillet M-C. Identification of pyridine analogs as new predator-derived kairomones. Front NeuroSci, 2015. 9(253).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4517376</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26283896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ji Ram V, Sethi A, Nath M, Pratap R. Chap. 5 - Five-Membered Heterocycles. The Chemistry of Heterocycles. V. Ji Ram, et al., Editors.; 2019. pp. 149–478.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mogilnicka I, Bogucki P, Ufnal M. Microbiota and malodor-etiology and management. Int J Mol Sci. 2020;21:2886.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7215946</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32326126</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Franchitti E, Caredda C, Anedda E, Traversi D. Urban Aerobiome and effects on Human Health: a systematic review and missing evidence. Atmosphere. 2022;13(7):1148.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lai KM, Sung YH, Ma KK. Viable airborne microbial counts from air-cooling units with and without complaints of urine and body odors. Aerobiologia. 2017;33(2):229–41.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simmons RB, Rose LJ, Crow SA, Ahearn DG. The occurrence and persistence of mixed biofilms in automobile air conditioning systems. Curr Microbiol. 1999;39(3):141–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10441727</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Triadó-Margarit X, Veillette M, Duchaine C, Talbot M, Amato F, Minguillón MC, Martins V, de Miguel E, Casamayor EO, Moreno T. Bioaerosols in the Barcelona subway system. Indoor Air. 2017;27(3):564–75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27687789</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boraphech P, Thiravetyan P. Trimethylamine (fishy odor) adsorption by biomaterials: Effect of fatty acids, alkanes, and aromatic compounds in waxes. J Hazard Mater. 2015;284:269–77.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25664363</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo Q, Zhang X, Li X, Chen T, Yang B, Ding C, Wang C, Pan M, Ma W, Yu J. Variation and mitigation of musty, septic, chemical, grassy, fishy odors and corresponding odorants in a full-scale drinking water treatment plant with advanced treatments. Chemosphere. 2021;269:128691.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33162163</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xue C, He Z, Qin F, Chen J, Zeng M. Effects of amides from pungent spices on the free and protein-bound heterocyclic amine profiles of roast beef patties by UPLC-MS/MS and multivariate statistical analysis. Food Res Int. 2020;135:p109299.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32527489</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bir D, Tutin K. Quantitation of Trimethyl Amine by Headspace Gas Chromatography-Mass Spectrometry using a base-modified column. J Chromatogr Sci. 2002;40(6):337–42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12137206</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang C-T, Chen B-Y, Shiu IS, Jeng F-T. Biofiltration of trimethylamine-containing waste gas by entrapped mixed microbial cells. Chemosphere. 2004;55(5):751–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15013680</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keller A, Hempstead M, Gomez IA, Gilbert AN, Vosshall LB. An olfactory demography of a diverse metropolitan population. BMC Neurosci. 2012;13:122.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3493268</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23046643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Advisory Committee for Acute Exposure Guideline Levels for Hazardous Substances. Acute exposure Guideline levels (AEGLs) for trimethylamine (CAS Reg. No. 75-50-3) interim. USEPA; 2008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deichman WB, Gerarde HW. Methylamines, in Toxicology of Drugs and Chemicals. 1969, Academic Press: New York.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pasanen AL, Juutinen T, Jantunen MJ, Kalliokoski P. Occurrence and moisture requirements of microbial growth in building materials. Volume 30. International Biodeterioration &amp; Biodegradation; 1992. pp. 273–83. 4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kelly SM, Larsen KR, Darling R, Petersen AC, Bellaire BH, Wannemuehler MJ, Narasimhan B. Single-dose combination nanovaccine induces both rapid and durable humoral immunity and toxin neutralizing antibody responses against Bacillus anthracis. Vaccine. 2021;39(29):3862–70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8325489</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34090702</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olguín-Araneda V, Banawas S, Sarker MR, Paredes-Sabja D. Recent advances in germination of Clostridium spores. Res Microbiol. 2015;166(4):236–43.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25132133</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhai Y, Li D, Du P, Zhang Z, He Z, Guo Y, Chen Y, Kang Y, Hu S, Gao Z. Complete sequences of two new KPC-harbouring plasmids in Klebsiella pneumoniae ST11 strains in China. J Global Antimicrob Resist. 2021;24:114–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33321214</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pavia CS, Plummer MM. The evolution of rapid antigen detection systems and their application for COVID-19 and other serious respiratory infectious diseases. Immunology and Infection: Journal of Microbiology; 2021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8234251</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34272205</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mike S, Karina B, Andrew C, Ron D, Graham D, Ronald de G, David E, Susanna E, Adam F, Manolis G, Carlo G, Jim G, Paul H, Terho H, Ulrich H, Philipp H, Irja L, Hermione L, Federico Martinon T, Andrew P, Mary R, Andrew R, Fernanda R, Emmanuel R, Pablo R, Delane S, Steve T, Maria T. Manual of Childhood infections: the Blue Book. [N.p.]: OUP Oxford: Oxford Specialist Handbooks in Paediatrics; 2011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cristina ML, Sartini M, Spagnolo AM. Serratia marcescens infections in neonatal intensive care units (NICUs). Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2019;16(4):610.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6406414</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30791509</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khanna A, Khanna M, Aggarwal A. Serratia marcescens- a rare opportunistic nosocomial pathogen and measures to limit its spread in hospitalized patients. J Clin Diagn Res. 2013;7(2):243–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3592283</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23543704</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan HA, Ahmad A, Mehboob R. Nosocomial infections and their control strategies. Asian Pac J Trop Biomed. 2015;5(7):509–14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Möritz M, Peters H, Nipko B, Rüden H. Capability of air filters to retain airborne bacteria and molds in heating, ventilating and air-conditioning (HVAC) systems. Int J Hyg Environ Health. 2001;203(5):401–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11556144</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weather-Atlas. January weather forecast and climate Brisbane, Australia. 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sze To GN, Chao CYH. Review and comparison between the Wells–Riley and dose-response approaches to risk assessment of infectious respiratory diseases. Indoor Air. 2010;20(1):2–16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7202094</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19874402</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim K-H, Kabir E, Jahan SA. Airborne bioaerosols and their impact on human health. J Environ Sci. 2018;67:23–35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7128579</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29778157</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Union Agency for Railways. COVID-19 rail protocol- annex. European Centre for Disease Control and Prevention: Valenciennes Cedex, France; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lecamwasam L, Wilson J, Chokolich D. Guide to Best Practice Maintenance &amp; Operation of HVAC Systems for Energy Efficiency, D.o.C.C.a.E.E. ciency, Editor. 2012, Commonwealth of Australia. p. 95.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>NSW Transport Assets Standards Authority. Climate comfort and HVAC on passenger Rolling Stock. State of NSW; 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Australia SW. Workplace exposure standards for airborne contaminants. 2022, Safe Work Australia: Canberra, ACT.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rail Industry Safety &amp;, Standards, Board. AS 7482:022 railway rolling stock-heating ventilation and air conditioning (HVAC). Standards Australia: Sydney, NSW; 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jonidi Jafari A, Charkhloo E, Pasalari H. Urban air pollution control policies and strategies: a systematic review. J Environ Health Sci Eng. 2021;19(2):1911–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8617239</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34900316</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>