<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39464965</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2249-4863</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of family medicine and primary care</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Family Med Prim Care</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Mental health challenges within the LGBTQ community: A societal imperative.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>3529</StartPage><EndPage>3535</EndPage><MedlinePgn>3529-3535</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4103/jfmpc.jfmpc_321_24</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The LGBTQ community faces specific stressors rooted in societal discrimination, bias, and marginalization, impacting mental health significantly. Persistent discrimination, exclusion, and heteronormative expectations are identified as social determinants that contribute to heightened stress levels, resulting in increased rates of anxiety, depression, and suicidality. Moreover, the COVID-19 pandemic has also severely affected the physical and mental health of a large percentage of the population, particularly impacting the health of marginalized individuals such as LGBT individuals. Studies consistently reveal alarming mental health disparities between LGBTQ individuals and their heterosexual counterparts, with elevated rates of mood disorders, substance abuse, and self-harm. Transgender individuals, in particular, face unique challenges, including high rates of gender dysphoria and discrimination-induced mental distress. The concept of intersectionality within the LGBTQ community emphasizes the compounded burden faced by individuals with multiple marginalized identities, necessitating tailored mental health strategies. The societal context, including legal and policy frameworks, plays a pivotal role in shaping the mental health and scope for LGBTQ individuals. Supportive frameworks, such as anti-discrimination laws, marriage equality, and healthcare policies, contribute to societal acceptance and individual well-being. Additionally, efforts to destigmatize LGBTQ identities, comprehensive sex education, and public awareness campaigns challenging stereotypes are crucial for fostering a more inclusive societal mindset. Establishing robust support networks within the LGBTQ community, including initiatives providing mental health resources, counseling, community spaces, and allyship programs, is vital for community resilience. These efforts not only contribute to the well-being of individuals within the LGBTQ community but also work toward creating a more inclusive society. In conclusion, addressing mental health challenges within the LGBTQ community requires a multifaceted approach involving societal understanding, legal support, destigmatization efforts, and robust community resources. By acknowledging and comprehending the unique struggles faced by the LGBTQ community, society can collectively work toward building a more compassionate, supportive, and inclusive environment for all individuals, irrespective of their sexual orientation or gender identity.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: © 2024 Journal of Family Medicine and Primary Care.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shaikh</LastName><ForeName>Aman</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physiology, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Bibinagar, Telangana, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kamble</LastName><ForeName>Prafull</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physiology, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Bibinagar, Telangana, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Daulatabad</LastName><ForeName>Vandana</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physiology, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Bibinagar, Telangana, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Singhal</LastName><ForeName>Anish</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physiology, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Bibinagar, Telangana, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Madhusudhan</LastName><ForeName>U</ForeName><Initials>U</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physiology, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Bibinagar, Telangana, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>John</LastName><ForeName>Nitin Ashok</ForeName><Initials>NA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physiology, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Bibinagar, Telangana, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>India</Country><MedlineTA>J Family Med Prim Care</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101610082</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2249-4863</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Allyship program</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">LGBTQ community</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">community support</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mental health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">societal relevance</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">stressors</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>There are no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39464965</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11504819</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/jfmpc.jfmpc_321_24</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">JFMPC-13-3529</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Daulatabad VS, Kamble PA, Patil RS, Doijad VP, Waghmare PP, Madhuri BA, et al. Impact of COVID-19 lockdown on physical, mental and behavioral health. Eur J Mol Clin Med. 2022;9:4198209.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yarns BC, Abrams JM, Meeks TW, Sewell DD. The mental health of older LGBT adults. Curr Psychiatry Rep. 2016;18:60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27142205</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Di Marco D, Hoel H, Lewis D. Discrimination and exclusion on grounds of sexual and gender identity: Are LGBT people's voices heard at the workplace? Span J Psychol. 2021;24:e18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33745498</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jakobsen MD, Bromseth J, Siverskog A, Krane MS. The provision of healthcare services toolder LGBT adults in the Nordic countries: A scoping review. Scand J Prim Health Care. 2023;41:359–71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11001363</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37602941</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Lange J, Baams L, van Bergen DD, Bos HMW, Bosker RJ. Minority stress and suicidal ideation and suicide attempts among LGBT adolescents and young adults: A meta-analysis. LGBT Health. 2022;9:222–37.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35319281</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dhejne C, Van Vlerken R, Heylens G, Arcelus J. Mental health and gender dysphoria: A review of the literature. Int Rev Psychiatry. 2016;28:44–57.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26835611</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lamontagne E, Leroy V, Yakusik A, Parker W, Howell S, Ventelou B. Assessment and determinants of depression and anxiety on a global sample of sexual and gender diverse people at high risk of HIV: A public health approach. BMC Public Health. 2024;24:215.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10795213</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38238673</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cochran BN, Cauce AM. Characteristics of lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender individuals entering substance abuse treatment. J Subst Abuse Treat. 2006;30:135–46.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16490677</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams ND, Fish JN. The availability of LGBT-specific mental health and substance abuse treatment in the United States. Health Serv Res. 2020;55:932–43.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7704474</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32970327</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamble P, Daulatabad VS, Tandra H, Singhal A, U M, John NA. Yoganidra to alleviate anxiety: An interventional study. Cureus. 2023;15:e45083.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10568654</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37842496</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daulatabad VS, Rukadikar C, Kamble P. Role of Yoga in relieving anxiety in MBBS Students. Indian J Clin Anat Physiol. 2019;6:335–7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fraser B, Pierse N, Chisholm E, Cook H. LGBTIQ+homelessness: A review of the literature. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2019;16:2677.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6695950</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31357432</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Westwood S, Willis P, Fish J, Hafford-Letchfield T, Semlyen J, King A, et al. Older LGBT+health inequalities in the UK: Setting a research agenda. J Epidemiol Community Health. 2020;74:408–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32086374</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robinson MA, Brewster ME. Understanding affiliate stigma faced by heterosexual family and friends of LGB people: A measurement development study. J Fam Psychol. 2016;30:353–63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26414416</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keuroghlian AS, Ard KL, Makadon HJ. Advancing health equity for lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender (LGBT) people through sexual health education and LGBT-affirming health care environments. Sex Health. 2017;14:119122.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28160786</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beyrer C. Pushback: The current wave of anti-homo sexuality law sand impacts on health. PLoS Med. 2014;11:e1001658.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4068984</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24959671</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McConnell EA, Birkett MA, Mustanski B. Typologies of social support and associations with mental health outcomes among LGBT youth. LGBT Health. 2015;2:55–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4855776</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26790019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamble P, Daulatabad V, Patil R, John NA, John J. Omicron variantinCOVID-19 current pandemic: A reason for apprehension. Horm Mol Biol Clin Investig. 2022;44:89–96.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36064193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen JM, Joel S, Castro Lingl D. Antecedents and consequences of LGBT individuals’ perceptions of straight allyship. J PersSoc Psychol. 2023;125:827–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36996168</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>