<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39465255</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1758-7247</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>ahead-of-print</Volume><Issue>ahead-of-print</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>28</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of health organization and management</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Health Organ Manag</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Effective decision-making in public health organizations: reference to the COVID-19 pandemic.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1108/JHOM-02-2023-0036</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="PURPOSE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">The role of public health organizations during the COVID-19 pandemic was crucial. These groups acted to slow the spread of infection through the implementation of initiatives, policies, research and more. However, the rapidly changing and uncertain climate of the pandemic resulted in suboptimal processes and decision-making within these organizations. These already complex organizations and networks of people became even more nuanced. Thus, organizational decision-making processes must be improved upon based on previous experiences and lessons learnt. With minimal peer-reviewed literature available, resources for effective organizational decision-making in these organizations are scarce. This served as the impetus for this review.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DESIGN/METHODOLOGY/APPROACH" NlmCategory="METHODS">To conduct this literature review, both peer-reviewed and grey literature were incorporated to better understand effective organizational decision-making practices for public health organizations. Recommendations found in the literature review were identified, coded and themed to provide a novel decision-making framework to be used by public health executives.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="FINDINGS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Nine key themes of effective organizational decision-making were identified, including utilize decision-making tools, define the problem and acknowledge an imminent decision, establish decision rights, outline a clear escalation path, create a supportive organizational culture, set decision objectives and goals, and evaluate decision alternatives. These findings in conjunction with existing decision-making models were used to create a seven-step effective decision-making framework for public health organizations.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="ORIGINALITY/VALUE" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The review and analysis of effective organizational decision-making practices is instructive. Public health executives and decision-makers should incorporate the themes identified and employ the proposed decision-making framework to encourage improved decision-making practices.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© Emerald Publishing Limited.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liem</LastName><ForeName>Jessica</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Sciences, Brock University, St. Catharines, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Goodman School of Business, Brock University, St. Catharines, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Thongpapanl</LastName><ForeName>Narongsak</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Goodman School of Business, Brock University, St. Catharines, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Administration Center (RAC), Chiang Mai University, Chiang Mai, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Faught</LastName><ForeName>Brent E</ForeName><Initials>BE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health Sciences, Brock University, St. Catharines, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Health Organ Manag</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101179473</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1477-7266</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003659" MajorTopicYN="Y">Decision Making, Organizational</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="Y">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011635" MajorTopicYN="N">Public Health Administration</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011634" MajorTopicYN="N">Public Health</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19 pandemic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Decision-making framework</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Organizational decision-making</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Public health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Public organizations</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>32</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39465255</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1108/JHOM-02-2023-0036</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>Al Hasani, M. (2019), “Rationality and bounded rationality in decision making”, European Journal of Economics, Law and Politics, Vol. 6 No. 1, p. 20, doi: 10.19044/elp.v6no1a2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Dabbagh, Z.S. (2020), “The role of decision-maker in crisis management: a qualitative study using grounded theory (COVID‐19 pandemic crisis as a model)”, Journal of Public Affairs, Vol. 20 No. 4, 2186, doi: 10.1002/pa.2186.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Angeli, F., Camporesi, S. and Dal Fabbro, G. (2021), “The COVID-19 wicked problem in public health ethics: conflicting evidence, or incommensurable values?”, Humanities and Social Sciences Communications, Vol. 8 No. 1, 161, doi: 10.1057/s41599-021-00839-1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aragón, T.J., Cody, S.H., Farnitano, C., Hernandez, L.B., Morrow, S.A., Pan, E.S., Tzvieli, O. and Willis, M. (2021), “Crisis decision-making at the speed of COVID-19: field report on issues the first regional shelter-in-place orders in the United States”, Journal of Public Health Management and Practice, Vol. 27 Supplement 1, pp. S19-S28, doi: 10.1097/phh.0000000000001292.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Australia Government (2018), “Decision-making during crisis: a practical guide”, available at: https://www.organisationalresilience.gov.au/Documents/decision-making-during-a-crisis-a-practical-guide.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bäker, A. and Goodall, A. (2021), “Do expert clinicians make the best managers? Evidence from hospitals in Denmark, Australia, and Switzerland”, BMJ Leader, Vol. 5 No. 3, pp. 161-166, doi: 10.1136/leader-2021-000483.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonabeau, E. (2003), “Don't trust your gut”, available at: https://hbr.org/2003/05/dont-trust-your-gut</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CDC Foundation (2022), “Public health in action”, available at: https://www.cdcfoundation.org/what-public-health#:∼:text=Public%20health%20is%20the%20science,and%20responding%20to%20infectious%20diseases</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohu, J. (2021), “Pandemic illustrates the necessity of intuitive decision-making skills”, available at: https://gbr.pepperdine.edu/2021/07/intuitive-decision-making-skills/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dane, E. and Pratt, M. (2007), “Exploring intuition and its role in managerial decision making”, Academy of Management Review, Vol. 32 No. 1, pp. 33-54, doi: 10.5465/amr.2007.23463682.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dane, E., Rockmann, K. and Pratt, M. (2012), “When should I trust my gut? Linking domain expertise to intuitive decision-making effectiveness”, Organizational Behavior and Human Decision Processes, Vol. 119 No. 2, pp. 187-194, doi: 10.1016/j.obhdp.2012.07.009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Smet, A., Lackey, G. and Weiss, L. (2017), “Untangling your organization's decision making”, available at: https://www.mckinsey.com/business-functions/people-and-organizational-performance/our-insights/untangling-your-organizations-decision-making</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fischhoff, B. (2020), “Making decisions in a COVID-19 world”, JAMA, Vol. 324 No. 2, pp. 139-140, doi: 10.1001/jama.2020.10178.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gillam, S. (2011), “Teaching doctors in training about management and leadership”, BMJ, Vol. 343 sep13 3, d5672, doi: 10.1136/bmj.d5672.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Graham, H. and Mollenhauer, L. (2019), “Shared decision-making for nonprofit governance”, available at: https://theonn.ca/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/SharedGovernance_final-Sep2019_v2-002.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Griggs, C., Kleinman, S., Maxwell, J. and Rieckhoff, K. (2020), “Increasing decision-making velocity: five steps for government leaders”, available at: https://www.mckinsey.com/industries/public-and-social-sector/our-insights/increasing-decision-making-velocity-five-steps-for-government-leaders</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hans, E., Van Houdenhoven, M. and Hulshof, P. (2011), “A framework for healthcare planning and control”, International Series in Operations Research and Management Science, Vol. 168 No. 1, pp. 303-320, doi: 10.1007/978-1-4614-1734-7_12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hernandez, J. and Ortega, R. (2019), “Bounded rationality in decision–making”, MOJ Research Review, Vol. 2 No. 1, pp. 1-8, doi: 10.15406/mojcrr.2019.02.00047.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnson, E. (2012), “Striving for no difference: examining effective leadership between nonprofit and for-profit contexts”, available at: warmislandwelcome.com/leadership-in-nonprofit-organizations-peer-reviewed-articles</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kontio, E., Lundgren-Laine, H., Kontio, J., Korvenranta, H. and Salantera, S. (2013), “Information utilization in tactical decision-making of middle management health managers”, Computers, Informatics, Nursing, Vol. 31 No. 1, pp. 9-16, doi: 10.1097/nxn.0b013e318261f192.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee, M. and Stinston, D. (2014), “Organizational decision-making models: comparing and contrasting to the stinson wellness model”, European Journal of Management, Vol. 14 No. 3, pp. 13-28, doi: 10.18374/ejm-14-3.2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leoveanu, A.C. (2013), “Rationalist model in public decision making”, Journal of Public Administration, Finance and Law, Vol. 4 No. 1, pp. 43-54.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levac, D., Colquhoun, H. and O'Brien, K.K. (2010), “Scoping studies: advancing the methodology”, Implementation Science, Vol. 5 No. 69, pp. 1-9, doi: 10.1186/1748-5908-5-69.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loh, E. (2015), “Doctors as health managers: an oxymoron, or a good idea?”, Journal of Work- Applied Management, Vol. 7 No. 1, pp. 52-60, doi: 10.1108/jwam-10-2015-005.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matzler, K., Bailom, F. and Mooradian, T.A. (2007), “Intuitive decision making”, MIT Sloan Management Review, Vol. 49 No. 1, p. 13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McDowell, T. and Mallon, D. (2020), “Getting decision rights right: how effective organizational decision-making can help boost performance”, available at: https://www2.deloitte.com/content/dam/insights/us/articles/6360_getting-decision-rights-right/DI_Getting-decision-rights-right.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miller, H. (2018), “Intuition and decision making for crisis situations”, in Engemann, K.J. (Ed.), The Routledge Companion to Risk, Crisis and Security in Business, Routledge, pp. 47-61.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neubauer, K. (2016), “Benefit corporations: providing A new shield for corporations with ideals beyond profits”, Journal of Business and Technology Law, Vol. 11 No. 1, p. 109.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Norwich University Online (2016), “7 key differences between nonprofit and for-profit organizations”, available at: https://online.norwich.edu/academic-programs/resources/7-key-differences-between-nonprofit-and-profit-organizations</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nutt, P.C. and Wilson, D.C. (2010), Handbook of Decision Making, John Wiley and Sons, New York, NY.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peirson, L., Ciliska, D., Dobbins, M. and Mowat, D. (2012), “Building capacity for evidence informed decision making in public health: a case study of organizational change”, BMC Public Health, Vol. 12, pp. 1-13, doi: 10.1186/1471-2458-12-137.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Power, N. (2017), “Decision Making during Emergencies: what we have Learned and where do we go from here?”, available at: https://crestresearch.ac.uk/comment/power-decision-making-emergencies/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schippers, M.C. and Rus, D.C. (2021), “Optimizing decision-making processes in times of COVID-19: using reflexivity to counteract information-processing failures”, Frontiers in Psychology, Vol. 12, 650525, doi: 10.3389/fpsyg.2021.650525.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silverman, L. and Taliento, L. (2006), “What business execs don't know – but should – about nonprofits”, available at: https://ssir.org/articles/entry/what_business_execs_dont_know_but_should_about_nonprofits</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Srivastava, A. (2022), “Challenges for evaluation practices and innovative approaches: lessons during COVID-19 pandemic”, Evaluation and Program Planning, Vol. 92, 102095, doi: 10.1016/j.evalprogplan.2022.102095.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thach, E. and Thompson, K. (2007), “Trading places: examining leadership competencies between for-profit vs public and non-profit leaders”, Leadership and Organization Development Journal, Vol. 28 No. 4, pp. 356-374, doi: 10.1108/01437730710752229.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>University of Minnesota (2010), “Principles of management”, available at: https://open.lib.umn.edu/principlesmanagement/chapter/1-1-introduction-to-principles-of-management/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uzonwanne, F.C. (2016), “Rational model of decision making”, in Global Encyclopedia of Public Administration, Public Policy, and Governance, pp. 1-6, doi: 10.1007/978-3-319-31816-5_2474-1.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>