<PubmedArticle xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39469227</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2504-3145</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>42</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Aug</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Portuguese journal of public health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Port J Public Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Epidemic Intelligence Threat Reporting Profile in Portugal during the COVID-19: 2 Years of Decrease in Reporting on Non-COVID-19 Threats.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>121</StartPage><EndPage>132</EndPage><MedlinePgn>121-132</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1159/000539616</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Epidemic intelligence (EI) ensures early detection, assessment, and communication of public health threats. Threat reporting defines priorities and mobilize resources for surveillance, prevention, and control. In Portugal, the Directorate-General of Health (DGS) is responsible for EI and publishes a weekly public health threat report (RONDA). Changes in threats in regular threat reports since COVID-19 have not been previously described. We analysed changes in non-COVID threat reporting in the weekly threat report.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Using the DGS Emergency Operations Centre's threat reporting database, we compared threats reported in RONDAs from 2016 to 2022 in three sequential periods: P1 before COVID-19 (January 2016-March 2020), P2 during acute COVID-19 restrictions (April 2020-February 2022), and P3 in post-acute COVID-19 phase (February 2022-September 2022). We described the monthly average frequency of reports on non-COVID-19 threats in those periods considering different disease groups, geographical focus, and information sources. We estimated expected non-COVID-19 reports on threats using a forecast model fitted to the time series until March 2020 and compared observed and expected values.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Non-COVID-19 threats had a decrease in the monthly average frequency of reporting in period 2 ( <ns0:math> <ns0:mrow><ns0:mover><ns0:mi>x</ns0:mi> <ns0:mo>¯</ns0:mo></ns0:mover> <ns0:mn>1</ns0:mn></ns0:mrow> </ns0:math> : 4.7 vs. <ns0:math> <ns0:mrow><ns0:mover><ns0:mi>x</ns0:mi> <ns0:mo>¯</ns0:mo></ns0:mover> </ns0:mrow> </ns0:math> : 2.3, <i>p</i> &lt; 0.001) compared to period 1. Using the forecast methods, there were 114 fewer non-COVID threats than the 162 expected (-70%) in period 2. In period 3, there were 105 more threats than expected (+256%). The ECDC and the WHO were the most frequent sources of information followed by national Public Health sources.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">During COVID-19, there was a decrease in reports on non-COVID threats in Portugal. COVID-19 possibly affected global EI, by shifting attention and resources from other threats to the pandemic. However, the number of threats that warrant follow-up and communication is increasing. Further research is necessary to inform the EI research and development agenda, to ensure that all relevant threats are detected, accessed, and communicated according to evolving EI objectives and priorities while resources and preparedness are guaranteed.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Published by S. Karger AG, Basel on behalf of NOVA National School of Public Health.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ricoca Peixoto</LastName><ForeName>Vasco</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Public Health Emergencies Centre, Directorate-General of Health, Lisbon, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>NOVA National School of Public Health, Public Health Research Centre, Comprehensive Health Research Center, CHRC, NOVA University Lisbon, Lisbon, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Grau-Pujol</LastName><ForeName>Berta</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Public Health Emergencies Centre, Directorate-General of Health, Lisbon, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>ECDC Fellowship Programme, Field Epidemiology path (EPIET), European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control (ECDC), Stockholm, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Directorate of Information and Analysis, Directorate-General of Health, Lisbon, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ourique</LastName><ForeName>Matilde</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>West-South Public Health Unit, Mafra, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lourenço da Silva</LastName><ForeName>Renato</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Public Health Emergencies Centre, Directorate-General of Health, Lisbon, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ferreira</LastName><ForeName>Mariana</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Public Health Emergencies Centre, Directorate-General of Health, Lisbon, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Firme</LastName><ForeName>Ana</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Public Health Emergencies Centre, Directorate-General of Health, Lisbon, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sentís</LastName><ForeName>Alexis</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Epidemiology Department, Epiconcept, Paris, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vasconcelos</LastName><ForeName>Paula</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Public Health Emergencies Centre, Directorate-General of Health, Lisbon, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Port J Public Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101719507</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2504-3145</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="por"><AbstractText Label="INTRODUÇÃO" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED"><i>A epidemic intelligence</i> (EI) assegura a deteção precoce, a avaliação e a comunicação das ameaças para a saúde pública para definir prioridades e mobilizar recursos para a investigação, vigilância, prevenção e controlo. Em Portugal, a Direção-Geral da Saúde (DGS) é responsável pela EI e publica semanalmente um relatório de ameaças para a saúde pública (RONDA) que é partilhado com a rede de autoridades de saúde, instituições e profissionais de saúde pública. As alterações nas ameaças comunicadas em relatórios periódicos de ameaças desde a COVID-19 não foram descritas anteriormente.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MÉTODOS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Comparámos as ameaças reportadas na RONDA entre 2016 a 2022 em três períodos sequenciais: antes da COVID-19 (janeiro de 2016 - março de 2020), P2 durante as restrições (abril de 2020 - fevereiro de 2022) e P3 na fase pós-aguda da COVID-19 (fevereiro de 2022 - setembro de 2022). Comparamos a frequência média mensal de ameaças não COVID-19 relatadas entre todas as ameaças relatadas nesses períodos, considerando diferentes categorias dentro do grupo de doenças, foco geográfico e fontes de informação.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTADOS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">As ameaças não-COVID-19 tiveram uma diminuição na frequência média mensal de reporte no Período2 (14,7 vs. 2,3 <i>p</i> &lt; 0.001) em comparação com o Período1, antes da COVID-19. Houve um retorno ao padrão pré-pandêmico de notificação no Período 3 (14,67 vs. 17,63 <i>p</i> &lt; 0.208) para ameaças não COVID-19 com um aumento nas doenças virais emergentes (2,20 vs. 7,62 <i>p</i> &lt; 0.001). O ECDC e a OMS são as fontes de informação mais frequentes, seguidas das fontes nacionais de saúde pública.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSÕES" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Durante a COVID-19, houve alterações no reporte de ameaças em Portugal. A COVID-19 possivelmente afetou a EI e os relatórios de ameaças epidémicas globais, possivelmente desviando a atenção e os recursos de outras ameaças para a pandemia. No entanto, a quantidade de ameaças que justificam o acompanhamento e a comunicação pode estar a aumentar. É necessária investigação em comunicação de ameaças detetadas no âmbito da EI a fim de assegurar que todas as ameaças relevantes são avaliadas e comunicadas de acordo com os objetivos da EI, garantindo simultaneamente o investimento em recursos e a preparação para a prevenção e resposta.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Published by S. Karger AG, Basel on behalf of NOVA National School of Public Health.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Communicable disease threat reports</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Emergency Operational Center</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Epidemic intelligence</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Event-based surveillance</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Preparedness and response</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Public health surveillance</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Threat reports</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors have no conflicts of interest to declare.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>38</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39469227</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11498916</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000539616</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">539616</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Bengtsson L, Borg S, Rhinard M. Assembling European health security: epidemic intelligence and the hunt for cross-border health threats. Secur Dialogue. 2019;50(2):115–30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coulombier D, Ciotti M, Freitas G, Frota A, Varela C, Vasconcelos P, et al. . Strengthening Europe’s epidemic intelligence capacity: the first collaboration between a European union member state and the European Centre for disease prevention and control. Euro Surveill. 2008;13(6):9–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18445423</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control . Weekly threats reports (CDTR) [Internet]. Stockholm, Sweden: ECDC; 2019. Available from: https://ecdc.europa.eu/en/threats-and-outbreaks/reports-and-data/weekly-threats (accessed April 13, 2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Eurosurveillance . National bulletins [Internet]. Stockholm, Sweden: ECDC; 2019. Available from: https://www.eurosurveillance.org/links (accessed August 5, 2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Despacho no. 11035-A/2016 Diário da República no. 176/2016. Série II. 1st Suplemento (2016-09-13): 2-2. Cria o Centro de Emergências em Saúde Pública (CESP) no âmbito da Direção-Geral da Saúde.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Norzin T, Ghiasbeglou H, Patricio M, Romanova S, Zaghlool A, Tanguay F, et al. . Event-based surveillance: providing early warning for communicable disease threats. Can Commun Dis Rep. 2023;49(2/3):29–34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10712973</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38090144</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Trust W. The cost of not preparing for infectious diseases [Internet]. London: Wellcome Trust; 2021. Available from: https://wellcome.org/news/cost-of-not-preparing-for-infectious-diseases (accessed March 26, 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carlson CJ, Boyce MR, Dunne M, Graeden E, Lin J, Abdellatif YO, et al. . The World Health Organization’s disease outbreak news: a retrospective database. PLoS Glob Public Heal. 2023;3(1):e0001083.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10021193</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36962988</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ullrich A, Schranz M, Rexroth U, Hamouda O, Schaade L, Diercke M, et al. . Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic and associated non-pharmaceutical interventions on other notifiable infectious diseases in Germany: an analysis of national surveillance data during week 1–2016 – week 32–2020. Lancet Reg Health Eur. 2021;6:100103.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8454829</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34557831</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tabachnick BG, Fidell LS. Using multivariate statistics. 6th ed.London: Pearson; 2012.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Furuse Y. Analysis of research intensity on infectious disease by disease burden reveals which infectious diseases are neglected by researchers. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2019;116(2):478–83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6329976</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30598444</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pires SM, Wyper GMA, Wengler A, Peñalvo JL, Haneef R, Moran D, et al. . Burden of disease of COVID-19: strengthening the collaboration for National studies. Front Public Heal. 2022;10:907012.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9208200</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35734754</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Google . COVID-19 community mobility reports [Internet]. Dublin: Google; 2020. Available from: https://www.google.com/covid19/mobility/ (accessed April 4, 2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bijkerk P, Monnier AA, Fanoy EB, Kardamanidis K, Friesema IH, Knol MJ. ECDC round table report and ProMed-mail most useful international information sources for The Netherlands early warning committee. Euro Surveill. 2017;22(14):30502.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5388122</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28422006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>MacIntyre CR, Chen X, Kunasekaran M, Quigley A, Lim S, Stone H, et al. . Artificial intelligence in public health: the potential of epidemic early warning systems. J Int Med Res. 2023;51(3):3000605231159335–18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10052500</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36967669</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
UK Government. Public Health England . Epidemic intelligence activities [Internet]. London: UK Health Security Agency; 2019. Available from: https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/emerging-infections-and-zoonoses-epidemic-intelligence-scanning-procedures/epidemic-intelligence-scanning-process (accessed March 7, 2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Robert Koch-Institut . Preparedness and response: epidemic intelligence [Internet]. Berlin: Robert Koch-Institut; 2020. Available from: https://www.rki.de/DE/Content/Infekt/Preparedness_Response/Epidemic_Intelligence.html (accessed February 17, 2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaiser R, Coulombier D. Different approaches to gathering epidemic intelligence in Europe. Wkly Releases. 2006;11(4):E060427.1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16809830</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilburn J, O’Connor C, Walsh AL, Morgan D. Identifying potential emerging threats through epidemic intelligence activities: looking for the needle in the haystack? Int J Infect Dis. 2019;89:146–53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7110621</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31629079</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rotureau B, Barboza P, Tarantola A, Paquet C. International Epidemic Intelligence at the Institut de Veille Sanitaire, France. Emerg Infect Dis. 2007;13(10):1590–2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2851537</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18258016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bohigas PA, Santos-O’connor F, Coulombier D. Epidemic intelligence and travel-related diseases: ECDC experience and further developments. Clin Microbiol Infect. 2009;15(8):734–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19486073</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>