<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39465790</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1536-5964</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>103</Volume><Issue>41</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>11</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Medicine (Baltimore)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Effect of stressors during COVID-19 lockdown on malnutrition and health-risk behaviors among Jordanian college students: A cross-sectional study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e40116</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e40116</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e40116</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/MD.0000000000040116</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>A stressful condition such as the emergence of the coronavirus and its related lockdown measures might trigger alterations in college students' behaviors. This cross-sectional study aimed to identify the changes in college students' dietary and lifestyle behaviors during the lockdown and the effect of lockdown-related stressors on health-risk behaviors. A web-based survey was conducted among undergraduate college students in Jordan. Weight and height were reported by the students. The students' dietary and lifestyle behaviors and their changes during 1 month of the countrywide lockdown were assessed. The Perceived Stress Scale-4 was utilized to assess stress levels. Results indicated that 77.2% of the students reported weight changes. Notably, 45.9% increased their intake of unhealthy food, while and 38% opted for healthier food choices. Most students experienced alterations in physical activity (80.0%), screen time (86.2%), smoking, and sleep patterns (85.4%), with a higher tendency toward adopting health-risk behaviors. Perceptions of curfew-related stress were associated with distance learning-related stress (OR = 2.73, CI: 1.08-6.90, P = .034), and a greater change in physical activity (OR = 3.59, CI: 1.36-9.48, P = .010). Additionally, weight changes were associated with perception of other types of stressors (OR = 3.39, CI: 1.39-8.28, P = .007). Overall, there was a considerable increase in malnutrition and health-risk behaviors among students during the lockdown. Understanding students' responses to these stressful conditions and the role of stress in driving behavioral changes are crucial for developing interventions that enhance college students' adaptation to such changes and maintaining healthy dietary and lifestyle behaviors in the future.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alkhalidy</LastName><ForeName>Hana</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8487-6349</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nutrition and Food Technology, Faculty of Agriculture, Jordan University of Science and Technology, Irbid, Jordan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Al-Shami</LastName><ForeName>Islam</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Nutrition and Dietetics, Faculty of Applied Medical Science, The Hashemite University, Zarqa, Jordan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alnaser</LastName><ForeName>Khadeejah</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nutrition and Food Technology, Faculty of Agriculture, Jordan University of Science and Technology, Irbid, Jordan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alkharabsheh</LastName><ForeName>Ana'am</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Hearing and Speech Sciences, Faculty of Rehabilitation Sciences, The University of Jordan, Amman, Jordan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nawaiseh</LastName><ForeName>Hala</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nutrition and Food Technology, School of Agriculture, The University of Jordan, Amman, Jordan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Dongmin</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Human Nutrition, Foods and Exercise, College of Agricultural and Life Sciences, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, VA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Medicine (Baltimore)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>2985248R</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0025-7974</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007597" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Jordan</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003430" MajorTopicYN="N">Cross-Sectional Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013334" MajorTopicYN="Y">Students</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055815" MajorTopicYN="N">Young Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013315" MajorTopicYN="Y">Stress, Psychological</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014495" MajorTopicYN="N">Universities</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D044342" MajorTopicYN="Y">Malnutrition</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000073599" MajorTopicYN="Y">Health Risk Behaviors</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000293" MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescent</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011790" MajorTopicYN="N">Quarantine</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008019" MajorTopicYN="N">Life Style</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015444" MajorTopicYN="N">Exercise</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>28</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>8</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39465790</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000040116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00005792-202410110-00008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11479516</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>The Jordan Times. Jordan confirms first case of coronavirus.
2020. http://jordantimes.com/news/local/jordan-confirms-first-case-coronavirus-0. Accessed April 26, 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khatatbeh M. Efficacy of nationwide curfew to encounter spread of COVID-19: a case from Jordan. Front Public Health. 2020;8:394.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7475701</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32984234</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) Situation Report – 83.
2020. https://www.who.int/docs/default-source/coronaviruse/situation-reports/20200412-sitrep-83-covid-19.pdf?sfvrsn=697ce98d_4. Accessed June 8, 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kebede TA, Stave SE, Kattaa M, Prokop M. Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on enterprises in Jordan. International Labour Organization: Beirut; 2020;1:1–62.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crawford J, Butler-Henderson K, Rudolph J, et al. . COVID-19: 20 countries’ higher education intra-period digital pedagogy responses. J Appl Learn Teach. 2020;3:1–20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Jordan. Overview of the coronavirus disease (COVID-19). https://www.who.int/countries/jor. Accessed October 7, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piot P, Muyembe JJ, Edmunds WJ. Ebola in west Africa: from disease outbreak to humanitarian crisis. Lancet Infect Dis. 2014;14:1034–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25282665</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Svoboda T, Henry B, Shulman L, et al. . Public health measures to control the spread of the severe acute respiratory syndrome during the outbreak in Toronto. N Engl J Med. 2004;350:2352–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15175437</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. China’s latest SARS outbreak has been contained, but biosafety concerns remain. 2004. https://www.who.int/emergencies/disease-outbreak-news/item/2004_05_18a-en. Accessed September 10, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmad A, Krumkamp R, Reintjes R. Controlling SARS: a review on China’s response compared with other SARS-affected countries. Trop Med Int Health. 2009;14:36–45.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7169812</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19508440</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leung GM, Quah S, Ho LM, et al. . A tale of two cities: community psychobehavioral surveillance and related impact on outbreak control in Hong Kong and Singapore during the severe acute respiratory syndrome epidemic. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol. 2004;25:1033–41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15636289</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bakare WA, Ilesanmi OS, Nabena EP, Famuyide T. Psychosocial stressors and support needs of survivors of Ebola virus disease, Bombali District, Sierra Leone, 2015. Healthc Low-Resour S. 2015;3:48–51.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nuriddin A, Jalloh MF, Meyer E, et al. . Trust, fear, stigma and disruptions: community perceptions and experiences during periods of low but ongoing transmission of Ebola virus disease in Sierra Leone, 2015. BMJ Glob Health. 2018;3:e000410.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5884263</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29629189</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McMahon SA, Ho LS, Brown H, Miller L, Ansumana R, Kennedy CE. Healthcare providers on the frontlines: a qualitative investigation of the social and emotional impact of delivering health services during Sierra Leone’s Ebola epidemic. Health Policy Plan. 2016;31:1232–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5035780</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27277598</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jalloh MF, Li WS, Bunnell RE, et al. . Impact of Ebola experiences and risk perceptions on mental health in Sierra Leone, July 2015. BMJ Glob Health. 2018;3:e000471.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5873549</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29607096</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patil NG, Yan YCH. SARS and its effect on medical education in Hong Kong. Med Educ. 2003;37:1127–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7168501</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14984121</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang HJ, Huang N, Lee CH, Hsu YJ, Hsieh CJ, Chou YJ. The impact of the SARS epidemic on the utilization of medical services: SARS and the fear of SARS. Am J Public Health. 2004;94:562–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1448298</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15054005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kwan MY, Arbour-Nicitopoulos KP, Duku E, Faulkner G. Patterns of multiple health risk-behaviours in university students and their association with mental health: application of latent class analysis. Health Promot Chronic Dis Prev Can. 2016;36:163–70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5215183</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27556920</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong JGWS, Cheung EPT, Cheung V, et al. . Psychological responses to the SARS outbreak in healthcare students in Hong Kong. Med Teach. 2004;26:657–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15763860</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torres SJ, Nowson CA. Relationship between stress, eating behavior, and obesity. Nutrition. 2007;23:887–94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17869482</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yau YHC, Potenza MN. Stress and eating behaviors. Minerva Endocrinol. 2013;38:255–67.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4214609</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24126546</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ku HY, Lohr LL. A case study of Chinese students’ attitudes toward their first Online learning experience. Etr D-Educ Tech Res. 2003;51:95–102.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alkhalidy H, Orabi A, Alzboun T, Alnaser K, Al-Shami I, Al-Bayyari N. Health-risk behaviors and dietary patterns among Jordanian college students: a pilot study. Front Nutr. 2021;8:225.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8160432</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34055850</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johal SS. Psychosocial impacts of quarantine during disease outbreaks and interventions that may help to relieve strain. N Z Med J. 2009;122:47–52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19652680</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deurenberg P, Weststrate JA, Seidell JC. Body mass index as a measure of body fatness: age-and sex-specific prediction formulas. Br J Nutr. 1991;65:105–14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2043597</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Waist Circumference and Waist–Hip Ratio: Report of a WHO Expert Consultation.
2008. https://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/handle/10665/44583/9789241501491_eng.pdf. Accessed September 15, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stok FM, Renner B, Allan J, et al. . Dietary behavior: an interdisciplinary conceptual analysis and taxonomy. Front Psychol. 2018;9:1689.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6160746</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30298030</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Afshin A, Sur PJ, Fay KA, et al. . Health effects of dietary risks in 195 countries, 1990-2017: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2017. Lancet. 2019;393:1958–72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6899507</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30954305</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen S, Kamarck T, Mermelstein R. A global measure of perceived stress. J Health Soc Behav. 1983;24:385–96.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6668417</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>American College of Sports Medicine. ACSM’s guidelines for exercise testing and prescription. Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins. 2013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23851406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>LeBlanc AG, Gunnell KE, Prince SA, Saunders TJ, Barnes JD, Chaput JP. The ubiquity of the screen: an overview of the risks and benefits of screen time in our modern world. Transl J Am Coll Sports Med. 2017;2:104–13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grontved A, Ried-Larsen M, Moller NC, et al. . Youth screen-time behaviour is associated with cardiovascular risk in young adulthood: the European Youth Heart Study. Eur J Prev Cardiol. 2014;21:49–56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22767966</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vella CA, Taylor K, Nelson MC. Associations of leisure screen time with cardiometabolic biomarkers in college-aged adults. J Behav Med. 2020;43:1014–25.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7677220</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32451650</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamer M, Stamatakis E, Mishra GD. Television-and screen-based activity and mental well-being in adults. Am J Prev Med. 2010;38:375–80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20307805</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suni E. Insomnia.
2020. https://www.sleepfoundation.org/insomnia. Accessed September 15, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shumack DC, Ogilvie JM, Smallbone S, Woodford EL. Chapter 17 - Increasing Self-Control. In: Bromberg DS, O’Donohue WT, eds. Toolkit for Working with Juvenile Sex Offenders. Academic Press. 2014:427–47.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balanzá-Martínez V, Kapczinski F, de Azevedo Cardoso T, et al. . The assessment of lifestyle changes during the COVID-19 pandemic using a multidimensional scale. Rev Psiquiatr Salud Ment. 2021;14:16–26.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7456305</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38620670</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goldstein C, Xie S, Hawkins M, Hughes J. Reducing risk for cardiovascular disease: negative health behaviors in college students. Emerging Adulthood. 2015;3:24–36.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bertrand L, Shaw KA, Ko J, Deprez D, Chilibeck PD, Zello GA. The impact of the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic on university students’ dietary intake, physical activity, and sedentary behaviour. Appl Physiol Nutr Metab. 2021;46:265–72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33449864</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almandoz JP, Xie L, Schellinger JN, et al. . Impact of COVID-19 stay-at-home orders on weight-related behaviours among patients with obesity. Clin Obes. 2020;10:e12386.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7300461</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32515555</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marchitelli S, Mazza C, Lenzi A, Ricci E, Gnessi L, Roma P. Weight gain in a sample of patients affected by overweight/obesity with and without a psychiatric diagnosis during the Covid-19 lockdown. Nutrients. 2020;12:3525.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7697678</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33207742</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mattioli AV, Sciomer S, Cocchi C, Maffei S, Gallina S. Quarantine during COVID-19 outbreak: changes in diet and physical activity increase the risk of cardiovascular disease. Nutr Metab Cardiovasc Dis. 2020;30:1409–17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7260516</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32571612</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olfert MD, Barr ML, Charlier CM, et al. . Self-reported vs. measured height, weight, and BMI in young adults. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2018;15:2216.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6210375</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30314261</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pellegrini M, Ponzo V, Rosato R, et al. . Changes in weight and nutritional habits in adults with obesity during the “lockdown” period caused by the COVID-19 virus emergency. Nutrients. 2020;12:2016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7400808</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32645970</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drywień ME, Hamulka J, Zielinska-Pukos MA, Jeruszka-Bielak M, Górnicka M. The COVID-19 pandemic lockdowns and changes in body weight among polish women. A cross-sectional online survey PLifeCOVID-19 study. Sustainability. 2020;12:7768.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao M, Piernas C, Astbury NM, et al. . Associations between body-mass index and COVID-19 severity in 6· 9 million people in England: a prospective, community-based, cohort study. Lancet Diabetes Endocrinol. 2021;9:350–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8081400</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33932335</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumari A, Ranjan P, Vikram NK, et al. . A short questionnaire to assess changes in lifestyle-related behaviour during COVID 19 pandemic. Diabetes Metab Syndr. 2020;14:1697–701.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7448879</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32911201</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ingram J, Maciejewski G, Hand CJ. Changes in diet, sleep, and physical activity are associated with differences in negative mood during COVID-19 lockdown. Front Psychol. 2020;11:2328.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7492645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32982903</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Górnicka M, Drywień ME, Zielinska MA, Hamułka J. Dietary and lifestyle changes during COVID-19 and the subsequent lockdowns among Polish adults: a cross-sectional online survey PLifeCOVID-19 study. Nutrients. 2020;12:2324.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7468840</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32756458</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khasawneh AI, Humeidan AA, Alsulaiman JW, et al. . Medical students and COVID-19: knowledge, attitudes, and precautionary measures. A descriptive study from Jordan. Front Public Health. 2020;8:253.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7274076</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32574313</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>López-Bueno R, Calatayud J, Casaña J, et al. . COVID-19 confinement and health risk behaviors in Spain. Front Psychol. 2020;11:1426.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7287152</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32581985</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Werneck AO, Silva DR, Malta DC, et al. . Associations of sedentary behaviours and incidence of unhealthy diet during the COVID-19 quarantine in Brazil. Public Health Nutr. 2021;24:422–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7684180</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33087204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rolland B, Haesebaert F, Zante E, Benyamina A, Haesebaert J, Franck N. Global changes and factors of increase in caloric/salty food intake, screen use, and substance use during the early COVID-19 containment phase in the general population in France: survey study. JMIR Public Health Surveill. 2020;6:e19630.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7505683</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32589149</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Romero-Blanco C, Rodríguez-Almagro J, Onieva-Zafra MD, Parra-Fernández ML, Prado-Laguna MDC, Hernández-Martínez A. Physical activity and sedentary lifestyle in university students: changes during confinement due to the Covid-19 pandemic. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020;17:6567.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7558021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32916972</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sokolovsky AW, Hertel AW, Micalizzi L, White HR, Hayes KL, Jackson KM. Preliminary impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on smoking and vaping in college students. Addict Behav. 2021;115:106783.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7834470</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33360444</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moriarty T, Bourbeau K, Fontana F, McNamara S, Pereira da Silva M. The relationship between psychological stress and healthy lifestyle behaviors during COVID-19 among students in a US midwest university. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18:4752.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8125243</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33946873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Majumdar P, Biswas A, Sahu S. COVID-19 pandemic and lockdown: cause of sleep disruption, depression, somatic pain, and increased screen exposure of office workers and students of India. Chronobiol Int. 2020;37:1191–200.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32660352</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ammar N, Aly NM, Folayan MO, et al. . Behavior change due to COVID-19 among dental academics—the theory of planned behavior: stresses, worries, training, and pandemic severity. PLoS One. 2020;15:e0239961.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7523990</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32991611</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheroun D, Wankhar D, Devrani A, Lissamma PV, Chatterjee K. A study to assess the perceived stress and coping strategies among B. Sc. nursing students of selected colleges in Pune during COVID-19 pandemic lockdown’. Int J Sci Healthc Res. 2020;5:280–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Promoting mental health: concepts, emerging evidence, practice: summary report/a report from the World Health Organization, Department of Mental Health and Substance Abuse in collaboration with the Victorian Health Promotion Foundation (VicHealth) and the University of Melbourne. 2004. https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/42940. Accessed September 10, 2024.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>