<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39464921</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2249-4863</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of family medicine and primary care</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Family Med Prim Care</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Utilization of telemedicine services of institute of national importance in the western region of INDIA: A mixed-method study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>3782</StartPage><EndPage>3787</EndPage><MedlinePgn>3782-3787</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4103/jfmpc.jfmpc_56_24</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Telemedicine has emerged as a crucial healthcare tool, especially during the COVID-19 pandemic, offering risk-free contactless communication between physicians and patients. In India, the introduction of official guidelines in 2019 and initiatives like the "e-Sanjeevani" national teleconsultation portal have accelerated telemedicine's adoption. However, the utilization and satisfaction levels of telemedicine services in Institutes of National Importance (INI) remain underexplored.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This mixed-method study aims to describe the utilization of telemedicine services at the All India Institute of Medical Sciences (AIIMS), Rajkot, an INI in western India, and assess patients' satisfaction with these services.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Data was collected from patients availing telemedicine services through the e-Sanjeevani portal at AIIMS Rajkot between February and December 2022. Quantitative analysis included patient demographics, specialty attended, location, call duration, and wrong call rates. Qualitative analysis involved interviews with patients to assess their experiences and satisfaction levels. Statistical analyses were performed using SPSS for quantitative data and Atlas Ti for qualitative data.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A total of 12,442 doctor-to-doctor and 7,876 patient-to-doctor consultations were recorded, with a diverse age distribution (21-40 years, 45.4%). Most patients were from medical specialties, with general medicine, Pulmonary Medicine, and Dermatology being the highest. The data revealed a wide geographic distribution, with over 70% of cases from more than 200 kilometers away. Despite some challenges, including a 38.2% wrong call rate, the telemedicine services were well-received, with 96% of respondents reporting overall satisfaction.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Telemedicine services at AIIMS Rajkot have shown high user satisfaction and accessibility, highlighting their potential in improving healthcare delivery and access, particularly in remote areas. However, efforts to enhance digital literacy and address challenges are necessary for further optimization of telemedicine services.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: © 2024 Journal of Family Medicine and Primary Care.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Joshi</LastName><ForeName>Krupal</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community and Family Medicine, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Rajkot, Gujarat, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Modi</LastName><ForeName>Bhautik</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community and Family Medicine, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Rajkot, Gujarat, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Katoch</LastName><ForeName>Cds</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pulmonary Medicine, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Rajkot, Gujarat, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>India</Country><MedlineTA>J Family Med Prim Care</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101610082</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2249-4863</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Healthcare</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">online consultation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">telemedicine</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>There are no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39464921</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11504795</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/jfmpc.jfmpc_56_24</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">JFMPC-13-3782</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>National TeleConsultation Service, Ministry of Health and Family Welfare. eSanjeevaniOPD. 2020.  [[Retrieved 2021 May 29]].  Available from: https://esanjeevaniopd.in/Home .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Press Information Bureau, Government of India. The government of India's telemedicine service completes 3 million consultations. Ministry of Health and Family Welfare. 2021.  [Retrieved 2021 May 29].  Available from: https://www.pib.gov.in/PressReleseDetailm.aspx?PRID=1705358 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryu S. Telemedicine: Opportunities and developments in member states: Report on the Second Global Survey on eHealth 2009 (Global Observatory for e-Health Series, Volume 2) Healthc Inform Res. 2012;18:153–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chellaiyan VG, Nirupama AY, Taneja N. Telemedicine in India: Where do we stand? J Family Med Prim Care. 2019;8:1872–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6618173</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31334148</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ateriya N, Saraf A, Meshram VP, Setia P. Telemedicine and virtual consultation: The Indian perspective. Natl Med J India. 2018;31:215–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31134926</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Telehealth Parity Laws. Health Affairs.  [[Last access on 2023 Dec 16]].  Available from: https://www.healthaffairs.org/do/10.1377/hpb20160815.244795 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kichloo A, Albosta M, Dettloff K, Wani F, El-Amir Z, Singh J, et al. Telemedicine, the current COVID-19 pandemic and the future: A narrative review and perspectives moving forward in the USA. Fam Med Community Health. 2020;8:e000530.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7437610</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32816942</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levine SR, Gorman M. “Telestroke”: The application of telemedicine for stroke. Stroke. 1999;30:464–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9933289</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramaswamy A, Yu M, Drangsholt S, Ng E, Culligan PJ, Schlegel PN, et al. Patient satisfaction with telemedicine during the COVID-19 pandemic: Retrospective cohort study. J Med Internet Res. 2020;22:e20786.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7511224</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32810841</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gabrielsson-Järhult F, Kjellström S, Josefsson KA. Telemedicine consultations with physicians in Swedish primary care: A mixed methods study of users' experiences and care patterns. Scand J Prim Health Care. 2021;39:204–13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8293950</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33974502</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cormi C, Chrusciel J, Fayol A, Van Rechem M, Abou-Amsha K, Tixier M, et al. The use of telemedicine in nursing homes: A mixed-method study to identify critical factors when connecting with a general hospital. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18:11148.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8583601</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34769665</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baxter R, Jemberie WB, Li X, Naseer M, Paulsen M, Shebehe J, et al. COVID-19: Opportunities for interdisciplinary research to improve care for older people in Sweden. Scand J Public Health. 2021;49:29–32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7859561</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33161880</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nymberg VM, Bolmsjö BB, Wolff M, Calling S, Gerward S, Sandberg M. 'Having to learn this so late in our lives… ‘Swedish elderly patients’ beliefs, experiences, attitudes, and expectations of e-health in primary health care. Scand J Prim Health Care. 2019;37:41–52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6452815</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30732519</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dorsey ER, Topol EJ. State of telehealth. N Engl J Med. 2016;375:154–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27410924</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ekman B, Thulesius H, Wilkens J, Lindgren A, Cronberg O, Arvidsson E. Utilization of digital primary care in Sweden: Descriptive analysis of claims data on demographics, socioeconomics, and diagnoses. Int J Med Inform. 2019;127:134–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31128825</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anell A. Choice and privatization in Swedish primary care. Health Econ Policy Law. 2011;6:549–69.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20701829</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumlin M, Berg GV, Kvigne K, Hellesø R. Elderly patients with complex health problems in the care trajectory: A qualitative case study. BMC Health Serv Res. 2020;20:595.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7325247</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32600322</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Granja C, Janssen W, Johansen MA. Factors determining the success and failure of eHealth interventions: Systematic review of the literature. J Med Internet Res. 2018;20:e10235.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5954232</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29716883</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ray KN, Chari AV, Engberg J, Bertolet M, Mehrotra A. Disparities in time spent seeking medical care in the United States. JAMA Intern Med. 2015;175:1983–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5055855</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26437386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>