<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39464916</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2249-4863</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>13</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of family medicine and primary care</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Family Med Prim Care</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Preventability and manageability of adverse drug reactions in COVID-19 with mucormycosis: An observational study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>3672</StartPage><EndPage>3678</EndPage><MedlinePgn>3672-3678</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4103/jfmpc.jfmpc_1691_23</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">In the intricate landscape of healthcare amid the COVID-19 pandemic, the emergence of mucormycosis as a severe complication posed a significant challenge to primary healthcare. This study delved into the complexities of adverse drug reactions (ADRs) in COVID-19 patients with mucormycosis undergoing treatment with conventional amphotericin B.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Ethically approved and meticulously conducted, the study scrutinized 154 ADRs in depth, shedding light on their classification, outcomes, and interventions in COVID patients with mucormycosis. A descriptive analysis was carried out to report the findings of this study.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The findings revealed that a substantial proportion (85.6%) of these ADRs were manageable, emphasizing the need for vigilant monitoring and timely interventions. Notably, gender disparities surfaced, indicating potential gender-specific responses to amphotericin B. Causality assessments based on the WHO-UMC scale classified the majority of ADRs as certain, providing a robust foundation for understanding the intricate relationships between amphotericin B and the observed adverse events.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This research not only categorizes ADRs as preventable and manageable but also offers practical insights into their nature and the diverse strategies employed for their management. The study's outcomes underline the importance of personalized healthcare approaches that can be adopted by primary care physicians for effective patient care.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: © 2024 Journal of Family Medicine and Primary Care.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Dhingra</LastName><ForeName>Sajal</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Veer Madho Singh Bhandari, Uttarakhand Technical University, Dehradun, Uttarakhand, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacology, Regional Adverse Drug Reaction Monitoring Center, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Rishikesh, Uttarakhand, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Hanjong</LastName><ForeName>Raj</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Veer Madho Singh Bhandari, Uttarakhand Technical University, Dehradun, Uttarakhand, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacology, Regional Adverse Drug Reaction Monitoring Center, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Rishikesh, Uttarakhand, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bisht</LastName><ForeName>Khushboo</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacology, Regional Adverse Drug Reaction Monitoring Center, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Rishikesh, Uttarakhand, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dhamija</LastName><ForeName>Puneet</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacology, Regional Adverse Drug Reaction Monitoring Center, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Rishikesh, Uttarakhand, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dhar</LastName><ForeName>Minakshi</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Rishikesh, Uttarakhand, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>India</Country><MedlineTA>J Family Med Prim Care</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101610082</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2249-4863</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Adverse drug reactions</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mucormycosis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">preventability</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>There are no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39464916</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11504753</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/jfmpc.jfmpc_1691_23</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">JFMPC-13-3672</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Dangi N, Mehendiratta H, Sharma S. Mucormycosis: A serious catastrophe involving COVID-19 patients. Coronaviruses. 2023;4 doi: 10.2174/2666796704666230801092541.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zakaria OM, Alkuwaity DW. View of mucormycosis during the era of COVID-19 infection: A cross-sectional study. J Family Med Prim Care. 2023;12:2608.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10771181</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38186843</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andreescu M, Moldovan C, Lespezeanu DA, Mocanu AI, Schipor MA, Mocanu H. COVID-19-associated rhinocerebral mucormycosis, an incidental finding or a matter of concern – mixed-method systematic review. Infect Drug Resist. 2024;17:387–402.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10838509</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38312523</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahesh S, Srivastava S, Sakshi, Tripathi R. The impact of SARS-CoV-2 on the sudden onset of mucormycosis in the Indian subcontinent-A review. J Family Med Prim Care. 2022;11:4246.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9638668</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36352915</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jose D, Nair KS, Alagesan M, Pappachan JM. The safety and effectiveness of antifungal medications in the management of mucormycosis during the COVID-19 pandemic. Curr Drug Saf. 2023;19:3–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37031384</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shimoda C, Yanagishima N, Sakurai A, Tamura S. Mating reaction in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. IX. Regulation of sexual cell agglutinability of a type cells by a sex factor produced by alpha type cells. Arch Microbiol. 1976;108:27–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">776112</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeong W, Keighley C, Wolfe R, Lee WL, Slavin MA, Kong DCM, et al. The epidemiology and clinical manifestations of mucormycosis: A systematic review and meta-analysis of case reports. Clin Microbiol Infect. 2019;25:26–34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30036666</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deb T, Garg R, Kaur M, Beniwal A, Gupta V. ADR profile of the covishield vaccine among healthcare workers in a tertiary care teaching hospital in India. Curr Drug Saf. 2022;17:344–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35049437</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robinson EG, Hedna K, Hakkarainen KM, Gyllensten H. Healthcare costs of adverse drug reactions and potentially inappropriate prescribing in older adults: A population-based study. BMJ Open. 2022;12:e062589.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9511550</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36153031</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahadevappa M, Meher C, Pushpa N, Kulkarni P, Poornima K, Desai N. Study of pattern &amp; distribution of adverse drug reactions in acute coronary syndrome patients in a tertiary care hospital. Indian J Med Res. 2022;156:111–21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9903395</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36510903</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma S, Swamy S, Bhambhani A, Nadig P. Adverse drug reactions attributed to fondaparinux and unfractionated heparin in cardiovascular care unit: An observational prospective pilot study in a tertiary care Hospital. J Pharm Bioallied Sci. 2018;10:90–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5998699</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29962798</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shukla A, Jhaj R, Misra S, Ahmed S, Nanda M, Chaudhary D. Agreement between WHO-UMC causality scale and the Naranjo algorithm for causality assessment of adverse drug reactions. J Family Med Prim Care. 2021;10:3303.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8565125</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34760748</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaikh S, Raut A, Jambhale P, Iyer S, Shah J. Incidence and severity of adverse drug reactions in medical intensive care unit. Curr Drug Saf. 2023 doi: 10.2174/1574886318666230816090606.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37587829</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chatterjee S, Bhattacharjee M, Hazra A, Mukhopadhyay P, Ray B, Chatterjee S, et al. Pharmacovigilance study of amphotericin B for mucormycosis in post-COVID and non-COVID patients at a tertiary care hospital in Eastern India. Indian J Pharmacol. 2022;54:417–22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10043824</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36722553</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balushi A Al, Ajmi A Al, Sinani Q Al, Menon V, Berieki Z Al, Shezawi A Al, et al. COVID-19-associated mucormycosis: An opportunistic fungal infection. A case series and review. Int J Infect Dis. 2022;121:203.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9075983</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35533833</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sachdeva K, Saji TA. Adverse drug reaction of antifungals in the management of black fungus: A tertiary care centre experience. Indian J Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg. 2022;74((Suppl 2)):3111–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8409694</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34490072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar R, Misra AK, Dutta S, Gupta A, Kumar B, Charan J. A systematic review of mucormycosis cases in COVID-19: Is it an unholy trilogy of COVID-19, diabetes mellitus, and corticosteroids? J Family Med Prim Care. 2022;11:2573.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9480822</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36119210</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prakash H, Ghosh AK, Rudramurthy SM, Singh P, Xess I, Savio J, et al. A prospective multicenter study on mucormycosis in India: Epidemiology, diagnosis, and treatment. Med Mycol. 2019;57:395–402.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30085158</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garbino J, Markham L, Matulionyte R, Rives V, Lew D. Should we continue using amphotericin B deoxycholate for the treatment of fungal infections? Adverse events and clinical outcomes. Scand J Infect Dis. 2006;38:110–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16449001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamill RJ, Sobel JD, El-Sadr W, Johnson PC, Graybill JR, Javaly K, et al. Comparison of 2 doses of liposomal amphotericin b and conventional amphotericin B deoxycholate for treatment of AIDS-associated acute cryptococcal meningitis: A randomized, double-blind clinical trial of efficacy and safety. Clin Infect Dis. 2010;51:225–32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20536366</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferner RE, Aronson JK, Heneghan C. Crisis in the supply of medicines. BMJ. 2019;367:l5841.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31585945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aronson JK, Heneghan C, Ferner RE. Drug shortages. Part 1. Definitions and harms. Br J Clin Pharmacol. 2023;89:2950–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37455356</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Urbańczyk K, Guntschnig S, Antoniadis V, Falamic S, Kovacevic T, Kurczewska-Michalak M, et al. Recommendations for wider adoption of clinical pharmacy in Central and Eastern Europe in order to optimise pharmacotherapy and improve patient outcomes. Front Pharmacol. 2023;14:1244151.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10433912</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37601045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>