<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39460642</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1469-8749</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>26</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Developmental medicine and child neurology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Dev Med Child Neurol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Policy and practice recommendations for services for disabled children during emergencies: Learning from COVID-19.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/dmcn.16126</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="AIM" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To seek consensus on recommendations for the delivery of services to disabled children in England during future emergencies.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHOD" NlmCategory="METHODS">Candidate recommendations were drafted based on our related mapping review and qualitative research related to experiences during the COVID-19 pandemic. Iterative workshops with professionals and parent carers helped to refine the recommendations. A Delphi survey, rating the importance of each recommendation, was conducted with (1) parent carers of disabled children, (2) disabled young people aged 8 to 19 years, and (3) health, education, and social care professionals. A consensus meeting was convened online to discuss the findings and ratify the recommendations.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Twenty-eight recommendations were included in the Delphi survey. There were 141 participants in round 1 and 91 in round 2. Seven recommendations reached the agreed consensus criteria for being critical across all stakeholder groups, while 21 recommendations did not reach consensus across all groups. Fourteen participants ratified 23 recommendations, which when aggregated and refined further produced our final 19 recommendations.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="INTERPRETATION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Reductions in services for disabled children and their families during the COVID-19 pandemic had serious and lasting consequences. This study enabled parent carers, disabled young people, and health, education, and social care professionals to agree recommendations on services for disabled children during future emergencies.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Developmental Medicine &amp; Child Neurology published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Mac Keith Press.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Merrick</LastName><ForeName>Hannah</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2714-0129</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Population Health Sciences Institute, Newcastle University, Newcastle upon Tyne, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Morris</LastName><ForeName>Christopher</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9916-507X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Peninsula Childhood Disability Research Unit, University of Exeter Medical School, University of Exeter, Exeter, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Allard</LastName><ForeName>Amanda</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Children's Bureau, London, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Council for Disabled Children, London, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Parr</LastName><ForeName>Jeremy R</ForeName><Initials>JR</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2507-7878</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Population Health Sciences Institute, Newcastle University, Newcastle upon Tyne, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cumbria, Northumberland, Tyne and Wear NHS Foundation Trust, Newcastle upon Tyne, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Great North Children's Hospital, Newcastle upon Tyne Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust, Newcastle upon Tyne, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pennington</LastName><ForeName>Lindsay</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4540-2586</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Population Health Sciences Institute, Newcastle University, Newcastle upon Tyne, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Great North Children's Hospital, Newcastle upon Tyne Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust, Newcastle upon Tyne, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><CollectiveName>Resetting Services to Disabled Children team</CollectiveName></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>NIHR202478</GrantID><Agency>National Institute for Health and Care Research</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Dev Med Child Neurol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0006761</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0012-1622</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><InvestigatorList><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bola</LastName><ForeName>Kulwinder</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Carr</LastName><ForeName>Sara</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gray</LastName><ForeName>Laura</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Haining</LastName><ForeName>Shona</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Platts</LastName><ForeName>Lesley</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Heslop</LastName><ForeName>Philip</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Grahame</LastName><ForeName>Vicki</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Teare</LastName><ForeName>Dawn</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yu</LastName><ForeName>Ge</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials></Investigator></InvestigatorList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39460642</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/dmcn.16126</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Department for Work and Pensions. Family Resources Survey: financial year 2021 to 2022. London: Department for Work and Pensions; 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Department for Education and Department for Health. Special educational needs and disability code of practice: 0 to 25years. In: Health DfEaDf, editor. 2015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Merrick H, Driver H, Main C, Kenny RP, Richmond C, Allard A, et al. Impacts of health care service changes implemented due to COVID‐19 on children and young people with long‐term disability: a mapping review. Developmental Medicine &amp; Child Neurology. 2023;65(7):885–99.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Department for Education. Special Educational Needs and Disabilities (SEND) and Alternative Provision (AP) Improvement Plan: Right Support, Right Place, Right Time. In: Education Df, editor. 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Swann OV, Holden KA, Turtle L, Pollock L, Fairfield CJ, Drake TM, et al. Clinical characteristics of children and young people admitted to hospital with covid‐19 in United Kingdom: prospective multicentre observational cohort study. BMJ 2020;370.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Asbury K, Fox L, Deniz E, Code A, Toseeb U. How is COVID‐19 affecting the mental health of children with special educational needs and disabilities and their families? Journal of autism and developmental disorders. 2021;51(5):1772–80.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Disabled Children's Partnership. Failed and Forgotten. Disabled Children's Partnership 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Royal College of Paediatrics and Child Health. Reser, Restore, Recover ‐ RCPCH principles for recovery. London; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Merrick H, Driver H, Main C, Potts L, Russell S, Exley C, et al. Professional perspectives on facilitators and barriers for high quality provision of health, education and social care services to disabled children in England during the COVID‐19 pandemic: a qualitative study. BMJ Open. 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Council for Disabled Children. CDC's National Virtual Event. London: Council for Disabled Children; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Merrick H, Driver H, Potts L, Exley C, Allard A, Morris C, et al. Parent carer and disabled young people's perspectives on the impacts of changes to service provision for children and young people in England during the COVID‐19 pandemic: a qualitative study. BMJ Openunder review.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>NHS England. Emergency Preparedness, Resilience and Response (EPRR). Available from: https://www.england.nhs.uk/ourwork/eprr/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organisation. Health emergencies: World Health Organization. Available from: https://www.who.int/our‐work/health‐emergencies</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Staniszewska S, Brett J, Simera I, Seers K, Mockford C, Goodlad S, et al. GRIPP2 reporting checklists: tools to improve reporting of patient and public involvement in research. BMJ. 2017;358:j3453.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ritchie J, Spencer L, Bryman A, Burgess RG. Analysing qualitative data. Routledge, London; 1994.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williamson PR, Altman DG, Bagley H, Barnes KL, Blazeby JM, Brookes ST, et al. The COMET Handbook: version 1.0. Trials. 2017;18(3):280.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crew R, Williamson P, D. A. DelphiManager brochure. 2015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taggart L, Mulhall P, Kelly R, Trip H, Sullivan B, Wallén EF. Preventing, mitigating, and managing future pandemics for people with an intellectual and developmental disability‐Learnings from COVID‐19: A scoping review. Journal of Policy and Practice in Intellectual Disabilities. 2022;19(1):4–34.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kavanagh A, Dickinson H, Carey G, Llewellyn G, Emerson E, Disney G, et al. Improving health care for disabled people in COVID‐19 and beyond: lessons from Australia and England. Disability and health journal. 2021;14(2):101050.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuper H, Banks LM, Bright T, Davey C, Shakespeare T. Disability‐inclusive COVID‐19 response: What it is, why it is important and what we can learn from the United Kingdom's response. Wellcome open research. 2020;5:79.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Disabled Children's Partnership. Then there was silence: The impact of the pandemic on disabled children, young people and their families; 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kirkby J, Ashworth E, Bray L, Alghrani A. A Rapid Scoping Review‐The Impact of the COVID‐19 Pandemic on the Education, Health and Social Care Provision for Children with Special Educational Needs and Disabilities (SEND). 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anderson M, Pitchforth E, Asaria M, Brayne C, Casadei B, Charlesworth A, et al. LSE–Lancet Commission on the future of the NHS: re‐laying the foundations for an equitable and efficient health and care service after COVID‐19. The Lancet. 2021;397(10288):1915–78.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Connon ILC, Crampton A, Dyer C, Hu RX. Social Disability as Disaster: Case Studies of the COVID‐19 Pandemic on People Living with Disabilities. Social Sciences. 2024;13(4):203.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shikako K, Lencucha R, Hunt M, Jodoin S, Elsabbagh M, Hudon A, et al. How Did Governments Address the Needs of People With Disabilities During the COVID‐19 Pandemic? An Analysis of 14 Countries' Policies Based on the UN Convention on the Rights of Persons With Disabilities. Int J Health Policy Manag. 2023;12:7111.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blackburn CM, Spencer NJ, Read JM. Prevalence of childhood disability and the characteristics and circumstances of disabled children in the UK: secondary analysis of the Family Resources Survey. BMC pediatrics. 2010;10:1–12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lach LM, Kohen DE, Garner RE, Brehaut JC, Miller AR, Klassen AF, et al. The health and psychosocial functioning of caregivers of children with neurodevelopmental disorders. Disability and rehabilitation. 2009;31(9):741–52.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pearson A. Who cares about the carers? A call to action on behalf of mothers of disabled children. Frontiers in Sociology. 2024;8.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>