<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39468427</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1525-1446</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>28</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Public health nursing (Boston, Mass.)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Public Health Nurs</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Factors Associated With Health-Promoting Behaviors Among South Korean Adults: A Cross-Sectional Study.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/phn.13474</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To examine the association between positive psychological capital, social support, illness attitudes toward COVID-19, and health-promoting behaviors in Korean adults.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DESIGN" NlmCategory="METHODS">An online cross-sectional study.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="SAMPLE" NlmCategory="METHODS">The participants were 820 South Korean adults aged 19-64, recruited through quota sampling. The sample was census-matched in terms of age and gender based on the Korean Population Census.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MEASUREMENTS" NlmCategory="METHODS">The participants completed measures assessing psychological capital, social support, illness attitude toward COVID-19, and health-promoting behaviors. The t-test, one-way analysis of variance, Pearson's correlation, and multiple stepwise regression analysis were used to analyze the data.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Participants who were religious, perceived themselves as physically healthy, had negative illness attitudes, had high positive psychological capital, and received high social support were more likely to engage in health-promoting behaviors. These variables explained 44.5% of the participants' health-promoting behaviors.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">This study is the first to examine illness attitudes toward COVID-19 and health-promoting behaviors among South Korean adults during the COVID-19 pandemic. The results can pave the way for effective public health intervention strategies that consider religiosity, physical health status, illness attitude, and social support, to promote healthy living during future public health crises.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kim</LastName><ForeName>Yoonjung</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1192-8248</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nursing, Red Cross College of Nursing, Chung-Ang University, Seoul, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chae</LastName><ForeName>Heemin</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8148-0373</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nursing, The Graduate School, Chung-Ang University, Seoul, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kwak</LastName><ForeName>Yeun Hee</ForeName><Initials>YH</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9884-0635</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nursing, Red Cross College of Nursing, Chung-Ang University, Seoul, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kim</LastName><ForeName>Ji-Su</ForeName><Initials>JS</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9512-1934</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nursing, Red Cross College of Nursing, Chung-Ang University, Seoul, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Public Health Nurs</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8501498</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0737-1209</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">adults</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">health‐promoting behavior</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">illness attitude</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nursing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">positive psychological capital</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">social support</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39468427</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/phn.13474</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>Ahmadboukani, S., D. Fathi, M. Karami, S. Bashirgonbadi, A. Mahmoudpour, and B. Molaei. 2022. “Providing a Health‐Promotion Behaviors Model in Elderly: Psychological Capital, Perceived Social Support, and Attitudes Toward Death With Mediating Role of Cognitive Emotion Regulation Strategies.” Health Science Reports 6, no. 1: e1020. https://doi.org/10.1002/hsr2.1020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al‐Sejari, M. M., and H. B. Al‐Ma'Seb. 2021. “Precautionary Measures and Illness Attitudes Toward COVID‐19 Among a Sample of the Kuwaiti Population.” Social Work in Public Health 36, no. 1: 1–11. https://doi.org/10.1080/19371918.2020.1835774.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anaki, D., and J. Sergay. 2021. “Predicting Health Behavior in Response to the Coronavirus Disease (COVID‐19): Worldwide Survey Results From Early March 2020.” PLoS ONE 16, no. 1: e0244534. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0244534.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashgar, R. I. 2021. “Health‐Promoting Behaviour During the COVID‐19 Pandemic Among Saudi Adults: A Cross‐Sectional Study.” Journal of Advanced Nursing 77, no. 8: 3389–3397. https://doi.org/10.1111/jan.14863.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cho, I. Y., S. H. Moon, and J. Y. Yun. 2021. “Mediating and Moderating Effects of Family Cohesion Between Positive Psychological Capital and Health Behavior Among Early Childhood Parents in Dual Working Families: A Focus on the COVID‐19 Pandemic.” International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 18, no. 9: 4781. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph18094781.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Counted, V., K. I. Pargament, A. O. Bechara, S. Joynt, and R. G. Cowden. 2022. “Hope and Well‐Being in Vulnerable Contexts During the COVID‐19 Pandemic: Does Religious Coping Matter?.” Journal of Positive Psychology 17, no. 1: 70–81. https://doi.org/10.1080/17439760.2020.1832247.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Escolà‐Gascón, Á., J. L. Micó-Sanz, and A. Casero‐Ripollés. 2022. “Global Evidence of Environmental and Lifestyle Effects on Medical Expenditures Across 154 Countries.” Preventive medicine reports 30: 102036. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pmedr.2022.102036.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fishbein, M., and I. Ajzen. 1977. Belief, Attitude, Intention, and Behavior: An Introduction to Theory and Research. Massachusetts: Addison‐Wesley.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fisher, B., and G. Chanan. 2015. “Social Action for Health Gain: The Potential of Community Development.” British Journal of General Practice 65, no. 631: 97–98. https://doi.org/10.3399/bjgp15X683641.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fisher, J. D., W. A. Fisher, K. R. Amico, and J. J. Harman. 2006. “An Information‐Motivation‐Behavioral Skills Model of Adherence to Antiretroviral Therapy.” Health Psychology 25, no. 4: 462–473. https://doi.org/10.1037/0278‐6133.25.4.462.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Groarke, J. M., E. Berry, L. Graham‐Wisener, P. E. McKenna‐Plumley, E. McGlinchey, and C. Armour. 2020. “Loneliness in the UK During the COVID‐19 Pandemic: Cross‐Sectional Results From the COVID‐19 Psychological Wellbeing Study.” PLoS ONE 15, no. 9: e0239698. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0239698.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hong, M., J. C. De Gagne, and H. Shin. 2018. “Social Networks, Health Promoting‐Behavior, and Health‐Related Quality of Life in Older Korean Adults.” Nursing and Health Sciences 20, no. 1: 79–88. https://doi.org/10.1111/nhs.12390.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hong, M., Y. Park, E. Y. Chen, J. W. Yun, and M. H. Oh. 2017. “Body Esteem, Stress, and Health Promoting Behavior Among Korean Adults in a Community.” Korean Journal of Rehabilitation Nursing 20, no. 1: 61–68. https://doi.org/10.7587/kjrehn.2017.61.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeong, Y. H., and M. S. Song. 2018. “Health Belief, Social Support, and Health‐Promoting Behaviors of Korean International Students Studying in the United States.” Journal of Korean Academic Society of Home Health Care Nursing 25, no. 1: 5–14. https://doi.org/10.22705/JKASHCN.2018.25.1.005.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jing, X., H. Meng, Y. Li, L. Lu, and Y. Yao. 2022. “Associations of Psychological Capital, Coping Style and Emotional Intelligence With Self‐Rated Health Status of College Students in China During COVID‐19 Pandemic.” Psychology Research and Behavior Management 15: 2587–2597. https://doi.org/10.2147/PRBM.S383743.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kellner, R. 1986. Somatization and Hypochondriasis. New York: Praeger Publishers.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, H. A. 2021. “The Effects of Illness Attitude on Quality of Life in the COVID‐19 Era.” Unpublished master's thesis, Hanyang University.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, J., M. Kwon, and S. Jung. 2017. “The Influence of Health Locus of Control, Social Support, and Self‐Efficacy on Health Promoting Behavior in Middle‐Aged Adults.” Journal of the Korea Academia‐Industrial Cooperation Society 18, no. 4: 494–503. https://doi.org/10.5762/KAIS.2017.18.4.494.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim, S. I. 2020. “A Study on the Transformation of Perception for Rethink the Efficiency of Social Distancing in the Prolonged COVID‐19 Pandemic.” Journal of Humanities and Social Sciences 21 11, no. 6: 1411–1424. https://doi.org/10.22143/HSS21.11.6.100.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korea Disease Control and Prevention Agency. 2020. Changes in Infectious Diseases, Health Behaviors, and Medical Uses During COVID‐19 Pandemic in the Republic of Korea. https://www.kdca.go.kr/board/board.es?mid=a20602010000&amp;bid=0034&amp;list_no=717047&amp;act=view.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee, S. G., and B. Kim. 2022. “Factors Affecting Nurses' Health Promotion Behavior During the COVID‐19 Pandemic Based on the Information–Motivation–Behavioral Skills Model.” Medicina 58, no. 6: 720. https://doi.org/10.3390/medicina58060720.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lim, T. H. 2014. “Validation of the Korean Version of Positive Psychological Capital (K‐PPC).” Journal of Coaching Development 16: 157–166.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luthans, F., B. J. Avolio, J. B. Avey, and S. M. Norman. 2007. “Positive Psychological Capital: Measurement and Relationship With Performance and Satisfaction.” Personnel Psychology 60, no. 3: 541–572. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1744‐6570.2007.00083.x.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luthans, F., C. M. Youssef‐Morgan, and B. Avolio. 2015. Psychological Capital and Beyond. New York: Oxford University Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Massar, K., N. Kopplin, and K. Schelleman‐Offermans. 2021. “Childhood Socioeconomic Position, Adult Educational Attainment and Health Behaviors: The Role of Psychological Capital and Health Literacy.” International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 18, no. 17: 9399. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph18179399.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Min, Y., and J. Young. 2018. “The Effect of Job Stress on Health Promotion Behaviors of Nurses in a Regional General Hospital: The Mediating Effects of Positive Psychological Capital and Nursing Work Environment.” Korean Journal of Occupational Health Nursing 27: 160–170. https://doi.org/10.5807/KJOHN.2018.27.3.160.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Health and Welfare, &amp; Korea Health Promotion Institute. 2021. Reduced Alcohol Consumption After COVID‐19, Increasing Again COVID‐19 Alcohol Use and Problems. https://www.khealth.or.kr/board/view?pageNum=1&amp;rowCnt=10&amp;no1=638&amp;linkId=1003102&amp;menuId=MENU00907&amp;schType=0&amp;schText=&amp;searchType=&amp;boardStyle=&amp;categoryId=&amp;continent=&amp;country=&amp;contents1=.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Health and Welfare, &amp; Korean Society of Traumatic Stress Studies. 2021. Announcement of the Results of the COVID‐19 National Mental Health Survey in the Second Quarter of 2021. http://www.mohw.go.kr/react/al/sal0301vw.jsp?PAR_MENU_ID=04&amp;MENU_ID=0403&amp;page=1&amp;;CONT_SEQ=366599.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Health and Welfare. 2021. South Korea Announces the Road Map for Gradual Return to Normal (10.29). https://www.mohw.go.kr/eng/nw/nw0101vw.jsp?PAR_MENU_ID=1007&amp;MENU_ID=100701&amp;page=8&amp;CONT_SEQ=368308.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murdaugh, C. L., M. A. Parsons, and N. J. Pender. 2018. Health Promotion in Nursing Practice (8th ed.). New York: Pearson.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orji, R., J. Vassileva, and R. Mandryk. 2012. “Towards an Effective Health Interventions Design: An Extension of the Health Belief Model.” Online Journal of Public Health Informatics 4, no. 3. https://doi.org/10.5210/ojphi.v4i3.4321.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paleari, F. G., M. Pivetti, D. Galati, and F. D. Fincham. 2021. “Hedonic and Eudaimonic Well‐Being During the COVID‐19 Lockdown in Italy: The Role of Stigma and Appraisals.” British Journal of Health Psychology 26, no. 2: 657–678. https://doi.org/10.1111/bjhp.12508.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park, J. W. 1985. “A Study to Develop a Scale of Social Support.” Unpublished doctoral diss., Yonsei University.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park, S., B. Kim, and K. A. Kim. 2021. “Preventive Behavioral Insights for Emerging Adults: A Survey During the COVID‐19 Pandemic.” International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 18, no. 5: 2569. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph18052569.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park, S., and Y. H. Lee. 2016. “Effects of Perceived Health Status, Health Attitude, and Health Concern on Health Promoting Behavior in Adults.” Journal of the Korea Contents Association 16, no. 12: 192–202. https://doi.org/10.5392/JKCA.2016.16.12.192.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park, S. H. 2019. “Knowledge, Attitude, and Preventive Behaviors Related to Middle East Respiratory Syndrome (MERS) in Adults.” Journal of Korean Public Health Nursing 33: 33–46. https://doi.org/10.5932/JKPHN.2019.33.1.33.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Puspitasari, I. M., L. Yusuf, R. K. Sinuraya, R. Abdulah, and H. Koyama. 2020. “Knowledge, Attitude, and Practice During the COVID‐19 Pandemic: A Review.” Journal of Multidisciplinary Healthcare 13: 727–733. https://doi.org/10.2147/JMDH.S265527.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quan, L. H., and M. H. Seo. 2018. “The Effects of Objective and Subjective Economic Status and Health‐Related Interpersonal Communication on Health‐Enhancing Behaviors.” Korean Journal of Communication and Information 91: 288–318. https://doi.org/10.46407/kjci.2018.10.91.288.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanaati, F., M. Geranmayeh, Z. B. Moghadam, A. Zareiyan, K. S. Gelehkolaee, and M. Mirghafourvand. 2021. “A Population‐Based Study of Health‐Promoting Behaviors and Their Predictors in Iranian Males, 2019.” Archives of Public Health 79: 1–7. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13690‐021‐00543‐1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seo, J. H., and H. K. Kim. 2021. “Factors Affecting the Health Promoting Behaviors of Office Male Workers During the COVID‐19 Pandemic: Using Pender's Health Promotion Model.” Journal of Korean Academic Society of Nursing Education 27, no. 4: 412–422. https://doi.org/10.5977/jkasne.2021.27.4.412.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Southwick, S. M., R. Satodiya, and R. H. Pietrzak. 2016. “Disaster Mental Health and Positive Psychology: An Afterward to the Special Issue.” Journal of Clinical Psychology 72, no. 12: 1364–1368. https://doi.org/10.1002/jclp.22418.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tjahjadi, B., N. Soewarno, W. Adibah Wan Ismail, N. Kustiningsih, and L. Nasihatun Nafidah. 2023. “Community Behavioral Change and Management of COVID‐19 Pandemic: Evidence From Indonesia.” Journal of King Saud University ‐ Science 35, no. 2: 102451. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jksus.2022.102451.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turliuc, M. N., and O. S. Candel. 2022. “The Relationship Between Psychological Capital and Mental Health During the COVID‐19 Pandemic: A Longitudinal Mediation Model.” Journal of Health Psychology 27, no. 8: 1913–1925. https://doi.org/10.1177/13591053211012771.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>United Nations. 2023. The Sustainable Development Goals Report Special Edition. https://unstats.un.org/sdgs/report/2023/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walker, S. N., K. R. Sechrist, and N. J. Pender. 1995. Health Promotion Model—Instruments to Measure Health Promoting Lifestyle: Health‐Promoting Lifestyle Profile [HPLP II] (Adult Version). https://deepblue.lib.umich.edu/handle/2027.42/85349.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, H., K. R. Paulson, S. A. Pease, et al. 2022. “Estimating Excess Mortality Due to the COVID‐19 Pandemic: A Systematic Analysis of COVID‐19‐Related Mortality, 2020–21.” Lancet 399, no. 10334: 1513–1536. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140‐6736(21)02796‐3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. 2020. COVID‐19 Public Health Emergency of International Concern (PHEIC) Global Research and Innovation Forum. https://www.who.int/publications/m/item/covid‐19‐public‐health‐emergency‐of‐international‐concern‐(pheic)‐global‐research‐and‐innovation‐forum.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. 2024. Achieving Well‐Being: A Global Framework for Integrating Well‐Being Into Public Health Utilizing a Health Promotion Approach. https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240084858.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yi, I. H. 2004. “Factor Structure of the Illness Attitudes Scale (IAS) in a Korean College Sample.” Korean Journal of Health Psychology 9: 203–218.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu, E. K., and H. S. Seol. 2015. “Factorial Structure of the Social Support Scale.” Survey Research 16: 155–184.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yun, S. N., and J. H. Kim. 1999. “Health‐Promoting Behaviors of the Women Workers at the Manufacturing Industry‐Based on the Pender's Health Promotion Model.” Korean Journal of Occupational Health Nursing 8: 130–140.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>