<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39463611</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A Fragile Balance: Managing Femoral Neck Fracture, Transient Osteoporosis, and COVID-19 in Late Pregnancy.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70326</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70326</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e70326</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.70326</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Transient osteoporosis of the hip (TOH) during pregnancy is a rare, self-limiting condition that frequently goes undiagnosed. However, if not managed properly, TOH can lead to significant complications, such as pathological fractures. We report a case of a 29-year-old primigravida at 33 weeks and four days of gestation who presented with a right femoral neck fracture following a fall. She had experienced prodromal hip pain for one month, initially misdiagnosed as pelvic girdle pain. Radiological evaluation revealed osteopenia and a sub-capital femoral neck fracture. Blood investigations were unremarkable. During hospitalisation, the patient was also diagnosed with asymptomatic COVID-19 infection, complicating the management approach. A multidisciplinary team decided on an elective caesarean section followed by closed manipulative reduction (CMR) and percutaneous screw fixation. Therefore, TOH in pregnancy requires timely diagnosis and intervention to prevent complications such as fractures. In cases complicated by concurrent conditions like COVID-19, multidisciplinary management is essential to ensure optimal outcomes for both mother and child.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Tan et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tan</LastName><ForeName>Weng Liang</ForeName><Initials>WL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Orthopaedics and Traumatology, Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia, Kuala Lumpur, MYS.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hayyun</LastName><ForeName>Muhammad Fathi</ForeName><Initials>MF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Orthopaedics and Traumatology, Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia, Kuala Lumpur, MYS.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Leong</LastName><ForeName>Juzaily F</ForeName><Initials>JF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Orthopaedics and Traumatology, Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia, Kuala Lumpur, MYS.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abdul Rani</LastName><ForeName>Rizal</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Orthopaedics and Traumatology, Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia, Kuala Lumpur, MYS.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mohamad Yahaya</LastName><ForeName>Nor Hamdan</ForeName><Initials>NH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Orthopaedics and Traumatology, Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia, Kuala Lumpur, MYS.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D002363">Case Reports</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">covid-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">covid-19 and pregnancy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">fracture femoral neck</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">percutaneous screw fixation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">transient osteoporosis of the hip (toh)</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39463611</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11512794</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.70326</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Transitory demineralization of the hip in pregnancy. A report of three cases. Curtiss PH Jr, Kincaid WE. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/13849487/ J Bone Joint Surg Am. 1959;41-A:1327–1333.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">13849487</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Transient osteoporosis of the hip. A nontraumatic variety of Südeck's atrophy. Lequesne M. Ann Rheum Dis. 1968;27:463–471.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1031153</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4175667</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Transient hip osteoporosis: etiopathogenetic, clinical, and imaging approach. Maisi N, Patoulias D, Tsagkaris C, Tsagatakis M, Goules D. Mediterr J Rheumatol. 2022;33:196–200.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9450209</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36128206</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pregnancy associated transient osteoporosis of the hip (PR-TOH): a non-obstetric indication to caesarean section. A case report with literature review. Quaresima P, Angeletti M, Luziatelli D, Luziatelli S, Venturella R, Di Carlo C, Bernardo S. Eur J Obstet Gynecol Reprod Biol. 2021;262:28–35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33989941</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pregnancy-associated transient osteoporosis of the hip: results of a case-control study. Hadji P, Boekhoff J, Hahn M, Hellmeyer L, Hars O, Kyvernitakis I. Arch Osteoporos. 2017;12:11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28110481</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Distinguishing transient osteoporosis of the hip from avascular necrosis. Balakrishnan A, Schemitsch EH, Pearce D, McKee MD. https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3211740/#:~:text=Symptoms%20of%20TOH%20are%20sudden,of%20movement%2C%20especially%20internal%20rotation. Can J Surg. 2003;46:187–192.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3211740</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12812240</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guidelines for clinical diagnosis and treatment of osteonecrosis of the femoral head in adults (2019 version) Zhao D, Zhang F, Wang B, et al. J Orthop Translat. 2020;21:100–110.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7152793</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32309135</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guidelines for computed tomography and magnetic resonance imaging use during pregnancy and lactation. Chen MM, Coakley FV, Kaimal A, Laros RK Jr. Obstet Gynecol. 2008;112:333–340.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18669732</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ACR guidance document on MR safe practices: 2013. Kanal E, Barkovich AJ, Bell C, et al. J Magn Reson Imaging. 2013;37:501–530.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23345200</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>MR imaging of transient osteoporosis of the hip: an update on 155 hip joints. Klontzas ME, Vassalou EE, Zibis AH, Bintoudi AS, Karantanas AH. Eur J Radiol. 2015;84:431–436.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25533717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Transient osteoporosis of the hip, complete resolution after treatment with alendronate as observed by MRI description of eight cases and review of the literature. Emad Y, Ragab Y, El-Shaarawy N, Rasker JJ. Clin Rheumatol. 2012;31:1641–1647.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22933125</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The use of bisphosphonates in women prior to or during pregnancy and lactation. Stathopoulos IP, Liakou CG, Katsalira A, Trovas G, Lyritis GG, Papaioannou NA, Tournis S. Hormones (Athens) 2011;10:280–291.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22281884</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Avascular necrosis and nonunion after osteosynthesis of femoral neck fractures: effect of fracture displacement and time to surgery. Karaeminogullari O, Demirors H, Atabek M, Tuncay C, Tandogan R, Ozalay M. Adv Ther. 2004;21:335–342.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15727403</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Timing of internal fixation of femoral neck fractures. A systematic review and meta-analysis of the final outcome. Papakostidis C, Panagiotopoulos A, Piccioli A, Giannoudis PV. Injury. 2015;46:459–466.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25616675</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>