<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39467410</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1873-2518</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>42</Volume><Issue>26</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>27</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Vaccine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Vaccine</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Exploring the delivery of adult vaccination outside of primary care settings: A mixed methods scoping review.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>126458</StartPage><MedlinePgn>126458</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.vaccine.2024.126458</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0264-410X(24)01140-X</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">There are several identified barriers to immunisation delivery and uptake in adults, including governance issues, provider limitations, and patient access. While primary care settings have traditionally been responsible for vaccine delivery, there is a growing need to look to other settings to expand the equitable uptake of vaccinations in adults.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">This scoping review aims to identify and explore the role of non-primary care settings in delivering adult vaccinations, operational barriers and facilitators to immunisation delivery in these settings, and interventions delivered to improve uptake.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">This scoping review was conducted following the Joanna Briggs Institute (JBI) guidance for scoping reviews and the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses extension for Scoping Reviews (PRISMA-ScR). Peer-reviewed studies published from 01/01/2010 to 31/12/2022 that focused on the delivery of influenza, COVID-19, pneumococcal and herpes zoster vaccines in adult populations outside of primary care settings were included. Studies were also included if they explored barriers and facilitators to delivery, and interventions to improve uptake.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">75 studies were identified for inclusion. Most were quasi-experimental studies, and 58/75 were from the US. Studies were most frequently conducted in in-patient settings, outpatient clinics, nursing homes, and workplaces. Operational planning and logistics, and provider-level issues, such as poor documentation and workflow interruption were commonly identified barriers to delivery. Government funding, continuity of care, and patient convenience were frequently reported facilitators. Interventions shown to improve uptake were operational planning and clinical improvement systems (Plan-Do-Study-Act [PDSA] cycles), provider education and reminders, on-site vaccination, patient education, and financial incentives.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Mapping of the evidence indicates that adult immunisation delivery may be achievable across tertiary and secondary care settings, as well as non-clinical settings, such as workplaces. There are several identified barriers to delivery, predominantly at the provider-level in tertiary-care settings. Intervention such as operational planning, clinical reminders, and on-site vaccination, may facilitate uptake.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd.. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lentakis</LastName><ForeName>Eleftheria</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Population Health, Faculty of Medicine and Health, University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Seale</LastName><ForeName>Holly</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Population Health, Faculty of Medicine and Health, University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW, Australia. Electronic address: h.seale@unsw.edu.au.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lazarus</LastName><ForeName>Rajeka</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Severn Pathology, UK Health Security Agency, Bristol, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mounier-Jack</LastName><ForeName>Sandra</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, London, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Vaccine</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8406899</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0264-410X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Secondary care</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Tertiary care</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Vaccination</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Vaccines</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Workplace</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare the following financial interests/personal relationships which may be considered as potential competing interests: Holly Seale reports a relationship with University of New South Wales that includes: consulting or advisory and funding grants. Rajeka Lazarus reports a relationship with Severn Pathology that includes: board membership, consulting or advisory, and funding grants. Sandra Mounier-Jack reports a relationship with London School of Hygiene &amp; Tropical Medicine that includes: board membership, consulting or advisory, and funding grants. HS receives institutional funding from Moderna for investigator driven research focused on factors impacting COVID-19 vaccine uptake, payment from Sanofi Pasteur for contributing to a review of vaccine reactogenicity, and support from Moderna for attending a COVID-19 expert meeting. RL receives funding from GSK via an investigator initiated grant to investigate coadministration of the shingles vaccine with influenza and COVID-19 vaccines, funding from the National Institute of Health Research UK for policy grant: National Immunisation Schedule Consortium, payment from Astra Zeneca for conference presentation in non-promotional sessions, support for attending a conference from Astra Zeneca, is part of the Sanofi Pasteur advisory board, and University of Oxford Data Safety Monitoring Board for three phase one vaccine trials (nipah, plague, and non-typhoid salmonella), is vice president of the British Infection Association, and co-founder of the Clinical Vaccine Network UK. SMJ receives funding from the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation for zero dose strategies in fragile countries, the National Institute of Health Research UK for health protection research in immunisation, and UNITAID for the evaluation of IPTI, consulting fees from The Global Alliance on Vaccines and Immunisation as part of an independent review committee, is part of the GABI independent review committee, and currently seconded at UNICEF. If there are other authors, they declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39467410</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2024.126458</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0264-410X(24)01140-X</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>