<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39465193</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1937-8688</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>48</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Pan African medical journal</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Pan Afr Med J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Challenges and adaptations of mental health services during the COVID-19 Pandemic in Uganda.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>84</StartPage><MedlinePgn>84</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">84</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.11604/pamj.2024.48.84.43031</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) significantly impacted mental health and mental health services worldwide. We sought to explore the challenges faced by mental health services from the perspectives of service users, providers, and policymakers during the COVID-19 pandemic in Uganda and the strategies put in place to ensure the continuity of these services.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">qualitative data were collected using semi-structured interviews with eight mental health service users, four mental health workers, four hospital administrators, four district mental health focal persons, and two policymakers. The data were analyzed using thematic analysis.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">the challenges reported by participants included human resource shortages, loss of space for service provision, low funding, drug shortages, changes in patient load, and lack of access to services due to restrictive measures. The adaptations included the use of innovative means like mobile phone technology, reorientation of health facility functioning to COVID-19 restrictions, using different methods to deliver medications, integration of mental health in general health services, and alternative financing for mental health services.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">the COVID-19 pandemic posed significant challenges to mental health service provision. Nevertheless, the health system responded by implementing various measures to ensure continuity of care. Further research is needed to evaluate the effectiveness and scalability of these innovations in the long term.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: Anita Arinda et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Arinda</LastName><ForeName>Anita</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, College of Health Sciences, Makerere University Kampala, Uganda.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kalani</LastName><ForeName>Kenneth</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Ministry of Health, Kampala, Uganda.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mpamizo</LastName><ForeName>Emmanuel</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychiatry, Gulu University, Gulu, Uganda.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sebuliba</LastName><ForeName>Raymond</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Infectious Disease Institute, Makerere University, Kampala, Uganda.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Akinyange</LastName><ForeName>Vanessa</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Infectious Disease Institute, Makerere University, Kampala, Uganda.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lofgren</LastName><ForeName>Sarah</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases and International Medicine, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, Minnesota, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>02</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Uganda</Country><MedlineTA>Pan Afr Med J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101517926</NlmUniqueID></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014454" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Uganda</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008605" MajorTopicYN="Y">Mental Health Services</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000458" MajorTopicYN="N">organization &amp; administration</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006297" MajorTopicYN="Y">Health Services Accessibility</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007407" MajorTopicYN="N">Interviews as Topic</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003266" MajorTopicYN="N">Continuity of Patient Care</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000458" MajorTopicYN="N">organization &amp; administration</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006282" MajorTopicYN="N">Health Personnel</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000458" MajorTopicYN="N">organization &amp; administration</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008603" MajorTopicYN="N">Mental Health</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001523" MajorTopicYN="N">Mental Disorders</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000628" MajorTopicYN="N">therapy</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D036301" MajorTopicYN="N">Qualitative Research</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mental health services</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Uganda</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">continuity of patient care</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>29</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39465193</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11512146</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.11604/pamj.2024.48.84.43031</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">PAMJ-48-84</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (WHO) Novel Coronavirus (2019-nCoV) SITUATION REPORT-1: 21 JANUARY 2020. Accessed 26th March 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Musoke D, Nalinya S, Lubega GB, Deane K, Ekirapa-Kiracho E, McCoy D. The effects of COVID-19 lockdown measures on health and healthcare services in Uganda. PLOS Glob Public Health. 2023;3(1):e0001494.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10021763</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36963035</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashcroft R, Donnelly C, Dancey M, Gill S, Lam S, Kourgiantakis T, et al. Primary care teams´ experiences of delivering mental health care during the COVID-19 pandemic: a qualitative study. BMC Fam Pract. 2021 Jul 1;22(1):143.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8248293</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34210284</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu X, Lin Z. COVID-19, Economic Impact, Mental Health, and Coping Behaviors: A Conceptual Framework and Future Research Directions. Front Psychol. 2021 Nov 11;12:759974.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8660126</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34899503</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Serrano-Alarcón M, Kentikelenis A, Mckee M, Stuckler D. Impact of COVID-19 lockdowns on mental health: Evidence from a quasi-natural experiment in England and Scotland. Health Econ. 2022;31(2):284–96.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8646947</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34773325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiong J, Lipsitz O, Nasri F, Lui LMW, Gill H, Phan L, et al. Impact of COVID-19 pandemic on mental health in the general population: A systematic review. J Affect Disord. 2020;277:55–64.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7413844</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32799105</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clarke-Deelder E, Rokicki S, McGovern ME, Birabwa C, Cohen JL, Waiswa P, et al. Levels of depression, anxiety, and psychological distress among Ugandan adults during the first wave of the COVID-19 pandemic: cross-sectional evidence from a mobile phone-based population survey. Glob Ment Health (Camb) 2022;9:274–84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9807010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36618739</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lemuel AM, Usman IM, Kasozi KI, Alghamdi S, Aigbogun EO, Archibong V, et al. COVID-19-Related Mental Health Burdens: Impact of Educational Level and Relationship Status Among Low-Income Earners of Western Uganda. Front Public Health. 2021 Nov 18;9:739270.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8663024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34900896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nantaayi B, Ndawula RK, Musoke P, Ssewante N, Nakyagaba L, Wamala JN, et al. Psychological Distress and Access to Mental Health Services Among Undergraduate Students During the COVID-19 Lockdown in Uganda. Front Psychiatry. 2022 Jun 2;13:792217.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9201074</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35722591</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katongole SP, Yaro P, Bukuluki P. Chapter 3 - The impact of COVID-19 on mental health of frontline health workers in Ghana and Uganda. In: Moustafa AA, editor. Mental Health Effects of COVID-19. Academic Press; 2021. pp. 37–68.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenberg S, Mendoza J, Tabatabaei-Jafari H, Salvador-Carulla L. International experiences of the active period of COVID-19-Mental health care. Health Policy Technol. 2020;9(4):503–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7452826</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32874855</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Revet A, Hebebrand J, Anagnostopoulos D, Kehoe LA, Child C, Adolescent Psychiatry C, et al. ESCAP CovCAP survey of heads of academic departments to assess the perceived initial (April/May 2020) impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on child and adolescent psychiatry services. Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2022;31(5):795–804.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7816838</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33474653</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nair S, Kannan P, Mehta K, Raju A, Mathew J, Ramachandran P. The COVID-19 pandemic and its impact on mental health services: the provider perspective. J Public Health (Oxf) 2021;43(Supplement_2):ii51–ii6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34622289</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carpiniello B, Tusconi M, Zanalda E, Di Sciascio G, Di Giannantonio M, Zanalda E, et al. Psychiatry during the COVID-19 pandemic: a survey on mental health departments in Italy. BMC Psychiatry. 2020;20(1):593.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7739792</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33327940</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mason M, Welch SB, Arunkumar P, Post LA, Feinglass JM. Notes from the Field: Opioid Overdose Deaths Before, During, and After an 11-Week COVID-19 Stay-at-Home Order-Cook County, Illinois, January 1, 2018-October 6, 2020. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2021;70(10):362–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7951817</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33705372</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Assenza G, Lanzone J, Brigo F, Coppola A, Di Gennaro G, Di Lazzaro V, et al. Epilepsy Care in the Time of COVID-19 Pandemic in Italy: Risk Factors for Seizure Worsening. Front Neurol. 2020;11:737.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7350269</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32719655</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>United Nations (UN) Policy brief: COVID-19 and the need for action on mental health. Accessed 17th June 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mutlu E, Anιl Yağcιoğlu AE. Relapse in patients with serious mental disorders during the COVID-19 outbreak: a retrospective chart review from a community mental health center. Eur Arch Psychiatry Clin Neurosci. 2021;271(2):381–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7587161</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33104904</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adhanom Ghebreyesus T. Addressing mental health needs: an integral part of COVID-19 response. World Psychiatry. 2020;19(2):129–30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7214944</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32394569</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abbo C, Nakku J, Kalani K, Lukwata H. Mental health and psychosocial support in a time of COVID-19. Africa Health. 2021;42(4):28–30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mwine P, Atuhaire I, Ahirirwe SR, Nansikombi HT, Senyange S, Elayeete S, et al. Readiness of health facilities to manage individuals infected with COVID-19, Uganda, June 2021. BMC Health Serv Res. 2023;23(1):441.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10159667</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37143093</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ojeahere MI, de Filippis R, Ransing R, Karaliuniene R, Ullah I, Bytyçi DG, et al. Management of psychiatric conditions and delirium during the COVID-19 pandemic across continents: lessons learned and recommendations. Brain Behav Immun Health. 2020;9:100147.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7501517</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32984854</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnson S, Dalton-Locke C, Vera San Juan N, Foye U, Oram S, Papamichail A, et al. Impact on mental health care and on mental health service users of the COVID-19 pandemic: a mixed methods survey of UK mental health care staff. Soc Psychiatry Psychiatr Epidemiol. 2021;56(1):25–37.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7453694</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32857218</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roncero C, García-Ullán L, de la Iglesia-Larrad JI, Martín C, Andrés P, Ojeda A, et al. The response of the mental health network of the Salamanca area to the COVID-19 pandemic: The role of the telemedicine. Psychiatry Res. 2020;291:113252.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7329660</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32623263</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sibeoni J, Manolios E, Costa-Drolon E, Meunier JP, Verneuil L, Revah-Levy A. Clinical practice during the COVID-19 pandemic: a qualitative study among child and adolescent psychiatrists across the world. Child Adolesc Psychiatry Ment Health. 2021;15(1):68.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8608359</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34809693</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization . Geneva: World Health Organization; 2020. The impact of COVID-19 on mental, neurological and substance use services: results of a rapid assessment; p. 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organisation State of health financing in the African region. Geneva. 2013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antiporta DA, Bruni A. Emerging mental health challenges, strategies, and opportunities in the context of the COVID-19 pandemic: Perspectives from South American decision-makers. Rev Panam Salud Publica. 2020 Nov 20;44:e154.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7679046</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33245299</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Independent People living with epilepsy find solace in drug banks. Accessed 3rd April 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sammons MT, Elchert DM, Martin JN. Mental Health Service Provision During COVID-19: Results of the Third Survey of Licensed Psychologists. J Health Serv Psychol. 2021;47(3):119–27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8370457</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34423313</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Honey A, Waks S, Hines M, Glover H, Hancock N, Hamilton D, et al. COVID-19 and Psychosocial Support Services: Experiences of People Living with Enduring Mental Health Conditions. Community Ment Health J. 2021;57(7):1255–66.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8262584</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34235615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen S, Jones PB, Underwood BR, Moore A, Bullmore ET, Banerjee S, et al. The early impact of COVID-19 on mental health and community physical health services and their patients' mortality in Cambridgeshire and Peterborough, UK. J Psychiatr Res. 2020;131:244–54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7508053</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33035957</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naslund JA, Aschbrenner KA, Araya R, Marsch LA, Unützer J, Patel V, et al. Digital technology for treating and preventing mental disorders in low-income and middle-income countries: a narrative review of the literature. Lancet Psychiatry. 2017;4(6):486–500.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5523650</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28433615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uganda Bureau of Statistics (UBOS) ICF . Kampala. Uganda Rockville, Maryland, USA: 2018. Uganda Demographic and Health Survey 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pajević I, Hasanović M, Avdibegović E, Džubur-Kulenović A, Burgić-Radmanović M, Babić D, et al. Organization of mental healthcare in Bosnia and Herzegovina during coronavirus disease 2019 pandemic. Indian J psychiatry. 2020;62(Suppl 3):S479–s91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7659768</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33227053</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ornell F, Borelli WV, Benzano D, Schuch JB, Moura HF, Sordi AO, et al. The next pandemic: impact of COVID-19 in mental healthcare assistance in a nationwide epidemiological study. Lancet Reg Health Am. 2021 Dec;4:100061.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8427141</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34518824</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Izudi J, Kiragga AN, Okoboi S, Bajunirwe F, Castelnuovo B. Adaptations to HIV services delivery amidst the COVID-19 pandemic restrictions in Kampala, Uganda: A qualitative study. PLOS Global Public Health. 2022;2(8):e0000908.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10022311</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36962823</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoeft TJ, Fortney JC, Patel V, Unützer J. Task-Sharing Approaches to Improve Mental Health Care in Rural and Other Low-Resource Settings: A Systematic Review. J Rural Health. 2018;34(1):48–62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5509535</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28084667</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adiukwu F, de Filippis R, Orsolini L, Gashi Bytyçi D, Shoib S, Ransing R, et al. Scaling Up Global Mental Health Services During the COVID-19 Pandemic and Beyond. Psychiatr Serv. 2022;73(2):231–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34235945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>