<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39464566</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2054-4251</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>11</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Global mental health (Cambridge, England)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Glob Ment Health (Camb)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Impact of social support on PTSD : Chain mediating effects of insomnia and anxiety.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e100</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e100</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e100</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1017/gmh.2024.91</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">To reveal the chain mediating roles of insomnia and anxiety between social support and PTSD in nursing staff under the stage of COVID-19 regular pandemic prevention and control in China.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A total of 784 nurses were recruited using the convenience sampling method in Jiangsu Province, China. Demographic questionnaire, Perceived Social Support Scale, Impact of Event Scale-Revised, Generalized Anxiety Disorder-7 and Insomnia Severity Index were applied to collect data.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Social support, PTSD, insomnia and anxiety were significantly correlated with each other. Insomnia and anxiety acted as chain mediators between social support and PTSD.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Insufficient social support may trigger PTSD through the chain mediating effects of insomnia and anxiety in nursing staff under the stage of COVID-19 regular pandemic prevention and control. Measures focusing on social support, insomnia and anxiety should be taken to reduce or even prevent PTSD in nursing staff in Chinese hospitals in similar crises in the future.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s) 2024.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mao</LastName><ForeName>Xiaofei</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Lab for Post-traumatic Stress Disorder, Faculty of Psychology, Naval Medical University, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hou</LastName><ForeName>Tianya</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7361-1935</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Psychology, Navy Medical University, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Yulin</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Key Laboratory of Human Factors Engineering, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>China Institute of Marine Technology and Economy, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Jianguo</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Psychology, Navy Medical University, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Fan</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Lab for Post-traumatic Stress Disorder, Faculty of Psychology, Naval Medical University, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Weizhi</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Lab for Post-traumatic Stress Disorder, Faculty of Psychology, Naval Medical University, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Glob Ment Health (Camb)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101659641</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2054-4251</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">PTSD</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">anxiety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">insomnia</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nurses</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">social support</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39464566</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11504932</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/gmh.2024.91</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2054425124000918</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Asif IM, Price DE, Ewing A, Rao AL, Harmon KG and Drezner JA (2016) The impact of diagnosis: Measuring the psychological response to being diagnosed with serious or potentially lethal cardiac disease in young competitive athletes. British Journal of Sports Medicine 50(3), 163–166. 10.1136/bjsports-2015-095560.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bjsports-2015-095560</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26612845</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bae SY, Yoon HJ, Kim Y and Kim J (2022). Posttraumatic stress disorder and related factors among nurses working during the COVID‐19 pandemic. Journal of Nursing Management 30(5), 1096–1104. 10.1111/jonm.13615.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jonm.13615</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9115141</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35403266</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bastien CH, Vallieres A and Morin CM (2001) Validation of the Insomnia Severity Index as an outcome measure for insomnia research. Sleep Medicine 2, 297–307. 10.1016/s1389-9457(00)00065-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/s1389-9457(00)00065-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11438246</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benfante A, Di Tella M, Romeo A and Castelli L (2020) Traumatic stress in healthcare workers during COVID-19 pandemic: A review of the immediate impact. Frontiers in Psychology 11, 569935. 10.3389/fpsyg.2020.569935.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2020.569935</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7645025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33192854</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brewin CR, Andrews B and Valentine JD (2000) Meta-analysis of risk factors for posttraumatic stress disorder in trauma-exposed adults. Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology 68(5), 748–766. 10.1037//0022-006x.68.5.748.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037//0022-006x.68.5.748</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11068961</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blekas A, Voitsidis P, Athanasiadou M, Parlapani E, Chatzigeorgiou AF, Skoupra M, Syngelakis M, Holeva V and Diakogiannis I (2020) COVID-19: PTSD symptoms in Greek health care professionals. Psychological Trauma: Theory, Research, Practice, and Policy 12(7), 812–819. 10.1037/tra0000914.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/tra0000914</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32853011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campbell DT and Fiske DW (1959) Convergent and discriminant validation by the multitrait-multimethod matrix. Psychological Bulletin 56, 81–105.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">13634291</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chatzittofis A, Karanikola M, Michailidou K and Constantinidou A (2021) Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on the mental health of healthcare workers. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 18(4), 1435. 10.3390/ijerph18041435.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph18041435</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7913751</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33546513</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen PJ, Huang CLC, Weng SF, Wu MP, Ho CH, Wang JJ, Tsai WC and Hsu YW (2017) Relapse insomnia increases greater risk of anxiety and depression: Evidence from a population-based 4-year cohort study. Sleep Medicine 8, 122–129. 10.1016/j.sleep.2017.07.016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2017.07.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29031746</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen R, Sun C, Chen JJ, Jen HJ, Kang XL, Kao CC and Chou KR (2021a) A large-scale survey on trauma, burnout, and posttraumatic growth among nurses during the COVID-19 pandemic. International Journal of Mental Health Nursing 30(1), 102–116. 10.1111/inm.12796.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/inm.12796</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7894338</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33107677</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen X, Arber A, Gao J, Zhang L, Ji M, Wang D, Wu J and Du J (2021b) The mental health status among nurses from low-risk areas under normalized COVID-19 pandemic prevention and control in China: A cross-sectional study. International Journal of Mental Health Nursing 30(4), 975–987. 10.1111/inm.12852.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/inm.12852</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8250992</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33811426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chew NWS, Lee GKH, Tan BY, Jing M, Goh Y, Ngiam NJH, Yeo LLL, Ahmad A, Ahmed Khan F, Napolean Shanmugam G, Sharma AK, Komalkumar RN, Meenakshi PV, Shah K, Patel B, Chan BPL, Sunny S, Chandra B, Ong JJY, Paliwal PR, Wong LYH, Sagayanathan R, Chen JT, Ying Ng AY, Teoh HL, Tsivgoulis G, Ho CSH, Ho RCM, Sharma VK (2020a) A multinational, multicentre study on the psychological outcomes and associated physical symptoms amongst healthcare workers during COVID-19 outbreak. Brain, Behavior, and Immunity, 88, 559–565. 10.1016/j.bbi.2020.04.049.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2020.04.049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7172854</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32330593</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chew NWS, Ngiam JN, Tan BY, Tham SM, Tan CY, Jing M, Sagayanathan R, Chen JT, Wong LYH, Ahmad A, Khan FA, Marmin M, Hassan FB, Sharon TM, Lim CH, Mohaini MIB, Danuaji R, Nguyen TH, Tsivgoulis G, Tsiodras S, Fragkou PC, Dimopoulou D, Sharma AK, Shah K, Patel B, Sharma S, Komalkumar RN, Meenakshi RV, Talati S, Teoh HL, Ho CSH, Ho RCM and Sharma VK (2020b) Asian-Pacific perspective on the psychological well-being of healthcare workers during the evolution of the COVID-19 pandemic. BJPsych Open 6(6):e116. 10.1192/bjo.2020.98.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1192/bjo.2020.98</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7542327</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33028449</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chinese Society of Neurology, Chinese Society of Sleep Disorders and Chinese Society of Neuropsychology and Behavioral Neurology (2020) Expert consensus on the diagnosis and treatment of insomnia with depression and anxiety in Chinese adults. Chinese Journal of Neurology 53(8), 564–574.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen S and Wills TA (1985) Stress, social support, and the buffering hypothesis. Psychological Bulletin 98(2), 310–357.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3901065</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>d’Ettorre G, Ceccarelli G, Santinelli L, Vassalini P, Innocenti GP, Alessandri F, Koukopoulos AE, Russo A, d’Ettorre G and Tarsitani L (2021) Post-traumatic stress symptoms in healthcare workers dealing with the COVID-19 pandemic: A systematic review. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 18(2), 601. 10.3390/ijerph18020601.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph18020601</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7828167</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33445712</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dong Y, Yeo MC, Tham XC, Danuaji R, Nguyen TH, Sharma AK, Rn K, Pv M, Tai MS, Ahmad A, Tan BY, Ho RCM, Chua MCH and Sharma VK (2022). Investigating psychological differences between nurses and other health care workers from the Asia-Pacific region during the early phase of COVID-19: Machine learning approach. JMIR Nursing 5(1), e32647. 10.2196/32647.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/32647</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9162133</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35648464</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du J, Liu Z, Zhang X, Shao P, Hua Y, Li Y, Lang H and Ni C (2022) Occupational stress and insomnia symptoms among nurses during the outbreak of COVID-19 in China: The chain mediating effect of perceived organizational support and psychological capital. Frontiers in Psychiatry 13, 882385. 10.3389/fpsyt.2022.882385.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2022.882385</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9300995</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35873265</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goh KK, Jou S, Lu ML, Yeh LC, Kao YF, Liu CM and Kan BL (2021) Younger, more senior, and most vulnerable? Interaction effects of age and job seniority on psychological distress and quality of life among firefighters. Psychological Trauma: Theory, Research, Practice and Policy 13(1):56–65. 10.1037/tra0000662.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/tra0000662</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32853012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grey I, Arora T, Thomas J, Saneh A, Tohme P and Abi-Habib R (2020) The role of perceived social support on depression and sleep during the COVID-19 pandemic. Psychiatry Research 293, 113452. 10.1016/j.psychres.2020.113452.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2020.113452</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7500407</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32977047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guay S, Billette V and Marchand A (2006) Exploring the links between posttraumatic stress disorder and social support: Processes and potential research avenues. Journal of Traumatic Stress 19(3), 327–338. 10.1002/jts.20124.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jts.20124</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16788995</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hayes AF (2013) Introduction to Mediation, Moderation, and Conditional Process Analysis: A Regression-Based Approach. New York, NY: Guilford Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ho CS, Chee CY and Ho RC (2020). Mental health strategies to combat the psychological impact of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) beyond paranoia and panic. Annals of the Academy of Medicine, Singapore 49(3), 155–160.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32200399</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hou T, Yin Q, Xu Y, Gao J, Bin L, Li H, Cai W, Liu Y, Dong W, Deng G and Ni C (2021) The mediating role of perceived social support between resilience and anxiety 1 year after the COVID-19 pandemic: Disparity between high-risk and low-risk nurses in China. Frontiers in Psychiatry 12, 666789. 10.3389/fpsyt.2021.666789.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2021.666789</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8180566</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34108897</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang Y, Wu R, Wu J, Yang Q, Zheng S and Wu K (2020) Psychological resilience, self-acceptance, perceived social support and their associations with mental health of incarcerated offenders in China. Asian Journal of Psychiatry, 52, 102166. 10.1016/j.ajp.2020.102166.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ajp.2020.102166</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32447270</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jansson-Fröjmark M and Lindblom K (2008) A bidirectional relationship between anxiety and depression, and insomnia? A prospective study in the general population. Journal of Psychosomatic Research 64(4), 443–449. 10.1016/j.jpsychores.2007.10.016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychores.2007.10.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18374745</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang Z, Wang S, Shen Z, Zhao X, Wang F, Chen Y, Qiao Y, Wei T, Dong P, Ding S and Yang X (2022) Nurses’ experience of work stress related to COVID-19 regular prevention and control in China: A qualitative study. Journal of Nursing Management 30(2), 375–383. 10.1111/jonm.13528.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jonm.13528</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9305213</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34845777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kerasiotis B and Motta RW (2004) Assessment of PTSD symptoms in emergency room, intensive care unit, and general floor nurses. International Journal of Emergency Mental Health 6(3), 121–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15481474</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim SJ and Yeo JH (2020) Factors affecting posttraumatic stress disorder in south Korean trauma nurses. Journal of Trauma Nursing 27(1), 50–57. 10.1097/JTN.0000000000000482.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/JTN.0000000000000482</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31895320</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lai J, Ma S, Wang Y, Cai Z, Hu J, Wei N, Wu J, Du H, Chen T, Li R, Tan H, Kang L, Yao L, Huang M, Wang H, Wang G, Liu Z and Hu S (2020) Factors associated with mental health outcomes among health care workers exposed to coronavirus disease 2019. JAMA Network Open 3(3), e203976. 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.3976.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.3976</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7090843</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32202646</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lau SSS, Ho CCY, Pang RCK, Su S, Kwok H, Fung SF and Ho RC (2022) Measurement of burnout during the prolonged pandemic in the Chinese zero-COVID context: COVID-19 burnout views scale. Frontiers in Public Health 10, 1039450. 10.3389/fpubh.2022.1039450.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2022.1039450</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9686433</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36438233</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Le XTT, Nguyen QT, Onyango B, Nguyen QN, Pham QT, Ta NTK, Nguyen TT, Le HT, Vu LG, Hoang MT, Vu GT, Latkins CA, Ho RCM and Ho CSH (2021) Perception toward exposure risk of COVID-19 among health workers in Vietnam: Status and correlated factors. Frontiers in Public Health 9, 589317. 10.3389/fpubh.2021.589317.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2021.589317</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8185209</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34113595</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li L, Wang X, Tan J, Li J and Yuan Y (2022) Influence of sleep difficulty on post-traumatic stress symptoms among frontline medical staff during COVID-19 pandemic in China. Psychology Health &amp; Medicine 27(9), 1924–36. 10.1080/13548506.2021.1981411.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/13548506.2021.1981411</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34541987</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu S S and Ling W S (2009) Multiple mediation models and their applications. Psychological Science 32(2), 433–435. (Published in Chinese).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu MY, Ahorsu DK, Kukreti S, Strong C, Lin YH, Kuo YJ, Chen YP, Lin CY, Chen PL, Ko NY and Ko WC. (2021) The prevalence of post-traumatic stress disorder symptoms, sleep problems, and psychological distress among COVID-19 frontline healthcare workers in Taiwan. Frontiers in Psychiatry 12, 705657. 10.3389/fpsyt.2021.705657.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2021.705657</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8312888</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34322044</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marcks BA and Weisberg RB (2009) Co-occurrence of insomnia and anxiety disorders: A review of the literature. American Journal of Lifestyle Medicine 3(4), 300–309. 10.1177/1559827609334681.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1559827609334681</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mao X, Dong W, Zhang J, Zhang F, Deng W, Li Z and Hou T (2023a) Mental health status and its associated factors among female nurses in the normalization of COVID-19 epidemic prevention and control in China. Frontiers in Public Health 10, 1088246. 10.3389/fpubh.2022.1088246.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2022.1088246</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9859657</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36684890</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mao X, Lin X, Liu P, Zhang J, Deng W, Li Z, Hou T and Dong W (2023b) Impact of insomnia on burnout among Chinese nurses under the regular COVID-19 epidemic prevention and control: Parallel mediating effects of anxiety and depression. International Journal of Public Health 68, 1605688. 10.3389/ijph.2023.1605688.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/ijph.2023.1605688</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10060543</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37006829</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mao X, Zhang F, Wei C, Li Z, Huang C, Sun Z, Zhang J, Deng W, Hou T and Dong W (2023c) The impact of insomnia on anxiety and depression: A longitudinal study of non-clinical young Chinese adult males. BMC Psychiatry 23(1), 360. 10.1186/s12888-023-04873-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12888-023-04873-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10210401</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37226120</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mao X, Luo P, Li F, Zhang F, Zhang J, Deng W, Li Z, Hou T and Dong W (2023d) PTSD of Chinese nurses in the normalisation of COVID-19 pandemic prevention and control: Prevalence and correlates. Journal of Global Health 13, 06033. 10.7189/jogh.13.06033.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7189/jogh.13.06033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10449031</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37616126</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mao X, Hou T, Wang H, Tang Y, Ni C, Zhang Y, Zhang J, Deng W, Chen L, Wang X, Li Z, Jia Y, Dong W and Qian X (2024) Status and influencing factors of nurses’ burnout: A cross-sectional study during COVID-19 regular prevention and control in Jiangsu Province, China. Global Mental Health 11, e54. 10.1017/gmh.2024.42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/gmh.2024.42</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11076924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38721485</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mason EC and Harvey AG (2014) Insomnia before and after treatment for anxiety and depression. Journal of Affective Disorders 168, 415–421. 10.1016/j.jad.2014.07.020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2014.07.020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25108278</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mirzaei A, Molaei B and Habibi-Soola A (2022) Post-traumatic stress disorder and its related factors in nurses caring for COVID-19 patients. Iranian Journal of Nursing and Midwifery Research 14, 27(2), 106–111. 10.4103/ijnmr.ijnmr_456_20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/ijnmr.ijnmr_456_20</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8997177</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35419268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mo PKH, Chen X, Lam EHK, Li J, Kahler CW and Lau JTF (2020) The moderating role of social support on the relationship between anxiety, stigma, and intention to use illicit drugs among HIV-positive men who have sex with men. AIDS and Behavior 24(1), 55–64. 10.1007/s10461-019-02719-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10461-019-02719-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9258037</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31754966</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nakata A, Haratani T, Takahashi M, Kawakami N, Arito H, Kobayashi F and Araki S (2004) Job stress, social support, and prevalence of insomnia in a population of Japanese daytime workers. Social Science &amp; Medicine 59(8), 1719–1730. 10.1016/j.socscimed.2004.02.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2004.02.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15279928</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ozer EJ, Best SR, Lipsey TL and Weiss DS (2003) Predictors of posttraumatic stress disorder and symptoms in adults: A meta-analysis. Psychological Bulletin 129(1), 52–73. 10.1037/0033-2909.129.1.52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/0033-2909.129.1.52</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12555794</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pham QT, Le XTT, Phan TC, Nguyen QN, Ta NKT, Nguyen AN, Nguyen TT, Nguyen QT, Le HT, Luong AM, Koh D, Haoang MT, Pham HQ, Vu LG, Nguyen TH, Tran BX, Latkin CA, Ho CSH and Ho RCM (2021) Impacts of COVID-19 on the life and work of healthcare workers during the nationwide partial lockdown in Vietnam. Frontiers in Psychology 12, 563193.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8417359</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34489769</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Preacher KJ and Hayes AF (2008) Asymptotic and resampling strategies for assessing and comparing indirect effects in multiple mediator models. Behavior Research Methods 40, 879–891. 10.3758/brm.40.3.879.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3758/brm.40.3.879</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18697684</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Podsakoff PM, Mackenzie SB, Lee JY and Podsakoff NP (2003) Common method biases in behavioral research: A critical review of the literature and recommended remedies. The Journal of Applied Psychology 88(5), 879–903. 10.1037/0021-9010.88.5.879.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/0021-9010.88.5.879</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14516251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roohafza H R, Afshar H, Keshteli A H, Mohammadi N, Feizi A, Taslimi M and Adibi P (2014) What’s the role of perceived social support and coping styles in depression and anxiety? Journal of Research in Medical Sciences 19(10), 944–949.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4274570</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25538777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schnurr, PP, Lunney CA and Sengupta A (2004) Risk factors for the development versus maintenance of posttraumatic stress disorder. Journal of Traumatic Stress 17, 85–95. 10.1023/B:JOTS.0000022614.21794.f4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1023/B:JOTS.0000022614.21794.f4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15141781</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schuster M, Berbert L, Meyer S and Dwyer PA (2022) The impact of psychological capital and workplace social support on pediatric oncology nurses’ Post Traumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD) symptomology. Journal of Pediatric Hematology/Oncology Nursing 39(4), 231–342. 10.1177/275.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/275</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35791851</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Somville FJ, De Gucht V and Maes S (2016) The impact of occupational hazards and traumatic events among Belgian emergency physicians. Scandinavian Journal of Trauma, Resuscitation and Emergency Medicine, 24(1), 59. 10.1186/s13049-016-0249-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13049-016-0249-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4848801</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27121279</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spitzer RL, Kroenke K, Williams JB and Löwe B (2006) A brief measure for assessing generalized anxiety disorder: The GAD-7. Archives of Internal Medicine 166(10), 1092–1097. 10.1001/archinte.166.10.1092.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/archinte.166.10.1092</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16717171</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soh HL, Ho RC, Ho CS and Tam WW (2020) Efficacy of digital cognitive behavioural therapy for insomnia: A meta-analysis of randomised controlled trials. Sleep Medicine 75, 315–325. 10.1016/j.sleep.2020.08.020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.sleep.2020.08.020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32950013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song X, Fu W, Liu X, Luo Z, Wang R, Zhou N, Yan S and Lv C (2020) Mental health status of medical staff in emergency departments during the coronavirus disease 2019 pandemic in China. Brain, Behavior, and Immunity 88, 60–65. 10.1016/j.bbi.2020.06.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2020.06.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7273140</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32512134</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sripada RK, Lamp KE, Defever M, Venners M and Rauch SA (2016) Perceived social support in multi-era veterans with posttraumatic stress disorder. The Journal of Nervous and Mental Disease 204(4), 317–320. 10.1097/NMD.0000000000000476.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/NMD.0000000000000476</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27015395</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan YQ, Wang Z, Yap QV, Chan YH, Ho RCM, Hamid ARAH, Landaluce-Olavarria A, Pellino G, Gauhar V, Chand M, Wroclawski ML, Hameed BZ, Ling SK, Sengupta S, Gallo G, Chiu PK, Tanidir Y, Tallada MPV, Garcia BN, Colleoni R, Abiddin ZAZ, Campi R, Esperto F, Carrion D, Elterman D, Chung ASJ, Ng ACF, Moschini M, Rivas JG, Mayol J, Teoh JY and Chiong E (2023) Psychological health of surgeons in a time of COVID-19: A global survey. Annals of Surgery, 277(1), 50–56. 10.1097/SLA.0000000000004775.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/SLA.0000000000004775</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9762613</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33491983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor DJ, Lichstein KL and Durrence HH (2003) Insomnia as a health risk factor. Behavioral Sleep Medicine 1(4), 227–247. 10.1207/S15402010BSM0104_5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1207/S15402010BSM0104_5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15600216</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor DJ, Lichstein KL, Durrence HH, Reidel BW and Bush AJ (2005) Epidemiology of insomnia, depression, and anxiety. Sleep 28(11), 1457–1464. 10.1093/sleep/28.11.1457.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/sleep/28.11.1457</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16335332</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The State Council (2020) Guiding opinions on novel coronavirus pneumonia epidemic prevention and control work by the State Council. Available at http://www.gov.cn/zhengce/content/2020-05/08/content_5509896.html (accessed 16 Aug 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wen L, Shen M, Zhang M, Liu W, Liu Z and XianYu Y (2022) Psychological stress and job burnout of frontline nurses in Wuhan in the context of normalized pandemic prevention and control for COVID-19—a cross-sectional study. Tobacco Regulatory Science 8(1), 59–74.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Q, Li D, Yan M and Li Y (2022) Mental health status of medical staff in Xinjiang Province of China based on the normalisation of COVID-19 epidemic prevention and control. International Journal of Disaster Risk Reduction 74, 102928. 10.1016/j.ijdrr.2022.102928.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijdrr.2022.102928</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8958729</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35368428</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao H, Zhang Y, Kong D, Li S and Yang N (2020) The effects of social support on sleep quality of medical staff treating patients with coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) in January and February 2020 in China. Medical Science Monitor 26, e923549. 10.12659/MSM.923549.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.12659/MSM.923549</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7075079</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32132521</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xinhua Press (2020) Latest Developments in Epidemic Control on May 8. Available at http://english.www.gov.cn/news/topnews/202005/08/content_WS5eb4914cc6d0b3f0e949729c.html (accessed 16 Aug 2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu Q, Li S and Yang L (2019) Perceived social support and mental health for college students in mainland China: The mediating effects of self-concept. Psychology, Health &amp; Medicine 24(5), 595–604. 10.1080/13548506.2018.1549744.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/13548506.2018.1549744</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30451537</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yao Z, Xie X, Bai R, Li L, Zhang X, Li S, Ma Y, Hui Z and Chen J (2022) The impact of eating behaviors during COVID-19 in health-care workers: A conditional process analysis of eating, affective disorders, and PTSD. Heliyon 8(10), e10892. 10.1016/j.heliyon.2022.e10892.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2022.e10892</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9529342</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36211998</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yılmaz M, Kıraç Y and Sahin MK (2021) Sleep quality and related factors in a sample of Turkish healthcare workers during the COVID‐19 pandemic: A cross‐sectional study. International Journal of Clinical Practice 75(11), e14813. 10.1111/ijcp.14813.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ijcp.14813</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8646597</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34486780</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yin Q, Chen A, Song X, Deng G and Dong W (2021) Risk perception and PTSD symptoms of medical staff combating against COVID-19: A PLS structural equation model. Frontiers in Psychiatry 12, 607612. 10.3389/fpsyt.2021.607612.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2021.607612</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7917132</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33658951</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yunitri N, Chu H, Kang XL, Jen HJ, Pien LC, Tsai HT, Kamil AR and Chou KR (2022) Global prevalence and associated risk factors of posttraumatic stress disorder during COVID-19 pandemic: A meta-analysis. International Journal of Nursing Studies 126, 104136. 10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2021.104136.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2021.104136</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8585564</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34856503</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang MW and Ho RC (2017) Moodle: The cost effective solution for internet cognitive behavioral therapy (I-CBT) interventions. Technology and Health Care 25(1), 163–165. 10.3233/THC-161261.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3233/THC-161261</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27689560</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang N, Liu C, Lu J and Cheng J (2021) Investigation on mental health status of frontline medical staff in Taiyuan city under the condition of COVID-19 normalization. Journal of Preventive Medicine Information 37(8), 1126–1130+1135 (in Chinese).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou YG, Shang ZL, Zhang F, Wu LL, Sun LN, Jia YP, Yu HB and Liu WZ (2021). PTSD: Past, present and future implications for China. Chinese Journal of Traumatology 24(4), 187–208. 10.1016/j.cjtee.2021.04.011.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cjtee.2021.04.011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8343811</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33994278</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou H and You LR (2004) Statistical remedies for common method biases. Advances in Psychological Science 6, 942–950.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu W, Wei Y, Meng X and Li J (2020) The mediation effects of coping style on the relationship between social support and anxiety in Chinese medical staff during COVID-19. BMC Health Services Research 20, 1007. 10.1186/s12913-020-05871-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12913-020-05871-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7609823</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33148229</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zimet GD, Dahlem NW, Zimet SG and Farley GK (1988) The multidimensional scale of perceived social support. Journal of Personality Assessment 52(1), 30–41. 10.1207/s15327752jpa5201_2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1207/s15327752jpa5201_2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2280326</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zou X, Liu S, Li J, Chen W, Ye J, Yang Y, Zhou F and Ling L (2021) Factors associated with healthcare workers’ insomnia symptoms and fatigue in the fight against COVID-19, and the role of organizational support. Frontiers in Psychiatry 12, 652717. 10.3389/fpsyt.2021.652717.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2021.652717</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8032945</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33841214</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>