<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39463557</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Effect of Coronavirus Disease 2019 Pandemic and Vaccination on Menstrual Cycle Among King Saud University Students in Riyadh: A Retrospective Online Survey.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70277</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70277</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e70277</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.70277</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Objectives We aimed to evaluate the prevalence of menstrual cycle changes following the COVID-19 pandemic and the COVID-19 vaccination among female students at King Saud University in Riyadh, Saudi Arabia. Methods A cross-sectional retrospective study using an online questionnaire was conducted between October 2022 and December 2022. Data were collected concerning demographic variables, clinical conditions, menstrual cycle characteristics, COVID-19 infection status, and vaccination history. Results Of the 525 female students who participated in the study (mean age, 21.5 ± 3.9 years; mean body mass index, 22.7 ± 4.7 kg/m<sup>2</sup>), 246 (46.9%) had tested positive for COVID-19, 15 (2.9%) had visited the emergency room, and eight (1.5%) had been hospitalized. The average duration between menstrual cycles increased significantly among the study sample (pre-pandemic, 25.9 ± 5.3 days; post-pandemic, 26.8 ± 6.7 days; p = 0.016). Pre-pandemic, 221 (42.1%) participants reported less than two days of variance between their shortest and longest cycles, as compared with 175 (33.3%) post-pandemic (p &lt; 0.001). Regarding vaccination, 393 (74.9%) participants had received three vaccinations, and 110 (21%) had received two vaccinations. Post-vaccination, 184 (35%) participants reported no changes to their menstrual cycle, 154 (29.3%) reported less disruption, and 44 (8.4%) experienced more disrupted menstrual cycles. Conclusion This study highlights potential associations between the COVID-19 pandemic, subsequent vaccinations, and changes in menstrual patterns, which can help to elucidate the physiological and psychological effects of pandemics and vaccination campaigns on women's health. Future studies must consider biological and psychosocial factors to elucidate underlying mechanisms and causal relationships.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Almosa et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Almosa</LastName><ForeName>Kawther N</ForeName><Initials>KN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Family and Community Medicine, King Saud University Medical City, Riyadh, SAU.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alshammari</LastName><ForeName>Sulaiman A</ForeName><Initials>SA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Family and Community Medicine, College of Medicine, King Saud University, Riyadh, SAU.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Almutairi</LastName><ForeName>Shahad M</ForeName><Initials>SM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Internal Medicine, King Saud University Medical City, Riyadh, SAU.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Almousa</LastName><ForeName>Yasmeen M</ForeName><Initials>YM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Primary Health Care, Ministry of Health, Riyadh, SAU.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">covid-19 pandemic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">covid-19 vaccine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">female students</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">menstrual cycle changes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">psychologic stress</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. The Institutional Research Board (IRB) Committee of the Health Sciences Colleges Research on Human Subjects at King Saud University issued approval IRB Approval No. E-22-7140. The study followed the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki. Animal subjects: All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39463557</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11512638</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.70277</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Menstruation in girls and adolescents: using the menstrual cycle as a vital sign. Care CA. https://www.acog.org/clinical/clinical-guidance/committee-opinion/articles/2015/12/menstruation-in-girls-and-adolescents-using-the-menstrual-cycle-as-a-vital-sign Obstet Gynecol. 2015;126:143–146.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The COVID-19 pandemic and the menstrual cycle: research gaps and opportunities. Sharp GC, Fraser A, Sawyer G, et al. Int J Epidemiol. 2022;51:691–700.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8690231</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34865021</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Experiences with prophylactic typhoid vaccination: its effect on menstruation. Lamb AR. https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamainternalmedicine/article-abstract/653642 Arch Intern Med. 1913;12:565–577.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Menstrual abnormalities after hepatitis B vaccine. Shingu T, Uchida T, Nishi M, Hayashida K, Kashiwagi S, Hayayashi J, Kaji M. https://www.jstage.jst.go.jp/article/kurumemedj1954/29/3/29_3_123/_article/-char/en Kurume Med J. 1982;29:123–125.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>No association between HPV vaccine and reported post-vaccination symptoms in Japanese young women: Results of the Nagoya study. Suzuki S, Hosono A. Papillomavirus Res. 2018;5:96–103.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5887012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29481964</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A retrospective case-control study on menstrual cycle changes following COVID-19 vaccination and disease. Alvergne A, Kountourides G, Argentieri MA, et al.  https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266709v1. iScience. 2023;26:106401.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10015085</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36987520</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Association between menstrual cycle length and coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) vaccination: a U.S. cohort. Hallberg E, Sundström A, Larsson M, Arthurson V, Ljung R. Obstet Gynecol. 2022;139:940–941.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35576361</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Investigating trends in those who experience menstrual bleeding changes after SARS-CoV-2 vaccination. Lee KM, Junkins EJ, Luo C, Fatima UA, Cox ML, Clancy KB. Sci Adv. 2022;8:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9286513</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35857495</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Menstrual symptoms after COVID-19 vaccine: a cross-sectional investigation in the MENA region. Muhaidat N, Alshrouf MA, Azzam MI, Karam AM, Al-Nazer MW, Al-Ani A. Int J Womens Health. 2022;14:395–404.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8976114</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35378876</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cross-sectional study of the impact of COVID-19 on domestic violence, menstruation, genital tract health, and contraception use among women in Jordan. Aolymat I. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2020;104:519–525.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7866327</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33377449</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Menstrual cycle changes: a cross-sectional study of Saudi females following SARS-CoV-2 infection. Abdel-Moneim YA, Alghamdi HY, Alrashed AM, Jawhari AM, Bukhari SM, Bukhari NM, Abdel-Moneim AS. PLoS One. 2022;17:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9767340</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36538566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Covid-19 vaccination and menstrual cycle changes: a United Kingdom (UK) retrospective case-control study [PREPRINT] Alvergne A, Kountouride G, Argentieri A, et al.  https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2021.11.23.21266709v1 medRxiv. 2021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The challenge of maintaining metabolic health during a global pandemic. King AJ, Burke LM, Halson SL, Hawley JA. Sports Med. 2020;50:1233–1241.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7245641</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32449141</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Have lifestyle habits and psychological well-being changed among adolescents and medical students due to COVID-19 lockdown in Croatia? Dragun R, Veček NN, Marendić M, et al.  https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/33396690/ Nutrients. 2020;13:97.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7830522</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33396690</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The influence of COVID-19 infection-associated immune response on the female reproductive system†. Saadedine M, El Sabeh M, Borahay MA, Daoud G. Biol Reprod. 2023;108:172–182.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9620712</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36173920</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Menstrual irregularities post-COVID-19 infection/vaccination in an Indian population. Moolamalla S, Bakshi K, Medarametla V. https://www.jsafog.com/doi/pdf/10.5005/jp-journals-10006-2163 J South Asian Feder Obs Gynae. 2022;14:694–699.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knowledge, attitudes and preventive behaviors toward COVID-19 among school students in Riyadh, Saudi Arabia. Alshammari SA, Alaraifi DK, Albassam FA, Alzahrani SA, AlWatban LH, Alharbi RM, Alkhalil MJ. https://discoveryjournals.org/medicalscience/current_issue/v27/n139/e343ms3167.htm Med Sci. 2023;27:0.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>