<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39460981</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1097-4679</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>26</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of clinical psychology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Clin Psychol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Effect of engagement in personal growth initiative skills on depression, anxiety, and stress: Multilevel mediation analysis with intensive longitudinal data.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/jclp.23749</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">The current study examined the association between the possession of personal growth initiative (PGI) skills and symptoms of mental illness (i.e., depression, anxiety, and stress) and the potential mediating role of daily engagement of PGI skills during the COVID-19 pandemic.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">The participants consisted of 73 individuals (M<sub>age</sub> = 41.62, SD<sub>age</sub> = 12.44) who were recruited from Amazon's Mechanical Turk (MTurk). Data for possessed PGI was collected in April 2020, and the daily survey started approximately 1 month later at the beginning of May 2020 for 29 days.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Controlling for demographic variables, multilevel mediation models revealed significant association between PGI skills and PGI engagement. However, our hypothesized indirect effects were not found. When inspecting the direct effects controlling for the effect of PGI engagement and demographic variables, the paths between PGI skills and both depression and anxiety were negatively associated. When examining the effect of time, there were no significant changes during the period of 29 days in the levels of PGI skills among individuals. However, a significant fluctuation within individuals in how much participants have utilized PGI skills during the study period was found.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The current study highlights the influence of PGI skills at both the between-individual as well as within-individual levels in predicting symptoms of mental illness, and it also uncovers the role of PGI skills by separating into general PGI skills and individual's daily engagement in utilizing the PGI skills in predicting symptoms of mental illness.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shigemoto</LastName><ForeName>Yuki</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9319-7188</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychology, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>White</LastName><ForeName>April</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychology, Prairie View A&amp;M University, Prairie View, Texas, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Baloch</LastName><ForeName>Rabeea</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychology, Prairie View A&amp;M University, Prairie View, Texas, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Clin Psychol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0217132</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0021-9762</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">anxiety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">depression</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">personal growth initiative</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">stress</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>34</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>34</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39460981</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jclp.23749</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Asparouhov, T., &amp; Muthén, B. (2019). Latent variable centering of predictors and mediators in multilevel and time‐series models. Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary Journal, 26, 119–142. https://doi.org/10.1080/10705511.2018.1511375</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baumgartner, H., &amp; Weijters, B. (2012). Commentary on “Common Method Bias in marketing: Causes, mechanisms, and procedural remedies”. Journal of Retailing, 88(4), 563–566. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jretai.2012.10.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blackie, L. E. R., Jayawickreme, E., Forgeard, M. J. C., &amp; Jayawickreme, N. (2015). The protective function of personal growth initiative among a genocide‐affected population in Rwanda. Psychological Trauma: Theory Research, Practice, and Policy, 7(4), 333–339. https://doi.org/10.1037/tra0000010</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carpenter, E. J. (2010). The tactical games model sport experience: An examination of student motivation and game performance during an ultimate frisbee unit (Doctoral dissertation, University of Massachusetts at Amherst). https://scholarworks.umass.edu/items/8a28cacc-55ba-4b4a-abbe-2fd5f4d850f8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Connolly, S. L., Hogan, T. P., Shimada, S. L., &amp; Miller, C. J. (2021). Leveraging implementation science to understand factors influencing sustained use of mental health apps: A narrative review. Journal of Technology in Behavioral Science, 6, 184–196. https://doi.org/10.1007/s41347-020-00165-4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dave, D. M., Friedson, A. I., Matsuzawa, K., &amp; Sabia, J. J. (2020). When do shelter‐in‐place orders fight COVID‐19 best? Policy heterogeneity across states and adoption time. National Bureau of Economic Research Working Paper Series, No. 27091. https://doi.org/10.3386/w27091</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dean, D. J., Tso, I. F., Giersch, A., Lee, H.‐S., Baxter, T., Griffith, T., Song, L., &amp; Park, S. (2021). Cross‐cultural comparisons of psychosocial distress in the USA, South Korea, France, and Hong Kong during the initial phase of COVID‐19. Psychiatry Research, 295, 113593. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.psychres.2020.113593</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ebert, D., Tarnowski, T., Gollwitzer, M., Sieland, B., &amp; Berking, M. (2013). A transdiagnostic Internet‐based maintenance treatment enhances the stability of outcome after inpatient cognitive behavioral therapy: A randomized controlled trial. Psychotherapy and Psychosomatics, 82(4), 246–256. https://doi.org/10.1159/000345967</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erbiçer, E. S., Metin, A., Çetinkaya, A., &amp; Şen, S. (2021). The relationship between fear of COVID‐19 and depression, anxiety, and stress: A meta‐analysis. European Psychologist, 26(4), 323–333. https://doi.org/10.1027/1016-9040/a000464</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ettman, C. K., Abdalla, S. M., Cohen, G. H., Sampson, L., Vivier, P. M., &amp; Galea, S. (2020). Prevalence of depression symptoms in US adults before and during the COVID‐19 pandemic. JAMA Network Open, 3(9), e2019686–e2019686.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fisher, J. D., &amp; Fisher, W. A. (1992). Changing AIDS risk behavior. Psychological Bulletin, 111, 455–474. https://doi.org/10.1037/0033-2909.111.3.455</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haliwa, I., Wilson, J., Lee, J., &amp; Shook, N. J. (2021). Predictors of change in mental health during the COVID‐19 pandemic. Journal of Affective Disorders, 291, 331–337. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jad.2021.05.045</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamel, L., Kearney, A., Kirzinger, A., Lopes, L., Munana, C., &amp; Brodie, M., (2020). Kaiser Family Foundation Health Tracking Poll – July 2020. https://www.kff.org/coronavirus-covid-19/report/kff-health-tracking-poll-july-2020/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hardin, E. E., Weigold, I. K., Robitschek, C., &amp; Nixon, A. E. (2007). Self‐discrepancy and distress: The role of personal growth initiative. Journal of Counseling Psychology, 54(1), 86–92. https://doi.org/10.1037/0022-0167.54.1.86</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Henry, J. D., &amp; Crawford, J. R. (2005). The short‐form version of the depression anxiety stress scales (DASS‐21): Construct validity and normative data in a large non‐clinical sample. British Journal of Clinical Psychology, 44(2), 227–239. https://doi.org/10.1348/014466505X29657</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kira, I. A., Shuwiekh, H. A. M., Rice, K. G., Ashby, J. S., Elwakeel, S. A., Sous, M. S. F., Alhuwailah, A., Baali, S. B. A., Azdaou, C., Oliemat, E. M., &amp; Jamil, H. J. (2021). Measuring COVID‐19 as traumatic stress: Initial psychometrics and validation. Journal of Loss &amp; Trauma, 26(3), 220. https://doi.org/10.1080/15325024.2020.1790160</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lovibond, P. F., &amp; Lovibond, S. H. (1995). The structure of negative emotional states: Comparison of the Depression Anxiety Stress Scales (DASS) with the beck depression and anxiety inventories. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 33(3), 335–343. https://doi.org/10.1016/0005-7967(94)00075-U</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McGinty, E. E., Presskreischer, R., Han, H., &amp; Barry, C. L. (2020). Psychological distress and loneliness reported by US adults in 2018 and April 2020. Journal of the American Medical Association, 324(1), 93. https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2020.9740</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muthén, L. K., &amp; Muthén, B. O. (2021). Mplus (Version 8.6) [Computer software]. Muthén &amp; Muthén. https://www.statmodel.com/index.shtml</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>New York Times. (2022). Coronavirus in the U.S.: Latest Map and Case Count. https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2021/us/covid-cases.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niles, J. K., Gutierrez, D., Dukes, A. T., Mullen, P. R., &amp; Goode, C. D. (2022). Understanding the relationships between personal growth initiative, hope, and abstinence self‐efficacy. Journal of Addictions &amp; Offender Counseling, 43, 15–25. https://doi.org/10.1002/jaoc.12099</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pinto Pizarro de Freitas, C., Damásio, B. F., Tobo, P. R., Kamei, H. H., &amp; Koller, S. H. (2016). Systematic review about personal growth initiative. Anales de Psicología, 32(3), 770–782. https://doi.org/10.6018/analesps.32.3.219101</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robitschek, C. (1998). Personal growth initiative: The construct and its measure. Measurement and Evaluation in Counseling and Development, 30(4), 183–198.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robitschek, C. (1999). Further validation of the Personal Growth Initiative Scale. Measurement and Evaluation in Counseling and Development, 31(4), 197–210.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robitschek, C. (2003). Validity of Personal Growth Initiative Scale scores with a Mexican American college student population. Journal of Counseling Psychology, 50, 496–502. https://doi.org/10.1037/0022-0167.50.4.496</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robitschek, C., Ashton, M. W., Spering, C. C., Geiger, N., Byers, D., Schotts, G. C., &amp; Thoen, M. A. (2012). Development and psychometric evaluation of the Personal Growth Initiative Scale–II. Journal of Counseling Psychology, 59, 274–287. https://doi.org/10.1037/a0027310</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robitschek, C., Cukrowicz, K., Brown, S. L., &amp; Ciavaglia, A. (2022). Personal growth initiative as a buffer against suicide ideation severity in psychotherapy outpatients with depressive symptoms. Journal of Clinical Psychology, 78, 1752–1763. https://doi.org/10.1002/jclp.23333</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shigemoto, Y. (2021). Association between trajectories of personal growth initiative and post‐traumatic stress after Hurricane Harvey: A latent growth mixture modeling approach. Stress and Health, 37(2), 285–296. https://doi.org/10.1002/smi.2995</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shigemoto, Y. (2022). Association between daily rumination and posttraumatic growth during the COVID‐19 pandemic: An experience sampling method. Psychological Trauma: Theory, Research, Practice, and Policy, 14(2), 229–236. https://doi.org/10.1037/tra0001061</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sinclair, S. J., Siefert, C. J., Slavin‐Mulford, J. M., Stein, M. B., Renna, M., &amp; Blais, M. A. (2012). Psychometric evaluation and normative data for the Depression, Anxiety, and Stress Scales‐21 (DASS‐21) in a nonclinical sample of U.S. adults. Evaluation &amp; the Health Professions, 35(3), 259–279. https://doi.org/10.1177/0163278711424282</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simons, C. J. P., Drukker, M., Evers, S., van Mastrigt, G. A. P. G., Höhn, P., Kramer, I., Peeters, F., Delespaul, P., Menne-Lothmann, C., Hartmann, J. A., van Os, J., &amp; Wichers, M. (2017). Economic evaluation of an experience sampling method intervention in depression compared with treatment as usual using data from a randomized controlled trial. BMC Psychiatry, 17, 415. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12888-017-1577-7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thoen, M. A., &amp; Robitschek, C. (2013). Intentional growth training: Developing an intervention to increase personal growth initiative: Intentional growth training. Applied psychology. Health and well‐being, 5(2), 149–170. https://doi.org/10.1111/aphw.12001</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, C., Chudzicka‐Czupała, A., Tee, M. L., Núñez, M. I. L., Tripp, C., Fardin, M. A., Habib, H. A., Tran, B. X., Adamus, K., Anlacan, J., García, M. E. A., Grabowski, D., Hussain, S., Hoang, M. T., Hetnał, M., Le, X. T., Ma, W., Pham, H. Q., Reyes, P. W. C., … Sears, S. F. (2021). A chain mediation model on COVID‐19 symptoms and mental health outcomes in Americans, Asians and Europeans. Scientific Reports, 11(1), 6481. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-021-85943-7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, C., Tripp, C., Sears, S. F., Xu, L., Tan, Y., Zhou, D., Ma, W., Xu, Z., Chan, N. A., Ho, C., &amp; Ho, R. (2021). The impact of the COVID‐19 pandemic on physical and mental health in the two largest economies in the world: A comparison between the United States and China. Journal of Behavioral Medicine, 44(6), 741–759. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10865-021-00237-7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weigold, I. K., Weigold, A., Russell, E. J., Wolfe, G. L., Prowell, J. L., &amp; Martin, W. C. A. (2020). Personal growth initiative and mental health: A meta‐analysis. Journal of Counseling &amp; Development, 98(4), 376–390.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilson, J. M., Lee, J., Fitzgerald, H. N., Oosterhoff, B., Sevi, B., &amp; Shook, N. J. (2020). Job insecurity and financial concern during the COVID‐19 pandemic are associated with worse mental health. Journal of Occupational &amp; Environmental Medicine, 62(9), 686–691.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ziegelmann, J. P., Lippke, S., &amp; Schwarzer, R. (2006). Adoption and maintenance of physical activity: Planning interventions in young, middle‐aged, and older adults. Psychology &amp; Health, 21(2), 145–163. https://doi.org/10.1080/1476832050018891</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>