<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39463758</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2322-2220</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>12</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of advances in medical education &amp; professionalism</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Adv Med Educ Prof</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Expectation and Needs of Medical Students Towards the Implementation of Virtual Simulation in Learning Rational Use of Medicine.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>226</StartPage><EndPage>234</EndPage><MedlinePgn>226-234</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.30476/jamp.2024.102790.2010</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The irrational use of medicines remains prevalent globally despite education efforts, leading to decreased treatment quality and increased healthcare costs. With the rise of online learning during the COVID-19 pandemic, virtual simulation offers a promising solution to enhance the teaching of rational medicine use among medical students. This study aimed to investigate medical students' perspectives and needs regarding the implementation of virtual simulation in learning the rational use of medicines.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This study, conducted at Universitas Indonesia from August 2022 to September 2023, used a mixed-method approach to assess the needs for developing virtual simulation in education of rational medicine use. A validated questionnaire with 14 closed-ended and 14 open-ended questions was completed by 281 medical students. The quantitative data were analysed descriptively, using SPSS v16, while thematic analysis was applied to open-ended responses.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Students perceived virtual simulations to be the most effective tool for distance learning and suggested features like case scenarios, realistic representation, a good user interface, and user-friendly navigation. The majority preferred a 10-20-minute duration for virtual simulations. Additionally, 52.3% had no prior knowledge of the rational use of medicines, but acknowledged its importance. Virtual simulations could be used to explain the concept, management, and implementation of the rational use of medicines.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Virtual simulation should be implemented in distance learning on rational medicine use to increase students' motivation, understanding, retention, interactivity, and focus. The findings might be utilized by medical educators to tailor virtual simulation design to meet medical students' needs and expectations.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: © Journal of Advances in Medical Education &amp; Professionalism.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Krisnamurti</LastName><ForeName>Desak Gede Budi</ForeName><Initials>DGB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of e-Learning Cluster, Indonesian Medical Education and Research Institute (IMERI), Faculty of Medicine, Universitas Indonesia, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Pharmacy, Faculty of Medicine, Universitas Indonesia, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kekalih</LastName><ForeName>Aria</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of e-Learning Cluster, Indonesian Medical Education and Research Institute (IMERI), Faculty of Medicine, Universitas Indonesia, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, Universitas Indonesia, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dwijayanti</LastName><ForeName>Adisti</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Pharmacy, Faculty of Medicine, Universitas Indonesia, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Christianta</LastName><ForeName>David</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Undergraduate Medical Program, Faculty of Medicine, Universitas Indonesia, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wijaya</LastName><ForeName>Nicholas Jason</ForeName><Initials>NJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Undergraduate Medical Program, Faculty of Medicine, Universitas Indonesia, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Samudra</LastName><ForeName>Juan Felix</ForeName><Initials>JF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Undergraduate Medical Program, Faculty of Medicine, Universitas Indonesia, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rahadiani</LastName><ForeName>Pratiwi</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of e-Learning Cluster, Indonesian Medical Education and Research Institute (IMERI), Faculty of Medicine, Universitas Indonesia, Indonesia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Iran</Country><MedlineTA>J Adv Med Educ Prof</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101617859</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2322-2220</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Distance education</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Medical education</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Medication errors</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Simulation training</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39463758</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11511838</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.30476/jamp.2024.102790.2010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">JAMP-12-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>WHO.  Promoting rational use of medicines [Internet]. 2022 [Cited 2022 Feb 25] .  Available from: https://www.who.int/activities/improving-treatment-for-snakebite-patients. 
</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Humas Dinas Kesehatan Kota Bandung.  Dinkes Adakan Sosialisasi Penggunaan Obat Rasional (POR) [Internet]. Dinas Kesehatan Kota Bandung. 2019 [Cited 2022 Feb 27] .  Available from: https://dinkes.bandung.go.id/dinkes-adakan-sosialisasi-penggunaan-obat-rasional-por/ .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sodhi K, Singla MK. What’s new in critical illness and injury science? Rationale drug usage - A long way ahead! Int J Crit Illn Inj Sci. 2013;3(4):227.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3891186</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24459617</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mao W, Tang S, Chen W. Does perverse economic incentive lead to the irrational uses of medicines? Expert Rev Pharmacoecon Outcomes Res. 2013;13(6):693–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24219043</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>INRUD.  Promoting Rational Use of Drug, International Network Rational Use of Drug [Internet]. 2002 [Cited 2 July 2002] .  Available from: http://haiweb.org .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. The role of education in the rational use of medicines. New Delhi: World Health Organization, Regional Office for South-East Asia; 2006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Killam LA, Luctkar-Flude M. Virtual Simulations to Replace Clinical Hours in a Family Assessment Course: Development Using H5P, Gamification, and Student Co-Creation. Clin Simul Nurs. 2021;57:59–65.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garira E. Needs assessment for the development of educational interventions to improve quality of education: A case of Zimbabwean primary schools. Social Sciences &amp; Humanities Open. 2020;2(1):100020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patrício KP, Alves NAB, Arenales NG, Queluz TT. Teaching the Rational Use of Medicinesto medical students: a qualitative research. BMC Med Educ. 2012;12(1):56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3548729</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22812522</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Budakoğlu Iİ, Coşkun Ö, Kıyak YS, Uluoğlu C. Teaching rational prescribing in undergraduate medical education: a systematic search and review. Eur J Clin Pharmacol. 2023;79(3):341–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36622428</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coombes ID, Mitchell CA, Stowasser DA. Safe medication practice: attitudes of medical students about to begin their intern year. Med Educ. 2008;42(4):427–31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18338996</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heaton A, Webb DJ, Maxwell SRJ. Undergraduate preparation for prescribing: the views of 2413 UK medical students and recent graduates. Br J Clin Pharmacol. 2008;66(1):128–34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2485268</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18492128</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coyne E, Calleja P, Forster E, Lin F. A review of virtual-simulation for assessing healthcare students’ clinical competency. Nurse Educ Today. 2021;96:104623.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33125979</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Q, Wang Y, Lu L, Chen Y, Long H, Wang J. Virtual Simulation in Undergraduate Medical Education: A Scoping Review of Recent Practice. Front Med (Lausanne). 2022;9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9006810</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35433717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Foronda CL. What Is Virtual Simulation? Clin Simul Nurs. 2021;52:8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen J, Liang M. Play hard, study hard? The influence of gamification on students’ study engagement. Front Psychol. 2022;13:994700.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9589250</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36300058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mukhtar K, Javed K, Arooj M, Sethi A. Advantages, Limitations and Recommendations for online learning during COVID-19 pandemic era. Pak J Med Sci. 2020;36(COVID19-S4):S27–S31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7306967</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32582310</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leibold N, Schwarz L. Virtual Simulations: A Creative, Evidence-Based Approach to Develop and Educate Nurses. Creat Nurs. 2017;23(1):29–34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28196565</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dalbey S. Selection of virtual simulation products: making the right choice. Teaching and Learning in Nursing. 2021;16(2):135–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jallad ST, Işık B. The effectiveness of virtual reality simulation as learning strategy in the acquisition of medical skills in nursing education: a systematic review. Irish Journal of Medical Science. 2022;191(3):1407–26.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34227032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edgar AK, Macfarlane S, Kiddell EJ, Armitage JA, Wood-Bradley RJ. The perceived value and impact of virtual simulation-based education on students’ learning: a mixed methods study. BMC Med Educ. 2022;22(1):823.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9709374</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36451222</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barton AC, Sheen J, Byrne LK. Immediate Attention Enhancement and Restoration from Interactive and Immersive Technologies: A Scoping Review. Front Psychol. 2020;11:2050.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7466741</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32973620</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Herrera-Aliaga E, Estrada LD. Trends and Innovations of Simulation for Twenty First Century Medical Education. Front Public Health. 2022;10:619769.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8929194</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35309206</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sparrow R, Dartanto T, Hartwig R. Indonesia Under the New Normal: Challenges and the Way Ahead. Bull Indones Econ Stud. 2020;56(3):269–99.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H5P.  H5P [Internet]. 2022 [Cited 2022 Sep 16] .  Available from: https://h5p.org/ .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muthuprasad T, Aiswarya S, Aditya KS, Jha GK. Students’ perception and preference for online education in India during COVID -19 pandemic. Social sciences &amp; humanities open. 2021;3(1):100101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7836920</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34173507</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Q, Wang Y, Lu L, Chen Y, Long H, Wang J. Virtual Simulation in Undergraduate Medical Education: A Scoping Review of Recent Practice. Front Med (Lausanne). 2022;9:855403.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9006810</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35433717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang KC, Bernardoni ED, Cotter EJ, Levine BR, Frank RM. The Impact of Unguided Trauma Simulation Practice on Novice Performance: A Randomized Controlled Trial. Journal of the American Academy of Orthopaedic Surgeons. 2021;29(6):255–62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32694328</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rudolphi-Solero T, Jimenez-Zayas A, Lorenzo-Alvarez R, Domínguez-Pinos D, Ruiz-Gomez MJ, Sendra-Portero F. A team-based competition for undergraduate medical students to learn radiology within the virtual world Second Life. Insights Imaging. 2021;12(1):89.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8241985</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34185165</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu L, Zhang L, Yin R, Li Z, Shen J, Tan H, et al. NEOGAMES: A Serious Computer Game That Improves Long-Term Knowledge Retention of Neonatal Resuscitation in Undergraduate Medical Students. Front Pediatr. 2021;9:645776.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8096897</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33968850</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tomlinson A, Simpson A, Killingback C. Student expectations of teaching and learning when starting university: a systematic review. J Furth High Educ. 2023;47(8):1054–73.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>