<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39466553</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1872-4353</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>28</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of bioethical inquiry</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Bioeth Inq</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Clinicians' Perspectives and an Ethical Analysis of Safer Supply Opioid Prescribing.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s11673-024-10387-3</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>In British Columbia, Canada, many physicians providing care to individuals with high-risk opioid use disorder adopted safer supply (SS) opioid prescribing in the spring of 2020 with the goal of facilitating public health measures for COVID-19. This prescribing practice continued after measures were lifted. This study aimed to explore prescribers' perspectives following several years of local experience in prescribing SS opioids, primarily in the form of hydromorphone tablets, and to apply ethical concepts to explore current challenges and ongoing sources of provider distress. Addiction medicine SS prescribers participated in individual or small group semi-structured interviews. Each interview was transcribed and analysed for recurrent themes. Themes were then integrated into a narrative ethics discussion. Eleven addiction medicine physicians practicing in various settings within Vancouver participated in this study. Six themes were identified: clinical assessment, clinician distress, gaps in care, models of safer supply, research, and special populations. Ethical dilemmas in prescribing SS are identified and explored through a discussion of biomedical ethics principles and the physician role.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. Journal of Bioethical Inquiry Pty Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bird</LastName><ForeName>Kathleen</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>British Columbia Centre On Substance Use, 400-1045 Howe Street, Vancouver, BC, V6Z 2A9, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Genuis</LastName><ForeName>Quentin</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Emergency Medicine, University of British Columbia, St. Paul's Hospital, 608-1081 Burrard Street, Vancouver, B.C, V6Z 1Y6, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ickowicz</LastName><ForeName>Sarah</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0562-8035</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, University of British Columbia, St. Paul's Hospital, 608-1081 Burrard Street, Vancouver, B.C, V6Z 1Y6, Canada. sickowicz@providencehealth.bc.ca.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>J Bioeth Inq</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101250741</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1176-7529</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bioethics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Clinical ethics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Harm reduction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Opiate overdose</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Opioid use disorder</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39466553</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11673-024-10387-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s11673-024-10387-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Bardwell, G. 2022. More than a pipe dream? The need to adapt safer opioid supply programs for people who smoke drugs. Journal of Studies on Alcohol and Drugs 83(3): 309–311.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15288/jsad.2022.83.309</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35590170</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bardwell, G., J.M. Bowles, M. Mansoor, D. Werb, and T. Kerr. 2023. Access to tablet injectable opioid agonist therapy in rural and smaller urban settings in British Columbia, Canada: A qualitative study. Substance Abuse Treatment, Prevention and Policy 18: 14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13011-023-00525-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36869358</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bardwell, G., A. Ivsins, M.E. Socías, and T. Kerr. 2021a. Examining factors that shape use and access to diverted prescription opioids during an overdose crisis: A qualitative study in Vancouver, Canada. Journal of Substance Abuse Treatment 130: 108418.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bardwell, G., W. Small, J. Lavalley, R. McNeil, and T. Kerr. 2021b. "People need them or else they’re going to take fentanyl and die": A qualitative study examining the "problem" of prescription opioid diversion during an overdose epidemic. Social Science &amp; Medicine 279: 113986.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beauchamp, T., and J. Childress. 2019. Principles of biomedical ethics. 8<sup>th</sup> ed. Oxford: Oxford University Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>British Columbia Centre for Disease Control. 2021a. Post-mortem detection of hydromorphone among persons identified as having an illicit drug toxicity death since the introduction of risk mitigation guidance prescribing. September 15. http://www.bccdc.ca/resource-gallery/Documents/Statistics%20and%20Research/Statistics%20and%20Reports/Overdose/2021.09.15_Knowledge%20Update_Hydromorphone%20and%20drug%20toxicity%20deaths.pdf . Accessed October 11, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>____. 2021b. Post-mortem detection of hydromorphone among persons identified as having an illicit drug toxicity death since the introduction of risk mitigation guidance prescribing: Toxicology supplement. http://www.bccdc.ca/resource-gallery/Documents/Statistics%20and%20Research/Statistics%20and%20Reports/Overdose/20211209_BCCDC%20Knowledge%20Update_RMG%20Evaluation%20Hydromorphone%20Tox%20Supplement.pdf . Accessed June 19, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>British Columbia Centre on Substance Use. 2019. Heroin compassion clubs. February. https://www.bccsu.ca/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/Report-Heroin-Compassion-Clubs.pdf . Accessed October 11, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>____. 2022. Fentanyl patch: Prescribed safer supply protocols. https://www.bccsu.ca/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Prescribed-Safer-Supply-Protocols-Fentanyl-Patch.pdf . Accessed October 11, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>____. 2023. Prescribed safer supply protocols: Sufentanil. September. https://www.bccsu.ca/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/PSS-Protocols-Sufentanil.pdf . Accessed October 11, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>British Columbia Centre on Substance Use, BC Ministry of Health, and Ministry of Mental Health and Addictions. 2022. Risk mitigation in the context of dual health emergencies—interim clinical guidance: Update. January. https://www.bccsu.ca/COVID-19 . Accessed October 11, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>British Columbia Coroners Service. 2024. Youth unregulated drug toxicity deaths in British Columbia. May 29. https://www2.gov.bc.ca/assets/gov/birth-adoption-death-marriage-and-divorce/deaths/coroners-service/statistical/youth_unregulated_drug_toxicity_deaths_in_bc_2019-2023.pdf . Accessed October 10, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brothers, T.D., M. Leaman, M. Bonn, et al. 2022. Evaluation of an emergency safe supply drugs and managed alcohol program in COVID-19 isolation hotel shelters for people experiencing homelessness. Drug and Alcohol Dependence 235: 109440.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2022.109440</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35461084</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8988445</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Canadian Association of People Who Use Drugs. 2019. Safe supply concept document. https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.5637606 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dunn, K.E. 2022. Advocating for a thoughtful expansion of safer supply to realize bold impact on opioid overdose. Journal of Studies on Alcohol and Drugs 83(4): 621–622.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15288/jsad.2022.83.621</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35838441</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duthie, K., E. Mathison, H. Eyford, and S.M. Ghosh. 2023. Prescribing safe supply: Ethical considerations for clinicians. Journal of Medical Ethics 49(6): 377–382.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/jme-2021-108087</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35985806</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eydt, E., S. Glegg, C. Sutherland, et al. 2021. Service delivery models for injectable opioid agonist treatment in Canada: 2 sequential environmental scans. CMAJ Open 9(1): E115–124.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.9778/cmajo.20200021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33622764</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8034381</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Federal, Provincial, and Territorial Special Advisory Committee on the Epidemic of Opioid Overdoses. 2023. Opioid- and stimulant-related harms in Canada. Ottawa: Public Health Agency of Canada, September. https://health-infobase.canada.ca/substance-related-harms/opioids-stimulants . Accessed October 11, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferri, M., M. Davoli, and C.A. Perucci. 2011. Heroin maintenance for chronic heroin-dependent individuals. Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews 2011(12): CD003410.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Foreman-Mackey, A., B. Pauly, A. Ivsins, K. Urbanoski, M. Mansoor, and G. Bardwell. 2022. Moving towards a continuum of safer supply options for people who use drugs: A qualitative study exploring national perspectives on safer supply among professional stakeholders in Canada. Substance Abuse Treatment, Prevention and Policy 17(1): 1–11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13011-022-00494-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gehring, N.D., K.A. Speed, T.C. Wild, B. Pauly, G. Salvalaggio, and E. Hyshka. 2022. Policy actor views on structural vulnerability in harm reduction and policymaking for illegal drugs: A qualitative study. The International Journal of Drug Policy 108: 103805.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.drugpo.2022.103805</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35907373</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Genuis, Q.I.T. 2021. A genealogy of autonomy: Freedom, paternalism, and the future of the doctor–patient relationship. The Journal of Medicine and Philosophy 46(3): 330–349.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jmp/jhab004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33948633</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8188809</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giang, K., R. Charlesworth, M. Thulien, et al. 2023. Risk mitigation guidance and safer supply prescribing among young people who use drugs in the context of COVID-19 and overdose emergencies. The International Journal of Drug Policy 115: 104023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.drugpo.2023.104023</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37059025</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glegg, S., K. McCrae, G. Kolla, et al. 2022. "COVID just kind of opened a can of whoop-ass": The rapid growth of safer supply prescribing during the pandemic documented through an environmental scan of addiction and harm reduction services in Canada. The International Journal of Drug Policy 106: 103742.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.drugpo.2022.103742</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35679695</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gomes, T., G. Kolla, D. McCormack, A. Sereda, S. Kitchen, and T. Antoniou. 2022. Clinical outcomes and health care costs among people entering a safer opioid supply program in Ontario. CMAJ 194(36): E1233–E1242.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1503/cmaj.220892</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36122919</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9484622</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Government of Canada: Health Canada. 2022. Early findings from safer supply pilot projects. March 17. https://www.canada.ca/en/health-canada/services/opioids/responding-canada-opioid-crisis/safer-supply/early-findings-safer-supply-pilot-projects.html . Accessed October 11, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haines, M., and P. O’Byrne. 2023. Safer opioid supply: Qualitative program evaluation. Harm Reduction Journal 20: 53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12954-023-00776-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37081500</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10117245</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ivsins, A., J. Boyd, L. Beletsky, and R. McNeil. 2020. Tackling the overdose crisis: The role of safe supply. The International Journal of Drug Policy 80: 102769.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ivsins, A., J. Boyd, S. Mayer, et al. 2020. Barriers and facilitators to a novel low-barrier hydromorphone distribution program in Vancouver, Canada: A qualitative study. Drug and Alcohol Dependence 216: 108202.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>____. 2021. "It’s helped me a lot, just like to stay alive": A qualitative analysis of outcomes of a novel hydromorphone tablet distribution program in Vancouver, Canada. Journal of Urban Health 98(1): 59–69.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11524-020-00489-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33118145</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ivsins, A., L. MacKinnon, J.M. Bowles, A. Slaunwhite, and G. Bardwell. 2022. Overdose prevention and housing: A qualitative study examining drug use, overdose risk, and access to safer supply in permanent supportive housing in Vancouver, Canada. Journal of Urban Health 99(5): 855–864.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11524-022-00679-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36044156</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klaire, S., C. Sutherland, T. Kerr, and M.C. Kennedy. 2022. A low-barrier, flexible safe supply program to prevent deaths from overdose. Canadian Medical Association Journal 194(19): E674–E676.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1503/cmaj.211515</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35577374</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9438736</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lew, B., C. Bodkin, R. Lennox, T. O’Shea, G. Wiwcharuk, and S. Turner. 2022. The impact of an integrated safer use space and safer supply program on non-fatal overdose among emergency shelter residents during a COVID-19 outbreak: A case study. Harm Reduction Journal 19(1): 29.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12954-022-00614-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35313903</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8935259</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCrae, K., S. Glegg, M.É. Goyer, et al. 2022. The changing landscape of pharmaceutical alternatives to the unregulated drug supply during COVID-19. Harm Reduction Journal 19(1): 1–77.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12954-022-00657-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McNeil, R., T. Fleming, S. Mayer, et al. 2022. Implementation of safe supply alternatives during intersecting COVID-19 and overdose health emergencies in British Columbia, Canada, 2021. American Journal of Public Health 112(S2): S151–S158.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2021.306692</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35262376</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8965179</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Mental Health and Addictions and Ministry of Health. 2021. Access to prescribed safer supply in British Columbia: Policy direction, July. https://www2.gov.bc.ca/assets/gov/overdose-awareness/prescribed_safer_supply_in_bc.pdf . Accessed May 5, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nosyk, B., A. Slaunwhite, K. Urbanoski, et al. 2021. Evaluation of risk mitigation measures for people with substance use disorders to address the dual public health crises of COVID-19 and overdose in British Columbia: A mixed-method study protocol. BMJ Open 11(6): e048353.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2020-048353</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34108170</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olding, M., A. Ivsins, S. Mayer, et al. 2020. A low-barrier and comprehensive community-based harm-reduction site in Vancouver, Canada. American Journal of Public Health (1971) 110(6): 833–835.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oviedo-Joekes, E., S. Brissette, D.C. Marsh, et al. 2009. Diacetylmorphine versus methadone for the treatment of opioid addiction. The New England Journal of Medicine 361(8): 777–786.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa0810635</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19692689</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5127701</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oviedo-Joekes, E., S. Dobischok, J. Carvajal, et al. 2023. Clients’ experiences on North America’s first take-home injectable opioid agonist treatment (iOAT) program: A qualitative study. BMC Health Services Research 23(1): 553.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12913-023-09558-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37237256</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10215060</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oviedo-Joekes, E., D. Guh, S. Brissette, et al. 2016. Hydromorphone compared with diacetylmorphine for long-term opioid dependence: A randomized clinical trial. JAMA Psychiatry 73(5): 447–455.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2016.0109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27049826</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oviedo-Joekes, E., S. MacDonald, C. Boissonneault, and K. Harper. 2021. Take home injectable opioids for opioid use disorder during and after the COVID-19 pandemic is in urgent need: A case study. Substance Abuse Treatment, Prevention, and Policy 16(1): 22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13011-021-00358-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33673847</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7935000</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rieder, T.N. 2020. Solving the opioid crisis isn’t just a public health challenge—it’s a bioethics challenge. The Hastings Center Report 50(4): 24–32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/hast.1169</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33448415</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmidt, R.A., N. Kaminski, D.T. Kryszajtys, et al. 2023. "I don’t chase drugs as much anymore, and I’m not dead": Client reported outcomes associated with safer opioid supply programs in Ontario, Canada. Drug and Alcohol Review, September, dar.13745.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Slaunwhite, A., J.E. Min, H. Palis, et al. 2024. Effect of risk mitigation guidance for opioid and stimulant dispensations on mortality and acute care visits during dual public health emergencies: Retrospective cohort study. BMJ 384: e076336.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj-2023-076336</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38199614</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10777271</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strang, J., T. Groshkova, A. Uchtenhagen, et al. 2015. Heroin on trial: Systematic review and meta-analysis of randomised trials of diamorphine-prescribing as treatment for refractory heroin addiction. British Journal of Psychiatry 207(1): 5–14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1192/bjp.bp.114.149195</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Time. 2021. The "safe supply" movement aims to curb drug deaths linked to the opioid crisis. October 25. https://time.com/6108812/drug-deaths-safe-supply-opioids . Accessed October 11, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tyndall, M. 2020. A safer drug supply: A pragmatic and ethical response to the overdose crisis. Canadian Medical Association Journal 192(34): E986–E987.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1503/cmaj.201618</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7840515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vears, D.F., and L. Gillam. 2022. Inductive content analysis: A guide for beginning qualitative researchers. Focus on Health Professional Education: A Multi-Professional Journal 23(1): 111–127.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.11157/fohpe.v23i1.544</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weng, J., N. Fairbairn, C. Sutherland, C. Johnson, and S. Nolan. 2022. Supervised tablet injectable opioid agonist therapy (TiOAT): A strategy to address safer supply for individuals with an opioid use disorder? Journal of Addiction Medicine 16(3): 258–260.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/ADM.0000000000000887</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34145188</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Young, S., G. Kolla, D. McCormack, et al. 2022. Characterizing safer supply prescribing of immediate release hydromorphone for individuals with opioid use disorder across Ontario, Canada. The International Journal of Drug Policy 102: 103601.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.drugpo.2022.103601</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35124413</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>