<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39468571</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1743-422X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>21</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>28</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Virology journal</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Virol J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>First detection of D181 genotype of infectious bronchitis in poultry flocks of Morocco.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>267</StartPage><MedlinePgn>267</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12985-024-02539-z</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">This paper reports the first pathological and molecular characterization of the novel variant of infectious bronchitis virus (IBV) D181 in poultry flocks in Morocco and Africa.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">The study includes six poultry farms, involving three flocks of layers aged between 28 and 67 weeks and three broiler flocks aged 27, 39 and 42 days from different regions of Morocco. In all affected layer flocks, a severe drop in egg production with poor eggshell quality was reported. Necropsy of dead birds was carried out, and samples of trachea, lungs, oviduct, ovaries, and kidneys were fixed in 10% neutral buffered formalin for histopathologic examinations, while other portions were stored at -20 °C for molecular analysis. Real time RT-qPCR for IBV gene group was performed, and IBV variants were identified. Partial S1 gene sequences were amplified by conventional RT-PCR, sequenced, and aligned for phylogenetic and amino acid similarity analysis.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Necropsy of dead birds revealed misshapen and hemorrhagic ovarian follicles with an edematous oviduct and severe reaction in the cecal tonsils. A caseous material accumulation in the sinus was noted in few birds. In contrast, the broiler flocks exhibited respiratory clinical signs such as difficulty in breathing, sneezing, tracheal rales, watery eyes and lethargy, associated with a decrease in feed consumption. Mortality in broiler ranged from 2 to 15%. Histopathological analysis of samples showed a lympho-plasmocytic inflammation in the oviduct, trachea, and lungs. Individual necrosis of epithelial cells, with sloughing of the bronchial epithelium and accumulation of desquamated cells with mucus in the airways, was observed in some birds. Partial S1 gene sequencing and phylogenetic analyses showed that the Moroccan strains were very closely related to D181 strains isolated in Dutch layers and breeders in 2018. Nucleotide sequence identities reached 90.9-95% with the Dutch isolates (strain CK/NL/D181/2018).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Our sequencing results demonstrate for the first time that the D181 IBV genotype is circulating in Moroccan poultry. These findings justify permanent monitoring of circulating strains in order to appropriately adjust vaccination strategies to align with the evolving field situation.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Mohamed</LastName><ForeName>Mouahid</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Mouahid's Veterinary Clinic, Temara, 12000, Morocco.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Yassmina</LastName><ForeName>Bidoudan</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Mouahid's Veterinary Clinic, Temara, 12000, Morocco.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Pathology and Public Health, Agronomy and Veterinary Institute Hassan II, Rabat-Instituts, Rabat, BP 6202, Morocco.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rim</LastName><ForeName>Regragui</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Pathology and Public Health, Agronomy and Veterinary Institute Hassan II, Rabat-Instituts, Rabat, BP 6202, Morocco.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mouna</LastName><ForeName>El Kaouani</ForeName><Initials>EK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Pathology and Public Health, Agronomy and Veterinary Institute Hassan II, Rabat-Instituts, Rabat, BP 6202, Morocco.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Siham</LastName><ForeName>Fellahi</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Pathology and Public Health, Agronomy and Veterinary Institute Hassan II, Rabat-Instituts, Rabat, BP 6202, Morocco. fellahisiham2015@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Virol J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101231645</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1743-422X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001351" MajorTopicYN="Y">Infectious bronchitis virus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="N">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000145" MajorTopicYN="N">classification</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011201" MajorTopicYN="Y">Poultry Diseases</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018352" MajorTopicYN="Y">Coronavirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000662" MajorTopicYN="N">veterinary</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010802" MajorTopicYN="Y">Phylogeny</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002645" MajorTopicYN="Y">Chickens</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009018" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Morocco</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005838" MajorTopicYN="Y">Genotype</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Avian coronavirus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">D181</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">IBV</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Infectious bronchitis virus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Morocco</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Poultry</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39468571</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12985-024-02539-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12985-024-02539-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>-De Wit JJ, Cook JK, Van der Heijden HM. Infectious bronchitis virus variants: a review of the history, current situation and control measures. Avian Pathol. 2011;40:223–35. https://doi.org/10.1080/03079457.2011.566260</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/03079457.2011.566260</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Jackwood MW. Review of infectious bronchitis virus around the world. Avian dis. 2012;56:634–41. https://doi.org/10.1637/10227-043012-Review.1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1637/10227-043012-Review.1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23397833</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Cavanagh D. Coronavirus avian infectious bronchitis virus. Vet Res. 2007;38:281–97. https://doi.org/10.1051/vetres:2006055</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1051/vetres:2006055</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17296157</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Xu L, Ren M, Sheng J, Ma T, Han Z, Zhao Y, Sun J, Liu S. Genetic and biological characteristics of four novel recombinant avian infectious bronchitis viruses isolated in China. Virus res. 2019;263:87–97. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.virusres.2019.01.007</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.virusres.2019.01.007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30641197</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Jackwood MW, de Wit S. Infectious bronchitis. In: Swayne DE, editor. Diseases of poultry. Hoboken (NJ): Wiley; 2013. pp. 139–59.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/9781119421481.ch4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Cavanagh D. Coronaviruses in poultry and other birds. Avian Pathol. 2005;34:439–48. https://doi.org/10.1080/03079450500367682</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/03079450500367682</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16537157</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Cavanagh D, Elus MM, Cook JKA. Relationship between sequence variation in the S1 spike protein of infectious bronchitis virus and the extent of cross-protection in vivo. Avian Pathol. 1997;26:63–74. https://doi.org/10.1080/03079459708419194</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/03079459708419194</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18484262</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>-De Wit JJ, Cazaban C, Dijkman R, Ramon G, Gardin Y. Detection of different genotypes of infectious bronchitis virus and of infectious bursal disease virus in European broilers during an epidemiological study in 2013 and the consequences for the diagnostic approach. Avian Pathol. 2018;47:140–51. https://doi.org/10.1080/03079457.2017.1387231</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/03079457.2017.1387231</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28972403</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Marandino A, Vagnozzi A, Craig MI, Tomás G, Techera C, Panzera Y, Vera F, Pérez R. Genetic and antigenic heterogeneity of infectious bronchitis virus in South America: implications for control programmes. Avian Pathol. 2019;48:270–7. https://doi.org/10.1080/03079457.2019.1583315</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/03079457.2019.1583315</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30761909</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Jackwood MW, Hilt DA, McCall AW, Polizzi CN, McKinley ET, Williams SM. Infectious bronchitis virus field vaccination coverage and persistence of Arkansas-type viruses in commercial broilers. Avian dis. 2009;53:175–83. https://doi.org/10.1637/8465-090308-Reg.1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1637/8465-090308-Reg.1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19630221</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>-El Houadfi M, Jones R. Isolation of avian infectious bronchitis viruses in Morocco including an enterotropic variant. Vet Rec. 1985; 16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Jones RC, Savage CE, Naylor CJ, Cook JKA, El-Houadfi M. A possible North African progenitor of the major European infectious bronchitis virus variant (793B, 4/91, CR88, etc.). In: Heffels-Redmann U, Kaleta Ef, editors. Proceedings of the IV International symposium on avian corona-and pneumovirus infections; 2004 June 20–23; Rauischholzhausen (Germany). Wettenberg: VVB Laufersweiler Verlag. 2004. pp. 105–111.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Fellahi S, Harrak ME, Kuhn JH, Sebbar G, Bouaiti EA, Khataby K, Fassi Fihri O, El Houadfi M, Ennaji MM. Comparison of SYBR green I real-time RT-PCR with conventional agarose gel-based RT-PCR for the diagnosis of infectious bronchitis virus infection in chickens in Morocco. BMC Res Notes. 2016;9:1–9. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13104-016-2037-z</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13104-016-2037-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Fellahi S, Ducatez M, El Harrak M, Guérin J-L, Touil N, Sebbar G, Bouaiti E, Khataby K, Ennaji MM, El Houadfi M. Prevalence and molecular characterization of avian infectious bronchitis virus in poultry flocks in Morocco from 2010 to 2014 and first detection of Italy 02 in Africa. Avian Pathol. 2015;44:287–95. https://doi.org/10.1080/03079457.2015.1044422</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/03079457.2015.1044422</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25925561</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Sikht FZ, Camus C, Ducatez M, Kraimi M, Touzani CD, Tligui NS, El Houadfi M, Fellahi S. Prévalence De La Maladie De La Bronchite infectieuse aviaire Au Maroc entre juin 2018 et Avril 2019. Rev Maroc Des Sci Agron et Vétérinaires. 2021;9:434–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Belkasmi S, Fellahi S, Guerin J-L, Fassi Fihri O, Ducatez M, EL-Houadfi M. Etude moléculaire et phylogénique des souches du virus de la bronchite infectieuse aviaire circulants sur le terrain au Maroc entre 2015 et 2018. In: Editor. Proceedings des 10èmes Journées de l’Association marocaine de pathologie aviaire; 2018 Nov (jours), Tanger (Morocco). 2018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Fellahi S, Ducatez M, Mouahid M, Belkasmi S, EL-Houadfi M. 2022. Epidemiology and Molecular evolution of avian infectious bronchitis virus in Morocco between 2010–2022. In: Editor. Proceedings of the First World Veterinary Poultry Association-Africa Meeting Avian influenza, a threat for African poultry production and trade; 2022 June 23–25; Marrakech (Morocco). 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Wise MG, Suarez DL, Seal BS, Pedersen JC, Senne DA, King DJ, et al. Development of a real-time reverse-transcription PCR for detection of Newcastle Disease virus RNA in clinical samples. J Clin Microbiol. 2004;42:329–38. https://doi.org/10.1128/jcm.42.1.329-338.2004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/jcm.42.1.329-338.2004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">321685</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14715773</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Monne I, Ormelli S, Salviato A, De Battisti C, Bettini F, Salomoni A, et al. Development and validation of a one-step real-time PCR assay for simultaneous detection of subtype H5, H7, and H9 avian influenza viruses. J Clin Microbiol. 2008;46:1769–73. https://doi.org/10.1128/jcm.02204-07</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/jcm.02204-07</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2395090</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18367569</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Callison S, Riblet S, Oldoni I, Sun S, Zavala G, Williams S, et al. Development and validation of a real-time Taqman<sup>®</sup> PCR assay for the detection and quantitation of infectious laryngotracheitis virus in poultry. J Virol Methods. 2007;139:31–8. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jviromet.2006.09.001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jviromet.2006.09.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17030068</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Mo J, Angelichio M, Gow L, Leathers V, Jackwood MW. Quantitative real-time PCR assays for the concurrent diagnosis of infectious laryngotracheitis virus, Newcastle Disease virus and avian metapneumovirus in poultry. J Vet Sci. 2022;23:e21. https://doi.org/10.4142/jvs.21153</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4142/jvs.21153</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35187879</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Callison SA, Hilt DA, Boynton TO, Sample BF, Robison R, Swayne DE, et al. Development and evaluation of a real-time Taqman RT-PCR assay for the detection of infectious bronchitis virus from infected chickens. J Virol Methods. 2006;138:60–5. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jviromet.2006.07.018</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jviromet.2006.07.018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16934878</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Jones RC, Worthington KJ, Capua I, Naylor CJ. Efficacy of live infectious bronchitis vaccines against a novel European genotype, Italy 02. Vet Rec-English Ed. 2005;156:646–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/vr.156.20.646</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Molenaar RJ, Dijkman R, De Wit JJ. Characterization of infectious bronchitis virus D181, a new serotype (GII-2). Avian Pathol. 2020;49:243–50. https://doi.org/10.1080/03079457.2020.1713987</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/03079457.2020.1713987</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31951468</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Hall TA. BioEdit: a user-friendly biological sequence alignment editor and analysis program for Windows 95/98/NT. Nucleic Acids Symp ser. 1999;41:95–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>-National Center for Biotechnology Information, Bethesda MD. http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi , Accessed 10 November 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tamura K, Stecher G, Peterson D, Filipski A, Kumar S. MEGA6: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 6.0. Mol Biol Evol. 2013;30:2725–9. https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/mst197</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/molbev/mst197</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3840312</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24132122</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Tamura K, Peterson D, Peterson N, Stecher G, Nei M, Kumar S. MEGA5: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis using maximum likelihood, evolutionary distance, and maximum parsimony methods. Mol Biol Evol. 2011;28:2731–9. https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msr121</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/molbev/msr121</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21546353</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Chen L, Xiang B, Hong Y, Li Q, Du H, Lin Q, Liao M, Ren T, Xu C. Phylogenetic analysis of infectious bronchitis virus circulating in southern China in 2016–2017 and evaluation of an attenuated strain as a vaccine candidate. Arch Virol. 2021;166:73–81. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00705-020-04851-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00705-020-04851-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33067648</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Valastro V, Holmes EC, Britton P, Fusaro A, Jackwood MW, Cattoli G, Monne I. S1 gene-based phylogeny of infectious bronchitis virus: an attempt to harmonize virus classification. Infect Genet Evol. 2016;39:349–64. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.meegid.2016.02.015</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.meegid.2016.02.015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7172980</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26883378</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Raviv Z, Ley HD. Mycoplasma gallisepticum infection. In: Swayne DE, editor. Diseases of poultry. Hoboken (NJ): Wiley; 2013. pp. 877–93.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Barnes HJ, Fletcher OJ, Abdul-Aziz T. Reproductive system. In: Abdul-Aziz T, Fletcher OJ, Barnes HJ, editors. Avian histopathology. American Association of Avian Pathologists, Jacksonville (FL). 2016. pp. 581–613.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Domanska-Blicharz K, Lisowska A, Minta Z, Jatczak J, Mamczur J. D1466-like genotype of infectious bronchitis virus responsible for a new epidemic in chickens in Poland. Vet Rec. 2012;171:351. https://doi.org/10.1136/vr.100888</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/vr.100888</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22903901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Fédération. interprofessionnelle du secteur avicole au Maroc (FISA), https://www.fisamaroc.org.ma , accessed 24 January 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Lin SY, Chen HW. Infectious bronchitis virus variants: molecular analysis and pathogenicity investigation. Int J Mol Sci. 2017; 18 : 2030. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms18102030</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>-De Wit JJ, De Wit MK, Cook JA. Infectious bronchitis virus types affecting European countries—A review. Avian Dis. 2021;65:643–8. https://doi.org/10.1637/aviandiseases-D-21-00106</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1637/aviandiseases-D-21-00106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35068110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Vermeulen CJ, Dijkman R, de Wit JJ, Bosch BJ, Heesterbeek JAP, van Schaik G. Genetic analysis of infectious bronchitis virus (IBV) in vaccinated poultry populations over a period of 10 years. Avian Pathol. 2023;52:157–67. https://doi.org/10.1080/03079457.2023.2177140</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/03079457.2023.2177140</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10243407</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36745131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>-Legnardi M, Tucciarone CM, Franzo G, Cecchinato M. Infectious bronchitis virus evolution, diagnosis and control. Vet Sci. 2020;7:79. https://doi.org/10.3390/vetsci7020079</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/vetsci7020079</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7356646</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32580381</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>