<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39466499</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2731-4383</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>4</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>28</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Discover mental health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Discov Ment Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Social support and mental health outcomes in palestinian children victims of bullying and cyberbullying during the covid-19 pandemic: an exploratory investigation.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>48</StartPage><MedlinePgn>48</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s44192-024-00100-6</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Studies have shown that COVID-19 negatively impacted mental health by increasing depression and anxiety. Additionally, bullying might deteriorate children's psychological functioning. Nevertheless, social support has been studied as a positive buffer for mental well-being.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">Thus, our study aimed to examine the consequences of the COVID-19 outbreak on children's mental health when they are a victim of bullying and cyberbullying. Moreover, we tested the effect of social support as a mediating variable. A sample of 141 children (63 boys and 78 girls) 9 to 13 years old (M = 10.31, SD = 2.26) who reported having experienced bullying participated in the research. All were Palestinians living in Israel, attending primary schools.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Data was collected using the following measures, the Multidimensional Bullying Victimization Scale (MBVS), the Adolescents Cyber-Victimization Scale (CYBVICS), the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ), a questionnaire measuring the effect of COVID-19 on mental health outcomes, the Revised Child Anxiety and Depression Scale (RCADS), and the Multidimensional Scale of Perceived Social Support (MSPSS). Structural equation modelling was applied to test the association between variables and mediating effects.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="FINDINGS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">A positive correlation between Fear of COVID-19 and traditional bullying, cyberbullying, depression, and anxiety were found. Moreover, social support was negatively correlated with traditional forms of bullying and cyberbullying. Also, statistically significant differences between traditional bullying, cyberbullying, depression, and parents' difficulties emerged from parental marital status.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">findings might help victims of bullying by training teachers and guiding parents to construct intervention plans to empower the social networks of children victims.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Veronese</LastName><ForeName>Guido</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Milano-Bicocca, Milan, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mansour</LastName><ForeName>Shahd</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>An-Najah National University, Nablus, Palestine.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mahamid</LastName><ForeName>Fayez</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychology and Counseling, An-Najah National University, Nablus, Palestine. mahamid@najah.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bdier</LastName><ForeName>Dana</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Milano-Bicocca, Milan, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychology and Counseling, An-Najah National University, Nablus, Palestine.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Discov Ment Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9918350483906676</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2731-4383</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Anxiety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bullying</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Covid-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Cyberbullying</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Depression</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mental health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Social support</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39466499</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s44192-024-00100-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s44192-024-00100-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Mahamid FA, Veronese G, Bdier D. Fear of coronavirus (COVID-19) and mental health outcomes in Palestine: The mediating role of social support. Current Psychol. 2021;10:1–10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu JJ, Bao Y, Huang X, Shi J, Lu L. Mental health considerations for children quarantined because of COVID-19. Lancet Child Adolescent Health. 2020;4(5):347–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2352-4642(20)30096-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32224303</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phelps C, Sperry LL. Children and the COVID-19 pandemic. Psychol Trauma Theory Res Pract Policy. 2020;12(S1):S73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/tra0000861</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Sullivan K, Clark S, McGrane A, Rock N, Burke L, Boyle N, Marshall K. A qualitative study of child and adolescent mental health during the COVID-19 pandemic in Ireland. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18(3):1062.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph18031062</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33504101</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7908364</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Figueiredo CS, Sandre PC, Portugal LCL, Mázala-de-Oliveira T, da Silva Chagas L, RaonyBomfim ÍPOS. COVID-19 pandemic impacts children and adolescents’ mental health: biological, environmental, and social factors. Progress Neuro-Psychopharmacol Biol Psychiat. 2021. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pnpbp.2020.110171 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pnpbp.2020.110171</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Avgar, D. (2020). Concentration of data in preparation for the Day for the Struggle against Violence against Women [Report]. Information and Research Center, Knesset, Israel. https://fs.knesset.gov.il/globaldocs/MMM/4f565077-e22c-eb11-811a-00155d0af32a/2_4f565077-e22c-eb11-811a-00155d0af32a_11_16437.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaillancourt T, Brittain H, Krygsman A, Farrell AH, Landon S, Pepler D. School bullying before and during COVID-19: Results from a population-based randomized design. Aggressive Behav. 2021;47(5):557–69.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ab.21986</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cross, C. (2020, March 30). Cyberbullying may increase during COVID-19 pandemic, expert says. Healio. Retrieved from https://www.healio.com/news/pediatrics/20200330/cyberbullying-may-increase-during-covid19-pandemic-expert-says</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ye Y, Wang C, Zhu Q, He M, Havawala M, Bai X, Wang T. Parenting and teacher–student relationship as protective factors for Chinese adolescent adjustment during COVID-19. Sch Psychol Rev. 2022;51(2):187–205.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/2372966X.2021.1897478</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sasson H, Tur-Sinai A, Dvir K, Harel-Fisch Y. The role of parents and peers in cyberbullying perpetration: comparison among Arab and Jewish and youth in Israel. Child Indic Res. 2023;16(2):717–37.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12187-022-09986-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36310918</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heiman T, Olenik-Shemesh D. Cyber-victimization experience among higher education students: Effects of Social Support, loneliness, and self-efficacy. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19(12):7395.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph19127395</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35742641</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9223784</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Israel Internet Association. 2020. Israeli Surfer Survey - Internet Use in Israel with an Emphasis on the Corona Period. Retreived from https://www.isoc.org.il/sts-data/israeli-internet-usage-survey-2020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Golberstein E, Wen H, Miller BF. Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) and mental health for children and adolescents. JAMA Pediatr. 2020;174(9):819–20. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamapediatrics.2020.1456 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamapediatrics.2020.1456</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32286618</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Espelage D, Sung Hong J. Children who bully or are bullied. In: Ollendick TH, White SW, White BA, editors. The Oxford handbook of clinical child and adolescent psychology. Oxford: Oxford University Press; 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J, Iannotti RJ, Nansel TR. School bullying among adolescents in the United States: Physical, verbal, relational, and cyber. J Adolesc Health. 2009;45(4):368–75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jadohealth.2009.03.021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19766941</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2751860</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mann MJ, Kristjansson AL, Sigfusdottir ID, Smith ML. The role of community, family, peer, and school factors in group bullying: Implications for school-based intervention. J Sch Health. 2015;85(7):477–86.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/josh.12270</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26032278</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balkundi S, Fredrick SS. Students’ perceptions of COVID-19 stress and internalizing problems: is social support a buffer? Contemp Sch Psychol. 2024;28(1):3–14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40688-023-00457-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang D, Chen XY, Zhai S, Fan F. Gratitude and internalizing/externalizing symptoms among adolescents after the Wenchuan earthquake: Mediating roles of social support and resilience. J Adolesc. 2022;94(6):867–79.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jad.12070</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35790008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang F, Liang J, Zhang H, Kelifa MM, He Q, Wang P. COVID-19 related depression and anxiety among quarantined respondents. Psychol Health. 2021;36(2):164–78.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/08870446.2020.1782410</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32567952</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y, Yue S, Hu X, Zhu J, Wu Z, Wang J, Wu Y. Associations between feelings/behaviors during COVID-19 pandemic lockdown and depression/anxiety after lockdown in a sample of Chinese children and adolescents. J Affect Disord. 2021;284:98–103.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2021.02.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33592433</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8771471</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palmer AR, Lakhan-Pal S, Cicchetti D. Emotional development and depression In Handbook of emotional development. Cham: Springer; 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arseneault L, Bowes L, Shakoor S. Bullying victimization in youths and mental health problems: “Much ado about nothing”? Psychol Med. 2010;40(5):717–29.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0033291709991383</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19785920</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang S, Xiang M, Cheung T, Xiang YT. Mental health and its correlates among children and adolescents during COVID-19 school closure: The importance of parent-child discussion. J Affect Disord. 2021;279:353–60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2020.10.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33099049</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jadambaa A, Thomas HJ, Scott JG, Graves N, Brain D, Pacella R. The contribution of bullying victimization to the burden of anxiety and depressive disorders in Australia. Epidemiol Psychiat Sci. 2020;29(54):1–2335.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coursen-Neff Z. Discrimination against Palestinian Arab children in the Israeli education system. New York Univ J Int Law Policy. 2003;36:749–816.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chawla N, Sharma P, Sagar R. Psychological impact of COVID-19 on children and adolescents: Is there a silver lining? Indian J Pediat. 2021;88(1):91–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12098-020-03472-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32797389</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Colucci F. Gramsci in action: cultural hegemony and schooling in the Arab Israeli conflict. Int Gramsci J. 2024;5(3):54–77.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mizel O. “I lost my identity in the halls of academia”: Arab students on the use of Arabic in Israeli higher education. Issues Educat Res. 2021;31(3):930–51.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Satran C, Ali-Saleh O, Mashiach-Eizenberg M, Bord S. Stress and perceived discrimination among the Arab population in Israel: The mediation role of the perceived COVID-19 threat and trust in the healthcare system. Ethn Health. 2022;27(6):1377–94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/13557858.2021.1899139</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33734913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nouman H. Social work practice with ethnic minorities during the COVID-19 pandemic: Learning from the Arab minority in Israel. British J Social Work. 2021;51(5):1680–99.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/bjsw/bcab124</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harbin, S. M. (2016). The Multidimensional Bullying Victimization Scale: Development and Validation [Doctoral dissertation, LSU]. LSU Doctoral Dissertations. https://digitalcommons.lsu.edu/gradschool_dissertations/4470</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buelga S, Martínez-Ferrer B, Cava MJ, Ortega-Barón J. Psychometric properties of the CYBVICS cyber-victimization scale and its relationship with psychosocial variables. Social Sciences. 2019;8(1):13. https://doi.org/10.3390/socsci8010013 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/socsci8010013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goodman R, Meltzer H, Bailey V. The strengths and difficulties questionnaire: a pilot study on the validity of the self-report version. Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 1998;7:125–30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s007870050057</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9826298</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goodman R. The strengths and difficulties questionnaire: a research note. J Child Psychol Psychiat. 1997;38(5):581–6. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-7610.1997.tb01545.x .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1469-7610.1997.tb01545.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9255702</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mathyssek CM, Olino TM, Hartman CA, Ormel J, Verhulst FC, Van Oort FV. Does the revised child anxiety and depression scale (RCADS) measure anxiety symptoms consistently across adolescence? The TRAILS study. Int J Methods Psychiatr Res. 2013;22(1):27–35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/mpr.1380</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23483654</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3801212</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zimet GD, Dahlem NW, Zimet SG, Farley GK. The multidimensional scale of perceived social support. J Pers Assess. 1988;52(1):30–41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1207/s15327752jpa5201_2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gladden, R. M., Vivolo-Kantor, A. M., Hamburger, M. E., &amp; Lumpkin, C. D. (2014). Bullying surveillance among youths: Uniform definitions for public health and recommended data elements, version 1.0.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barton EA. Bully prevention: Tips and strategies for school leaders and classroom teachers. California: Corwin Press; 2006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiong J, Lipsitz O, Nasri F, Lui LM, Gill H, Phan L, McIntyre RS. Impact of COVID-19 pandemic on mental health in the general population: A systematic review. J Affective Dis. 2020;277:55–64.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2020.08.001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arzi, T., &amp; Sabag, Y. (2020). Increasing the risk situations of children and adolescents facing the corona crisis. MYERS-JDC-BROOKDALE. May.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Inhelder B, Piaget J. The growth of logical thinking: From childhood to adolescence: An essay on the construction of formal operational structure the international library of psychology. England: Routledge; 1958.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hannighofer J, Foran H, Hahlweg K, Zimmermann T. Impact of relationship status and quality (family type) on the mental health of mothers and their children: A 10-year longitudinal study. Front Psych. 2017;8(266):43.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lereya ST, Samara M, Wolke D. Parenting behavior and the risk of becoming a victim and a bully/victim: A meta-analysis study. Child Abuse Negl. 2013;37(12):1091–108. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chiabu.2013.03.001 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chiabu.2013.03.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23623619</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nazir T, Thabassum L. Cyberbullying: definition, types, effects, related factors and precautions to be taken during COVID-19 pandemic. Int J Indian Psychol. 2021;10(25215/0904):047.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doty J, Gabrielli J, Abraczinskas M, Girón K, Yourell J, Stormshak E. Parent-based prevention of bullying and cyberbullying during COVID-19 social distancing: A pilot intervention using the MOST framework. J Prevention. 2022;43(5):719–34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10935-022-00696-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>