<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39462390</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2050-7283</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>12</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>26</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC psychology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Psychol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Changes in health, lifestyle, and wellbeing of children with type 1 diabetes and their parents during the pandemic.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>593</StartPage><MedlinePgn>593</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">593</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s40359-024-02102-z</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">The COVID-19 pandemic restrictions have substantially affected people's health and rapidly changed their daily routines. This is a prospective study that investigated the impact of the pandemic on primary school children with Type 1 diabetes and their parents during the first lockdown in Kuwait.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A questionnaire battery related to mental health, well-being, and lifestyle was administered at baseline in Summer 2019 (face-to-face, at a diabetes outpatient clinic) and at follow-up during lockdown in Summer 2020 (via telephone, in adherence with COVID-19 restrictions). Data were collected for 70 dyads with children aged 9-12 years.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Significant differences were found in most scores for both children and parents. Their mental health worsened to a higher level of depression, anxiety, stress, and a poor level of wellbeing. The average scores on the follow-up tests fell within a clinical range on these measures. Significant differences in their lifestyle, compared to before the lockdown, included decreased levels of physical activity and lower healthy core nutritional intake.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Our findings indicate that the COVID-19 lockdown has had a significant psychological and possibly physiological impact on children with Type 1 diabetes and their parents. We conclude that there is a need for mental health support services focusing on these groups. Although full lockdown restrictions will have stopped in the past year, post-pandemic stressors may be expected to continue to adversely affect this cohort.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alazmi</LastName><ForeName>Afrah</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2875-810X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Human and Behavioural Science, Bangor University, Bangor, Gwynedd, UK. afrahssdd@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Viktor</LastName><ForeName>Simon</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Human and Behavioural Science, Bangor University, Bangor, Gwynedd, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Erjavec</LastName><ForeName>Mihela</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4355-6044</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Human and Behavioural Science, Bangor University, Bangor, Gwynedd, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Psychol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101627676</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2050-7283</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003922" MajorTopicYN="Y">Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010290" MajorTopicYN="Y">Parents</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008019" MajorTopicYN="Y">Life Style</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011446" MajorTopicYN="N">Prospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007730" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Kuwait</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008603" MajorTopicYN="Y">Mental Health</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001007" MajorTopicYN="N">Anxiety</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011795" MajorTopicYN="N">Surveys and Questionnaires</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015444" MajorTopicYN="N">Exercise</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013315" MajorTopicYN="N">Stress, Psychological</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003863" MajorTopicYN="N">Depression</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Chronic disease</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Covid-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Diabetes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mental health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Parenting</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Wellbeing</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>16</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39462390</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40359-024-02102-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s40359-024-02102-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11514897</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Hassan K, Loar R, Anderson BJ, Heptulla RA. The role of socioeconomic status, depression, quality of life, and glycemic control in type 1 diabetes mellitus. J Pediatr. 2006;149(4):526–31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17011326</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Powers MA, Richter SA, Ackard DM, Craft C. Diabetes distress among persons with type 1 diabetes: associations with disordered eating, depression, and other psychological health concerns. Diabetes Educ. 2017;43(1):105–13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27932687</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silverstein J, Klingensmith G, Copeland K, Plotnick L, Kaufman F, Laffel L, Deeb L, Grey M, Anderson B, Holzmeister LA, Clark N. Care of children and adolescents with type 1 diabetes: a statement of the American Diabetes Association. Diabetes Care. 2005;28(1):186–212.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15616254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diabetes. and Anxiety [internet]. Diabetes.co.uk. [cited 2007] https://www.diabetes.co.uk/emotions/diabetes-and-anxiety.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCarthy M, Kushner J. The Everything Parent’s Guide to Children with Juvenile Diabetes: Reassuring Advice for Managing Symptoms and Raising a Happy, Healthy Child. Simon and Schuster; 2007 Apr 2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alazmi A, Bashiru MB, Viktor S, Erjavec M. Psychological variables and lifestyle in children with type1 diabetes and their parents: a systematic review. Clin Child Psychol Psychiatry. 2023 May;30:13591045231177115.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11188552</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37249210</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wake M, Hesketh KF, Cameron F. The Child Health Questionnaire in children with diabetes: cross-sectional survey of parent and adolescent‐reported functional health status. Diabet Med. 2000;17(10):700–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11110502</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng XP, Chen SH. Psycho-behavioral changes in children with type 1 diabetes mellitus. World J Pediatr. 2013;9(3):261–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23929255</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alazmi A, Viktor S, Erjavec M. Exploring the determinants of mental health, wellbeing, and lifestyle in 8–11 year old children with type 1 diabetes and their healthy counterparts in Kuwait. PLoS ONE. 2022;17(12):e0272948.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9744296</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36508408</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaser SS, Foster NC, Nelson BA, Kittelsrud JM, DiMeglio LA, Quinn M, Willi SM, Simmons JH. T1D Exchange Clinic Network. Sleep in children with type 1 diabetes and their parents in the T1D Exchange. Sleep Med. 2017;39:108–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7650845</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29157581</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Michaud I, Henderson M, Legault L, Mathieu ME. Physical activity and sedentary behavior levels in children and adolescents with type 1 diabetes using insulin pump or injection therapy–the importance of parental activity profile. J Diabetes Complicat. 2017;31(2):381–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27989545</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moreira H, Frontini R, Bullinger M, Canavarro MC. Family cohesion and health-related quality of life of children with type 1 diabetes: the mediating role of parental adjustment. J Child Fam stud. 2014;23(2):347–59.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Mental health and psychosocial considerations during the COVID-19 outbreak, 18 March 2020. World Health Organization; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Russell BS, Hutchison M, Tambling R, Tomkunas AJ, Horton AL. Initial challenges of caregiving during COVID-19: caregiver burden, mental health, and the parent–child relationship. Child Psychiatry Hum Dev. 2020;51(5):671–82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7398861</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32749568</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Passanisi S, Pecoraro M, Pira F, Alibrandi A, Donia V, Lonia P, Pajno GB, Salzano G, Lombardo F. Quarantine due to the COVID-19 pandemic from the perspective of pediatric patients with type 1 diabetes: a web-based survey. Front Pead. 2020;8:491.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7411347</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32850562</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nagraj A. Covid-19: Kuwait begins three-week complete lockdown from May 10 [Internet]. 2020 [cited 2023 Dec 12]. https://gulfbusiness.com/covid-19-kuwait-begins-three-week-complete-lockdown-from-may-10/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh S, Roy D, Sinha K, Parveen S, Sharma G, Joshi G. Impact of COVID-19 and lockdown on mental health of children and adolescents: a narrative review with recommendations. Psychiatry Res. 2020;293:113429.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7444649</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32882598</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duan L, Shao X, Wang Y, Huang Y, Miao J, Yang X, Zhu G. An investigation of mental health status of children and adolescents in China during the outbreak of COVID-19. J Affect Disord. 2020;275:112–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7329661</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32658812</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salman A, Al-Ghadban F, Sigodo KO, Taher AK, Chun S. The psychological and social impacts of curfew during the COVID-19 outbreak in Kuwait: a cross-sectional study. Sustainability. 2021;13(15):8464.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ozamiz-Etxebarria N, Dosil-Santamaria M, Picaza-Gorrochategui M, Idoiaga-Mondragon N. Stress, anxiety, and depression levels in the initial stage of the COVID-19 outbreak in a population sample in the northern Spain. Cadernos De Saude Publica. 2020;36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32374806</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Abdulrazzaq D, Khalifa D, Alqaisi T, Al-Juailla F, Othman F, Qabazard S, Al-Kandari H. Health-related quality of life of children and adolescents with type 1 diabetes during the COVID-19 pandemic in Kuwait. Front Public Health. 2022;10:1056967.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9816431</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36620301</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Process. of translation and adaptation of instruments [Internet]. WHO.2021 [cited 2021 Nov 22]. https://www.who.int/substance_abuse/research_tools/translation/en/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Little RR, Sacks DB. HbA1c: how do we measure it and what does it mean? Curr Opin Endocrinol Diabetes Obes. 2009;16(2):113–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19300091</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lane GG, White AE, Henson RK. Expanding reliability generalization methods with KR-21 estimates an RG study of the Coopersmith Self-Esteem Inventory. Educ Psychol Meas. 2002;62(4):685–711.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Childress AC, Brewerton TD, Hodges EL, Jarrell MP. The kids’ eating disorders Survey (KEDS): a study of middle school students. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 1993;32(4):843–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8340308</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Wellbeing measures in primary health care/the DepCare Project: report on a WHO meeting: Stockholm, Sweden, 12–13 February 1998. World Health Organization. Regional Office for Europe; 1998.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chorpita BF, Yim L, Moffitt C, Umemoto LA, Francis SE. Assessment of symptoms of DSM-IV anxiety and depression in children: a revised child anxiety and depression scale. Behav Res Ther. 2000;38(8):835–55.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10937431</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petersen C, Schmidt S, Bullinger M. Brief report: development and pilot testing of a coping questionnaire for children and adolescents with chronic health conditions. J Pediatr Psychol. 2004;29(8):635–40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15491986</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Achenbach TM, Rescorla LA. Manual for the ASEBA preschool forms and profiles. Burlington, VT: University of Vermont, Research center for children, youth, &amp; families; 2000.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goodman R. The strengths and difficulties Questionnaire: a research note. J Child Psychol Psychiatry. 1997;38(5):581–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9255702</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Owens JA, Spirito A, McGuinn M. The children’s Sleep habits Questionnaire (CSHQ): psychometric properties of a survey instrument for school-aged children. Sleep-New York-. 2000;23(8):1043–52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11145319</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>West F, Sanders MR. The lifestyle Behaviour Checklist: a measure of weight-related problem behaviour in obese children. Int J Pediatr Obes. 2009;4(4):266–73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19922041</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Magarey A, Golley R, Spurrier N, Goodwin E, Ong F. Reliability and validity of the children’s Dietary Questionnaire; a new tool to measure children’s dietary patterns. Int J Pediatr Obes. 2009;4(4):257–65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19922040</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anderson YC, Wynter LE, Grant CC, Stewart JM, Cave TL, Wild CE, Derraik JG, Cutfield WS, Hofman PL. Physical activity is low in obese New Zealand children and adolescents. Sci Rep. 2017;7(1):1–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5291106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28157185</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allan S, Gilbert P, Goss K. An exploration of shame measures—II: psychopathology. Pers Indiv Differ. 1994;17(5):719–22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCubbin HI, McCubbin MA, Nevin R, Cauble E. Coping health inventory for parents (CHIP). Family assessment: Resiliency, coping, and adaptation-Inventories for research and practice. 1981:407 – 53.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cox DJ, Irvine A, Gonder-Frederick L, Nowacek G, Butterfield J. Fear of hypoglycemia: quantification, validation, and utilization. Diabetes Care. 1987;10(5):617–21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3677982</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lovibond PF, Lovibond SH. The structure of negative emotional states: comparison of the Depression anxiety stress scales (DASS) with the Beck Depression and anxiety inventories. Behav Res Ther. 1995;33(3):335–43.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7726811</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arnold DS, O’leary SG, Wolff LS, Acker MM. The parenting scale: a measure of dysfunctional parenting in discipline situations. Psychol Assess. 1993;5(2):137.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Birch LL, Fisher JO, Grimm-Thomas K, Markey CN, Sawyer R, Johnson SL. Confirmatory factor analysis of the child feeding questionnaire: a measure of parental attitudes, beliefs and practices about child feeding and obesity proneness. Appetite. 2001;36(3):201–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11358344</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miles J, Shevlin M. Applying regression and correlation: a guide for students and researchers. Sage; 2001 Mar. p. 8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holmes C, Levy M, Smith A, Pinne S, Neese P. A model for creating a supportive trauma-informed culture for children in preschool settings. J Child Fam stud. 2015;24(6):1650–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4419190</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25972726</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pandolfi V, Magyar CI, Dill CA. Confirmatory factor analysis of the child Behavior Checklist 1.5–5 in a sample of children with autism spectrum disorders. J Autism Dev Disord. 2009;39(7):986–95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2703003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19263208</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferguson RJ, Robinson AB, Splaine M. Use of the reliable change index to evaluate clinical significance in SF-36 outcomes. Qual Life Res. 2002;11(6):509–16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12206571</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morley S, Dowzer C. The Leeds Reliable Change Indicator. University of; 2014.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Busch RM, Lineweaver TT, Ferguson L, Haut JS. Reliable change indices and standardized regression-based change score norms for evaluating neuropsychological change in children with epilepsy. Epilepsy Behav. 2015;47:45–54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4475419</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26043163</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen J. Statistical power analysis. Curr Dir Psychol Sci. 1992;1(3):98–101.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campbell KA, Rohlman DS, Storzbach D, Binder LM, Anger WK, Kovera CA, Davis KL, Grossmann SJ. Test-retest reliability of psychological and neurobehavioral tests self-administered by computer. Assessment. 1999;6(1):21–32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9971880</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Devore JL, Peck R. Statistics: the exploration &amp; analysis of data. Cengage Learning; 1993.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imran N, Zeshan M, Pervaiz Z. Mental health considerations for children &amp; adolescents in COVID-19 pandemic. Pakistan J Med Sci. 2020;36(COVID19–S4):S67.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7306970</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32582317</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McArthur C, Saari M, Heckman GA, Wellens N, Weir J, Hebert P, Turcotte L, Jbilou J, Hirdes JP. Evaluating the effect of COVID-19 pandemic lockdown on long-term care residents’ mental health: a data-driven approach in New Brunswick. J Am Med Dir Assoc. 2021;22(1):187–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7587131</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33232682</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tornese G, Ceconi V, Monasta L, Carletti C, Faleschini E, Barbi E. Glycemic control in type 1 diabetes mellitus during COVID-19 quarantine and the role of in-home physical activity. Diabetes Technol Ther. 2020;22(6):462–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32421355</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Howell RT, Kern ML, Lyubomirsky S. Health benefits: Meta-analytically determining the impact of well-being on objective health outcomes. Health Psychol Rev. 2007;1(1):83–136.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Di Renzo L, Gualtieri P, Pivari F, Soldati L, Attinà A, Cinelli G, Leggeri C, Caparello G, Barrea L, Scerbo F, Esposito E. Eating habits and lifestyle changes during COVID-19 lockdown: an Italian survey. J Translational Med. 2020;18(1):1–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7278251</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32513197</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sweenie R, Mackey ER, Streisand R. Parent–child relationships in type 1 diabetes: associations among child behavior, parenting behavior, and pediatric parenting stress. Families Syst Health. 2014;32(1):31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3950351</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24294984</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benedict R. Racism is vulnerable. Engl J. 1946;35(6):299–303.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wolf AM, Wender RC, Etzioni RB, Thompson IM, D’Amico AV, Volk RJ, Brooks DD, Dash C, Guessous I, Andrews K, DeSantis C. American Cancer Society guideline for the early detection of prostate cancer: update 2010. Cancer J Clin. 2010;60(2):70–98.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20200110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calvano C, Engelke L, Di Bella J, Kindermann J, Renneberg B, Winter SM. Families in the COVID-19 pandemic: parental stress, parent mental health and the occurrence of adverse childhood experiences—results of a representative survey in Germany. Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2022;31(7):1–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7917379</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33646416</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>