<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39463524</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Healthcare-Associated Infections: Pre- and Post-pandemic Microbiological Profile and Antibiotic Resistance.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70263</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70263</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e70263</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.70263</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">In recent years, healthcare-associated infections (HAIs) have been a priority topic for global institutions such as the World Health Organization because, during the COVID-19 pandemic, the role of HAIs as co-morbidity in infected patients was evident. HAIs can cause disability and mortality and lead to excessive healthcare costs. This work aims to calculate the prevalence of HAIs from 2019 to 2023 to determine their microbiological profile and antibiotic resistance.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A cross-sectional design was used for this study. To describe the population, univariate analysis, measures of central tendency, frequencies, and proportions were used.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The present study included 3,936 HAI notifications, which showed a significant decrease in their number during the COVID-19 pandemic, especially in 2020. In 2021 and 2022, the numbers increased rapidly to around 30%. The most prevalent HAI type was ventilator-associated pneumonia, which had the highest prevalence in 2020. Regarding microorganism isolation, percentages increased after 2020 from 46% to 67%, with <i>Acinetobacter baumannnii </i>beingthe most frequent during and after pandemics. The microbiological profile showed multidrug resistance in several microorganisms.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">HAIs are a global health concern. The number of cases has been increasing since the COVID-19 pandemic with regard to the multidrug-resistant microorganism. HAIs have an important impact on the quality of life, morbidity, mortality, and financial concerns for health services. Global strategies should be adapted for different regions, since the panaroma in developed countries allows for programs to be established for the prevention and control of HAIs in a better way than in low-income countries that lack adequate infrastructure and resources.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Sierra-Diaz et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sierra-Diaz</LastName><ForeName>Erick</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Epidemiology and Public Health, Mexican Social Security Institute, Guadalajara, MEX.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Puron-Cid</LastName><ForeName>Gabriel</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Public Administration, Center for Economic Research and Teaching, A.C., Aguascalientes, MEX.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Torres-Sanchez</LastName><ForeName>Joselyne Paola</ForeName><Initials>JP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Epidemiology, Mexican Social Security Institute, Guadalajara, MEX.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>García-Quintero</LastName><ForeName>Héctor Israel</ForeName><Initials>HI</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Epidemiology, Mexican Social Security Institute, Guadalajara, MEX.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cisneros-García</LastName><ForeName>Diana Lorena</ForeName><Initials>DL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Public Health, University of Guadalajara, Guadalajara, MEX.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>García-Gutierrez</LastName><ForeName>Mariana</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pediatrics, School of Medicine and Health Sciences, Monterrey Institute of Technology and Higher Education, Guadalajara, MEX.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cremades</LastName><ForeName>Rosa</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Microbiology and Pathology, University of Guadalajara, Guadalajara, MEX.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sandoval-Pinto</LastName><ForeName>Elena</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cell and Molecular Biology, University of Guadalajara, Guadalajara, MEX.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antibiotic resistance</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">control</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">healthcare-associated infections</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">microbiological profile</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">notification</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">prevention</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sars-cov-2</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Animal subjects: All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39463524</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11512655</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.70263</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>The burden of health care-associated infection worldwide. World Health Organization.  [
Sep;
2023 
]. 2023. https://www.who.int/news-room/feature-stories/detail/the-burden-of-health-care-associated-infection-worldwide https://www.who.int/news-room/feature-stories/detail/the-burden-of-health-care-associated-infection-worldwide</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boletín infecciones asociadas a la atención de la salud (IAAS) red hospitalaria de Vigilancia Epidemiológica (RHOVE) Secretaría de Salud. Gobierno de México.  [
Sep;
2023 
]. 2023. https://www.gob.mx/cms/uploads/attachment/file/770528/BOLET_NRHOVEAGOSTO2022_Final_21102022_1.pdf https://www.gob.mx/cms/uploads/attachment/file/770528/BOLET_NRHOVEAGOSTO2022_Final_21102022_1.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Programa institucional de prevención y control de infecciones asociadas a la atención de la salud. Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social. Marco normativo. Gobierno de México. 2019. http://www.imss.gob.mx/conoce-al-imss/marco-normativo http://www.imss.gob.mx/conoce-al-imss/marco-normativo</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>PROYECTO de Norma Oficial Mexicana PROY-NOM-045-SSA-2024, para la vigilancia epidemiológica, prevención y control de las infecciones asociadas a la atención de la salud. Diario Oficial de la Federación. Secretaría de Gobernación. 2024. https://www.dof.gob.mx/nota_detalle.php?codigo=5732885&amp;fecha=09/07/2024#gsc.tab=0 https://www.dof.gob.mx/nota_detalle.php?codigo=5732885&amp;fecha=09/07/2024#gsc.tab=0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prevention of healthcare-associated infections in intensive care unit patients. Mazzeffi M, Galvagno S, Rock C. Anesthesiology. 2021;135:1122–1131.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34731244</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Healthcare associated infections (HAI) perspectives. Al-Tawfiq JA, Tambyah PA. J Infect Public Health. 2014;7:339–344.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24861643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pay for preventing (not causing) health care-associated infections. Katz MH. JAMA Intern Med. 2013;173:2046.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23999771</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Health care-associated infections: a meta-analysis of costs and financial impact on the US health care system. Zimlichman E, Henderson D, Tamir O, et al. JAMA Intern Med. 2013;173:2039–2046.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23999949</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manual Metodológico de Indicadores Médicos 2022. Dirección de prestaciones médicas. Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social 2023. Gobierno de México. Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social. 2023. http://www.imss.gob.mx/conoce-al-imss/marco-normativo http://www.imss.gob.mx/conoce-al-imss/marco-normativo</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Global report on infection prevention and control. World Health Organization. World Health Organization. 2022. https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240051164 https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240051164</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Apuntes en Salud. Boletín CONAMED-OPS, 3(17). Secretaría de Salud 2018. Salud. 2018. https://docplayer.es/123652637-Frecuencia-de-infecciones-asociadas-a-la-atencion-de-la-salud-en-los-principales-sistemas-de-informacion-de-mexico.html https://docplayer.es/123652637-Frecuencia-de-infecciones-asociadas-a-la-atencion-de-la-salud-en-los-principales-sistemas-de-informacion-de-mexico.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Con 79 años de existencia, el IMSS ha demostrado su capacidad de respuesta ante desastres naturales y crisis sanitarias. Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social 2021. Gobierno de México. https://www.imss.gob.mx/prensa/archivo/202201/030#:~:text=El%20Seguro%20Social%20atiende%20al,a%2011.6%20millones%20de%20beneficiarios Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social. 2021;20:20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manual de procedimientos estandarizados para la vigilancia epidemiológica hospitalaria. Dirección General de Epidemiología. Secretaría de Salud 2016. Secretaría de Salud. 2016. https://epidemiologia.salud.gob.mx/gobmx/salud/documentos/manuales/28_Manual_RHoVE.pdf https://epidemiologia.salud.gob.mx/gobmx/salud/documentos/manuales/28_Manual_RHoVE.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manual para la implementación de los paquetes de acciones para prevenir y vigilar las infecciones asociadas a la atención de la salud (IAAS) 2019. http://www.calidad.salud.gob.mx/site/editorial/docs/manual_IAAS.pdf http://www.calidad.salud.gob.mx/site/editorial/docs/manual_IAAS.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manual Metodológico de Indicadores Médicos 2019-2024. Manual Metodológico de Indicadores Médicos 2019-2024. Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social. 2020. https://www.imss.gob.mx/sites/all/statics/profesionalesSalud/investigacionSalud/normatividadInst/ManualMetodologico2019-2024.pdf https://www.imss.gob.mx/sites/all/statics/profesionalesSalud/investigacionSalud/normatividadInst/ManualMetodologico2019-2024.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antibiotic resistance. World Health Organization. https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/antibiotic-resistance https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/antibiotic-resistance</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Development and application of a surveillance method for healthcare-associated infections in long-term care hospitals in Korea. Jeong SY, Choi J, Kim JY, Ga H. Ann Geriatr Med Res. 2020;24:274–281.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7781959</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33389974</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>About antimicrobial resistance. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. https://www.cdc.gov/drugresistance/about.html https://www.cdc.gov/drugresistance/about.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antibiotic resistance and persistence-Implications for human health and treatment perspectives. Huemer M, Mairpady Shambat S, Brugger SD, Zinkernagel AS. EMBO Rep. 2020;21:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7726816</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33400359</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nosocomial infection and its molecular mechanisms of antibiotic resistance. Xia J, Gao J, Tang W. Biosci Trends. 2016;10:14–21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26877142</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sierra Díaz, Erick Erick. Infecciones asociadas a la atención de la salud: plan de mejora institucional para la prevención. Centro de Investigación y Docencia Económicas. 2023. http://hdl.handle.net/11651/549 http://hdl.handle.net/11651/549</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>