<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39469356</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome After Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) Vaccination: Findings From an Autopsy.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70370</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70370</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e70370</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.70370</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>A male patient in his 80s was brought to our emergency room with a one-day history of general malaise and cough. He had received a severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus-2 (SARS-CoV-2) vaccination seven days earlier. He initially presented with respiratory failure, and an alveolar hemorrhage was suspected. The patient was intubated and admitted to the intensive care unit. We suspected that the alveolar hemorrhage was caused by acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS). Treatment including high-dose corticosteroid therapy and venovenous extracorporeal membrane oxygenation (ECMO) was initiated, however, the patient did not respond to treatment and died 35 days after admission. Pathological autopsy revealed diffuse alveolar damage (DAD) and idiopathic diffuse alveolar hemorrhage (DAH) consistent with ARDS. ARDS should be considered as a differential diagnosis when a patient develops respiratory symptoms after receiving the SARS-CoV-2 vaccine.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Kawano et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kawano</LastName><ForeName>Fumiya</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cardiology, Nippon Medical School Hospital, Tokyo, JPN.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kato</LastName><ForeName>Mikiya</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emergency Medicine, Iseikai International General Hospital, Osaka, JPN.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tsuchida</LastName><ForeName>Yasuaki</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pathology, Iseikai International General Hospital, Osaka, JPN.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Okawa</LastName><ForeName>Jumpei</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emergency Medicine, Iseikai International General Hospital, Osaka, JPN.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Arimoto</LastName><ForeName>Hideki</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emergency Medicine, Iseikai International General Hospital, Osaka, JPN.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D002363">Case Reports</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">acute respiratory distress syndrome [ards]</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">autopsy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">corona virus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">covid-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sars cov-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vaccination</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>56</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>55</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39469356</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11513690</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.70370</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 Modified mRNA “Vaccines”: lessons learned from clinical trials, mass vaccination, and the bio-pharmaceutical complex, part 1. Mead MN, Seneff S, Wolfinger R, et al. Vaccine Theory Prac &amp;amp; Res. 2024;3:1112–1178.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Safety of the BNT162b2 mRNA covid-19 vaccine in a nationwide setting. Barda N, Dagan N, Ben-Shlomo Y, et al. N Engl J Med. 2021;385:1078–1090.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8427535</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34432976</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Risk of thrombocytopenia and thromboembolism after covid-19 vaccination and SARS-CoV-2 positive testing: self-controlled case series study. Hippisley-Cox J, Patone M, Mei XW, et al. BMJ. 2021;374:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8388189</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34446426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) as an adverse event following immunization: Case definition &amp; guidelines for data collection, analysis, and presentation of immunization safety data. Serazin NA, Edem B, Williams SR, et al. Vaccine. 2021;39:3028–3036.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7843093</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33583673</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A patient presenting with ARDS after COVID-19 vaccination: a COVID-19 case report. Sahin Tutak A, Söylemez F, Konuk HB, et al. J Infect Public Health. 2021;14:1395–1397.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8170910</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34175235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>An autopsy case of COVID-19-like acute respiratory distress syndrome after mRNA-1273 SARS-CoV-2 vaccination. Yoshimura Y, Sasaki H, Miyata N, et al. Int J Infect Dis. 2022;121:98–101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9054706</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35500794</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Acute respiratory distress syndrome secondary to COVID-19 mRNA vaccine administration in a pregnant woman: a case report. Abraham B, Mohammed Saeed H, Azeez Pasha SA. Qatar Med J. 2022;2022:40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9372495</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35974885</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Acute respiratory distress syndrome: the Berlin Definition. Ranieri VM, Rubenfeld GD, Thompson BT, et al. JAMA. 2012;307:2526–2533.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22797452</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Acute respiratory distress syndrome: causes, pathophysiology, and phenotypes. Bos LDJ, Ware LB. Lancet. 2022;400:1145–1156.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36070787</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Unexpected role for adaptive αβTh17 cells in acute respiratory distress syndrome. Li JT, Melton AC, Su G, et al. J Immunol. 2015;195:87–95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4475475</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26002979</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Immune responses induced by mRNA vaccination in mice, monkeys and humans. Cagigi A, Loré K. Vaccines (Basel) 2021;9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7831080</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33477534</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reaction of human monoclonal antibodies to SARS-CoV-2 proteins with tissue antigens: implications for autoimmune diseases. Vojdani A, Vojdani E, Kharrazian D. Front Immunol. 2020;11:617089.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7873987</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33584709</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antigen presentation of mRNA-based and virus-vectored SARS-CoV-2 vaccines. Rijkers GT, Weterings N, Obregon-Henao A, Lepolder M, Dutt TS, van Overveld FJ, Henao-Tamayo M. Vaccines (Basel) 2021;9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8402319</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34451973</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Incidence of acute exacerbation in patients with interstitial lung disease after COVID-19 vaccination. Sakayori M, Hagiwara E, Baba T, et al. J Infect Chemother. 2023;29:105–108.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9468306</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36113847</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delayed fatal pulmonary hemorrhage following COVID-19 vaccination: case repot, batch analysis, and proposed autopsy checklist. Hulscher N, McCullough PA. Preprints. 2024:2024021096.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>