<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39464845</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1564-0604</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>102</Volume><Issue>11</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Bulletin of the World Health Organization</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Bull World Health Organ</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Mass gathering events and COVID-19; lessons learnt from the 2020 European football championship.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>803</StartPage><EndPage>812</EndPage><MedlinePgn>803-812</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.2471/BLT.23.290044</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Evidence about the impact of mass gatherings during the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic on the number of disease cases and on the health-care systems of host countries is limited. Additionally, there have been few publications on the lessons identified from the adaptation of mass gatherings held during the pandemic, including the implementation of comprehensive public health and social measures aimed at reducing viral transmission. This article describes preparations made for the 2020 Union of European Football Associations (UEFA) European Football Championship (UEFA Euro 2020) by the World Health Organization's (WHO) Regional Office for Europe, UEFA and other stakeholders after the championship had been rescheduled because of the COVID-19 pandemic. Technical guidance on preparations for the football tournament and risk assessment tools were provided by WHO. A task force established by the WHO Regional Office for Europe conducted traditional and event-based disease surveillance before and during UEFA Euro 2020, monitored public health and social measures in the 11 host countries, and developed a risk communication and community engagement strategy that involved multimedia campaigns targeting news and social media, fans, athletes, event organizers and other stakeholders. The lessons and good practices identified during UEFA Euro 2020 are described to help guide preparations for future mass gatherings in health emergencies. Sharing data and recommendations on best practice from previous mass gatherings with the organizers and countries involved in planning for a major event is particularly important.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2024 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Schmidt</LastName><ForeName>Tanja</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>WHO Regional Office for Europe, UN City, Marmorvej 51, Copenhagen, DK-2100, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Beebeejaun</LastName><ForeName>Kazim</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>WHO Regional Office for Europe, UN City, Marmorvej 51, Copenhagen, DK-2100, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Latta</LastName><ForeName>Aimee</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>WHO Regional Office for Europe, UN City, Marmorvej 51, Copenhagen, DK-2100, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wippel</LastName><ForeName>Christoph</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>WHO Regional Office for Europe, UN City, Marmorvej 51, Copenhagen, DK-2100, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Addo</LastName><ForeName>Jennifer</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>WHO Regional Office for Europe, UN City, Marmorvej 51, Copenhagen, DK-2100, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Salvi</LastName><ForeName>Cristiana</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>WHO Regional Office for Europe, UN City, Marmorvej 51, Copenhagen, DK-2100, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tyler</LastName><ForeName>Sarah</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>WHO Regional Office for Europe, UN City, Marmorvej 51, Copenhagen, DK-2100, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Izhyk</LastName><ForeName>Olha</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>WHO Regional Office for Europe, UN City, Marmorvej 51, Copenhagen, DK-2100, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Smallwood</LastName><ForeName>Catherine</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>WHO Regional Office for Europe, UN City, Marmorvej 51, Copenhagen, DK-2100, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Perehinets</LastName><ForeName>Ihor</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>WHO Regional Office for Europe, UN City, Marmorvej 51, Copenhagen, DK-2100, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Bull World Health Organ</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7507052</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0042-9686</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005060" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Europe</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012916" MajorTopicYN="Y">Soccer</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="Y">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000090522" MajorTopicYN="Y">Mass Gatherings</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014944" MajorTopicYN="N">World Health Organization</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011634" MajorTopicYN="N">Public Health</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018570" MajorTopicYN="N">Risk Assessment</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="fre"><AbstractText>Peu de preuves existent concernant l'impact des rassemblements de masse lors de la pandémie de maladie à coronavirus 2019 (COVID-19) sur le nombre de cas et sur les systèmes de soins de santé des pays hôtes. En outre, rares sont les publications consacrées aux enseignements qui ont découlé de l'adaptation des rassemblements de masse organisés durant la pandémie, notamment la mise en œuvre de mesures sociales et sanitaires globales visant à limiter la transmission du virus. Le présent article décrit les préparatifs effectués dans le cadre du championnat d'Europe de football 2020 (UEFA Euro 2020) de l'Union européenne des associations de football (UEFA) par le Bureau régional de l'Organisation mondiale de la Santé (OMS) pour l'Europe, l'UEFA et d'autres parties prenantes après le report de la compétition en raison de la pandémie de COVID-19. Des directives techniques relatives à ces préparatifs ainsi que des outils d'évaluation des risques ont été fournis par l'OMS. Un groupe de travail créé par le Bureau régional de l'OMS pour l'Europe a mené une surveillance épidémiologique et événementielle avant et pendant l'UEFA Euro 2020, analysé les mesures sociales et sanitaires dans les 11 pays hôtes et développé une stratégie de communication des risques et d'engagement communautaire impliquant les médias et réseaux sociaux, les supporters, les athlètes, les organisateurs d'événements et d'autres intervenants. Les leçons tirées et les bonnes pratiques identifiées au cours de l'UEFA Euro 2020 sont détaillées ici afin d'aider à encadrer les préparatifs de futurs rassemblements de masse dans des situations d'urgence sanitaire. Partager les données et recommandations sur les meilleures pratiques observées lors de précédents rassemblements de masse avec les organisateurs et pays prenant part à la planification d'un événement de grande envergure est essentiel.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2024 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="spa"><AbstractText>Los datos sobre el impacto de las concentraciones masivas durante la pandemia de la enfermedad por coronavirus de 2019 (COVID-19) en el número de casos de la enfermedad y en los sistemas sanitarios de los países anfitriones son limitados. Además, ha habido pocas publicaciones sobre las lecciones identificadas a partir de la adaptación de las concentraciones masivas celebradas durante la pandemia, incluida la aplicación de medidas sanitarias y sociales integrales destinadas a reducir la transmisión viral. Este artículo describe los preparativos que la Oficina Regional para Europa de la Organización Mundial de la Salud (OMS), la UEFA y otras partes interesadas realizaron para el Campeonato Europeo de Fútbol 2020 de la Unión de Asociaciones Europeas de Fútbol (UEFA) (Eurocopa 2020 de la UEFA) tras la reprogramación del campeonato a causa de la pandemia de la COVID-19. La OMS proporcionó orientación técnica sobre los preparativos del torneo de fútbol y herramientas de evaluación de riesgos. Un grupo de trabajo creado por la Oficina Regional para Europa de la OMS se encargó de la vigilancia de enfermedades tradicional y basada en eventos antes y durante la Eurocopa 2020 de la UEFA, supervisó las medidas sociales y de salud pública en los 11 países anfitriones y elaboró una estrategia de comunicación de riesgos y participación de la comunidad que incluía campañas multimedia dirigidas a los medios de comunicación y las redes sociales, los aficionados, los atletas, los organizadores de eventos y otras partes interesadas. Se describen las lecciones y buenas prácticas identificadas durante la Eurocopa 2020 de la UEFA para ayudar a orientar los preparativos de futuras concentraciones masivas en emergencias sanitarias. Es fundamental compartir los datos y las recomendaciones sobre las mejores prácticas de anteriores concentraciones masivas con los organizadores y los países implicados en la planificación de un evento de gran envergadura.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2024 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="ara"><AbstractText>إن الأدلة محدودة حول تأثير التجمعات الجماهيرية خلال جائحة مرض فيروس كورونا 2019 (كوفيد 19) على عدد حالات الإصابة بالمرض، وعلى أنظمة الرعاية الصحية في الدول المضيفة. بالإضافة إلى ذلك، فقد كان هناك عدد قليل من المنشورات بخصوص الدروس المستفادة من تأقلم التجمعات الجماهيرية التي عقدت أثناء الجائحة، بما في ذلك تنفيذ تدابير الصحة العامة والاجتماعية الشاملة التي تهدف إلى تقييد انتقال الفيروس. تصف هذه المقالة الاستعدادات التي تم إجراؤها لبطولة أمم أوروبا (UEFA Euro 2020)، التابعة للاتحاد الأوروبي لكرة القدم (UEFA)، والتي قام بها المكتب الإقليمي لمنظمة الصحة العالمية (WHO) في أوروبا، والاتحاد الأوروبي لكرة القدم، وأصحاب المصلحة الآخرين بعد إعادة جدولة البطولة بسبب جائحة كوفيد 19. قامت منظمة الصحة العالمية بتقديم إرشادات فنية بخصوص الاستعدادات لبطولة كرة القدم، وأدوات تقييم المخاطر. وقد أجرى فريق عمل، أسسه المكتب الإقليمي لمنظمة الصحة العالمية لأوروبا، مراقبة تقليدية ومبنية على الأحداث قبل وأثناء بطولة أمم أوروبا Euro 2020، وقام الفريق برصد التدابير الصحية والاجتماعية في الدول الإحدى عشر المضيفة، ووضع استراتيجية للتواصل بشأن المخاطر وإشراك المجتمع، تضمنت حملات متعددة الوسائط تستهدف الأخبار، ووسائل التواصل الاجتماعي، والمشجعين، والرياضيين، ومنظمي الفعالية، وغيرهم من أصحاب المصلحة الآخرين. وقد تم وصف الدروس والممارسات الجيدة المستفادة خلال بطولة أمم أوروبا Euro 2020 للمساعدة في توجيه الاستعدادات للتجمعات الجماهيرية المستقبلية في حالات الطوارئ الصحية. إن مشاركة البيانات والتوصيات بخصوص أفضل الممارسات من التجمعات الجماهيرية السابقة، مع الجهات المنظمة والدول المشاركة في التخطيط لحدث كبير، يُعد أمرًا هامًا بشكل خاص.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2024 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="chi"><AbstractText>关于在 2019 冠状病毒病 (COVID-19) 大流行期间大型集会活动对疾病病例数量和东道国卫生保健系统所造成影响的证据有限。此外,介绍在大流行病期间调整举行大型集会活动所获得的相关经验教训(包括实施旨在减少病毒传播的综合性公共卫生和社会措施)的出版物也很少。本文介绍了世界卫生组织 (WHO) 欧洲区域办事处、欧洲足球协会联盟 (UEFA) 和其他利益相关者在确定 2020 年 UEFA 欧洲足球锦标赛 (UEFA Euro 2020) 因 COVID-19 大流行病而改期举办后,为确保其顺利进行所做的准备工作。WHO 为足球锦标赛筹备工作提供了技术指南和风险评估工具。WHO 欧洲区域办事处成立的一个特别工作组在 UEFA Euro 2020 开始之前和进行期间开展了传统和基于事件的疾病监测,监测了 11 个主办国的公共卫生和社会措施实施情况,并制定了风险沟通和社区参与战略,其中包括针对新闻和社交媒体、球迷、运动员、活动组织者和其他利益相关者的多媒体宣传活动。总结了从 UEFA Euro 2020 中所获得的经验教训和良好实践,以帮助指导今后在突发卫生事件情况下举办大型集会活动时如何开展准备工作。与参与重大活动规划的组织者和各国就以往大型集会活动的最佳实践分享相关资料并提供建议尤为重要。.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2024 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="rus"><AbstractText>Данные о влиянии массовых мероприятий во время пандемии коронавирусной инфекции 2019 года (COVID-19) на количество случаев заболевания и на системы здравоохранения принимающих стран ограниченны. Кроме того, существует небольшое количество публикаций, посвященных урокам, извлеченным из адаптации массовых мероприятий, проводившихся во время пандемии, включая реализацию комплексных медико-санитарных и социальных мер, направленных на снижение распространения вируса. В этой статье приводится описание подготовки к чемпионату Европы по футболу 2020 года (УЕФА Евро-2020), проведенной Европейским региональным бюро Всемирной организации здравоохранения (ВОЗ), УЕФА и другими заинтересованными сторонами после того, как чемпионат был перенесен из-за пандемии COVID-19. Техническое руководство по подготовке к проведению турнира по футболу и инструменты оценки рисков были предоставлены ВОЗ. Целевой группой, созданной Европейским региональным бюро ВОЗ, проводился традиционный и событийный эпиднадзор за заболеваниями до и во время проведения Евро-2020, мониторинг мер в области здравоохранения и социальной сферы в 11 принимающих странах и разработка стратегии информирования о рисках и вовлечения населения, включающей мультимедийные кампании, направленные на новостные и социальные СМИ, болельщиков, спортсменов, организаторов мероприятий и другие заинтересованные стороны. Приведены уроки и примеры рекомендуемых методов, извлеченные из опыта проведения Евро-2020, которые помогут подготовиться к работе с массовыми скоплениями людей в случае чрезвычайных ситуаций в сфере здравоохранения в будущем. Особенно важен обмен данными и рекомендациями по передовому опыту, полученному в результате ранее проведенных массовых мероприятий, с организаторами и странами, участвующими в планировании крупного события.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>(c) 2024 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>25</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39464845</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11500248</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2471/BLT.23.290044</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">BLT.23.290044</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Tavan A, Tafti AD, Nekoie-Moghadam M, Ehrampoush M, Vafaei Nasab MR, Tavangar H, et al. Risks threatening the health of people participating in mass gatherings: a systematic review. J Educ Health Promot. 2019. Oct 24;8(1):209. 10.4103/jehp.jehp_214_19</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/jehp.jehp_214_19</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6852309</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31807599</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karami M, Doosti-Irani A, Ardalan A, Gohari-Ensaf F, Berangi Z, Massad E, et al. Public health threats in mass gatherings: a systematic review. Disaster Med Public Health Prep. 2019. Dec;13(5-6):1035–46. 10.1017/dmp.2018.161</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/dmp.2018.161</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31250774</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Public health and social measures in response to COVID-19 [internet]. Copenhagen: WHO Regional Office for Europe: 2024. Available from: https://phsm.euro.who.int/covid-19 [cited 2024 Feb 28].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoneoka D, Eguchi A, Fukumoto K, Kawashima T, Tanoue Y, Tabuchi T, et al. Effect of the Tokyo 2020 Summer Olympic Games on COVID-19 incidence in Japan: a synthetic control approach. BMJ Open. 2022. Sep 20;12(9):e061444. 10.1136/bmjopen-2022-061444</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2022-061444</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9490294</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36127076</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamamoto N, Mitsuhashi T, Tsuchihashi Y, Yorifuji T. Causal effect of the Tokyo 2020 Olympic and Paralympic Games on the number of COVID-19 cases under COVID-19 pandemic: an ecological study using the synthetic control method. J Pers Med. 2022. Feb 3;12(2):209. 10.3390/jpm12020209</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/jpm12020209</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8879008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35207697</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gabrielli AF, Glaria AA, Borodina M, Mullen L, Watson CR, Kobokovich A, et al. Risk-based management of international sporting events during the COVID-19 pandemic. Bull World Health Organ. 2024. Aug 1;102(8):608–14. 10.2471/BLT.23.290034</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2471/BLT.23.290034</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11276152</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39070599</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Key planning recommendations for mass gatherings in the context of COVID-19: interim guidance, 29 May 2020. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2020. Available from: https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/332235 [cited 2024 Feb 28].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UEFA postpones EURO 2020 by 12 months. Nyon: Union of European Football Associations; 2020. Available from: https://www.uefa.com/news-media/news/025b-0f8e76aef315-8506a9de10aa-1000--uefa-postpones-euro-2020-by-12-months/ [cited 2024 Feb 28].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smallwood CAH, Arbuthnott KG, Banczak-Mysiak B, Borodina M, Coutinho AP, Payne-Hallström L, et al. Euro 2012 European Football Championship finals: planning for a health legacy. Lancet. 2014. Jun 14;383(9934):2090–7. 10.1016/S0140-6736(13)62384-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(13)62384-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24857705</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holding gatherings during the COVID-19 pandemic: WHO policy brief, 2 August 2021. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2021. Available from: https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/holding-gatherings-during-the-covid-19-pandemic-who-policy-brief-2-august-2021 [cited 2024 Feb 28].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO mass gathering COVID-19 risk assessment tool – sports events. Guidance for authorities and organizers of sports events planning mass gatherings during the current COVID-19 pandemic. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2020. Available from: https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/10665-333187 [cited 2024 Jul 26].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>National IHR focal points. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2024. Available from: https://www.who.int/teams/ihr/national-focal-points#:~:text=The%20Regulations%20define%20a%20National,Contact%20Points%20under%20these%20Regulations%22 [cited 2024 Jul 25].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marsh K, Griffiths E, Young JJ, Gibb C-A, McMenamin J. Contributions of the EURO 2020 football championship events to a third wave of SARS-CoV-2 in Scotland, 11 June to 7 July 2021. Euro Surveill. 2021. Aug;26(31):2100707. 10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2021.26.31.2100707</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2021.26.31.2100707</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8343549</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34355691</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith JAE, Hopkins S, Turner C, Dack K, Trelfa A, Peh J, et al. Public health impact of mass sporting and cultural events in a rising COVID-19 prevalence in England. Epidemiol Infect. 2022. Jan 31;150:e42. 10.1017/S0950268822000188</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0950268822000188</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9058658</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35094727</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heese H, Marquis A, Diercke M, Markus I, Böhm S, Metz J, et al. Results of the enhanced COVID-19 surveillance during UEFA EURO 2020 in Germany. Epidemiol Infect. 2022. Mar 3;150:1–18. 10.1017/S0950268822000449</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0950268822000449</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8924559</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35236530</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bennedbæk M, Button MSF, Nielsen LB, Bybjerg-Grauholm J, Wiid Svarrer C, Møller KL, et al. Increased transmission of SARS-CoV-2 in Denmark during UEFA European championships. Epidemiol Infect. 2022. Mar 23;150:e123. 10.1017/S095026882200019X</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S095026882200019X</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9254153</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35317884</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Riccardo F, Frisicale EM, Guzzetta G, Ferraro F, Merler S, Maringhini G, et al. Winning during a pandemic: epidemiology of SARS-CoV-2 during EURO2020 in Italy. Epidemiol Infect. 2022. Apr 22;150:e166. 10.1017/S0950268822000723</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0950268822000723</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9509794</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35450542</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. COVID-19 dashboard [internet]. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2024. Available from: https://data.who.int/dashboards/covid19/cases?n=c [cited 2024 Feb 28].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdelmalik P, Peron E, Schnitzler J, Fontaine J, Elfenkämper E, Barboza P. The Epidemic Intelligence from Open Sources initiative: a collaboration to harmonize and standardize early detection and epidemic intelligence among public health organizations. Wkly Epidemiol Rec. 2018;93:267–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Epidemic Intelligence from Open Sources. Zero impact from health threats. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2024. Available from: https://www.who.int/initiatives/eios [cited 2024 Jul 25].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO European Region UEFA EURO 2020 explorer [internet]. Copenhagen: WHO Regional Office for Europe: 2024. Available from: https://who.maps.arcgis.com/apps/dashboards/2e328f146c34408d808bba6ea6d18331 [cited 2024 Feb 28].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A systematic approach to monitoring and analysing public health and social measures (PHSM) in the context of the COVID-19 pandemic: underlying methodology and application of the PHSM database and PHSM Severity Index. Copenhagen: WHO Regional Office for Europe: 2020. Available from: https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/337686 [cited 2024 Feb 28].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>With the pandemic far from over, we all need to practice #SummerSense. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2021. Available from: https://www.who.int/europe/news/item/10-06-2021-with-the-pandemic-far-from-over-we-all-need-to-practice-summersense [cited 2024 Jul 25].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization Regional Office for Europe. With the #COVID19 pandemic far from over, we all need to practice #SummerSense [tweet 2021 Jun 26]. X Corp: San Francisco; 2021. Available from: https://x.com/WHO_Europe/status/1408703335306309632 [cited 2024 Feb 28].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization Regional Office for Europe. The #EURO2020 may be nearly over, but stay safe while enjoying the football. We all need to practice #SummerSense [tweet 2021 Jul 9]. X Corp: San Francisco; 2021. Available from: https://x.com/WHO_Europe/status/1413429971897307140 [cited 2024 Feb 28].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Our actions will determine end of pandemic: WHO officials. UN health agency representatives urge world to get vaccinated, adhere to safety measures in summer. Ankara: Anadolu Ajansı; 2021. Available from: https://www.aa.com.tr/en/health/our-actions-will-determine-end-of-pandemic-who-officials/2306848 [cited 2024 Feb 28].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Considerations for sports federations/sports event organizers when planning mass gatherings in the context of COVID-19: interim guidance. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2020. Available from: https://www.who.int/publications-detail-redirect/considerations-for-sports-federations-sports-event-organizers-when-planning-mass-gatherings-in-the-context-of-covid-19-interim-guidance [cited 2024 Feb 28].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The UEFA return to play protocol. Basel: Union of European Football Associations; 2021. Available from: https://www.uefa.com/news-media/news/0265-114289c53314-947427af4d25-1000--the-uefa-return-to-play-protocol/ [cited 2024 Jul 25].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UEFA minimum health and hygiene requirements for the return of spectators. Basel: Union of European Football Associations; 2020. Available from: https://editorial.uefa.com/resources/0262-1081a4df2c6d-98022dcc8f82-1000/uefa_minimum_health_hygiene_requirements_for_the_return_of_spectators_.pdf [cited 2024 Jul 26].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guidance on return to play with fans. Nyon: European Club Association; 2020. Available from: https://www.ecaeurope.com/media/4799/20200825_guidance_return-to-play-with-fans.pdf [cited 2024 Feb 28].</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>