<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39462985</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1365-2753</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>27</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of evaluation in clinical practice</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Eval Clin Pract</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Chest x-ray images: transfer learning model in COVID-19 detection.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/jep.14215</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="RATIONALE, AIMS AND OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">This research aims to develop an effective algorithm for diagnosing COVID-19 in chest X-rays using the transfer learning method and support vector machines.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHOD" NlmCategory="METHODS">In total, data was collected from 10 clinics, including both large city hospitals and smaller medical institutions. This ensured a diverse range of geographical and demographic information in the sample. An extensive data set was collected, including 10,000 chest X-ray images. 5000 images represent normal cases, 3993 images represent pneumonia cases, and 1007 images represent COVID-19 cases. Machine learning methods were applied to develop a classification model, and the results were compared with seven state-of-the-art models and a lightweight CNN architecture.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The results showed that the proposed method achieves high accuracy values (Accuracy): 0.95 for COVID-19, 0.89 for pneumonia, and 0.92 for normal images (p &lt; 0.05). Comparison with other models demonstrates statistically significant superiority of our method in accuracy across all three classes. The EfficientNet-B0 model surpasses our method only in accuracy for normal images with p &lt; 0.01, confirming the advantages of our method. Our method demonstrates high sensitivity values (Sensitivity): 0.96 for COVID-19, 0.88 for pneumonia, and 0.93 for normal images (p &lt; 0.05), outperforming most of the compared models. Correlation analysis showed Pearson coefficients of 0.92, 0.89, and 0.94 for COVID-19, pneumonia, and normal images, respectively, confirming a high degree of consistency between predicted and true class labels. In addition, the model was validated on external datasets to assess its generalizability. This validation confirmed its high level of effectiveness in a variety of clinical settings.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">This study confirms the importance of applying machine learning methods in medical applications and opens new perspectives for early diagnosis of infectious diseases. The practical application of the obtained results can enhance the efficiency of diagnosis and control the spread of COVID-19, as well as contribute to the development of innovative methods in medical practice.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mao</LastName><ForeName>Siqi</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0000-9193-1326</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Statistics, Florida State University, Tallahassee, Florida, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kulbayeva</LastName><ForeName>Saltanat</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, JSC South Kazakhstan Medical Academy, Shymkent, Kazakhstan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Osadchuk</LastName><ForeName>Mikhail</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Polyclinic Therapy, Institute of Clinical Medicine named after N.V. Sklifosovsky, I.M. Sechenov First Moscow State Medical University (Sechenov University), Moscow, Russian Federation.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Eval Clin Pract</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9609066</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1356-1294</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">EfficientNet‐B0</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">diagnostic efficiency</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">support vector machines</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">transfer learning</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39462985</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/jep.14215</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Alsattar HA, Qahtan S, Zaidan AA, et al. Developing deep transfer and machine learning models of chest x‐ray for diagnosing COVID‐19 cases using probabilistic single‐valued neutrosophic hesitant fuzzy. Expert Systems with Applications. 2024;236:121300.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar S, Kumar H. Classification of COVID‐19 x‐ray images using transfer learning with visual geometrical groups and novel sequential convolutional neural networks. MethodsX. 2023;11:102295.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loey M, Manogaran G, Taha MHN, Khalifa NEM. A hybrid deep transfer learning model with machine learning methods for face mask detection in the era of the COVID‐19 pandemic. Measurement. 2021;167:108288.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen DQ, Mao SQ, Niu XF. Tests and classification methods in adaptive designs with applications. J Appl Stat. 2023;50(6):1334‐1357.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin W, Dong S, Dong C, Ye X. Hybrid ensemble model for differential diagnosis between COVID‐19 and common viral pneumonia by chest x‐ray radiograph. Comput Biol Med. 2021;131:104252.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jawahar M, Anbarasi LJ, Jayachandran P, Ramachandran M, Al‐Turjman F. Utilization of transfer learning model in detecting COVID‐19 cases from chest x‐ray images. International Journal of E‐Health and Medical Communications. 2021;13(2):1‐11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Absar N, Mamur B, Mahmud A, et al. Development of a computer‐aided tool for detection of COVID‐19 pneumonia from CXR images using machine learning algorithm. J Radiat Res Appl Sci. 2022;15(1):32‐43.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hammadah NH, Das NR, Nayak M, Swarnkar T. A hybrid approach of deep learning algorithms for identification of COVID‐19 disease using chest X‐Ray images. In: International Conference in Advances in Power, Signal, and Information Technology (APSIT). 2021. IEEE; 2021:1‐5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nalepa J, Bosowski P, Dudzik W, Kawulok M. Fusing Deep Learning with Support Vector Machines to Detect COVID‐19 in X‐Ray Images. In: Szczerbicki E, Wojtkiewicz K, Nguyen SV, Pietranik M, Krótkiewicz M, eds. Asian Conference on Intelligent Information and Database Systems. Springer; 2022:340‐353.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khalifa NEM, Taha MHN, Chakrabortty RK, Loey M. COVID‐19 Chest X‐rays Classification Through the Fusion of Deep Transfer Learning and Machine Learning Methods. In: Kim JH, Deep K, Geem ZW, Sadollah A, Yadav A, eds. Proceedings of 7th International Conference on Harmony Search, Soft Computing and Applications: ICHSA. 2022. Springer; 2022:1‐11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barua PD, Muhammad Gowdh NF, Rahmat K, et al. Automatic COVID‐19 detection using exemplar hybrid deep features with x‐ray images. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18(15):8052.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kassania SH, Kassanib PH, Wesolowskic MJ, Schneidera KA, Detersa R. Automatic detection of coronavirus disease (COVID‐19) in x‐ray and CT images: a machine learning based approach. Biocybernetics and Biomedical Engineering. 2021;41(3):867‐879.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qaid TS, Mazaar H, Al‐Shamri MYH, Alqahtani MS, Raweh AA, Alakwaa W. Hybrid deep‐learning and machine‐learning models for predicting COVID‐19. Comput Intell Neurosci. 2021;2021:9996737.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahajan S, Raina A, Gao XZ, Pandit AK. COVID‐19 detection using hybrid deep learning model in chest x‐rays images. Concurrency and Computation: Practice and Experience. 2022;34(5):e6747.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bahgat WM, Balaha HM, AbdulAzeem Y, Badawy MM. An optimized transfer learning‐based approach for automatic diagnosis of COVID‐19 from chest x‐ray images. PeerJ Computer Science. 2021;7:e555.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saygılı A. A new approach for computer‐aided detection of coronavirus (COVID‐19) from CT and x‐ray images using machine learning methods. Applied Soft Computing. 2021;105:107323.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al‐Waisy AS, Al‐Fahdawi S, Mohammed MA, et al. COVID‐CheXNet: hybrid deep learning framework for identifying COVID‐19 virus in chest x‐rays images. Soft Computing. 2023;27(5):2657‐2672.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Özkaya U, Öztürk Ş, Budak S, Melgani F, Polat K. Classification of COVID‐19 in chest CT images using convolutional support vector machines. arXiv preprint arXiv:2011.05746. 2020;1:1‐20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Samsir S, Sitorus JHP, Zulkifli Z, Ritonga Z, Nasution FA, Watrianthos R. Comparison of machine learning algorithms for chest x‐ray image COVID‐19 classification. J Phys: Conf Ser. 2021;1933(1):012040.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rezaee K, Badiei A, Meshgini S. A hybrid deep transfer learning based approach for COVID‐19 classification in chest X‐ray images. In: 27th national and 5th international Iranian conference on biomedical engineering (ICBME). 2020. IEEE; 2020:234‐241.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan SH, Sohail A, Khan A, et al. COVID‐19 detection in chest x‐ray images using deep boosted hybrid learning. Comput Biol Med. 2021;137:104816.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ohata EF, Bezerra GM, das Chagas JVS, et al. Automatic detection of COVID‐19 infection using chest x‐ray images through transfer learning. IEEE/CAA Journal of Automatica Sinica. 2021;8(1):239‐248.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh AK, Kumar A, Mahmud M, Kaiser MS, Kishore A. COVID‐19 infection detection from chest x‐ray images using hybrid social group optimization and support vector classifier. Cogn Comput. 2024;16:1765–1777. doi:10.1007/s12559-021-09848-3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Das NN, Kumar N, Kaur M, Kumar V, Singh D. Automated deep transfer learning‐based approach for detection of COVID‐19 infection in chest x‐rays. Irbm. 2022;43(2):114‐119.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Umer MJ, Amin J, Sharif M, Anjum MA, Azam F, Shah JH. An integrated framework for COVID‐19 classification based on classical and quantum transfer learning from a chest radiograph. Concurrency and Computation: Practice and Experience. 2022;34(20):e6434.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ozdemir MF, Hanbay D. A novel Covid‐19 detection system based on PSO and hybrid feature using support vector machines. Comput Sci. 2022;2022:120‐129.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharifrazi D, Alizadehsani R, Roshanzamir M, et al. Fusion of convolution neural network, support vector machine and sobel filter for accurate detection of COVID‐19 patients using x‐ray images. Biomed Signal Process Control. 2021;68:102622.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smolyanova TI, Bagaeva NS, Kolganova MA, et al. Phase I pharmacokinetics study of drug «COVID‐globulin» (Specific Human Immunoglobulin Against COVID‐19). Drug. Dev Reg. 2022;11(2):180‐186.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nikolaeva AM, Ivanov AV, Smolyanova TI, et al. Preclinical evaluation of a new anti‐COVID‐19 intravenous immunoglobulin. Drug Dev Reg. 2023;12(1):155‐160.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matyushin N, Ermakov D, Vasileva I, Vakolyuk R, Spaska A. Investigating kidney function changes in young adults with COVID‐19: serum creatinine level, glomerular filtration rate, and biochemical profile analysis. Electronic Journal of General Medicine. 2023;20(6):em547. doi:10.29333/ejgm/13750</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yasar A. Wrapper and hybrid feature selection methods using metaheuristic algorithm for chest x‐ray images classification: COVID‐19 as a case study. Tehnički Glasnik. 2023;17(3):313‐323.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Enireddy V, Kumar MJK, Donepudi B, Karthikeyan C. Detection of COVID‐19 using hybrid ResNet and SVM. IOP Conference Series: Materials Science and Engineering. 2020;993(1):012046.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>