<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39463906</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Multisystem Inflammatory Syndrome in Children: A Case Report.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e72303</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e72303</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e72303</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.72303</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>This case report delves into the case of a patient in the Dominican Republic with multisystem inflammatory syndrome in children (MIS-C). MIS-C is a rare, hyper-inflammatory condition that develops in children as a delayed response to a severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) infection, typically appearing with general markers of inflammation such as erythema and, in severe cases, cardiorespiratory symptoms. The three-year-old patient discussed in this report presented with signs of inflammation, such as erythema, rashes, and chapped skin, and reported experiencing diarrhea, vomiting, and fever for multiple days. Notably, a concurrent parasitic presence was found in the patient's fecal sample, and antibiotics were heavily used throughout the course of treatment. We explain the merits and drawbacks behind using antibiotic therapy for MIS-C and suggest steps that clinicians and researchers can take in order to minimize the potential misuse of antibiotics. Specifically, we identify that prioritizing tests for concurrent infections or illnesses is imperative in treating MIS-C patients, and we conclude by stating that using blood cultures and coprological examinations in tandem is an effective strategy for this purpose.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Ganapathy et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ganapathy</LastName><ForeName>Thryambak</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medicine, American High School, Fremont, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Villagracia</LastName><ForeName>Kirsten Emily M</ForeName><Initials>KEM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medicine, Irvington High School, Fremont, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kuditini</LastName><ForeName>Saharsh S</ForeName><Initials>SS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medicine, North Hills Preparatory, Irving, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sosa Hilario</LastName><ForeName>Sorivel</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Department, Global Health Leaders, Punta Cana, DOM.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D002363">Case Reports</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">anti-parasitic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antibiotic therapy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">clinical case report</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">erythema</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mis-c</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>51</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>7</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39463906</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11503855</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.72303</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Multisystem inflammatory syndrome in children (MIS-C) Patel JM. Curr Allergy Asthma Rep. 2022;22:53–60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8938222</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35314921</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>MIS-C related to SARS-CoV-2 infection: a narrative review of presentation, differential diagnosis, and management. Gadiwala S, Mistry A, Patel S, et al. Infez Med. 2022;30:344–352.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9448305</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36148163</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Proteomic profiling of MIS-C patients indicates heterogeneity relating to interferon gamma dysregulation and vascular endothelial dysfunction. Diorio C, Shraim R, Vella LA, et al. Nat Commun. 2021;12:7222.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8664884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34893640</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Current insights into the pathophysiology of multisystem inflammatory syndrome in children. Vella LA, Rowley AH. Curr Pediatr Rep. 2021;9:83–92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8524214</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34692237</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Interferon-gamma (IFN-γ): exploring its implications in infectious diseases. Kak G, Raza M, Tiwari BK. Biomol Concepts. 2018;9:64–79.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29856726</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pathophysiological and clinical point of view on Kawasaki disease and MIS-C. Vaňková L, Bufka J, Křížková V. Pediatr Neonatol. 2023;64:495–504.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10286520</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37453902</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dynamic changes of the proportion of HLA-DR and CD38 coexpression subsets on T lymphocytes during IFN-based chronic hepatitis B treatment. Lin Y, Shen G, Xie S, et al. Front Immunol. 2022;13:1116160.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9902929</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36761161</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Immune dysregulation and multisystem inflammatory syndrome in children (MIS-C) in individuals with haploinsufficiency of SOCS1. Lee PY, Platt CD, Weeks S, et al. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2020;146:1194–1200.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7445138</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32853638</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Racial and ethnic disparities in multisystem inflammatory syndrome in children in the United States, March 2020 to February 2021. Stierman B, Abrams JY, Godfred-Cato SE, et al. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2021;40:0–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8505134</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34382615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Role of interleukin 10 transcriptional regulation in inflammation and autoimmune disease. Iyer SS, Cheng G. Crit Rev Immunol. 2012;32:23–63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3410706</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22428854</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Unraveling the mechanisms of IVIG immunotherapy in MIS-C. Ganigara M, Sharma C, Bayry J. Cell Rep Med. 2021;2:100431.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8481087</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34608458</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Immune response to intravenous immunoglobulin in patients with Kawasaki disease and MIS-C. Zhu YP, Shamie I, Lee JC, et al. J Clin Invest. 2021;131:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8516453</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34464357</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Treatment of MIS-C in children and adolescents. Mahmoud S, El-Kalliny M, Kotby A, El-Ganzoury M, Fouda E, Ibrahim H. Curr Pediatr Rep. 2022;10:1–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8741532</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35036079</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The role of therapeutic plasma exchange (TPE) in multisystem inflammatory syndrome in children (MIS-C) Atay G, Hasbal C, Türk M, Erdoğan S, Sözeri B. Children (Basel) 2021;8:498.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8230791</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34208141</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Extracorporeal membrane oxygenation for COVID-19-associated multisystem inflammatory syndrome in a 5-year-old. Schwartz SP, Walker TC, Kihlstrom M, et al. Am Surg. 2022;88:174–176.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7780062</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33372818</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Updated case definition of MIS-C and implications for clinical care. Day-Lewis M, Berbert L, Baker A, Dionne A, Newburger JW, Son MB. Pediatrics. 2024;153:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38204335</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A comparison of Kawasaki Disease and multisystem inflammatory syndrome in children. Wessels PA, Bingler MA. Prog Pediatr Cardiol. 2022;65:101516.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8925196</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35313700</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antibiotics and bacterial resistance—a short story of an endless arms race. Baran A, Kwiatkowska A, Potocki L. Int J Mol Sci. 2023;24:5777.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10056106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36982857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Antibiotic use in children with multisystem inflammatory syndrome associated with SARS-CoV-2. Zembles TN, Ray KM, Kuhn EM, Huppler AR. Acta Paediatr. 2022;111:1583–1584.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9347434</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35599606</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Epidemiological and diagnostic features of Blastocystis infection in symptomatic patients in Izmir province, Turkey. Dagci H, Kurt Ö, Demirel M, et al.  http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4345091/ Iran J Parasitol. 2014;9:519–529.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4345091</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25759733</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>