<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39469390</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Parental Stress and Psychological Distress and Their Association With Spousal Support Among Parents of School-Age Children During the COVID-19 Pandemic in South India: A Cross-Sectional Observational Study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70372</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70372</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e70372</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.70372</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="CONTEXT" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The COVID-19 pandemic presented unprecedented challenges to families in the form of social isolation, economic difficulties and inaccessibility of educational and supportive services.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="AIMS" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To assess the levels of parental stress and psychological distress among parents of school-age children during the COVID-19 pandemic and to analyse its correlation with spousal support.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIALS AND METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A cross-sectional, web-based study was conducted among the parents of school-age children in south India. One hundred thirty-two completed responses were obtained. Study tools included Parental Stress Scale, Spouse Support Scale and Kessler's psychological distress scale-6 item version.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The mean parental stress score was 42.39 ± 9.679. Sixty percent of the participants reported moderate to high levels of psychological distress. Parental stress and psychological distress scores were noted to have a significant negative correlation with spousal support scores (r=-.486, p=.000 and r=-.401, p=.000 respectively).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Our study findings show that the COVID-19 pandemic has taken a toll on the psychological well-being of parents of school-age children. Supportive interventions to address parenting difficulties need to be undertaken to prevent long-term adverse mental health outcomes. Lessons learnt from the pandemic are important for clinicians and policymakers to take measures to alleviate parental stress as well as to promote the psychological well-being of parents and children.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Shireen et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shireen</LastName><ForeName>Sthuthi</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Psychiatry, Amrita Institute of Medical Sciences, Kochi, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jith</LastName><ForeName>Arya</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Psychiatry, Sree Uthradom Thirunal (SUT) Academy of Medical Sciences, Thiruvananthapuram, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Thomas</LastName><ForeName>Priya E</ForeName><Initials>PE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Psychiatry, Kasturba Medical College, Mangalore, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Methala</LastName><ForeName>Sharon P</ForeName><Initials>SP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Gastroenterology, Amrita Institute of Medical Sciences, Kochi, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mathew</LastName><ForeName>Kathleen A</ForeName><Initials>KA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Psychiatry, Amrita Institute of Medical Sciences, Kochi, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pandemic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">parental stress</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">psychological distress</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">school-age children</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">spousal support</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Ethics Committee of Amrita School of Medicine issued approval ECASM-AIMS-2021-309. Animal subjects: All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39469390</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11513691</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.70372</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Stress and parenting during the global COVID-19 pandemic. Brown SM, Doom JR, Lechuga-Peña S, Watamura SE, Koppels T. https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0145213420303549. Child Abuse Negl. 2020;110:104699.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7440155</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32859394</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Families in the COVID-19 pandemic: parental stress, parent mental health and the occurrence of adverse childhood experiences-results of a representative survey in Germany. Calvano C, Engelke L, Di Bella J, Kindermann J, Renneberg B, Winter SM. https://link.springer.com/10.1007/s00787-021-01739-0 Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2022;31:1–13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7917379</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33646416</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perceived stress, parental stress, and parenting during COVID-19 lockdown: a preliminary study. Sahithya BR, Kashyap RS, Roopesh BN. http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/0973134220200404 J Indian Assoc Child Adolesc Ment Health. 2020;16:44–63.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mediating effects of parental stress on harsh parenting and parent-child relationship during coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic in Singapore. Chung G, Lanier P, Wong PY. J Fam Violence. 2022;37:801–812.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7467635</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32895601</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parent emotional distress and feeding styles in low-income families. The role of parent depression and parenting stress. Hughes SO, Power TG, Liu Y, Sharp C, Nicklas TA. https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0195666315002895. Appetite. 2015;92:337–342.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26050915</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Preschool children with and without developmental delay: behaviour problems, parents' optimism and well-being. Baker BL, Blacher J, Olsson MB. https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1365-2788.2005.00691.x. J Intellect Disabil Res. 2005;49:575–590.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16011551</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parenting stress mediates between maternal maltreatment history and maternal sensitivity in a community sample. Pereira J, Vickers K, Atkinson L, Gonzalez A, Wekerle C, Levitan R. https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0145213412000828. Child Abuse Negl. 2012;36:433–437.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22633056</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Supporting families to protect child health: parenting quality and household needs during the COVID-19 pandemic. Roos LE, Salisbury M, Penner-Goeke L, et al.  https://dx.plos.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0251720 PLoS One. 2021;16:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8143383</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34029311</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mothers' functioning and children's symptoms 5 years after a SCUD missile attack. Laor N, Wolmer L, Cohen DJ. Am J Psychiatry. 2001;158:1020–1026.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11431222</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stuck outside and inside: an exploratory study on the effects of the COVID-19 outbreak on Italian parents and children’s internalizing symptoms. Crescentini C, Feruglio S, Matiz A, Paschetto A, Vidal E, Cogo P, Fabbro F. Front Psychol. 2020;11:586074.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7649806</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33192917</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>An examination of validity and reliability of the Parental Stress Scale in a population based sample of Norwegian parents. Nærde A, Sommer Hukkelberg S. https://dx.plos.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0242735 PLoS One. 2020;15:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7710163</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33264325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The development of the Cleminshaw-Guidubaldi Parent Satisfaction Scale. Guidubaldi J, Cleminshaw HK. http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1207/s15374424jccp1404_4 J Clin Child Psychol. 1985;14:293–298.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Short screening scales to monitor population prevalences and trends in non-specific psychological distress. Kessler RC, Andrews G, Colpe LJ, et al.  https://www.cambridge.org/core/product/identifier/S0033291702006074/type/journal_article. Psychol Med. 2002;32:959–976.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12214795</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Relationship between parenting stress and school closures due to the COVID‐19 pandemic. Hiraoka D, Tomoda A. https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/pcn.13088. Psychiatry Clin Neurosci. 2020;74:497–498.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7323183</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32779846</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A preliminary study of COVID-19-related stressors, parenting stress, and parental psychological well-being among parents of school-age children. Chen CY, Byrne E, Vélez T. https://link.springer.com/10.1007/s10826-022-02321-1. J Child Fam Stud. 2022;31:1558–1569.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9045686</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35502365</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The roles of social support and coping strategies in predicting breast cancer patients' emotional well-being: testing mediation and moderation models. Kim J, Han JY, Shaw B, McTavish F, Gustafson D. http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1359105309355338. J Health Psychol. 2010;15:543–552.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3145334</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20460411</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The relationships among perceived stress, conflict resolution styles, spousal support and marital satisfaction during the COVID-19 quarantine. Işık RA, Kaya Y. Curr Psychol. 2022;41:3328–3338.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9203771</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35730053</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A systemic-transactional conceptualization of stress and coping in couples. Bodenmann G. https://psycnet.apa.org/record/1996-14234-001 Swiss J Psychol. 1995;54:34–49.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The role of stress on close relationships and marital satisfaction. Randall AK, Bodenmann G. https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0272735808001402. Clin Psychol Rev. 2009;29:105–115.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19167139</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bodenmann G. Couples Coping With Stress: Emerging Perspectives on Dyadic Coping. Washington, DC: American Psychological Association; 2005. Dyadic coping and its significance for marital functioning; pp. 33–49.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Use and benefit of dyadic coping for couple relationship satisfaction in parents of children with autism. Putney JM, Greenlee JL, Hartley SL. https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/famp.12617. Fam Process. 2021;60:1331–1346.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8155113</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33247443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parental stress during the COVID-19 pandemic: a one-year follow-up. Bjørknes R, Skogen JC, Nærde A, et al. PLoS One. 2022;17:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9725124</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36472999</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pearcey S, Creswell C. Co-SPACE Study. March.  [
Sep;
2024 
]. 2021. https://cospaceoxford.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/Report_09_9march2021-1.pdf https://cospaceoxford.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/Report_09_9march2021-1.pdf</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>