<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39465918</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">0970-2113</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>41</Volume><Issue>6</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Lung India : official organ of Indian Chest Society</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Lung India</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Persistent pulmonary impairment after 2 years of COVID-19 infection: An observational study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>405</StartPage><EndPage>410</EndPage><MedlinePgn>405-410</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4103/lungindia.lungindia_87_24</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Persistent dyspnoea and pulmonary function impairment are common after coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19). However, long-term outcomes beyond 2 years of infection are unknown.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">In this single-center study, we observed the trend of self-reported dyspnoea and pulmonary functions among subjects attending a post-COVID clinic in India after 2 years of COVID-19 illness. Using logistic regression, we explored the clinico-demographic factors associated with persistent dyspnoea and impaired lung functions beyond 2 years.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Among 231 included subjects (68.8% male) with a mean [standard deviation (SD)] age of 44.8 (13.2) years, 119 (51.5%) had recovered from moderate-to-severe COVID-19. The median [inter-quartile range (IQR)] time intervals from COVID-19 diagnosis (T0) to clinical enrolment (T1) and final follow-up (T2) were 3.3 (1.9-5.5) months and 29.5 (27.2-32.2) months, respectively. Between T1 and T2, the prevalence of self-reported dyspnoea remained stable in the whole cohort (39.4% vs. 36.4%, P = 0.26) but declined in the sub-group with moderate-to-severe COVID-19 (63% vs. 54.6%, P = 0.03). Persistent dyspnoea at T2 was associated with female sex (P = 0.007), moderate-to-severe COVID-19 (P &lt; 0.001), and infection during the delta wave (P &lt; 0.001). At T2, impairment in forced vital capacity (FVC) was seen in 48.1% subjects. Persistently impaired FVC was associated with older age (P value = 0.047), female sex (P value &lt;0.001), and infection during the delta wave (P value = 0.02).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Persistent self-reported dyspnoea and impaired pulmonary functions were common in COVID-19 survivors beyond 2 years of infection. Female sex and infection during the delta wave were associated with long-term impairments.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Copyright: © 2024 Indian Chest Society.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Suri</LastName><ForeName>Tejas Menon</ForeName><Initials>TM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pulmonary, Critical Care and Sleep Medicine, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, New Delhi, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Srivastava</LastName><ForeName>Garima</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kumar</LastName><ForeName>Sunil</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Surendranath</LastName><ForeName>A</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shaji</LastName><ForeName>Syam</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mittal</LastName><ForeName>Saurabh</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tiwari</LastName><ForeName>Pawan</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hadda</LastName><ForeName>Vijay</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Madan</LastName><ForeName>Karan</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chauhan</LastName><ForeName>Abhishek</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mohan</LastName><ForeName>Anant</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>India</Country><MedlineTA>Lung India</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8405380</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0970-2113</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>9</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39465918</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/lungindia.lungindia_87_24</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">01408641-202411000-00002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Hussain A, Yadav S, Hadda V, Suri TM, Tiwari P, Mittal S, et al. Covid-19:A comprehensive review of a formidable foe and the road ahead. Expert Rev Respir Med 2020;14:869–79.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>. COVID-19 deaths |WHO COVID-19 dashboard Available from: https://data.who.int/dashboards/covid19/cases Last accessed on 2023 Dec 23.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed H, Patel K, Greenwood DC, Halpin S, Lewthwaite P, Salawu A, et al. Long-term clinical outcomes in survivors of severe acute respiratory syndrome and Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus outbreaks after hospitalisation or ICU admission:A systematic review and meta-analysis. J Rehabil Med 2020;52:jrm00063.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CDC. Post-COVID Conditions. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention 2023 Available from: https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/long-term-effects/index.html Last accessed on 2023 Dec 23.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davis HE, McCorkell L, Vogel JM, Topol EJ. Long COVID:Major findings, mechanisms and recommendations. Nat Rev Microbiol 2023;21:133–46.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hadda V, Suri TM, Iyer H, Jain A, Mittal S, Madan K, et al. A Delphi consensus statement for the management of post-COVID interstitial lung disease. Expert Rev Respir Med 2022;16:983–95.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang P, Li J, Liu H, Han N, Ju J, Kou Y, et al. Long-term bone and lung consequences associated with hospital-acquired severe acute respiratory syndrome:A 15-year follow-up from a prospective cohort study. Bone Res 2020;8:8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faverio P, Paciocco G, Tassistro E, Rebora P, Rossi E, Monzani A, et al. Two-year cardio-pulmonary follow-up after severe COVID-19:A prospective study. Intern Emerg Med 2023;19:183–90.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peghin M, De Martino M, Palese A, Chiappinotto S, Fonda F, Gerussi V, et al. Post-COVID-19 syndrome 2 years after the first wave:The role of humoral response, vaccination and reinfection. Open Forum Infect Dis 2023;10:ofad364.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang L, Li X, Gu X, Zhang H, Ren L, Guo L, et al. Health outcomes in people 2 years after surviving hospitalisation with COVID-19:A longitudinal cohort study. Lancet Respir Med 2022;10:863–76.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang W, Shaman J. COVID-19 pandemic dynamics in India, the SARS-CoV-2 Delta variant and implications for vaccination. J R Soc Interface 2022;19:20210900.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>. Clinical anagement Protocol for COVID-19 (In Adults), Version 6. Ministry of Health &amp;Family Welfare, Government of India 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bode SFN, Haendly M, Fabricius D, Mayer B, Zernickel M, Haddad ADM, et al. Pulmonary function and persistent clinical symptoms in children and their parents 12 months after mild SARS-CoV-2 infection. Front Pediatr 2022;10:894331.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wahlgren C, Forsberg G, Divanoglou A, Östholm Balkhed Å, Niward K, Berg S, et al. Two-year follow-up of patients with post-COVID-19 condition in Sweden:A prospective cohort study. Lancet Reg Health Eur 2023;28:100595.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cascino TM, Desai AA, Kanthi Y. At a crossroads:COVID-19 recovery and the risk of pulmonary vascular disease. Curr Opin Pulm Med 2021;27:342–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polkey MI. Diaphragm dysfunction as a contributor to breathlessness after COVID-19 Infection. Am J Respir Crit Care Med;207:964–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suppini N, Fira-Mladinescu O, Traila D, Motofelea AC, Marc MS, Manolescu D, et al. Longitudinal analysis of pulmonary function impairment one year post-COVID-19:A single-center study. J Pers Med 2023;13:1190.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Willigen HDG, Wynberg E, Verveen A, Dijkstra M, Verkaik BJ, Figaroa OJA, et al. One-fourth of COVID-19 patients have an impaired pulmonary function after 12 months of disease onset. PLoS One 2023;18:e0290893.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lenoir A, Christe A, Ebner L, Beigelman-Aubry C, Bridevaux PO, Brutsche M, et al. Pulmonary recovery 12 months after non-severe and severe covid-19:The prospective Swiss covid-19 lung study. Respiration 2023;102:120–33.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tarraso J, Safont B, Carbonell-Asins JA, Fernandez-Fabrellas E, Sancho-Chust JN, Naval E, et al. Lung function and radiological findings 1 year after COVID-19:A prospective follow-up. Respir Res 2022;23:242.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu X, Liu X, Zhou Y, Yu H, Li R, Zhan Q, et al. 3-month, 6-month, 9-month, and 12-month respiratory outcomes in patients following COVID-19-related hospitalisation:A prospective study. Lancet Respir Med 2021;9:747–54.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaiwong W, Deesomchok A, Pothirat C, Liwsrisakun C, Duangjit P, Bumroongkit C, et al. The long-term impact of COVID-19 pneumonia on pulmonary function and exercise capacity. J Thorac Dis 2023;15:4725–35.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang H, Li X, Huang L, Gu X, Wang Y, Liu M, et al. Lung-function trajectories in COVID-19 survivors after discharge:A two-year longitudinal cohort study. EClinicalMedicine 2022;54:101668.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cho SJ, Stout-Delgado HW. Aging and lung disease. Annu Rev Physiol 2020;82:433–59.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kragholm K, Andersen MP, Gerds TA, Butt JH, Østergaard L, Polcwiartek C, et al. Association between male sex and outcomes of coronavirus disease 2019 (covid-19)-A Danish nationwide, register-based study. Clin Infect Dis 2021;73:e4025–30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petrilli CM, Jones SA, Yang J, Rajagopalan H, O'Donnell L, Chernyak Y, et al. Factors associated with hospital admission and critical illness among 5279 people with coronavirus disease 2019 in New York City:Prospective cohort study. BMJ 2020;369:m1966.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernández-de-las-Peñas C, Martín-Guerrero JD, Pellicer-Valero ÓJ, Navarro-Pardo E, Gómez-Mayordomo V, Cuadrado ML, et al. Female sex is a risk factor associated with long-term post-covid related-symptoms but not with covid-19 symptoms:The long-covid-exp-cm multicenter study. J Clin Med 2022;11:413.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma P, Basu S, Mishra S, Gupta E, Agarwal R, Kale P, et al. SARS-CoV-2 Seroprevalence in Delhi, India, During September-October 2021:A population-based seroepidemiological study. Cureus 2022;14:e27428.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ngai JC, Ko FW, Ng SS, To KW, Tong M, Hui DS. The long-term impact of severe acute respiratory syndrome on pulmonary function, exercise capacity and health status. Respirology 2010;15:543–50.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>