<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39462922</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1998-3689</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>72</Volume><Issue>11</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Indian journal of ophthalmology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Indian J Ophthalmol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Descriptive study of patient outcome and satisfaction with telemedicine and physical consultation during and after the COVID-19 pandemic.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1586</StartPage><EndPage>1592</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1586-1592</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4103/IJO.IJO_2020_23</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="PURPOSE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">This study was conducted to assess patients' outcome and satisfaction with the eye care received with telemedicine and physical consultation at a tertiary care hospital during and after the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A descriptive study was carried out on 6052 patients who consulted for eye illness at a tertiary care hospital between April 2020 and December 2022. An outcome scoring system was developed and validated for the assessment of patient outcome after providing treatment on telemedicine consultation and physical consultation. Outcome scores for various symptoms were compared pretreatment and posttreatment. Telehealth Usability Questionnaire (TUQ) was used through an online survey to assess patients' satisfaction with teleophthalmology services during the COVID-19 pandemic. An 18-item Patient Satisfaction Questionnaire (PSQ-18) was used to assess the same with physical consultation.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">A total of 6052 patients were included in the study. Physical consultation group had 2485 patients (41.06%) and the telemedicine group had 3567 patients (58.93%). Male patients constituted 63.11% and females were 36.89%. There was a significant improvement in outcome scores for pain and redness in both physical and telemedicine consultation groups (P &lt; 0.0001). All subgroups of TUQ had significantly high scores (including usefulness, ease of use and learnability, interface quality, interaction quality, and satisfaction and future use), except one subgroup (reliability). Uneducated patients were significantly more satisfied with telemedicine compared to educated patients (P = 0.044).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Majority of patients expressed satisfaction with teleophthalmology services. The recent pandemic paved the way for the future integration of telemedicine in ophthalmology, especially if virtual eye examinations attain a higher level of reliability.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Copyright: © 2024 Indian Journal of Ophthalmology.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Asodariya</LastName><ForeName>Ronak</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Ophthalmology, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Jodhpur, Rajasthan, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bhatnagar</LastName><ForeName>Kavita R</ForeName><Initials>KR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Ophthalmology, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Jodhpur, Rajasthan, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jaisingh</LastName><ForeName>Kirti</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Ophthalmology, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Jodhpur, Rajasthan, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tandon</LastName><ForeName>Manjari</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Ophthalmology, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Jodhpur, Rajasthan, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pandey</LastName><ForeName>Latika</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Ophthalmology, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Jodhpur, Rajasthan, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Agrawal</LastName><ForeName>Nikhil</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Ophthalmology, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Jodhpur, Rajasthan, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Misra</LastName><ForeName>Sanjeev</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Surgical Oncology, Vice Chancellor, Atal Bihari, Vajpayee Medical University, Lucknow, Uttar Pradesh, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>India</Country><MedlineTA>Indian J Ophthalmol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0405376</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0301-4738</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017060" MajorTopicYN="Y">Patient Satisfaction</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017216" MajorTopicYN="Y">Telemedicine</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="Y">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005128" MajorTopicYN="Y">Eye Diseases</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000628" MajorTopicYN="N">therapy</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011795" MajorTopicYN="N">Surveys and Questionnaires</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012017" MajorTopicYN="N">Referral and Consultation</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009885" MajorTopicYN="N">Ophthalmology</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007194" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">India</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000368" MajorTopicYN="N">Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055815" MajorTopicYN="N">Young Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000293" MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescent</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39462922</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/IJO.IJO_2020_23</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">02223307-202472110-00010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Kaushik S, Kaushik S, Sharma Y, Kumar R, Yadav JP. The Indian perspective of COVID-19 outbreak. Virusdisease 2020;31:146–53.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rothan HA, Byrareddy SN. The epidemiology and pathogenesis of coronavirus disease (COVID-19) outbreak. J Autoimmun 2020;109:102433.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalra G, Williams AM, Commiskey PW, Bowers EMR, Schempf T, Sahel JA, et al. Incorporating video visits into ophthalmology practice: A retrospective analysis and patient survey to assess initial experiences and patient acceptability at an academic eye center. Ophthalmol Ther 2020;9:549–62.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al Owaifeer AM, Al-Swailem SA, Al Dehailan AM, Al Naim A, Al Molhim MF, Khandekar RB. Physician satisfaction with virtual ophthalmology clinics during the covid-19 pandemic: A tertiary eye care center experience. Cureus 2022;14:e23837.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Lott LB, Newman-Casey PA, Lee PP, Ballouz D, Azzouz L, Cho J, et al. Change in ophthalmic clinicians’ attitudes toward telemedicine during the coronavirus 2019 pandemic. Telemed E-Health 2021;27:231–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saleem SM, Pasquale LR, Sidoti PA, Tsai JC. Virtual ophthalmology: Telemedicine in a COVID-19 Era. Am J Ophthalmol 2020;216:237–42.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryu S. Telemedicine: Opportunities and developments in member states: Report on the second global survey on eHealth 2009 (Global Observatory for eHealth Series, Volume 2). Healthc Inform Res 2012;18:153–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galagali PM, Ghosh S, Bhargav H. The role of telemedicine in child and adolescent healthcare in India. Curr Pediatr Rep 2021;9:154–61.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sommer AC, Blumenthal EZ. Telemedicine in ophthalmology in view of the emerging COVID-19 outbreak. Graefes Arch Clin Exp Ophthalmol 2020;258:2341–52.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dhingra D, Dabas A. Global strategy on digital health. Indian Pediatr 2020;57:356–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de la Torre-Díez I, López-Coronado M, Vaca C, Aguado JS, de Castro C. Cost-utility and cost-effectiveness studies of telemedicine, electronic, and mobile health systems in the literature: A systematic review. Telemed E-Health 2015;21:81–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma M, Jain N, Ranganathan S, Sharma N, Honavar SG, Sharma N, et al. Tele-ophthalmology: Need of the hour. Indian J Ophthalmol 2020;68:1328–38.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Portnoy JM, Pandya A, Waller M, Elliott T. Telemedicine and emerging technologies for health care in allergy/immunology. J Allergy Clin Immunol 2020;145:445–54.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta PC, Kumar MP, Ram J. COVID-19 pandemic from an ophthalmology point of view. Indian J Med Res 2020;151:411–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Newman-Casey PA, De Lott L, Cho J, Ballouz D, Azzouz L, Saleh S, et al. Telehealth-based eye care during the covid-19 pandemic: Utilization, safety, and the patient experience. Am J Ophthalmol 2021;230:234–42.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tousif S, Hasaneen M, Mehta S, Mehta V, Natarajan, Hasan, et al. Utility of telemedicine in ophthalmology clinic during COVID-19 era. Hematol Res Rev 2021;3:46–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yip MP, Chang AM, Chan J, MacKenzie AE. Development of the telemedicine satisfaction questionnaire to evaluate patient satisfaction with telemedicine: A preliminary study. J Telemed Telecare 2003;9:46–50.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parmanto B, Lewis AN, Graham KM, Bertolet MH. Development of the Telehealth Usability Questionnaire (TUQ). Int J Telerehabilitation 2016;8:3–10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thayaparan AJ, Mahdi E. The patient satisfaction questionnaire short form (PSQ-18) as an adaptable, reliable, and validated tool for use in various settings. Med Educ Online 2013;18:21747.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polinski JM, Barker T, Gagliano N, Sussman A, Brennan TA, Shrank WH. Patients’ satisfaction with and preference for telehealth visits. J Gen Intern Med 2016;31:269–75.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caycedo A, Serrano A, Ucrós A, Caycedo A, Serrano A, Ucrós A. Telemedicine and ophthalmology amidst covid-19: A descriptive study. Univ Medica 2022;63:1–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kapoor S, Eldib A, Hiasat J, Scanga H, Tomasello J, Alabek M, et al. Developing a pediatric ophthalmology telemedicine program in the COVID-19 crisis. J Am Assoc Pediatr Ophthalmol Strabismus 2020;24:204–8.e2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Golash V, Athwal S, Khandwala M. Teleophthalmology and COVID-19: The patient perspective. Future Healthc J 2021;8:e54–9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ceprnja D, Clark T, Young J, Lee R, Flynn K, Maka K. Evaluating experiences, usability and patient satisfaction with telehealth for tertiary outpatient physiotherapy services during COVID-19: A mixed-methods study. Physiother Theory Pract 2022;39:1929–37.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peterson KM, Huisingh CE, Girkin C, Owsley C, Rhodes LA. Patient satisfaction with care in an urban tertiary referral academic glaucoma clinic in the US. Patient Prefer Adherence 2018;12:775–81.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sakti DH, Firdaus AT, Utami TP, Jati KDP, Mahayana IT, Wardhana FS, et al. Patients’ satisfaction with ophthalmology clinic services in a public teaching hospital. Patient Prefer Adherence 2022;16:723–35.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nikolaidou A, Tsaousis KT. Teleophthalmology and artificial intelligence as game changers in ophthalmic care after the COVID-19 pandemic. Cureus 2021;13:e16392.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>