<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39468002</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2196-8837</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>28</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of racial and ethnic health disparities</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Racial Ethn Health Disparities</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A Review of the Public Health Literature Examining the Roles of Socioeconomic Status and Race/Ethnicity on Health Outcomes in the United States.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s40615-024-02195-7</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>This review of reviews examines the role of socioeconomic status (SES) indicators on health inequities among different racial and ethnic groups in the United States (US) between 2019 and 2023. Of the 419 articles, 27 reviews met the inclusion criteria and were aggregated into seven categories: COVID-19 and respiratory pandemic disparities; neighborhoods, gentrification, and food environment; surgical treatments; mental, psychological, and behavioral health; insurance, access to care, and policy impact; cancers; and other topics. The findings revealed a documented impact of SES indicators on racial/ethnic health inequities, with racial/ethnic minority communities, especially Black Americans, consistently showing poor health outcomes associated with lower SES, regardless of the outcome or indicator examined. These findings call attention to the importance of policies and practices that address socioeconomic factors and systemic racial/ethnic inequities affecting the social determinants of health affecting racial/ethnic inequities to improve health outcomes in the US population.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. W. Montague Cobb-NMA Health Institute.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>White</LastName><ForeName>Trenton M</ForeName><Initials>TM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology &amp; Biostatistics, Graduate School of Public Health &amp; Health Policy, The City University of New York (CUNY), 55 West 125th Street, 530, New York, NY, 10027, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Barcelona Institute for Global Health (ISGlobal), Barcelona, Spain.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Borrell</LastName><ForeName>Luisa N</ForeName><Initials>LN</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0560-4853</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology &amp; Biostatistics, Graduate School of Public Health &amp; Health Policy, The City University of New York (CUNY), 55 West 125th Street, 530, New York, NY, 10027, USA. Luisa.Borrell@sph.cuny.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>El-Mohandes</LastName><ForeName>Ayman</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology &amp; Biostatistics, Graduate School of Public Health &amp; Health Policy, The City University of New York (CUNY), 55 West 125th Street, 530, New York, NY, 10027, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>J Racial Ethn Health Disparities</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101628476</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2196-8837</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Health inequity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Inequity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Social determinants</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Socioeconomic indicators</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>28</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39468002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40615-024-02195-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s40615-024-02195-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Taylor S. Wealth, health and equity: convergence to divergence in late 20th century globalization. Br Med Bull. 2009;91:29–48. https://doi.org/10.1093/bmb/ldp024 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/bmb/ldp024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19654137</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Preda A, Voigt K. The social determinants of health: why should we care? Am J Bioeth. 2015;15:25–36. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/25786009/ . Accessed 22 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackson H, Engelman M. Deaths, disparities, and cumulative (dis)advantage: how social inequities produce an impairment paradox in later life. J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci [Internet]. 2022;77:392–401. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34165517/ . Accessed 22 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braveman P, Gottlieb L. The social determinants of health: it’s time to consider the causes of the causes. Public Health Reports [Internet]. 2014;129(Suppl 2):19–31. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/24385661/ . Accessed 22 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rigal L, Saurel-Cubizolles MJ, Falcoff H, Bouyer J, Ringa V. Do social inequalities in cervical cancer screening persist among patients who use primary care? The Paris prevention in general practice survey. Prev Med (Baltim) [Internet]. 2011;53:199–202. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/21726576/ . Accessed 22 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Álvarez-Gálvez J, Ortega-Martín E, Carretero-Bravo J, Pérez-Muñoz C, Suárez-Lledó V, Ramos-Fiol B. Social determinants of multimorbidity patterns: a systematic review. Front Public Health [Internet]. 2023;11. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/37050950/ . Accessed 22 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sum G, Hone T, Atun R, Millett C, Suhrcke M, Mahal A, et al. Multimorbidity and out-of-pocket expenditure on medicines: a systematic review. BMJ Glob Health [Internet]. 2018;3. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29564155/ . Accessed 22 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahajan S, Lu Y, Spatz ES, Nasir K, Krumholz HM. Trends and predictors of use of digital health technology in the United States. Am J Med [Internet]. 2021;134:129–34. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/32717188/ . Accessed 22 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Labrique A, Vasudevan L, Weiss W, Wilson K. Establishing standards to evaluate the impact of integrating digital health into health systems. Glob Health Sci Pract. 2018;6:S5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30305335</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6203412</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.9745/GHSP-D-18-00230</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pfeffer FT, Killewald A. Intergenerational wealth mobility and racial inequality. Socius [Internet]. 2019;5. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31312720/ . Accessed 22 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Brookings Institution. Homeownership, racial segregation, and policy solutions to racial wealth equity. 2021. https://www.brookings.edu/articles/homeownership-racial-segregation-and-policies-for-racial-wealth-equity/ .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khera R, Valero-Elizondo J, Okunrintemi V, Saxena A, Das SR, De Lemos JA, et al. Association of out-of-pocket annual health expenditures with financial hardship in low-income adults with atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease in the United States. JAMA Cardiol [Internet]. 2018;3:729–38. https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamacardiology/fullarticle/2686709 . Accessed 22 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Christopher AS, Himmelstein DU, Woolhandler S, McCormick D. The effects of household medical expenditures on income inequality in the United States. Am J Public Health [Internet]. 2018;108:351–4. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29345995/ . Accessed 22 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bakkila BF, Basu S, Lipska KJ. Catastrophic spending on insulin in the United States, 2017–18. Health Aff [Internet]. 2022;41:1053–60. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/35787081/ . Accessed 22 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richard P, Walker R, Alexandre P. The burden of out of pocket costs and medical debt faced by households with chronic health conditions in the United States. PLoS One. 2018;13:e0199598. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0199598 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0199598</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29940025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6016939</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rakshit S, Rae M, Claxton G, Amin K, Cox C, Kaiser Family Foundation. The burden of medical debt in the United States [Internet]. Health System Tracker. 2024. https://www.healthsystemtracker.org/brief/the-burden-of-medical-debt-in-the-united-states/?_hsmi=206419781&amp;_hsenc=p2ANqtz-8cSdzB6arxPwFVkSUSFDyu4TcJtQ6ZcsaFpovrnIZmWLzopuV2n9EcPQf32itTeovy76Gvabj0CMXPkbAgWM_5sPH8nQ&amp;utm_campaign=KFF-2022-Health-Costs&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_content=206419781&amp;utm_source=hs_email . Accessed 22 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mendes De Leon CF, Griggs JJ. Medical debt as a social determinant of health. JAMA [Internet]. 2021;326:228–9. https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/fullarticle/2782205 . Accessed 22 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Janevic T, Zeitlin J, Egorova NN, Hebert P, Balbierz A, Stroustrup AM, et al. Racial and economic neighborhood segregation, site of delivery, and morbidity and mortality in neonates born very preterm. J Pediatr. 2021;235:116–23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33794221</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9582630</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jpeds.2021.03.049</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krieger N, Van Wye G, Huynh M, Waterman PD, Maduro G, Li W, et al. Structural racism, historical redlining, and risk of preterm birth in New York City, 2013–2017. Am J Public Health. 2020;110:1046–53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32437270</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7287548</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2020.305656</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kapadia F, Borrell LN. Structural racism and health inequities: moving from evidence to action. Am J Public Health [Internet]. 2023;113:S6–9. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36696612/ . Accessed 22 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeffers NK, Berger BO, Marea CX, Gemmill A. Investigating the impact of structural racism on black birthing people - associations between racialized economic segregation, incarceration inequality, and severe maternal morbidity. Soc Sci Med [Internet]. 2023;317. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36542927/ . Accessed 22 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alroy KA, Cavalier H, Crossa A, Wang SM, Liu SY, Norman C, et al. Can changing neighborhoods influence mental health? An ecological analysis of gentrification and neighborhood-level serious psychological distress-New York City, 2002–2015. PLoS One [Internet]. 2023;18. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/37018221/ . Accessed 22 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farooq M, Madan S, Diab K, Melainis AA, Jorde U. Healthcare disparities in heart failure patients and use of sodium glucose co-transport inhibitors (SGLT2-i). J Card Fail. 2022;28:S33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cardfail.2022.03.088</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lieberman-Cribbin W, Tuminello S, Flores RM, Taioli E. Disparities in COVID-19 testing and positivity in New York City. Am J Prev Med [Internet]. 2020;59:326–32. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/32703702/ . Accessed 22 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Truong N, Asare AO. Assessing the effect of socio-economic features of low-income communities and COVID-19 related cases: an empirical study of New York City. Glob Public Health [Internet]. 2021;16:1–16. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/33222624/ . Accessed 22 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khanijahani A, Iezadi S, Gholipour K, Azami-Aghdash S, Naghibi D. A systematic review of racial/ethnic and socioeconomic disparities in COVID-19. Int J Equity Health. 2021;20:248.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34819081</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8611382</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12939-021-01582-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Magesh S, John D, Li WT, Li Y, Mattingly-App A, Jain S, et al. Disparities in COVID-19 outcomes by race, ethnicity, and socioeconomic status: a systematic-review and meta-analysis. JAMA Netw Open. 2021;4:e2134147.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34762110</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8586903</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.34147</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Renson A, Dennis AC, Noppert G, McClure ES, Aiello AE. Interventions on socioeconomic and racial inequities in respiratory pandemics: a rapid systematic review. Curr Epidemiol Rep. 2022;9:66–76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35287290</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8907033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40471-022-00284-x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larrabee Sonderlund A, Charifson M, Schoenthaler A, Carson T, Williams NJ. Racialized economic segregation and health outcomes: a systematic review of studies that use the index of concentration at the extremes for race, income, and their interaction. PLoS ONE. 2022;17:e0262962.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35089963</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8797220</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0262962</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhavsar NA, Kumar M, Richman L. Defining gentrification for epidemiologic research: a systematic review. PLoS ONE. 2020;15:e0233361.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32437388</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7241805</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0233361</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith GS, Breakstone H, Dean LT, Thorpe RJ. Impacts of gentrification on health in the us: a systematic review of the literature. J Urban Health. 2020;97:845–56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32829469</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7704880</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11524-020-00448-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnson KA, Showell NN, Flessa S, Janssen M, Reid N, Cheskin LJ, et al. Do neighborhoods matter? A systematic review of modifiable risk factors for obesity among low socio-economic status Black and Hispanic children. Child Obes. 2019;15:71–86.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30565954</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6386088</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/chi.2018.0044</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tulier ME, Reid C, Mujahid MS, Allen AM. ‘Clear action requires clear thinking’: a systematic review of gentrification and health research in the United States. Health Place. 2019;59:102173.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31357049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6868313</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.healthplace.2019.102173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kraft AN, Thatcher EJ, Zenk SN. Neighborhood food environment and health outcomes in U.S. low-socioeconomic status, racial/ethnic minority, and rural populations: a systematic review. J Health Care Poor Underserved. 2020;31:1078–114.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33416683</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1353/hpu.2020.0083</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matsuzaki M, Sánchez BN, Acosta ME, Botkin J, Sanchez-Vaznaugh EV. Food environment near schools and body weight-a systematic review of associations by race/ethnicity, gender, grade, and socio-economic factors. Obes Rev. 2020;21:e12997.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32026567</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7058504</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/obr.12997</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mendoza J, Pangal DJ, Cardinal T, Bonney PA, Lechtholz-Zey E, Strickland BA, et al. Systematic review of racial, socioeconomic, and insurance status disparities in neurosurgical care for intracranial tumors. World Neurosurg. 2022;158:38–64.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34710578</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.wneu.2021.10.126</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cardinal T, Strickland BA, Bonney PA, Lechtholz-Zey E, Mendoza J, Pangal DJ, et al. Disparities in the surgical treatment of cerebrovascular pathologies: a contemporary systematic review. World Neurosurg. 2022;158:244–257.e1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34856403</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.wneu.2021.11.106</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cardinal T, Bonney PA, Strickland BA, Lechtholz-Zey E, Mendoza J, Pangal DJ, et al. Disparities in the surgical treatment of adult spine diseases: a systematic review. World Neurosurg. 2022;158:290–304.e1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34688939</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.wneu.2021.10.121</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lechtholz-Zey E, Bonney PA, Cardinal T, Mendoza J, Strickland BA, Pangal DJ, et al. Systematic review of racial, socioeconomic, and insurance status disparities in the treatment of pediatric neurosurgical diseases in the United States. World Neurosurg. 2022;158:65–83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34718199</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.wneu.2021.10.150</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ingram M-CE, Calabro K, Polites S, McCracken C, Aspelund G, Rich BS, et al. Systematic review of disparities in care and outcomes in pediatric appendectomy. J Surg Res. 2020;249:42–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31918329</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jss.2019.12.018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schein J, Houle C, Urganus A, Cloutier M, Patterson-Lomba O, Wang Y, et al. Prevalence of post-traumatic stress disorder in the United States: a systematic literature review. Curr Med Res Opin. 2021;37:2151–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34498953</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/03007995.2021.1978417</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korous KM, Causadias JM, Bradley RH, Levy R, Cahill KM, Li L, et al. ‘More is better’ or ‘better near the middle’? A U.S.-based individual participant data meta-analysis of socioeconomic status and depressive symptoms. Am Psychol. 2023;78:305–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36326635</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/amp0001076</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alcántara C, Giorgio Cosenzo L, McCullough E, Vogt T, Falzon AL, Perez II. Cultural adaptations of psychological interventions for prevalent sleep disorders and sleep disturbances: a systematic review of randomized controlled trials in the United States. Sleep Med Rev. 2021;56:101455.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33735638</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.smrv.2021.101455</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eilenberg JS, Paff M, Harrison AJ, Long KA. Disparities based on race, ethnicity, and socioeconomic status over the transition to adulthood among adolescents and young adults on the autism spectrum: a systematic review. Curr Psychiatry Rep. 2019;21:32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30903399</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11920-019-1016-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adams NJ, Vincent B. Suicidal thoughts and behaviors among transgender adults in relation to education, ethnicity, and income: a systematic review. Transgend Health. 2019;4:226–46.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31637302</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6798808</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/trgh.2019.0009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bellerose M, Collin L, Daw JR. The ACA Medicaid expansion and perinatal insurance, health care use, and health outcomes: a systematic review. Health Aff. 2022;41:60–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1377/hlthaff.2021.01150</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wouk K, Morgan I, Johnson J, Tucker C, Carlson R, Berry DC, et al. A systematic review of patient-, provider-, and health system-level predictors of postpartum health care use by people of color and low-income and/or uninsured populations in the United States. J Womens Health. 2021;30:1127–59.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/jwh.2020.8738</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Russo DP, Tham T, Bardash Y, Kraus D. The effect of race in head and neck cancer: a meta-analysis controlling for socioeconomic status. Am J Otolaryngol. 2020;41:102624.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32663732</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.amjoto.2020.102624</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karanth S, Fowler ME, Mao X, Wilson LE, Huang B, Pisu M, et al. Race, socioeconomic status, and health-care access disparities in ovarian cancer treatment and mortality: systematic review and meta-analysis. JNCI Cancer Spectr. 2019;3:pkz084.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31840133</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6899434</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jncics/pkz084</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gliedt JA, Spector AL, Schneider MJ, Williams J, Young S. Disparities in chiropractic utilization by race, ethnicity and socioeconomic status: a scoping review of the literature. J Integr Med. 2023;21:159–67.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36841750</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.joim.2023.02.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deshpande SB, Deshpande AK. Race/ethnicity, gender, and socioeconomic status representation in U.S.-based randomized controlled trials of tinnitus: a systematic review. Am J Audiol. 2022;31:1320–33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36170574</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1044/2022_AJA-21-00244</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lam PH, Chiang JJ, Chen E, Miller GE. Race, socioeconomic status, and low-grade inflammatory biomarkers across the lifecourse: a pooled analysis of seven studies. Psychoneuroendocrinology. 2021;123:104917.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33160231</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.psyneuen.2020.104917</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walls FN, McGarvey DJ. A systems-level model of direct and indirect links between environmental health, socioeconomic factors, and human mortality. Sci Total Environ. 2023;874:162486.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36858240</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.162486</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee H, Kravitz-Wirtz N, Rao S, Crowder K. Effects of prolonged exposure to air pollution and neighborhood disadvantage on self-rated health among adults in the United States: evidence from the panel study of income dynamics. Environ Health Perspect. 2023;131(8):087001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37531580</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10396329</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1289/EHP11268</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klompmaker JO, Hart JE, Bailey CR, Browning MHEM, Casey JA, Hanley JR, et al. Racial, ethnic, and socioeconomic disparities in multiple measures of blue and green spaces in the United States. Environ Health Perspect. 2023;131(1):017007.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36696102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9875842</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1289/EHP11164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koh C, Kondo MC, Rollins H, Bilal U. Socioeconomic disparities in hypertension by levels of green space availability: a cross-sectional study in Philadelphia, PA. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19:2037.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35206224</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8872624</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph19042037</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jennings V, Browning MH, Rigolon A. Urban green spaces: public health and sustainability in the United States. Springer International Publishing; 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong MS, Steers WN, Frochen S, Washington DL. Assessment of exposure to environmental toxins and racial and ethnic disparities in COVID-19 hospitalizations among US Veterans. JAMA Netw Open. 2022;5:E2224249.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35900766</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9335138</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.24249</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boing AF, Desouza P, Boing AC, Kim R, Subramanian SV. Air pollution, socioeconomic status, and age-specific mortality risk in the United States. JAMA Netw Open [Internet]. 2022;5:e2213540. https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/2792600 . Accessed 22 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cushing LJ, Ju Y, Kulp S, Depsky N, Karasaki S, Jaeger J, et al. Toxic tides and environmental injustice: social vulnerability to sea level rise and flooding of hazardous sites in Coastal California. Environ Sci Technol. 2023;57:7370–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37129408</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10193577</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acs.est.2c07481</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banner GC, Weaver KN, Rushovich T, York SL, Yee LM. Association between food deserts and gestational diabetes mellitus in a large metropolitan area. Am J Perinatol [Internet]. 2021;38:E39–45. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/32120416/ . Accessed 22 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Congdon P. Obesity and urban environments. Int J Environ Res Public Health [Internet]. 2019;16. Available from: https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/30764541/ . Accessed 22 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Opper IM, Park RJ, Husted L. The effect of natural disasters on human capital in the United States. Nat Hum Behav. 2023;7:1442–53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37264085</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41562-023-01610-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schnall DAH, Kieszak MMS, Heiman MMHJ, Bayleyegn MMT, Daniel PJ, Hanchey MA, et al. Characterizing household emergency preparedness levels for natural disasters during the COVID-19 pandemic: United States, 2020–2021. J Emergency Manage. 2023;21:51–69.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5055/jem.0737</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Masozera M, Bailey M, Kerchner C. Distribution of impacts of natural disasters across income groups: a case study of New Orleans. Ecol Econ. 2007;63:299–306.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecolecon.2006.06.013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pohl DJ, Seblova D, Avila JF, Dorsman KA, Kulick ER, Casey JA, et al. Relationship between residential segregation, later-life cognition, and incident dementia across race/ethnicity. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18:11233.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34769752</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8583156</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph182111233</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Avila-Rieger J, Turney IC, Vonk JMJ, Esie P, Seblova D, Weir VR, et al. Socioeconomic status, biological aging, and memory in a diverse national sample of older US men and women. Neurology [Internet]. 2022;99:E2114–24. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36038275/ . Accessed 22 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Franzini L, Spears W. Contributions of social context to inequalities in years of life lost to heart disease in Texas, USA. Soc Sci Med [Internet]. 2003;57:1847–61. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/14499510/ . Accessed 22 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Neill AMS, Newsom JT, Trubits EF, Elman MR, Botoseneanu A, Allore HG, et al. Racial, ethnic, and socioeconomic disparities in trajectories of morbidity accumulation among older Americans. SSM Popul Health [Internet]. 2023;22. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36941895/ . Accessed 22 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murphy SL, Kochanek KD, Xu J, Arias E. Mortality in the United States. NCHS Data Brief. 2020;2021:1–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roth GA, Fleszar LG, Bryant AS, Johnson CO, Blacker BF, Aravkin A, et al. Trends in state-level maternal mortality by racial and ethnic group in the United States. JAMA [Internet]. 2023;330:52–61. https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/fullarticle/2806661 . Accessed 22 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steele CB, Li J, Huang B, Weir HK. Prostate cancer survival in the United States by race and stage (2001–2009): Findings from the CONCORD-2 study. Cancer. 2017;123:5160–77.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29205313</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/cncr.31026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Keefe EB, Meltzer JP, Bethea TN. Health disparities and cancer: racial disparities in cancer mortality in the United States, 2000–2010. Front Public Health. 2015;3:51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25932459</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4398881</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2015.00051</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flentje A, Heck NC, Brennan JM, Meyer IH. The relationship between minority stress and biological outcomes: a systematic review. J Behav Med [Internet]. 2020;43:673–94. https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31863268/ . Accessed 22 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zahodne LB, Sol K, Kraal Z. Psychosocial pathways to racial/ethnic inequalities in late-life memory trajectories. J Gerontol: Series B. 2019;74:409–18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/geronb/gbx113</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carden KD, McDuffie DL, Murry K, Bui C, Allen RS. Minority stress process among older Black Americans: the role of age, perceived discrimination, and anxiety. Aging Ment Health. 2022;26:852–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33836631</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/13607863.2021.1904380</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okobi OE, Beeko PKA, Nikravesh E, Beeko MAE, Ofiaeli C, Ojinna BT, et al. Trends in obesity-related mortality and racial disparities. Cureus. 2023;15(7):e41432.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olson NC, Koh I, Reiner AP, Judd SE, Irvin MR, Howard G, et al. Soluble CD14, ischemic stroke, and coronary heart disease risk in a prospective study: the REGARDS cohort. J Am Heart Assoc. 2020;9(6):e014241.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32157955</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7335508</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1161/JAHA.119.014241</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao S, Kumar RG, Wisniewski SR, Fabio A. Disparities in health care utilization of adults with traumatic brain injuries are related to insurance, race, and ethnicity: a systematic review. J Head Trauma Rehabil. 2018;33:E40–50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28926481</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5857393</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/HTR.0000000000000338</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hall WJ, Chapman MV, Lee KM, Merino YM, Thomas TW, Payne BK, et al. Implicit racial/ethnic bias among health care professionals and its influence on health care outcomes: a systematic review. Am J Public Health. 2015;105:e60–76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26469668</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4638275</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2015.302903</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chinn JJ, Martin IK, Redmond N. Health equity among black women in the United States. J Womens Health. 2021;30:212–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/jwh.2020.8868</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang GY, Urwin JW, Wasfy JH. Medicaid expansion under the affordable care act and association with cardiac care: a systematic review. Circ Cardiovasc Qual Outcomes. 2023;16:e009753.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37339189</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1161/CIRCOUTCOMES.122.009753</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>García JL, Heckman JJ. Early childhood education and life-cycle health. Health Econ. 2021;30(Suppl 1):119–41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32885902</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/hec.4148</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lawson E. The health benefits of universal basic income. Br J Gen Pract. 2021;71:291.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34319878</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8249026</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3399/bjgp21X716453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>