<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39553520</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2292-5503</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Mar</Month><Day>06</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Plastic surgery (Oakville, Ont.)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Plast Surg (Oakv)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Enhanced Recovery After Surgery in Immediate DIEP Flap Breast Reconstruction: Reducing Length of Stay and Opioid Use.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>22925503241234935</StartPage><MedlinePgn>22925503241234935</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">22925503241234935</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1177/22925503241234935</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText><b>Background:</b> To improve patient outcomes amid reduced healthcare resources during the COVID-19 pandemic, a single Canadian cancer center implemented an Enhanced Recovery After Surgery (ERAS) protocol for autologous DIEP flap breast reconstruction. <b>Methods:</b> This retrospective cohort study included 100 consecutive patients undergoing microsurgical breast reconstruction with DIEP flaps using the ERAS protocol and 100 patients using a standard protocol. Primary outcomes were the hospital length of stay and opioid use. Secondary outcomes included postoperative complications, laxative and antiemetic consumption. <b>Results:</b> In this study, 80% of the patients had immediate reconstruction, while the remaining patients received either delayed immediate or delayed reconstruction. Patients in the ERAS group had shorter hospital stays (2.8 vs 4.5 days; <i>P</i> &lt; 0.001) and lower total opioid use (50.2 vs 136.3 mg; <i>P</i> &lt; 0.001). This reduction was also observed when breaking down opiates per day of hospitalization (30.2 vs 18.2 mg; <i>P</i> &lt; 0.001), and in the first 24 postoperatively hours (35.7 vs 67.6 mg; <i>P</i> &lt; 0.001). The control group had a higher incidence of postoperative complications, including seroma, partial and total flap necrosis, compared to the ERAS group. However, readmission rates were similar between the two groups. <b>Conclusion:</b> Implementing the ERAS protocol for DIEP flap breast reconstruction can significantly reduce hospital length of stay and postoperative opioid requirements without increasing the risk of adverse events. This pattern holds true for immediate reconstructions with DIEP flaps.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>El-Jebaoui</LastName><ForeName>Jad</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5257-1436</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Montreal, Montreal, Quebec, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Awaida</LastName><ForeName>Cyril J</ForeName><Initials>CJ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8779-9342</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery, University of Montreal Hospital Center, Montreal, Quebec, Canada.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="RINGGOLD">25443</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bou-Merhi</LastName><ForeName>Joseph</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery, University of Montreal Hospital Center, Montreal, Quebec, Canada.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="RINGGOLD">25443</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bernier</LastName><ForeName>Christina</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery, University of Montreal Hospital Center, Montreal, Quebec, Canada.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="RINGGOLD">25443</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gagnon</LastName><ForeName>Alain</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery, University of Montreal Hospital Center, Montreal, Quebec, Canada.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="RINGGOLD">25443</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Aribert</LastName><ForeName>Marion</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery, University of Montreal Hospital Center, Montreal, Quebec, Canada.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="RINGGOLD">25443</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Saint-Cyr</LastName><ForeName>Michel</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery, Banner MD Anderson Cancer Center, Gilbert, Arizona, USA.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="RINGGOLD">540220</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Harris</LastName><ForeName>Patrick G</ForeName><Initials>PG</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery, University of Montreal Hospital Center, Montreal, Quebec, Canada.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="RINGGOLD">25443</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Odobescu</LastName><ForeName>Andrei</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery, University of Texas Southwestern, Dallas, Texas, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>06</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Plast Surg (Oakv)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101623618</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2292-5503</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="fre"><AbstractText><b>Contexte :</b> Pour améliorer les résultats des patientes dans un contexte de réduction des ressources de santé au cours de la pandémie de COVID-19, un centre anticancéreux canadien unique a mis en œuvre un protocole de convalescence améliorée après chirurgie (ERAS) pour la reconstruction mammaire par lambeau perforant AIEP autologue. <b>Méthodes :</b> Cette étude de cohorte rétrospective a inclus 100 patientes consécutives subissant une reconstruction mammaire microchirurgicale avec lambeau perforant AIEP selon le protocole ERAS et 100 patientes suivant le protocole standard. Les critères d’évaluation principaux ont été la durée de l’hospitalisation et l’utilisation d’opioïdes. Les critères d’évaluation secondaires ont été les complications postopératoires, la consommation de laxatifs et d’antiémétiques. <b>Résultats :</b> Dans cette étude, 80% des patientes ont bénéficié d’une reconstruction immédiate, tandis que les patientes restantes ont eu une reconstruction immédiate retardée ou retardée. Les patientes du groupe ERAS ont eu une durée de séjour plus courte (2.8 vs 4.5 jours; <i>P </i>&lt; 0.001) et une consommation totale d’opioïdes plus faible (50.2 vs 136.3 mg; <i>P </i>&lt; 0.001). Cette réduction a été également observée après répartition de la consommation d’opioïdes par jour d’hospitalisation (30.2 vs 18.2 mg; <i>P </i>&lt; 0.001) et au cours des 24 premières heures postopératoires (35.7 vs 67.6 mg; <i>P </i>&lt; 0.001). L’incidence des complications postopératoires (notamment un sérome et la nécrose totale du lambeau) a été plus élevée dans le groupe contrôle que dans le groupe ERAS. Cependant, les taux de réhospitalisation ont été comparables entre les deux groupes. <b>Conclusion :</b> La mise en œuvre du protocole ERAS pour la reconstruction mammaire avec lambeau perforant AIEP peut réduire significativement la durée de séjour et le besoin d’opioïdes, sans augmenter le risque d’événements indésirables. Ce schéma reste vrai pour les reconstructions immédiates avec lambeau perforant AIEP.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">DIEP</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ERAS protocol</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">breast reconstruction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">length of stay</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">microsurgery</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">opioids</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39553520</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11562207</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/22925503241234935</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1177_22925503241234935</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Thomakos N, Pandraklakis A, Bisch SP, Rodolakis A, Nelson G. ERAS Protocols in gynecologic oncology during COVID-19 pandemic. Int J Gynecol Cancer. 2020;30(6):728-729.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32354796</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sohrabi C, Alsafi Z, O’Neill N, et al. World Health Organization declares global emergency: A review of the 2019 novel coronavirus (COVID-19). Int J Surg. 2020;76:71-76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7105032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32112977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brindle ME, Gawande A. Managing COVID-19 in surgical systems. Ann Surg. 2020;272(1):e1–e2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7188040</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32209891</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Emanuel EJ, Persad G, Upshur R, et al. Fair allocation of scarce medical resources in the time of COVID-19. N Engl J Med. 2020;382(21):2049-2055.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32202722</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fortin J, Rivest-Beauregard M, Defer C, et al. The impact of Canadian medical delays and preventive measures on breast cancer experience: A silent battle masked by the COVID-19 pandemic. Can J Nurs Res. 2023;55(1):55-67.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9086203</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35484788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Québec GD. Soins et services psychosociaux en cancérologie: Constats, enjeux et recommandations en contexte de la pandémie COVID-19. Ministère de la Santé et des Services Sociaux du Québec; 2020. https://publications.msss.gouv.qc.ca/msss/fichiers/directives-covid/archives/dgaumip-005_cancerologie-services-psychosociaux-covid-19.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>ASPS Statement on Breast Reconstruction in the face of COVID-19 Pandemic. 2020: Accessed 2 April 2020. https://www.plasticsurgery.org/documents/medical-professionals/COVID19-Breast-Reconstruction-Statement.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kehlet H. Multimodal approach to control postoperative pathophysiology and rehabilitation. Br J Anaesth. 1997;78(5):606-617.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9175983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scott MJ, Baldini G, Fearon KC, et al. Enhanced recovery after surgery (ERAS) for gastrointestinal surgery, part 1: Pathophysiological considerations. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand. 2015;59(10):1212-1231.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5049676</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26346577</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vukovic N, Dinic L. Enhanced recovery after surgery protocols in major urologic surgery. Front Med (Lausanne). 2018 Apr 9;5:93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5900414</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29686989</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Modesitt SC, Sarosiek BM, Trowbridge ER, et al. Enhanced recovery implementation in major gynecologic surgeries: Effect of care standardization. Obstet Gynecol. 2016;128(3):457-466.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27500337</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaye AD, Urman RD, Cornett EM, et al. Enhanced recovery pathways in orthopedic surgery. J Anaesthesiol Clin Pharmacol. 2019;35(Suppl 1):S35-s39.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6515716</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31142957</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ljungqvist O, Francis NK, Urman RD. (eds) Enhanced recovery after surgery: A complete guide to optimizing outcomes. Springer International Publishing; 2020. doi:10.1007/978-3-030-33443-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-33443-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khajuria A, Smith OJ, Prokopenko M, Greenfield M, Mosahebi A. Protocol for a systematic review and meta-analysis on the clinical outcomes and cost of deep inferior epigastric perforator (DIEP) flap versus implants for breast reconstruction. Syst Rev. 2017;6(1):232.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5700517</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29166926</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Offodile AC, Gu C, Boukovalas S, et al. Enhanced recovery after surgery (ERAS) pathways in breast reconstruction: Systematic review and meta-analysis of the literature. Breast Cancer Res Treat. 2019;173(1):65-77.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30306426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Batdorf NJ, Lemaine V, Lovely JK, et al. Enhanced recovery after surgery in microvascular breast reconstruction. J Plast Reconstr Aesthet Surg. 2015;68(3):395-402.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25488326</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Afonso A, Oskar S, Tan KS, et al. Is enhanced recovery the new standard of care in microsurgical breast reconstruction? Plast Reconstr Surg. 2017;139(5):1053-1061.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5640259</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28092334</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaoutzanis C, Ganesh Kumar N, O’Neill D, et al. Enhanced recovery pathway in microvascular autologous tissue-based breast reconstruction: Should it become the standard of care? Plast Reconstr Surg. 2018;141(4):841-851.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5876075</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29465485</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan YY, Liaw F, Warner R, Myers S, Ghanem A. Enhanced recovery pathways for flap-based reconstruction: Systematic review and meta-analysis. Aesthetic Plast Surg. 2021;45(5):2096-2115.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33821314</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lassen K, Soop M, Nygren J, et al. Consensus review of optimal perioperative care in colorectal surgery: Enhanced recovery after surgery (ERAS) group recommendations. Arch Surg. 2009;144(10):961-969.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19841366</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kehlet H. Multimodal approach to control postoperative pathophysiology and rehabilitation. Br J Anaesth. 1997;78(5):606-617.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9175983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gort N, van Gaal B, Tielemans H, Ulrich D, Hummelink S. Positive effects of the enhanced recovery after surgery (ERAS) protocol in DIEP flap breast reconstruction. Breast. 2021;60:53-57.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8406354</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34464847</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Astanehe A, Temple-Oberle C, Nielsen M, et al. An enhanced recovery after surgery pathway for microvascular breast reconstruction is safe and effective. Plast Reconstr Surg Glob Open. 2018;6(1):e1634.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5811294</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29464164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ochoa O, Rajan M, Garza R3. Et al. Enhanced recovery pathway reduces hospital stay and opioid use in microsurgical breast reconstruction: A single-center, private practice experience. Plast Reconstr Surg. 2022;150(1):13e-21e.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35500278</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ljungqvist O, Scott M, Fearon KC. Enhanced recovery after surgery: A review. JAMA Surg. 2017;152(3):292-298.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28097305</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nelson G, Altman AD, Nick A, et al. Guidelines for postoperative care in gynecologic/oncology surgery: Enhanced recovery after surgery (ERAS®) society recommendations–part II. Gynecol Oncol. 2016;140(2):323-332.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6038804</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26757238</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stone AB, Wick EC, Wu CL, Grant MC. The US opioid crisis: A role for enhanced recovery after surgery. Anesth Analg. 2017;125(5):1803-1805.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28678072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williams JB, McConnell G, Allender JE, et al. One-year results from the first US-based enhanced recovery after cardiac surgery (ERAS cardiac) program. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2019;157(5):1881-1888.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30665758</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haddock NT, Garza R, Boyle CE, Liu Y, Teotia SS. Defining enhanced recovery pathway with or without liposomal bupivacaine in DIEP flap breast reconstruction. Plast Reconstr Surg. 2021;148(5):948-957.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34705768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hedderson M, Lee D, Hunt E, et al. Enhanced recovery after surgery to change process measures and reduce opioid use after cesarean delivery: A quality improvement initiative. Obstet Gynecol. 2019;134(3):511-519.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7282661</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31403591</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ong CK, Seymour RA, Lirk P, Merry AF. Combining paracetamol (Acetaminophen) with nonsteroidal antiinflammatory drugs: A qualitative systematic review of analgesic efficacy for acute postoperative pain. Anesth Analg. 2010;110(4):1170-1179.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20142348</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klifto KM, Elhelali A, Payne RM, et al. Perioperative systemic nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) in women undergoing breast surgery. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2021;11(11). doi:10.1002/14651858.CD013290.pub2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD013290.pub2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8577884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34753201</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sahin E, Terzioglu F. The effect of gum chewing, early oral hydration, and early mobilization on intestinal motility after cesarean birth. Worldviews Evid Based Nurs. 2015;12(6):380-388.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26613392</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li M, Zhang J, Gan TJ, et al. Enhanced recovery after surgery pathway for patients undergoing cardiac surgery: A randomized clinical trial. Eur J Cardiothorac Surg. 2018;54(3):491-497.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29514224</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salibian AA, Frey JD, Thanik VD, Karp NS, Choi M. Transversus abdominis plane blocks in microsurgical breast reconstruction: Analysis of pain, narcotic consumption, length of stay, and cost. Plast Reconstr Surg. 2018;142(3):252e-263e.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29879000</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chi D, Chen AD, Ha AY, Yaeger LH, Lee BT. Comparative effectiveness of transversus abdominis plane blocks in abdominally based autologous breast reconstruction: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Ann Plast Surg. 2020;85(6):e76-e83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32960515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Charlton S, Cyna AM, Middleton P, Griffiths JD. Perioperative transversus abdominis plane (TAP) blocks for analgesia after abdominal surgery. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2010(12). doi:10.1002/14651858.CD007705.pub2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD007705.pub2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21154380</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen KT, Mardini S, Chuang DC, et al. Timing of presentation of the first signs of vascular compromise dictates the salvage outcome of free flap transfers. Plast Reconstr Surg. 2007;120(1):187-195.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17572562</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharif-Askary B, Hompe E, Broadwater G, Anolik R, Hollenbeck ST. The effect of enhanced recovery after surgery pathway implementation on abdominal-based microvascular breast reconstruction. J Surg Res. 2019;242:276-285.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31125841</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Temple-Oberle C, Shea-Budgell MA, Tan M, et al. Consensus review of optimal perioperative care in breast reconstruction: Enhanced recovery after surgery (ERAS) society recommendations. Plast Reconstr Surg. 2017;139(5):1056e-1071e.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9074892</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28445352</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>