<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39555721</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2050-4527</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>12</Volume><Issue>11</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Immunity, inflammation and disease</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Immun Inflamm Dis</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The Complex Relationship Between Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease With Cardiovascular Disease and Their Interactions With COVID-19 Vaccination: A Retrospective Study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70068</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e70068</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/iid3.70068</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Previously, most researchers explored the association between chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) and cardiovascular disease (CVD). This study investigates the distinct influence of COVID-19 vaccination status on patients with both conditions.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">We investigate the relationship between COPD and CVD in a cohort of 838 individuals who presented with both conditions. Our aim is to understand how these conditions interact and how COVID-19 vaccination status affects patient outcomes.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A retrospective analysis was conducted on 838 patients with COPD and CVD treated at DHQ Hospital in Muzaffargarh, Punjab, Pakistan, from November 2022 to April 2023. We employed multiple logistic regression and the Wilcoxon signed-rank test to assess the odds ratio and relative risk of COPD in patients with-CVD under various conditions. Additionally, we analyzed time-to-death and survival using Kaplan-Meier methods.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Findings reveal a 7.95 times higher risk of death in patients without COVID-19 vaccination compared with those who were vaccinated (95% CI, 6.12-10.33). Conversely, COVID-19-vaccinated patients exhibited a 0.221 times lower risk of recovery than their nonvaccinated counterparts (95% CI, 0.08-0.60). We also observed significant differences in time-to-death and recovery based on the presence of COPD and CVD, with vaccinated patients generally experiencing milder disease.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Our study assessed the impact of COVID-19 vaccination status on patient outcomes in patients with overlapping COPD and CVD. Individuals diagnosed with COPD and CVD display significant differences in terms of their probability of survival, with those who have received vaccinations.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Immunity, Inflammation and Disease published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hassan</LastName><ForeName>Muhammad Muneeb</ForeName><Initials>MM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1989-2622</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Statistics, The Islamia University of Bahawalpur, Bahawalpur, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Statistics, DHQ Hospital Muzaffargarh, Punjab, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sikandar</LastName><ForeName>Sheikh Muhammad</ForeName><Initials>SM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9314-7981</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, DHQ Hospital Muzaffargarh, Punjab, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jamal</LastName><ForeName>Farrukh</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6192-9890</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Statistics, The Islamia University of Bahawalpur, Bahawalpur, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ameeq</LastName><ForeName>Muhammad</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3677-2075</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Statistics, The Islamia University of Bahawalpur, Bahawalpur, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kargbo</LastName><ForeName>Alpha</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8248-2511</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physical and Natural Sciences, University of the Gambia, Brikama Campus, Serrekunda, Gambia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>The authors received no specific funding for this work.</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Immun Inflamm Dis</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101635460</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2050-4527</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000086663">COVID-19 Vaccines</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D029424" MajorTopicYN="Y">Pulmonary Disease, Chronic Obstructive</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012189" MajorTopicYN="N">Retrospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002318" MajorTopicYN="Y">Cardiovascular Diseases</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000401" MajorTopicYN="N">mortality</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086663" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19 Vaccines</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000008" MajorTopicYN="N">administration &amp; dosage</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000368" MajorTopicYN="N">Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="Y">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014611" MajorTopicYN="Y">Vaccination</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010154" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Pakistan</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COPD</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">CVD</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS‐CoV‐2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">matched cohort</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39555721</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/iid3.70068</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>C. H. Chiang, Y. C. Jiang, W. T. Hung, et al., “Impact of Medications on Outcomes in Patients With Acute Myocardial Infarction and Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease: A Nationwide Cohort Study,” Journal of the Chinese Medical Association 86, no. 2 (2023): 183–190, https://doi.org/10.1097/JCMA.0000000000000835.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Kumar, A. B. Singh, T. Arora, S. Singh, and R. Singh, “Critical Review on Emerging Health Effects Associated With the Indoor Air Quality and Its Sustainable Management,” Science of the Total Environment 872 (2023): 162163, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.162163.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Souliotis, L. Silva Miguel, G. Hillas, et al., “The Cost‐Saving Switch From Inhaled Corticosteroid‐Containing Treatments to Dual Bronchodilation: A Two‐Country Projection of Epidemiological and Economic Burden in Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease,” Therapeutic Advances in Respiratory Disease 14 (2020): 1753466620926802, https://doi.org/10.1177/1753466620926802.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Ramesh and K. Kosalram, “The Burden of Non‐Communicable Diseases: A Scoping Review Focus on the Context of India,” Journal of Education and Health Promotion 12, no. 1 (2023): 41, https://journals.lww.com/jehp/fulltext/2023/02280/The_burden_of_non_communicable_diseases__A_scoping.41.aspx.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Cavill, N. Lakeman, R. Lowe, H. Burdge, and P. Boyden, “Non‐Communicable Diseases and Other Shared Health Risks,” in One Health for Veterinary Nurses and Technicians: An Introduction (GB: CABI, 2023), 62–87, https://books.google.com.pk/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=ENGwEAAAQBAJ&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA62&amp;dq=6.%09Cavill+K,+Lakeman+N,+Lowe+R,+Burdge+H,+Boyden+P.+Non-Communicable+Diseases+and+Other+Shared+Health+Risks.+InOne+Health+for+Veterinary+Nurses+and+Technicians:+An+Introduction+2023+Feb+23+(pp.+62-87).+GB:+CABI.&amp;ots=UGP3sc9B2g&amp;sig=naf9TbCZStyA33uYlMWvL9SGMiE&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. B. Hossain, J. C. Johnston, V. J. Cook, et al., “Role of Latent Tuberculosis Infection on Elevated Risk of Cardiovascular Disease: A Population‐Based Cohort Study of Immigrants in British Columbia, Canada, 1985–2019,” Epidemiology and Infection 151 (2023): e68, https://doi.org/10.1017/S0950268823000559.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Rozanski, S. Sakul, J. Narula, and D. Berman, “Assessment of Lifestyle “Vital Signs” in Healthcare Settings,” Progress in Cardiovascular Diseases 77 (2023): 107–118, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pcad.2023.02.002.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. S. Vassiliou, V. Tsampasian, A. Abreu, et al., “Promotion of Healthy Nutrition in Primary and Secondary Cardiovascular Disease Prevention: A Clinical Consensus Statement From the European Association of Preventive Cardiology,” European Journal of Preventive Cardiology 30 (2023): zwad057, https://doi.org/10.1093/eurjpc/zwad057.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Giezeman, J. Sundh, Å. Athlin, et al., “Comorbid Heart Disease in Patients With COPD Is Associated With Increased Hospitalization and Mortality—A 15‐Year Follow‐Up,” International Journal of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease 18 (2023): 11–21, https://doi.org/10.2147/COPD.S378979.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. Li, “The Prevention and Treatment of the Non‐Communicable Diseases (NCDs) in Covid‐19,” Highlights in Science, Engineering and Technology 36 (2023): 1146–1151, https://doi.org/10.54097/hset.v36i.6194.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Roy, A. T. Protity, S. Das, and P. Dhar, “Prevalence and Major Risk Factors of Non‐Communicable Diseases: A Machine Learning Based Cross‐Sectional Study,” arXiv preprint arXiv:2303.04808 (2023): https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.04808.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Huang, A. Mehta, J. Kalmanovich, et al., “Immunological and Inflammatory Effects of Infectious Diseases in Circadian Rhythm Disruption and Future Therapeutic Directions,” Molecular Biology Reports 50 (2023): 3739–3753, https://doi.org/10.1007/s11033-023-08276-w.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. P. Putri, R. I. Sembiring, T. Kembaren, and P. Eyanoer, “Relationship of D‐Dimer Value to Mortality in Covid‐19 Patients With Acute Coronary Syndrome at Haji Adam Malik Hospital Medan,” Journal of Society Medicine 2, no. 4 (2023): 74–82, https://doi.org/10.7759/cureus.37671.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Simon, O. Joean, T. Welte, and J. Rademacher, “The Role of Vaccination in COPD: Influenza, SARS‐CoV‐2, Pneumococcus, Pertussis, RSV and Varicella Zoster Virus,” European Respiratory Review 32, no. 169 (2023): 230034, https://doi.org/10.1183/16000617.0034-2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B. Behrouzi, M. V. Araujo Campoverde, K. Liang, et al., “Influenza Vaccination to Reduce Cardiovascular Morbidity and Mortality in Patients With COVID‐19,” Journal of the American College of Cardiology 76, no. 15 (2020): 1777–1794, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jacc.2020.08.028.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Muneeb Hassan, M. Ameeq, F. Jamal, M. H. Tahir, and J. T. Mendy, “Prevalence of COVID‐19 Among Patients With Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease and Tuberculosis,” Annals of Medicine 55, no. 1 (2023): 285–291, https://doi.org/10.1080/07853890.2022.2160491.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Thomas, C. O'Donoghue, N. McCarthy, et al., An Analysis of Resilience and Sustainability in the Irish Health System–The PRESTO Report. PHSSR. (Dublin: Trinity College Dublin, 2023), 1–98.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. 2023, “Number of COVID‐19 Cases Reported to WHO,” https://data.who.int/dashboards/covid19/cases?n=c.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. A. Faghy, J. Yates, A. P. Hills, et al., “Cardiovascular Disease Prevention and Management in the COVID‐19 Era and Beyond: An International Perspective,” Progress in Cardiovascular Diseases 76 (2023): 102–111, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pcad.2023.01.004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. M. K. Lee, A. Page, S. Kim, et al., “Perceptions and Expectations of Health Professionals Regarding Hospital Pharmacy Services and the Roles of Hospital Pharmacists: A Qualitative Systematic Review and Meta‐Synthesis,” Exploratory Research in Clinical and Social Pharmacy 10 (2023): 100264, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.rcsop.2023.100264.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. M. Lee, A. Page, S. Kim, et al., “Perceptions and Expectations of Health Professionals Regarding Hospital Pharmacy Services and the Roles of Hospital Pharmacists: A Qualitative Systematic Review and Meta‐Synthesis,” Exploratory Research in Clinical and Social Pharmacy 10 (2023): 100264.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Choi and J. D. Chalmers, “Bronchiectasis Exacerbation: A Narrative Review of Causes, Risk Factors, Management and Prevention,” Annals of Translational Medicine 11, no. 1 (2023): 25, https://doi.org/10.21037/atm-22-3437.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Fan, J. Han, E. Zhao, et al., “The Effects of Obesity and Metabolic Abnormalities on Severe COVID‐19‐Related Outcomes After Vaccination: A Population‐Based Study,” Cell Metabolism 35 (2023): 585–600.e5, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmet.2023.02.016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. M. Hassan, M. Ameeq, L. Fatima, et al., “Assessing Socio‐Ecological Factors on Caesarean Section and Vaginal Delivery: An Extended Perspective Among Women of South‐Punjab, Pakistan,” Journal of Psychosomatic Obstetrics and Gynaecology 44, no. 1 (2023): 2252983, https://doi.org/10.1080/0167482X.2023.2252983.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. M. Hassan, M. Ameeq, M. H. Tahir, S. Naz, L. Fatima, and A. Kargbo, “Investigating Socioeconomic Disparities of Kangaroo Mother Care on Preterm Infant Health Outcomes,” Journal of Psychosomatic Obstetrics and Gynaecology 45, no. 1 (2024): 2299982, https://doi.org/10.1080/0167482X.2023.2299982.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Jamal, A. A. H. Ahmadini, M. M. Hassan, W. Sami, M. Ameeq, and A. Naeem, “Exploring Critical Factors in Referral Systems at Different Health‐Care Levels,” World Medical &amp; Health Policy. Published ahead of print, August 22, 2024, https://doi.org/10.1002/wmh3.632.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. M. Hassan, M. H. Tahir, M. Ameeq, F. Jamal, J. T. Mendy, and C. Chesneau, “Risk Factors Identification of COVID‐19 Patients With Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease: A Retrospective Study in Punjab‐Pakistan,” Immunity, Inflammation and Disease 11, no. 8 (2023): e981, https://doi.org/10.1002/iid3.981.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>