<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39552926</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2052-2975</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>62</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Dec</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>New microbes and new infections</Title><ISOAbbreviation>New Microbes New Infect</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Real world effectiveness of early ensitrelvir treatment in patients with SARS-CoV-2, a retrospective case series.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>101522</StartPage><MedlinePgn>101522</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">101522</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.nmni.2024.101522</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Ensitrelvir, a 3C-like protease inhibitor, received emergency approval in Japan in November 2022 for treating non-hospitalized patients with mild-to-moderate COVID-19. However, confirmation of its real-world clinical effectiveness is limited.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This retrospective study evaluated 18 vaccinated outpatients (15 men; median age, 39.5 years; range, 26-56), treated with a 5-day oral ensitrelvir regimen (375 mg loading dose, followed by 125 mg daily) between December 1, 2022, and January 31, 2023. Nasal swabs were collected on days 0, 3, 6, and 9 for RT-qPCR to assess viral load. Variants were identified by Sanger sequencing, and outcomes were compared to historical controls. Patients were followed for 60 days to monitor for post-acute sequelae of COVID-19 (PASC).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Symptoms such as mild fever and sore throat improved rapidly after one day of ensitrelvir treatment, with 66 % of patients recovering within six days. All individuals were infected with the BA.5 Omicron variant. Viral loads, as measured by Ct values, increased significantly from 21.82 at symptom onset to 37.65 b y day 6, with SARS-CoV-2 RNA undetectable in most patients by day 9. Those treated within 48 h of symptom onset showed the viral load reduction. Compared to historical controls, where symptom resolution took 8.5 days, ensitrelvir shortened recovery time to as little as 1.4 days for over 66 % of patients.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Ensitrelvir treatment resulted in rapid symptom relief and significant viral load reduction, with no adverse events, viral rebound, or PASC symptoms, demonstrating its potential efficacy and safety. Larger studies are needed for further confirmation.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abe</LastName><ForeName>Shuichi</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Diseases and Infection Control, Yamagata Prefectural Central Hospital, Yamagata, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pathogen Hunter's Research Team, Department of Infectious Diseases and Infection Control, Yamagata Prefectural Central Hospital, Yamagata, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wannigama</LastName><ForeName>Dhammika Leshan</ForeName><Initials>DL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Diseases and Infection Control, Yamagata Prefectural Central Hospital, Yamagata, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pathogen Hunter's Research Team, Department of Infectious Diseases and Infection Control, Yamagata Prefectural Central Hospital, Yamagata, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Diseases, Faculty of Medicine Yamagata University, Yamagata, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Medicine, Faculty of Health and Medical Sciences, The University of Western Australia, Nedlands, Western Australia, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biofilms and Antimicrobial Resistance Consortium of ODA Receiving Countries, The University of Sheffield, Sheffield, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Suzuki</LastName><ForeName>Yu</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Laboratory, Yamagata Prefectural Central Hospital, Yamagata, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Akaneya</LastName><ForeName>Daisuke</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Laboratory, Yamagata Prefectural Central Hospital, Yamagata, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Igarashi</LastName><ForeName>Junko</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Laboratory, Yamagata Prefectural Central Hospital, Yamagata, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Suto</LastName><ForeName>Mayu</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Laboratory, Yamagata Prefectural Central Hospital, Yamagata, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Moriya</LastName><ForeName>Kazunori</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Diseases and Infection Control, Yamagata Prefectural Central Hospital, Yamagata, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ishizawa</LastName><ForeName>Daisuke</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy, Yamagata Prefectural Central Hospital, Yamagata, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Okuma</LastName><ForeName>Yoshikazu</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy, Yamagata Prefectural Central Hospital, Yamagata, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hongsing</LastName><ForeName>Parichart</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Mae Fah Luang University Hospital, Chiang Rai, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Integrative Medicine, Mae Fah Luang University, Chiang Rai, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hurst</LastName><ForeName>Cameron</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Molly Wardaguga Research Centre, Charles Darwin University, Queensland, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Epidemiology, Faculty of Medicine, Thammasat University, Rangsit, Thailand, 10120.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center of Excellence in Applied Epidemiology, Thammasat University, Rangsit, Thailand, 10120.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Saethang</LastName><ForeName>Thammakorn</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Computer Science, Faculty of Science, Kasetsart University, Bangkok, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Higgins</LastName><ForeName>Paul G</ForeName><Initials>PG</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Medical Microbiology, Immunology and Hygiene, Faculty of Medicine and University Hospital Cologne, University of Cologne, Cologne, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>German Centre for Infection Research, Partner Site Bonn-Cologne, Cologne, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Stick</LastName><ForeName>Stephen M</ForeName><Initials>SM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wal-yan Respiratory Centre, Telethon Kids Institute, University of Western Australia, Nedlands, 6009, Western Australia, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Respiratory and Sleep Medicine, Perth Children's Hospital, Nedlands, 6009, Western Australia, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Cell Therapy and Regenerative Medicine, Medical School, The University of Western Australia, Nedlands, 6009, Western Australia, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kicic</LastName><ForeName>Anthony</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wal-yan Respiratory Centre, Telethon Kids Institute, University of Western Australia, Nedlands, 6009, Western Australia, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Respiratory and Sleep Medicine, Perth Children's Hospital, Nedlands, 6009, Western Australia, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Cell Therapy and Regenerative Medicine, Medical School, The University of Western Australia, Nedlands, 6009, Western Australia, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Population Health, Curtin University, Bentley, 6102, Western Australia, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>New Microbes New Infect</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101624750</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2052-2975</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CoiStatement>No author declares any potential conflict of interest or competing financial or non-financial interest in relation to the manuscript.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>58</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39552926</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11567130</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.nmni.2024.101522</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2052-2975(24)00306-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Murakami N., Hayden R., Hills T., Al-Samkari H., Casey J., Del Sorbo L., et al. Therapeutic advances in COVID-19. Nat Rev Nephrol. 2023;19(1):38–52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9574806</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36253508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ning Q., Wu D., Wang X., Xi D., Chen T., Chen G., et al. The mechanism underlying extrapulmonary complications of the coronavirus disease 2019 and its therapeutic implication. Signal Transduct Targeted Ther. 2022;7(1):57.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8863906</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35197452</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wannigama D.L., Hurst C., Phattharapornjaroen P., Hongsing P., Sirichumroonwit N., Chanpiwat K., et al. Early treatment with fluvoxamine, bromhexine, cyproheptadine, and niclosamide to prevent clinical deterioration in patients with symptomatic COVID-19: a randomized clinical trial. eClinicalMedicine. 2024;70</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10955208</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38516100</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imsuwansri T., Jongthitinon T., Pojdoung N., Meesiripan N., Sakarin S., Boonkrai C., et al. Assessment of safety and intranasal neutralizing antibodies of HPMC-based human anti-SARS-CoV-2 IgG1 nasal spray in healthy volunteers. Sci Rep. 2023;13(1)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10511465</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37730833</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davis H.E., McCorkell L., Vogel J.M., Topol E.J. Long COVID: major findings, mechanisms and recommendations. Nat Rev Microbiol. 2023</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9839201</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36639608</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wannigama D.L., Amarasiri M., Phattharapornjaroen P., Hurst C., Modchang C., Chadsuthi S., et al. Increased faecal shedding in SARS-CoV-2 variants BA.2.86 and JN.1. Lancet Infect Dis. 2024;24(6):e348–e350.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38522445</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wannigama D.L., Amarasiri M., Phattharapornjaroen P., Hurst C., Modchang C., Chadsuthi S., et al. Wastewater-based epidemiological surveillance of SARS-CoV-2 new variants BA.2.86 and offspring JN.1 in south and Southeast Asia. J Trav Med. 2024</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38438141</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wannigama D.L., Amarasiri M., Hongsing P., Hurst C., Modchang C., Chadsuthi S., et al. COVID-19 monitoring with sparse sampling of sewered and non-sewered wastewater in urban and rural communities. iScience. 2023</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10250052</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37351501</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rad S.M.A.H., Wannigama D.L., Hirankarn N., McLellan A.D. The impact of non-synonymous mutations on miRNA binding sites within the SARS-CoV-2 NSP3 and NSP4 genes. Sci Rep. 2023;13(1)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10560223</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37805621</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wannigama D.L., Amarasiri M., Phattharapornjaroen P., Hurst C., Modchang C., Chadsuthi S., et al. Tracing the new SARS-CoV-2 variant BA.2.86 in the community through wastewater surveillance in Bangkok, Thailand. Lancet Infect Dis. 2023;23(11):e464–e466.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37813112</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anupong S., Chantanasaro T., Wilasang C., Jitsuk N.C., Sararat C., Sornbundit K., et al. Infectious disease modelling. 2023. Modeling vaccination strategies with limited early COVID-19 vaccine access in low- and middle-income countries: a case study of Thailand.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10709621</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38074078</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anupong S., Chadsuthi S., Hongsing P., Hurst C., Phattharapornjaroen P., Ali Hosseini R.S.M., et al. Exploring indoor and outdoor dust as a potential tool for detection and monitoring of COVID-19 transmission. iScience. 2024</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10875567</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38375225</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sasaki M., Tabata K., Kishimoto M., Itakura Y., Kobayashi H., Ariizumi T., et al. S-217622, a SARS-CoV-2 main protease inhibitor, decreases viral load and ameliorates COVID-19 severity in hamsters. Sci Transl Med. 2023;15(679)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9765455</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36327352</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mukae H., Yotsuyanagi H., Ohmagari N., Doi Y., Imamura T., Sonoyama T., et al. A randomized phase 2/3 study of ensitrelvir, a novel oral SARS-CoV-2 3C-like protease inhibitor, in Japanese patients with mild-to-moderate COVID-19 or asymptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infection: results of the phase 2a part. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2022;66(10) 22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9578433</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36098519</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shimizu R., Sonoyama T., Fukuhara T., Kuwata A., Matsuo Y., Kubota R. Safety, tolerability, and pharmacokinetics of the novel antiviral agent ensitrelvir fumaric acid, a SARS-CoV-2 3CL protease inhibitor, in healthy adults. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2022;66(10)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9578392</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36094202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamato M., Kinoshita M., Miyazawa S., Seki M., Mizuno T., Sonoyama T. Ensitrelvir in patients with SARS-CoV-2: a retrospective chart review. J Infect Chemother. 2024;30(9):946–950.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38367932</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin M., Zeng X., Duan Y., Yang Z., Ma Y., Yang H., et al. Molecular mechanism of ensitrelvir inhibiting SARS-CoV-2 main protease and its variants. Commun Biol. 2023;6(1):694.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10322880</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37407698</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yotsuyanagi H., Ohmagari N., Doi Y., Yamato M., Fukushi A., Imamura T., et al. Prevention of post COVID-19 condition by early treatment with ensitrelvir in the phase 3 SCORPIO-SR trial. Antivir Res. 2024;229</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38972603</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mukae H., Yotsuyanagi H., Ohmagari N., Doi Y., Sakaguchi H., Sonoyama T., et al. Efficacy and safety of ensitrelvir in patients with mild-to-moderate COVID-19: the phase 2b part of a randomized, placebo-controlled, phase 2/3 study. Clin Infect Dis. 2022</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10110269</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36477182</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nobori H., Fukao K., Kuroda T., Anan N., Tashima R., Nakashima M., et al. Efficacy of ensitrelvir against SARS-CoV-2 in a delayed-treatment mouse model. J Antimicrob Chemother. 2022;77(11):2984–2991.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9384569</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35914182</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wannigama D.L., Amarasiri M., Hurst C., Phattharapornjaroen P., Abe S., Hongsing P., et al. Tracking COVID-19 with wastewater to understand asymptomatic transmission. Int J Infect Dis. 2021;108:296–299.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8111879</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33989774</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu B., Guo H., Zhou P., Shi Z.-L. Characteristics of SARS-CoV-2 and COVID-19. Nat Rev Microbiol. 2021;19(3):141–154.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7537588</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33024307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong C.K.H., Au I.C.H., Lau K.T.K., Lau E.H.Y., Cowling B.J., Leung G.M. Real-world effectiveness of early molnupiravir or nirmatrelvir–ritonavir in hospitalised patients with COVID-19 without supplemental oxygen requirement on admission during Hong Kong's omicron BA.2 wave: a retrospective cohort study. Lancet Infect Dis. 2022;22(12):1681. 93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9401976</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36029795</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vegivinti C.T.R., Evanson K.W., Lyons H., Akosman I., Barrett A., Hardy N., et al. Efficacy of antiviral therapies for COVID-19: a systematic review of randomized controlled trials. BMC Infect Dis. 2022;22(1):107.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8802260</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35100985</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>