<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39553063</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Evaluating the Adverse Effects and Associated Risk Factors of COVID-19 Vaccines Among Healthcare Workers: A Retrospective Study in the Duhok Province, Iraq.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e71671</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e71671</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e71671</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.71671</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND AND AIM" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">The COVID-19 pandemic has profoundly impacted global health, necessitating the rapid development of vaccines to reduce its effects. However, concerns among healthcare workers regarding vaccine safety and side effects have led to increased hesitancy towards COVID-19 vaccination. Therefore, this study aims to assess the severity of adverse effects and associated factors of three COVID-19 vaccines among healthcare workers in Iraqi Kurdistan.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS"> A retrospective cross-sectional study was conducted among healthcare workers in Duhok province, Kurdistan Region, Iraq, with 625 participants aged 18 to 65 years (mean age 38.42±13.96) from August to December 2022. Data were collected through face-to-face interviews. The study questionnaire consisted of two parts: the first part collected demographic information about the participants, while the second part focused on their COVID-19 infection and vaccination status.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Of the total participants, 52.8% were female, with a mean age of 38.42 years (±13.96 SD). Approximately 67.5% received the Pfizer/BioNTech vaccine, and 60.9% had a prior history of COVID-19 infection. A significant proportion (82.24%) reported side effects, which were mostly mild or moderate, with 13.6% experiencing severe symptoms. The most commonly reported side effects across all three vaccines were pain at the injection site, fever, headache, and fatigue. Participants aged 36-50 reported significantly higher rates of severe side effects (87.88%, p = 0.047). Individuals with a history of allergies experienced significantly fewer adverse effects (48.93%) (p = 0.001). Those with prior COVID-19 infection also reported more severe symptoms post-vaccination (p = 0.001) and vaccine type-influenced side effects (p &lt; 0.001), with Oxford/AstraZeneca recipients more likely to experience severe reactions compared to Pfizer recipients. Fatigue, chills, tremors, and myalgia were significantly more common in females than males (p &lt; 0.005).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">This study identified the most common side effects of COVID-19 vaccines among healthcare workers in Kurdistan Region of Iraq. AstraZeneca vaccine was associated with a higher prevalence of systemic effects, including fever, fatigue, headache and myalgia. These findings provide valuable insights into the safety and side effect profile of COVID-19 vaccines in the region.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Naqid et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Naqid</LastName><ForeName>Ibrahim A</ForeName><Initials>IA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Sciences, College of Medicine, University of Zakho, Zakho Duhok, IRQ.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">covid-19 vaccines</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">healthcare worker</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">kurdistan region</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">risk factors</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">side-effect</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Animal subjects: All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>7</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>59</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39553063</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11568403</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.71671</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>The impact of COVID-19 pandemic on the care of patients with kidney diseases in Duhok City, Kurdistan Region of Iraq. Hussein NR, M Saleem ZS, Ibrahim N, Musa DH, Naqid IA. Diabetes Metab Syndr. 2020;14:1551–1553.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7434471</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32846367</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Impact of Covid-19 pandemic on surgical practice in Kurdistan, Iraq: an online cross-sectional survey. Hussein NR, Musa DH, Ibrahim N, Naqid IA, M Saleem ZS, Jacksi K. Int J Surg Open. 2020;27:47–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7609234</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34568615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Assessment of COVID-19 vaccination among healthcare workers in Iraq; adverse effects and hesitancy. Darweesh O, Khatab N, Kheder R, et al. PLoS One. 2022;17:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9674125</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36399454</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 Vaccines, Effectiveness, and Immune Responses. Abufares HI, Oyoun Alsoud L, Alqudah MA, et al. Int J Mol Sci. 2022;23</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9737588</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36499742</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strict social distancing measures helped early control of SARS-CoV-2 spread in Duhok city, Iraq. Hussein NR, Naqid I. J Infect Dev Ctries. 2022;16:1370–1371.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36099383</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>SARS-CoV-2 immunity: review and applications to phase 3 vaccine candidates. Poland GA, Ovsyannikova IG, Kennedy RB. Lancet. 2020;396:1595–1606.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7553736</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33065034</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hesitancy towards Covid-19 vaccination among the healthcare workers in Iraqi Kurdistan. Luma AH, Haveen AH, Faiq BB, Stefania M, Leonardo EG. Public Health Pract (Oxf) 2022;3:100222.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8662956</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34909704</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knowledge, attitudes and behaviour of hospital health-care workers regarding influenza A/H1N1: a cross sectional survey. Albano L, Matuozzo A, Marinelli P, Di Giuseppe G. BMC Infect Dis. 2014;14:208.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4021506</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24739890</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Perception and Attitudes toward COVID-19 vaccines: a cross-sectional study in Poland. Rzymski P, Zeyland J, Poniedziałek B, Małecka I, Wysocki J. Vaccines (Basel) 2021;9:382.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8069794</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33919672</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Efficacy and safety of the mRNA-1273 SARS-CoV-2 vaccine. Baden LR, El Sahly HM, Essink B, et al. N Engl J Med. 2021;384:403–416.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7787219</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33378609</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Side effects and perceptions following COVID-19 vaccination in Jordan: a randomized, cross-sectional study implementing machine learning for predicting severity of side effects. Hatmal MM, Al-Hatamleh MA, Olaimat AN, Hatmal M, Alhaj-Qasem DM, Olaimat TM, Mohamud R. Vaccines (Basel) 2021;9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8229440</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34073382</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaccine side effects following COVID-19 vaccination among the residents of the UAE-an observational study. Ganesan S, Al Ketbi LM, Al Kaabi N, et al. Front Public Health. 2022;10:876336.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9120526</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35602146</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Public fear of COVID-19 vaccines in Iraqi Kurdistan region: a cross-sectional study. Tahir AI, Ramadhan DS, Taha AA, Abdullah RY, Karim SK, Ahmed AK, Ahmed SF. 2021;28:46.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Potential adverse effects of COVID19 vaccines among Iraqi population; a comparison between the three available vaccines in Iraq; a retrospective cross-sectional study. Almufty HB, Mohammed SA, Abdullah AM, Merza MA. Diabetes Metab Syndr. 2021;15:102207.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8274281</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34280733</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Assessment of acceptance, concerns and side effects towards COVID-19 vaccination among the community: a cross-sectional study from Baghdad, Iraq. Albasry Z, Al-Taie A. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cegh.2023.101217. Clin Epidemiol Glob Health. 2023;20:101217.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9839460</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36684813</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Safety and efficacy of the BNT162b2 mRNA Covid-19 vaccine. Polack FP, Thomas SJ, Kitchin N, et al. N Engl J Med. 2020;383:2603–2615.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7745181</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33301246</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Safety and efficacy of the ChAdOx1 nCoV-19 vaccine (AZD1222) against SARS-CoV-2: an interim analysis of four randomised controlled trials in Brazil, South Africa, and the UK. Voysey M, Clemens SA, Madhi SA, et al. Lancet. 2021;397:99–111.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7723445</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33306989</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Effectiveness of COVID-19 vaccine in preventing infection and disease severity: a case-control study from an Eastern State of India. Singh C, Naik BN, Pandey S, Biswas B, Pati BK, Verma M, Singh PK. Epidemiol Infect. 2021;149:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8545845</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34632972</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaccine side-effects and SARS-CoV-2 infection after vaccination in users of the COVID Symptom Study app in the UK: a prospective observational study. Menni C, Klaser K, May A, et al. Lancet Infect Dis. 2021;21:939–949.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8078878</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33930320</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Side effects and perceptions of COVID-19 vaccination in Saudi Arabia: a cross-sectional study. Al-Hanawi MK, Keetile M, Kadasah NA, Alshareef N, Qattan AM, Alsharqi O. Front Med (Lausanne) 2022;9:899517.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9210956</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35746946</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Covid-19 vaccination reported side effects and hesitancy among the Syrian population: a cross-sectional study. Najjar M, Albuaini S, Fadel M, et al. Ann Med. 2023;55:2241351.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10405764</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37544017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Side effects of COVID-19 vaccines: a systematic review and meta-analysis protocol of randomised trials. Medeiros KS, Costa AP, Sarmento AC, Freitas CL, Gonçalves AK. BMJ Open. 2022;12:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8882642</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35210336</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A comparative analysis of COVID-19 vaccines based on over 580,000 cases from the vaccination adverse event reporting system. Gallo K, Goede A, Mura C, et al. Vaccines (Basel) 2022;10</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8950485</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35335040</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Side effects and efficacy of COVID-19 vaccines among the Egyptian population. Elgendy MO, El-Gendy AO, Mahmoud S, Mohammed TY, Abdelrahim ME, Sayed AM. Vaccines (Basel) 2022;10:109.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8779934</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35062770</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The evolution of greater humoral immunity in females than males: implications for vaccine efficacy. Fink AL, Klein SL. Curr Opin Physiol. 2018;6:16–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6181235</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30320243</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Side effects of COVID-19 vaccines in Iraqi Kurdistan: a population-based study. Naqid IA, Mosa AA, Hito LS, Jamil DS, Shukur IT, Abdulkareem DS, Hussein NR. Cureus. 2024;16</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11549252</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39525127</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>