<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39553043</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Impact of Vaccination Time on Anti-SARS-CoV-2 Antibody Levels in Adults: A Quasi-experimental Study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e71505</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e71505</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e71505</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.71505</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND AND AIM" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">Vaccination time may provide an opportunity to advance immunogenicity in terms of the immune system's circadian nature. This analytical study was planned to determine the impact of forenoon and afternoon administration of the COVID-19 vaccine to adults on the magnitude of antibody response.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHOD" NlmCategory="METHODS">A total of 33 healthy adults with no history of COVID-19 infection or any other disease participated in the study. They were allotted a forenoon (900-1200 hours) or afternoon (1200-500 hours) slot for vaccination. They were categorized as a forenoon or afternoon group, with 16 subjects in the forenoon and 17 in the afternoon group. With the consent of the participants, a blood sample was collected before vaccination, 30 days after the first and 30 days after the second dose of vaccination from all the subjects. The antibody titer response was measured using a commercial semi-quantitative assay, SARS-CoV-2 IgG II.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The baseline antibody titer against COVID-19 was 51.41 ± 22.22 AU/mL and 53.21 ± 15.67 AU/mL in the forenoon and afternoon groups, respectively, which increased to 15773.00 ± 3231.41 AU/mL and 12970.82 ± 7608.00 AU/mL after 30 days of the first dose of the COVID-19 vaccine in the forenoon and afternoon groups, respectively. This further increased to 37007.00 ± 1697.75 AU/mL and 38012.00 ± 14001.16 AU/mL after 30 days of the second dose of the COVID-19 vaccine in the forenoon and afternoon groups, respectively. There was no difference in antibody response in subjects with forenoon and afternoon vaccinations. There was no significant difference in antibody titer in males vs. females. The study reported that antibody titers decreased with increasing age and BMI of participants.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The time of the day of vaccination does not impact the immune response to COVID-19, but age and BMI are important factors to consider during vaccination against SARS-CoV-2 in the adult population.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Gangwar et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gangwar</LastName><ForeName>Vibha</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physiology, Dr. Ram Manohar Lohia Institute of Medical Sciences, Lucknow, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Verma</LastName><ForeName>Manish</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physiology, Dr. Ram Manohar Lohia Institute of Medical Sciences, Lucknow, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Singh</LastName><ForeName>Arvind K</ForeName><Initials>AK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Medicine, Dr. Ram Manohar Lohia Institute of Medical Sciences, Lucknow, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Agarwal</LastName><ForeName>Jyotsana</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Dr. Ram Manohar Lohia Institute of Medical Sciences, Lucknow, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kumari</LastName><ForeName>Rashmi</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Medicine, Dr. Ram Manohar Lohia Institute of Medical Sciences, Lucknow, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Garg</LastName><ForeName>Jaya</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Dr. Ram Manohar Lohia Institute of Medical Sciences, Lucknow, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shukla</LastName><ForeName>Vinita</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Medicine, Dr. Ram Manohar Lohia Institute of Medical Sciences, Lucknow, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pathak</LastName><ForeName>Anumesh K</ForeName><Initials>AK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biochemistry, Dr. Ram Manohar Lohia Institute of Medical Sciences, Lucknow, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jasrotia</LastName><ForeName>Rajani Bala</ForeName><Initials>RB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physiology, Dr. Ram Manohar Lohia Institute of Medical Sciences, Lucknow, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kumari</LastName><ForeName>Sarita</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Physiology, Dr. Ram Manohar Lohia Institute of Medical Sciences, Lucknow, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">antibody titer</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">circadian rhythm</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">india</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sars-cov-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vaccination time</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Institute Ethics Committee of Dr. Ram Manohar Lohia Institute of Medical Sciences, Lucknow issued approval letter no. 326 dated 23/04/2022, IEC no. 29/22. Animal subjects: All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: This study received a grant from the Indian Council of Medical Research as per sanction letter no. 55/11/2022-PHY/BMS dated 30/01/2023. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>59</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39553043</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11563762</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.71505</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>COVID-19, circadian rhythms and sleep: from virology to chronobiology. Liu Z, Ting S, Zhuang X. Interface Focus. 2021;11:20210043.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8504895</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34956600</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 vaccine development: milestones, lessons and prospects. Li M, Wang H, Tian L, et al. Signal Transduct Target Ther. 2022;7:146.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9062866</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35504917</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Circadian control of the immune system. Scheiermann C, Kunisaki Y, Frenette PS. Nat Rev Immunol. 2013;13:190–198.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4090048</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23391992</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Circadian rhythms. Persson PB, Bondke PA. Acta Physiol. 2019;225:13220.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30457219</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mechanisms of communication in the mammalian circadian timing system. Astiz M, Heyde I, Oster H. Int J Mol Sci. 2019;20</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6359556</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30650649</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pharmacological activation of the circadian component REV-ERB inhibits HIV-1 replication. Borrmann H, Davies R, Dickinson M, et al. Sci Rep. 2020;10:13271.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7413328</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32764708</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The circadian clock and viral infections. Borrmann H, McKeating JA, Zhuang X. J Biol Rhythms. 2021;36:9–22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7924106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33161818</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Circadian transcription factor BMAL1 regulates innate immunity against select RNA viruses. Majumdar T, Dhar J, Patel S, Kondratov R, Barik S. Innate Immun. 2017;23:147–154.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27913791</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Circadian control of hepatitis B virus replication. Zhuang X, Forde D, Tsukuda S, et al. Nat Commun. 2021;12:1658.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7955118</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33712578</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The circadian clock components BMAL1 and REV-ERBα regulate flavivirus replication. Zhuang X, Magri A, Hill M, et al. Nat Commun. 2019;10:377.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6343007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30670689</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Preliminary evidence that morning vaccination is associated with an enhanced antibody response in men. Phillips AC, Gallagher S, Carroll D, Drayson M. Psychophysiology. 2008;45:663–666.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18346041</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morning vaccination enhances antibody response over afternoon vaccination: a cluster-randomised trial. Long JE, Drayson MT, Taylor AE, Toellner KM, Lord JM, Phillips AC. Vaccine. 2016;34:2679–2685.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4874947</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27129425</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Interactomes of SARS-CoV-2 and human coronaviruses reveal host factors potentially affecting pathogenesis. Chen Z, Wang C, Feng X, et al. EMBO J. 2021;40:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8447597</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34232536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Time of day of vaccination affects SARS-CoV-2 antibody responses in an observational study of health care workers. Wang W, Balfe P, Eyre DW, et al. J Biol Rhythms. 2022;37:124–129.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8825702</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34866459</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Time of day of vaccination does not associate with SARS-CoV-2 antibody titer following first dose of mRNA COVID-19 vaccine. Yamanaka Y, Yokota I, Yasumoto A, Morishita E, Horiuchi H. J Biol Rhythms. 2022;37:700–706.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9726636</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36154515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diurnal variation in SARS-CoV-2 PCR test results: test accuracy may vary by time of day. McNaughton CD, Adams NM, Johnson CH, Ward MJ, Schmitz JE, Lasko TA. J Biol Rhythms. 2021;36:595–601.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8599649</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34696614</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 variants in India: potential role in second wave and impact on vaccination. Kunal S, Aditi Aditi, Gupta K, Ish P. Heart Lung. 2021;50:784–787.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8173455</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34217989</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The circadian clock component BMAL1 regulates SARS-CoV-2 entry and replication in lung epithelial cells. Zhuang X, Tsukuda S, Wrensch F, et al. iScience. 2021;24:103144.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8443536</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34545347</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization: interim recommendations for use of the ChAdOx1-S [recombinant] vaccine against COVID-19 (AstraZeneca COVID-19 vaccine AZD1222, SII Covishield, SK Bioscience)  [
Jul;
2024 
]. 2021. https://apps.who.int/iris/rest/bitstreams/1343289/retrieve. https://apps.who.int/iris/rest/bitstreams/1343289/retrieve.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The effect of timing of influenza vaccination and sample collection on antibody titers and responses in the aged. Kurupati RK, Kossenkoff A, Kannan S, et al. Vaccine. 2017;35:3700–3708.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28583307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Comparative study of SARS-CoV-2 antibody titers between male and female COVID-19 patients living in Kurdistan region of Iraq. Ishaq SE, Abdulqadir SZ, Khudhur ZO, et al. Gene Rep. 2021;25:101409.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8541827</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34722951</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quantitation of antibodies against SARS‐CoV‐2 spike protein after two doses of CoronaVac in healthcare workers. Bayram A, Demirbakan H, Günel Karadeniz P, Erdoğan M, Koçer I. J Med Virol. 2021;93:5560–5567.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8242724</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34019704</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Characterization of SARS-CoV-2-specific humoral and cellular immune responses induced by inactivated COVID-19 vaccines in a real-world setting. Li Z, Xiang T, Liang B, et al. Front Immunol. 2021;12:802858.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8727357</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35003131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sex-associated differences between BMI and SARS-CoV-2 antibody titers following the BNT162b2 vaccine. Yamamoto S, Mizoue T, Tanaka A, et al. Obesity (Silver Spring) 2022;30:999–1003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9088326</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35226399</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>