<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39556163</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1439-0973</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>18</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Infection</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Infection</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Post-COVID recovery is faster after an infection with the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant: a population-based cohort study.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s15010-024-02438-z</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="PURPOSE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">Post-COVID-19 condition (PCC) poses a substantial burden to affected individuals, health care systems, and society as a whole. We examined factors associated with recovery from PCC, focusing on the vaccination status prior to infection and the virus variant.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Our analyses are based on the population-based cohort study for digital health research in Germany (DigiHero). Respondents who reported a SARS-CoV-2 infection and COVID-related symptoms ≥ 12 weeks post-infection were classified as having PCC. Those with ongoing PCC were followed-up in six-month intervals based on their date of infection. We used a Cox model for interval-censored data to analyze PCC recovery.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Among the 4,529 respondents with PCC included in our analyses, about 26%, 19%, 36%, and 44% of those infected during dominance of the SARS-CoV-2 wildtype, Alpha, Delta, and Omicron variant had recovered one year after infection, respectively. When stratifying by virus variant, vaccination was not associated with a faster recovery. Conversely, those infected with Omicron (HR = 2.20; 95%CI: 1.96-2.48) or Delta (HR = 1.69; 95%CI: 1.43-2.01) recovered faster than those infected with the SARS-CoV-2 wildtype or Alpha strain.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Although the recovery from PCC is faster for the newer virus variants, still a substantial fraction of those who developed PCC after an infection with the Omicron variant report prolonged persistence of symptoms.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pfrommer</LastName><ForeName>Laura Rebecca</ForeName><Initials>LR</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0000-1763-2336</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Medical Epidemiology, Biometry and Informatics (IMEBI), Interdisciplinary Centre for Health Sciences, Medical Faculty of the Martin Luther University Halle-Wittenberg, Halle (Saale), Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Diexer</LastName><ForeName>Sophie</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Medical Epidemiology, Biometry and Informatics (IMEBI), Interdisciplinary Centre for Health Sciences, Medical Faculty of the Martin Luther University Halle-Wittenberg, Halle (Saale), Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Klee</LastName><ForeName>Bianca</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5453-7207</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Medical Epidemiology, Biometry and Informatics (IMEBI), Interdisciplinary Centre for Health Sciences, Medical Faculty of the Martin Luther University Halle-Wittenberg, Halle (Saale), Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Massag</LastName><ForeName>Janka</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0995-0593</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Medical Epidemiology, Biometry and Informatics (IMEBI), Interdisciplinary Centre for Health Sciences, Medical Faculty of the Martin Luther University Halle-Wittenberg, Halle (Saale), Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gottschick</LastName><ForeName>Cornelia</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Medical Epidemiology, Biometry and Informatics (IMEBI), Interdisciplinary Centre for Health Sciences, Medical Faculty of the Martin Luther University Halle-Wittenberg, Halle (Saale), Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Purschke</LastName><ForeName>Oliver</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Medical Epidemiology, Biometry and Informatics (IMEBI), Interdisciplinary Centre for Health Sciences, Medical Faculty of the Martin Luther University Halle-Wittenberg, Halle (Saale), Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Binder</LastName><ForeName>Mascha</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Medical Oncology, University Hospital Basel, Basel, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Frese</LastName><ForeName>Thomas</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of General Practice and Family Medicine, Interdisciplinary Centre for Health Sciences, Medical Faculty of the Martin Luther University Halle-Wittenberg, Halle (Saale), Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Girndt</LastName><ForeName>Matthias</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2823-0847</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine II, Martin Luther University Halle-Wittenberg, Halle (Saale), Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sedding</LastName><ForeName>Daniel</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Mid-German Heart Centre, Department of Cardiology and Intensive Care Medicine, University Hospital, Martin Luther University Halle-Wittenberg, Halle (Saale), Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rosendahl</LastName><ForeName>Jonas</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine I, Martin Luther University Halle-Wittenberg, Halle (Saale), Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hoell</LastName><ForeName>Jessica I</ForeName><Initials>JI</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Paediatric Haematology and Oncology, Martin Luther University Halle-Wittenberg, Halle (Saale), Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Moor</LastName><ForeName>Irene</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3245-5176</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Medical Sociology, Interdisciplinary Centre for Health Sciences, Medical Faculty of the Martin Luther University Halle-Wittenberg, Halle (Saale), Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gekle</LastName><ForeName>Michael</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1581-8767</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Julius-Bernstein-Institute of Physiology, Medical Faculty of the Martin Luther University Halle-Wittenberg, Halle (Saale), Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Allwang</LastName><ForeName>Christine</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2874-6168</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychosomatic Medicine and Psychotherapy, Klinikum rechts der Isar, Technical University Munich, Munich, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Junne</LastName><ForeName>Florian</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychosomatic Medicine and Psychotherapy, Otto-von-Guericke-University Magdeburg, Magdeburg, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mikolajczyk</LastName><ForeName>Rafael</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Medical Epidemiology, Biometry and Informatics (IMEBI), Interdisciplinary Centre for Health Sciences, Medical Faculty of the Martin Luther University Halle-Wittenberg, Halle (Saale), Germany. rafael.mikolajczyk@uk-halle.de.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Infection</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0365307</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0300-8126</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19 recovery</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19 vaccine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Long Haul COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Post Acute COVID-19 syndrome</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2 virus variants</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement><b>Declarations</b> <b>Ethics approval and consent to participate</b> The responsible Ethics Committee of the Martin Luther University Halle-Wittenverg provided ethical approval (Registration number 2020-076). Informed consent was obtained from all participants. <b>Competing interests</b> The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>31</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>31</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39556163</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s15010-024-02438-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s15010-024-02438-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Fernandez-de-Las-Peñas C, Notarte KI, Macasaet R, Velasco JV, Catahay JA, Ver AT, Chung W, Valera-Calero JA, Navarro-Santana M. Persistence of post-COVID symptoms in the general population two years after SARS-CoV-2 infection: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Infect. 2024;88:77–88. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jinf.2023.12.004 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2023.12.004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38101521</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Post COVID-19 condition (Long COVID). 2022. https://www.who.int/europe/news-room/fact-sheets/item/post-covid-19-condition . Accessed 21 Mar 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Atchison CJ, Davies B, Cooper E, Lound A, Whitaker M, Hampshire A, Azor A, Donnelly CA, Chadeau-Hyam M, Cooke GS, Ward H, Elliot P. Long-term health impacts of COVID-19 among 242,712 adults in England. Nat Commun. 2023;14:6588. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-023-41879-2 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-023-41879-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37875536</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10598213</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malik P, Patel K, Pinto C, Jaiswal R, Tirupathi R, Pillai S, Patel U. Post-acute COVID-19 syndrome (PCS) and health-related quality of life (HRQoL)-A systematic review and meta-analysis. J Med Virol. 2022;94:253–62. https://doi.org/10.1002/jmv.27309 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.27309</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34463956</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walker S, Goodfellow H, Pookarnjanamorakot P, Murray E, Bindman J, Blandford A, Bradbury K, Cooper B, Hamilton FL, Hurst JR, Hylton H, Linke S, Pfeffer P, Ricketts W, Robson C, Stevenson FA, Sunkersing D, Wang J, Gomes M, Henley W, Living With Covid Recovery Collaboration. Impact of fatigue as the primary determinant of functional limitations among patients with post-COVID-19 syndrome: a cross-sectional observational study. BMJ Open. 2023;13:e069217. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen-2022-069217 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2022-069217</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37286327</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10335413</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diexer S, Klee B, Gottschick C, Xu C, Broda A, Purschke O, Binder M, Frese T, Girndt M, Hoell JI, Moor I, Gekle M, Mikolajczyk R. Association between virus variants, vaccination, previous infections, and post-COVID-19 risk. Int J Infect Dis. 2023;136:14–21. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijid.2023.08.019 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2023.08.019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37634619</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Durstenfeld MS, Peluso MJ, Peyser ND, Lin F, Knight SJ, Djibo A, Khatib R, Kitzman H, O’Brien E, Williams N, Isasi C, Kornak J, Carton TW, Olgin JE, Pletcher MJ, Marcus GM, Beatty AL. Factors Associated with Long COVID symptoms in an online cohort study. Open Forum Infect Dis. 2023;10:ofad047. https://doi.org/10.1093/ofid/ofad047 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ofid/ofad047</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36846611</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9945931</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hernández-Aceituno A, García-Hernández A, Larumbe-Zabala E. COVID-19 long-term sequelae: Omicron versus Alpha and Delta variants. Infect Dis Now. 2023;53:104688. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.idnow.2023.104688 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.idnow.2023.104688</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36858287</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9970656</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jassat W, Mudara C, Vika C, Welch R, Arendse T, Dryden M, Blumberg L, Mayet N, Tempia S, Parker A, Nel J, Perumal R, Groome MJ, Conradie F, Ndjeka N, Sigfrid L, Merson L, Cohen C. A cohort study of post-COVID-19 condition across the Beta, Delta, and Omicron waves in South Africa: 6-month follow-up of hospitalized and nonhospitalized participants. Int J Infect Dis. 2023;128:102–11. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijid.2022.12.036 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2022.12.036</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36587841</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9800016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luo J, Zhang J, Tang HT, Wong HK, Lyu A, Cheung CH, Bian Z. Prevalence and risk factors of long COVID 6–12 months after infection with the Omicron variant among nonhospitalized patients in Hong Kong. J Med Virol. 2023;95:e28862. https://doi.org/10.1002/jmv.28862 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.28862</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37334978</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marra AR, Sampaio VS, Ozahata MC, Lopes R, Brito AF, Bragatte M, Kalil J, Miraglia JL, Malheiro DT, Guozhang Y, Teich VD, da Silva Victor E, Pinho JRR, Cypriano A, Vieira LW, Polonio M, de Oliveira SM, Ricardo VCV, Maezato AM, Callado GY, de Paula Pinto Schettino G, de Oliveira KG, Santana RAF, de Malta M, Amgarten F, Boechat D, Kobayashi AL, Perencevich T, Edmond E, Rizzo MB. LV. Risk factors for long coronavirus disease 2019 (long COVID) among healthcare personnel, Brazil, 2020–2022. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol. 2023;44:1972–78. https://doi.org/10.1017/ice.2023.95</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mikolajczyk R, Diexer S, Klee B, Pfrommer L, Purschke O, Fricke J, Ahnert P, Gabrysch S, Gottschick C, Bohn B, Brenner H, Buck C, Castell S, Gastell S, Greiser KH, Harth V, Heise J-K, Holleczek B, Kaaks R, Keil T, Krist L, Leitzmann M, Lieb W, Meinke-Franze C, Michels KB, Velásquez IM, Obi N, Panreck L, Peters A, Pischon T, Schikowski T, Schmidt B, Standl M, Stang A, Völzke H, Weber A, Zeeb H, Karch A. Likelihood of Post-COVID Condition in people with hybrid immunity; data from the German National Cohort (NAKO). 2024;89: 106206. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jinf.2024.106206</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reme B-A, Gjesvik J, Magnusson K. Predictors of the post-COVID condition following mild SARS-CoV-2 infection. Nat Commun. 2023;14:5839. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-023-41541-x .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41467-023-41541-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37730740</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10511472</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Subramanian A, Nirantharakumar K, Hughes S, Myles P, Williams T, Gokhale KM, Taverner T, Chandan JS, Brown K, Simms-Williams N, Shah AD, Singh M, Kidy F, Okoth K, Hotham R, Bashir N, Cockburn N, Lee SI, Turner GM, Gkoutos GV, Aiyegbusi OL, McMullan C, Denniston AK, Sapey E, Lord JM, Wraith DC, Leggett E, Iles C, Marshall T, Price MJ, Marwaha S, Davies EH, Jackson LJ, Matthews KL, Camaradou J, Calvert M, Haroon S. Symptoms and risk factors for long COVID in non-hospitalized adults. Nat Med. 2022;28:1706–14. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41591-022-01909-w .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41591-022-01909-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35879616</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9388369</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sugiyama A, Takafuta T, Sato T, Kitahara Y, Yoshinaga Y, Abe K, Chanroth C, Ataa AG, Phyo Z, Kurisu A, Ko K, Akita T, Kishita E, Kuwabara M, Tanaka J. Natural course of post-COVID symptoms in adults and children. Sci Rep. 2024;14:3884. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-54397-y .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-54397-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38365846</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10873293</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thi Khanh HN, Cornelissen L, Castanares-Zapatero D, De Pauw R, Van Cauteren D, Demarest S, Drieskens S, Devleesschauwer B, De Ridder K, Charafeddine R, Smith P. Association between SARS-CoV-2 variants and post COVID-19 condition: findings from a longitudinal cohort study in the Belgian adult population. BMC Infect Dis. 2023;23:774. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12879-023-08787-8 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12879-023-08787-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37940843</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10634063</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsampasian V, Elghazaly H, Chattopadhyay R, Debski M, Naing TKP, Garg P, Clark A, Ntatsaki E, Vassiliou VS. Risk factors Associated with Post-COVID-19 Condition: a systematic review and Meta-analysis. JAMA Intern Med. 2023;183:566–80. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamainternmed.2023.0750 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2023.0750</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36951832</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10037203</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ceban F, Kulzhabayeva D, Rodrigues NB, Di Vincenzo JD, Gill H, Subramaniapillai M, Lui LMW, Cao B, Mansur RB, Ho RC, Burke MJ, Rhee TG, Rosenblat JD, McIntyre RS. COVID-19 vaccination for the prevention and treatment of long COVID: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Brain Behav Immun. 2023;111:211–29. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bbi.2023.03.022 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2023.03.022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36990297</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10067136</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klee B, Diexer S, Sarajan MH, Glaser N, Binder M, Frese T, Girndt M, Sedding D, Hoell JI, Moor I, Gekle M, Mikolajczyk R, Gottschick C. Regional differences in Uptake of Vaccination against COVID-19 and Influenza in Germany: results from the DigiHero Cohort. Vaccines (Basel). 2023;11:1640. https://doi.org/10.3390/vaccines11111640 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/vaccines11111640</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38005973</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robert-Koch-Institute. Wöchentlicher Lagebericht des RKI zur Coronavirus-Krankheit-2019 (COVID-19). 03.03.2022 - Aktualisierter Stand für Deutschland. https://www.rki.de/DE/Content/InfAZ/N/Neuartiges_Coronavirus/Situationsberichte/Wochenbericht/Wochenbericht_2022-03-03.pdf . Accessed 22 March 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fay MP, Shaw PA. Exact and asymptotic weighted logrank tests for interval Censored Data: the interval R package. J Stat Softw. 2010;36:1–34. https://doi.org/10.18637/jss.v036.i02 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18637/jss.v036.i02</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morello R, Mariani F, Mastrantoni L, De Rose C, Zampino G, Munblit D, Sigfrid L, Valentini P, Buonsenso D. Risk factors for post-COVID-19 condition (Long Covid) in children: a prospective cohort study. EClinicalMedicine. 2023;59:101961. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eclinm.2023.101961 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2023.101961</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37073325</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10101848</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Organisation for Economic Co-Operation and Development. Classifying Educational Programmes: Manual for ISCED-97 Implementation in OECD Countries. 1999 Edition.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ssentongo P, Ssentongo AE, Voleti N, Groff D, Sun A, Ba DM, Nunez J, Parent LJ, Chinchilli VM, Paules CI. SARS-CoV-2 vaccine effectiveness against infection, symptomatic and severe COVID-19: a systematic review and meta-analysis. BMC Infect Dis. 2022;22:439. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12879-022-07418-y .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12879-022-07418-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35525973</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9077344</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boufidou F, Medić S, Lampropoulou V, Siafakas N, Tsakris A, Anastassopoulou C. SARS-CoV-2 reinfections and Long COVID in the Post-omicron phase of the pandemic. Int J Mol Sci. 2023;24:12962. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms241612962 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms241612962</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37629143</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10454552</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mateu L, Tebe C, Loste C, Santos JR, Lladós G, López C, España-Cueto S, Toledo R, Font M, Chamorro A, Muñoz-López F, Nevot M, Vallejo N, Teis A, Puig J, Fumaz CR, Muñoz-Moreno JA, Prats A, Estany-Quera C, Coll-Fernández R, Herrero C, Casares P, Garcia A, Clotet B, Paredes R. Massanella, M. Determinants of the onset and prognosis of the post-COVID-19 condition: a 2-year prospective observational cohort study. Lancet Reg Health Eur. 2023;33:100724. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lanepe.2023.100724 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.lanepe.2023.100724</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37954002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10636281</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Núñez I, Gillard J, Fragoso-Saavedra S, Feyaerts D, Islas-Weinstein L, Gallegos-Guzmán AA, Valente-García U, Meyerowitz J, Kelly JD, Chen H, Ganio E, Benkendorff A, Flores-Gouyonnet J, Dammann-Beltrán P, Heredia-González JF, Rangel-Gutiérrez GA, Blish CA, Nadeau KC, Nolan G, Crispín JC, McIlwain DR, Gaudillière B, Valdés-Ferrer SI. Longitudinal clinical phenotyping of post COVID condition in Mexican adults recovering from severe COVID-19: a prospective cohort study. Front Med (Lausanne). 2023;10:1236702. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmed.2023.1236702 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmed.2023.1236702</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37727759</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hartung TJ, Bahmer T, Chaplinskaya-Sobol I, Deckert J, Endres M, Franzpötter K, Geritz J, Haeusler KG, Hein G, Heuschmann PU, Hopff SM, Horn A, Keil T, Krawczak M, Krist L, Lieb W, Maetzler C, Montellano FA, Morbach C, Neumann C, Nürnberger C, Russ A-K, Schmidbauer L, Schmidt S, Schreiber S, Steigerwald F, Störk S, Zoller T, Maetzler W, Finke C. On behalf of the NAPKON Study Group. Predictors of non-recovery from fatigue and cognitive deficits after COVID-19: a prospective, longitudinal, population-based study. EClinicalMedicine. 2024;69:102456. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eclinm.2024.102456 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2024.102456</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38333368</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10847699</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Servier C, Porcher R, Pane I, Ravaud P, Tran V-T. Trajectories of the evolution of post-COVID-19 condition, up to two years after symptoms onset. Int J Infect Dis. 2023;133:67–74. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijid.2023.05.007 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2023.05.007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37182548</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10176960</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>