<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39557941</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2045-2322</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>14</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>19</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Scientific reports</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Sci Rep</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Privacy guarantees for personal mobility data in humanitarian response.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>28565</StartPage><MedlinePgn>28565</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1038/s41598-024-79561-2</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Personal mobility data from mobile phones and other sensors are increasingly used to inform policymaking during pandemics, natural disasters, and other humanitarian crises. However, even aggregated mobility traces can reveal private information about individual movements to potentially malicious actors. This paper develops and tests an approach for releasing private mobility data, which provides formal guarantees over the privacy of the underlying subjects. Specifically, we (1) introduce an algorithm for constructing differentially private mobility matrices and derive privacy and accuracy bounds on this algorithm; (2) use real-world data from mobile phone operators in Afghanistan and Rwanda to show how this algorithm can enable the use of private mobility data in two high-stakes policy decisions: pandemic response and the distribution of humanitarian aid; and (3) discuss practical decisions that need to be made when implementing this approach, such as how to optimally balance privacy and accuracy. Taken together, these results can help enable the responsible use of private mobility data in humanitarian response.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Kohli</LastName><ForeName>Nitin</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Effective Global Action, UC Berkeley, Berkeley, 94704, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Aiken</LastName><ForeName>Emily</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Information, UC Berkeley, Berkeley, 94704, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Blumenstock</LastName><ForeName>Joshua E</ForeName><Initials>JE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Effective Global Action, UC Berkeley, Berkeley, 94704, USA. jblumenstock@berkeley.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Information, UC Berkeley, Berkeley, 94704, USA. jblumenstock@berkeley.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>IIS-1942702</GrantID><Agency>National Science Foundation</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>N66001-15-C-4066</GrantID><Agency>Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Sci Rep</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101563288</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2045-2322</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018907" MajorTopicYN="Y">Privacy</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000465" MajorTopicYN="Y">Algorithms</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D040421" MajorTopicYN="Y">Cell Phone</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012432" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Rwanda</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000346" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Afghanistan</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000533" MajorTopicYN="N">Altruism</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement><b>Declarations</b> <b>Competing interests</b> The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>35</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39557941</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-79561-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1038/s41598-024-79561-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Wesolowski, A. et al. Impact of human mobility on the emergence of dengue epidemics in Pakistan. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 112, 11887–11892 (2015).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.1504964112</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26351662</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4586847</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wesolowski, A. et al. Quantifying the impact of human mobility on malaria. Science 338, 267–270 (2012).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.1223467</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23066082</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3675794</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bengtsson, L. et al. Using mobile phone data to predict the spatial spread of cholera. Sci. Rep. 5, 1–5 (2015).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/srep08923</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu, X., Bengtsson, L. &amp; Holme, P. Predictability of population displacement after the 2010 Haiti earthquake. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 109, 11576–11581 (2012).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.1203882109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22711804</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3406871</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pastor-Escuredo, D. et al. Flooding through the lens of mobile phone activity. Proceedings of the 2014 IEEE Global Humanitarian Technology Conference (GHTC) (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tai, X. H., Mehra, S. &amp; Blumenstock, J. E. Mobile phone data reveal the effects of violence on internal displacement in Afghanistan. Nature Human Behaviour 1–11, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-022-01336-4 (2022). Publisher: Nature Publishing Group.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aiken, E., Bellue, S., Karlan, D., Udry, C. R. &amp; Blumenstock, J. Machine Learning and Mobile Phone Data Can Improve the Targeting of Humanitarian Aid. Nature 603. https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-022-04484-9 (2022)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blumenstock, J. Machine learning can help get COVID-19 aid to those who need it most. Nature 581. https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-020-01393-7 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dobra, N., A. Williams &amp; Eagle, N. Spatiotemporal detection of unusual human population behavior using mobile phone data. PLoS ONE 10 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gundogdu, D., Incel, O., Salah, A. &amp; Lepri, B. Countrywide arrhythmia: emergency event detection using mobile phone data. EPJ Data Sci. 5 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kraemer, M. U. et al. The effect of human mobility and control measures on the COVID-19 epidemic in China. Science 368, 493–497 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.abb4218</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32213647</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Warren, M. S. &amp; Skillman, S. W. Mobility changes in response to COVID-19. arXiv preprint. arXiv:2003.14228 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chinazzi, M. et al. The effect of travel restrictions on the spread of the 2019 novel coronavirus (COVID-19) outbreak. Science 368, 395–400 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.aba9757</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32144116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7164386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ilin, C. et al. Public mobility data enables COVID-19 forecasting and management at local and global scales. Sci. Rep. 11, 1–11. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-021-92892-8 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lai, S. et al. Effect of non-pharmaceutical interventions to contain COVID-19 in China. Nature 585, 410–413 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oliver, N. et al. Mobile phone data for informing public health actions across the COVID-19 pandemic life cycle. Sci. Adv. (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thompson, S. A. &amp; Warzel, C. Twelve million phones, one dataset, zero privacy. The New York Times 19, 2019 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ovide, S. The Nightmare of Our Snooping Phones. The New York Times (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boorstein, M., Iati, M. &amp; Shin, A. Top U.S. Catholic Church official resigns after cellphone data used to track him on Grindr and to gay bars. The Washington Post (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Montjoye, Y.-A., Hidalgo, C., Verleysen, M. &amp; Blondel, V. Unique in the crowd: The privacy bounds of human mobility. Sci. Rep. 3 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Privacy &amp; Board, C. L. O. Report on the government’s use of the call detail records program under the usa freedom act. Privacy and Civil Liberties Oversight Board (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hosein, G. &amp; Nyst, C. Aiding surveillance: an exploration of how development and humanitarian aid initiatives are enabling surveillance in developing countries. Available at SSRN 2326229 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor, L. No place to hide? the ethics and analytics of tracking mobility using mobile phone data. Environ. Plann. D Soc. Sp. 34 (2016).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Montjoye, Y.-A. et al. On the privacy-conscientious use of mobile phone data. Sci. Data 5, 1–6 (2018).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/sdata.2018.286</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu, F., Tu, Z., Zhang, P., Fu, X. &amp; Jin, D. Trajectory recovery from ash: User privacy is not preserved in aggregated mobility data. In Proceedings of the 26th World Wide Web Conference, 1241–1250 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abul, O., Bonchi, F. &amp; Nanni, M. Never walk alone: Uncertainty for anonymity in moving objects databases. In 2008 IEEE 24th international conference on data engineering, 376–385 (Ieee, 2008).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Primault, V., Mokhtar, S. B., Lauradoux, C. &amp; Brunie, L. Time distortion anonymization for the publication of mobility data with high utility. In 2015 IEEE Trustcom/BigDataSE/ISPA, vol. 1, 539–546 (IEEE, 2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meyerowitz, J. &amp; Roy Choudhury, R. Hiding stars with fireworks: location privacy through camouflage. In Proceedings of the 15th annual international conference on Mobile computing and networking, 345–356 (2009).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi, J., Zhang, R., Liu, Y. &amp; Zhang, Y. Prisense: privacy-preserving data aggregation in people-centric urban sensing systems. In 2010 Proceedings IEEE INFOCOM, 1–9 (IEEE, 2010).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dwork, C., McSherry, F., Nissim, K. &amp; Smith, A. Calibrating noise to sensitivity in private data analysis. In Theory of cryptography conference, 265–284 (Springer, 2006).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mir, D. J., Isaacman, S., Cáceres, R., Martonosi, M. &amp; Wright, R. N. DP-Where: Differentially private modeling of human mobility. In 2013 IEEE international conference on big data, 580–588 (IEEE, 2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qardaji, W., Yang, W. &amp; Li, N. Differentially private grids for geospatial data. In 2013 IEEE 29th international conference on data engineering (ICDE), 757–768 (IEEE, 2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aktay, A. et al. Google covid-19 community mobility reports: Anonymization process description (version 1.0). arXiv preprint[SPACE] arXiv:2004.04145 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Machanavajjhala, A., Kifer, D., Abowd, J., Gehrke, J. &amp; Vilhuber, L. Privacy: Theory meets practice on the map. In 2008 IEEE 24th international conference on data engineering, 277–286 (IEEE, 2008).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pratesi, F. et al. Privacy-aware distributed mobility data analytics. In Proceedings of the 21th Italian Symposium on Advanced Database Systems, SEBD 2013 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang, K., Shao, D., Bressan, S., Kister, T. &amp; Tan, K.-L. Publishing trajectories with differential privacy guarantees. In Proceedings of the 25th International conference on scientific and statistical database management, 1–12 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghane, S., Kulik, L. &amp; Ramamohanarao, K. Tgm: A generative mechanism for publishing trajectories with differential privacy. IEEE Internet Things J. 7, 2611–2621 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/JIOT.2019.2943719</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shao, D., Jiang, K., Kister, T., Bressan, S. &amp; Tan, K.-L. Publishing trajectory with differential privacy: A priori vs. a posteriori sampling mechanisms. In Database and Expert Systems Applications: 24th International Conference, DEXA 2013, Prague, Czech Republic, August 26-29, 2013. Proceedings, Part I 24, 357–365 (Springer, 2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, M., Zhu, L., Zhang, Z. &amp; Xu, R. Achieving differential privacy of trajectory data publishing in participatory sensing. Inf. Sci. 400, 1–13 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Savi, M. K. et al. A standardised differential privacy framework for epidemiological modelling with mobile phone data. medRxiv 2023–03 (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaham, S., Ghinita, G. &amp; Shahabi, C. Differentially-Private Publication of Origin-Destination Matrices with Intermediate Stops. arXiv preprint. arXiv:2202.12342 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dwork, C., Kohli, N. &amp; Mulligan, D. Differential privacy in practice: Expose your epsilons! J. Privacy Confident. 9 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kermack, W. O. &amp; McKendrick, A. G. A contribution to the mathematical theory of epidemics. Proc. R. Soc. Lond. Ser. A 115, 700–721 (1927).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goel, R. &amp; Sharma, R. Mobility based sir model for pandemics-with case study of covid-19. In 2020 IEEE/ACM International Conference on Advances in Social Networks Analysis and Mining (ASONAM), 110–117 (IEEE, 2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schroader, A. The Kincade Fire: Population Movement and Displacement. ArcGIS Story Maps (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CrisisReady. 7.8 and 7.5 Magnitude Earthquakes strike Turkey, Cause Mass Destruction and Growing Death Toll. CrisisReady (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Afghan forces struggle as Taliban seeks northern stronghold. Military Times (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pyrgelis, A., Troncoso, C. &amp; De Cristofaro, E. Knock knock, who’s there? membership inference on aggregate location data. arXiv preprintarXiv:1708.06145 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naldi, M. &amp; D’Acquisto, G. Differential privacy: An estimation theory-based method for choosing epsilon. arXiv preprint. arXiv:1510.00917 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsu, J. et al. Differential privacy: An economic method for choosing epsilon. In 2014 IEEE 27th Computer Security Foundations Symposium, 398–410 (IEEE, 2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kohli, N. &amp; Laskowski, P. Epsilon voting: Mechanism design for parameter selection in differential privacy. In 2018 IEEE Symposium on Privacy-Aware Computing (PAC), 19–30 (IEEE, 2018).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ligett, K., Neel, S., Roth, A., Waggoner, B. &amp; Wu, S. Z. Accuracy first: Selecting a differential privacy level for accuracy constrained erm. Adv. Neural Inf. Process. Syst. 30 (2017).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Whitehouse, J., Ramdas, A., Wu, S. Z. &amp; Rogers, R. M. Brownian noise reduction: Maximizing privacy subject to accuracy constraints. Adv. Neural. Inf. Process. Syst. 35, 11217–11228 (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu, J. &amp; Talwar, K. Private selection from private candidates. In Proceedings of the 51st Annual ACM SIGACT Symposium on Theory of Computing, 298–309 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papernot, N. &amp; Steinke, T. Hyperparameter tuning with renyi differential privacy. In International Conference on Learning Representations (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cummings, R. et al. Advancing differential privacy: Where we are now and future directions for real-world deployment. Harvard Data Sci. Rev. 6 (2024).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kohli, N. &amp; Laskowski, P. Differential privacy for black-box statistical analyses. Proc. Privacy Enhancing Technol. 3, 418–431 (2023).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.56553/popets-2023-0089</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu, K., Van Hentenryck, P. &amp; Fioretto, F. Bias and variance of post-processing in differential privacy. In Proceedings of the AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence 35, 11177–11184 (2021).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1609/aaai.v35i12.17333</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kohli, N. Leveraging differential privacy while attending to social and political commitments (PhD diss. University of California, Berkeley, 2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Z. &amp; Reiter, J. P. Post-processing differentially private counts to satisfy additive constraints. Trans. Data Priv. 14, 65–77 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pujol, D. et al. Fair decision making using privacy-protected data. In Proceedings of the 2020 Conference on Fairness, Accountability, and Transparency, 189–199 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen, A., Duchin, M. &amp; Matthews, J. &amp; Suwal, B (Private numbers in public policy, Census, differential privacy, and redistricting. Harvard Data Science Review, 2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu, K., Fioretto, F. &amp; Van Hentenryck, P. Post-processing of differentially private data: A fairness perspective. In International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI) (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suppression of Rates and Counts. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), United States Cancer Statistics (USCS) (2023).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dataquest Home. Data Suppression (Stability Reports) California Department of Education .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matthews, G. J., Harel, O. &amp; Aseltine, R. H. Jr. A review of statistical disclosure control techniques employed by web-based data query systems. J. Public Health Manag. Pract. JPHMP 23, e1 (2017).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27798533</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suppression of Rates, Trends, and Counts. U.S. An Ecosystem of Health Disparities and Minority Health Resources. Department of Health &amp; Human Services National Institutes of Health.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bertozzi, A. L., Franco, E., Mohler, G., Short, M. B. &amp; Sledge, D. The challenges of modeling and forecasting the spread of covid-19. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 117, 16732–16738 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.2006520117</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32616574</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7382213</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bagal, D. K., Rath, A., Barua, A. &amp; Patnaik, D. Estimating the parameters of susceptible-infected-recovered model of covid-19 cases in india during lockdown periods. Chaos, Solitons &amp; Fractals 140, 110154 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.chaos.2020.110154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lounis, M. &amp; Bagal, D. K. Estimation of SIR model’s parameters of COVID-19 in Algeria. Bull. Natl. Res. Centre 44, 1–6 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s42269-020-00434-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>