<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39554268</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1535-7597</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Apr</Month><Day>30</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Epilepsy currents</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Epilepsy Curr</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Brain on Fire: How Brain Infection and Neuroinflammation Drive Worldwide Epilepsy Burden.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>15357597241242238</StartPage><MedlinePgn>15357597241242238</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">15357597241242238</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1177/15357597241242238</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Roughly 80% of the global burden of epilepsy resides in low- and middle-income countries (LMICs; WHO, 2022). Despite numerous new therapies for the treatment of epilepsy, the number of patients who remain resistant to available medications is unchanged. Additionally, no therapy has yet been clinically proven to prevent or attenuate the development of epilepsy in at-risk individuals. Unfortunately, access to next generation therapies in LMICs is low, the stigma associated with epilepsy remains high, and access to adequate resources is unchanged. Thus, the global epilepsy burden disproportionately falls on LMICs such that strategies to conscientiously integrate global epilepsy risk factors into preclinical research may meaningfully advance 21st century epilepsy therapies. Brain infections are one of the main risk factors for epilepsy in resource-poor settings. Further, both infection- and autoimmune-associated encephalitis contribute to worldwide epilepsy risk and remain relatively understudied. For example, clinical SARS CoV-2 infection can induce rare instances of encephalopathy and acute seizures. Among viruses known to cause acute brain infection, enteroviruses increase risk for encephalitis-induced epilepsy, but are not associated with risk for other neurodevelopmental disorders (eg, autism spectrum or attentional deficit hyperactivity disorders). Naturally occurring models of viral infection-induced epilepsy therefore provide an exquisite opportunity to uncover novel contributors to epileptogenesis. Moreover, the convergent neuroinflammatory pathways that are associated with viral infection-induced encephalitis and autoimmune encephalitis reflect an untapped therapeutic opportunity to meaningfully reduce the global burden of epilepsy. This review summarizes the latest advances in translational research integrating encephalitis-induced seizure and epilepsy models, in tandem with progress in clinical diagnosis of inflammation and virally mediated epilepsy. This improved awareness of the shared biological underpinnings of epileptogenesis following brain infection or autoimmune encephalitis is anticipated to beneficially impact the global burden of epilepsy.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s) 2024.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Barker-Haliski</LastName><ForeName>Melissa</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8175-0553</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacy, School of Pharmacy, University of Washington, Seattle, WA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>DePaula-Silva</LastName><ForeName>Ana Beatriz</ForeName><Initials>AB</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2452-3215</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacology and Toxicology, University of Utah, Salt Lake City, UT, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pitsch</LastName><ForeName>Julika</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epileptology, University Hospital Bonn, Bonn, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sontheimer</LastName><ForeName>Harald</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neuroscience, School of Medicine, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hirsch</LastName><ForeName>Lawrence J</ForeName><Initials>LJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurology, School of Medicine, Yale University, New Haven, CT, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Galanopoulou</LastName><ForeName>Aristea S</ForeName><Initials>AS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Saul R. Korey Department of Neurology, Isabelle Rapin Division of Child Neurology, Dominick P. Purpura Department of Neuroscience, Albert Einstein College of Medicine, Bronx, NY, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kearney</LastName><ForeName>Jennifer A</ForeName><Initials>JA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1726-4769</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pharmacology, Feinberg School of Medicine, Northwestern University, Chicago, IL, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>30</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Epilepsy Curr</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101135954</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1535-7511</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">FIRES</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">NORSE</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Theiler’s virus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">autoimmune encephalitis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cytokines</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">drebin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">global health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">minocycline</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">perineuronal nets</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">refractory status epilepticus</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The author(s) declared the following potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: LJH has received consulting fees from Accure, Ceribell, Gilead, Marinus, Natus, Neurelis, Neuropace, Rafa Laboratories, Rapport Therapeutics, UCB, &amp; Vial Health Technology; honoraria for speaking from Neuropace, Natus, and UCB; royalites from Wolters-Kluwer for authoring chapters for UpToDate-Neurology, and from Wiley for coauthoring the book “Atlas of EEG in Critical Care,” 1st and 2nd editions; and is co-chair of the medical and scientific advisory board for the NORSE Institute. AS Galanopoulou is the Editor-in-Chief of Epilepsia Open and associate editor of Neurobiology of Disease and receives royalties from Elsevier, Walters Kluwer, and Medlink for publications. JAK receives royalties for disease model licensing from GW Pharma, Novartis, Pfizer, Tevard, Emugen, Stoke Therapeutics, Regulus, Pfizer, Regel, Sangamo Biosciences, GSK, Biogen, and Encoded Therapeutics. None of the other authors has any conflict to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39554268</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11562294</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/15357597241242238</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1177_15357597241242238</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Singh G, Prabhakar S. The association between central nervous system (CNS) infections and epilepsy: epidemiological approaches and microbiological and epileptological perspectives. Epilepsia. 2008;49(Suppl 6):2–7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18754954</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Honnorat J, Plazat LO. Autoimmune encephalitis and psychiatric disorders. Rev Neurol (Paris). 2018;174(4):228–236.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29609960</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>DePaula-Silva AB. The contribution of microglia and brain-infiltrating macrophages to the pathogenesis of neuroinflammatory and neurodegenerative diseases during TMEV infection of the central nervous system. Viruses. 2024;16(1):119.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10819099</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38257819</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vezzani A, Fujinami RS, White HS, et al. Infections, inflammation and epilepsy. Acta Neuropathol. 2016;131(2):211–234.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4867498</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26423537</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barker-Haliski M, Nishi T, White HS. Soticlestat, a novel cholesterol 24-hydroxylase inhibitor, modifies acute seizure burden and chronic epilepsy-related behavioral deficits following Theiler’s virus infection in mice. Neuropharmacology. 2023;222:109310.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36341806</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barker-Haliski ML, Loscher W, White HS, Galanopoulou AS. Neuroinflammation in epileptogenesis: insights and translational perspectives from new models of epilepsy. Epilepsia. 2017;58(Suppl 3):39–47.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5604891</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28675559</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Broer S, Kaufer C, Haist V, et al. Brain inflammation, neurodegeneration and seizure development following picornavirus infection markedly differ among virus and mouse strains and substrains. Exp Neurol. 2016;279:57–74.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26892877</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>DePaula-Silva AB, Sonderegger FL, Libbey JE, Doty DJ, Fujinami RS. The immune response to picornavirus infection and the effect of immune manipulation on acute seizures. J Neurovirol. 2018;24(4):464–477.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6105529</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29687406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galic MA, Riazi K, Pittman QJ. Cytokines and brain excitability. Front Neuroendocrinol. 2012;33(1):116–125.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3547977</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22214786</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li G, Bauer S, Nowak M, et al. Cytokines and epilepsy. Seizure. 2011;20(3):249–256.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21216630</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uludag IF, Duksal T, Tiftikcioglu BI, Zorlu Y, Ozkaya F, Kirkali G. IL-1beta, IL-6 and IL1Ra levels in temporal lobe epilepsy. Seizure. 2015;26:22–25.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25799897</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kirkman NJ, Libbey JE, Wilcox KS, White HS, Fujinami RS. Innate but not adaptive immune responses contribute to behavioral seizures following viral infection. Epilepsia. 2010;51(3):454–464.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3046460</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19845729</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Haggar SM, Hegazy SK, Mustafa W, Khrieba MO. Possible immuno-modulatory effects of tocilizumab in patients with refractory status epilepticus. Eur Rev Med Pharmacol Sci. 2023;27(4):1512–1521.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36876691</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Girardin ML, Flamand T, Roignot O, et al. Treatment of new onset refractory status epilepticus/febrile infection-related epilepsy syndrome with tocilizumab in a child and a young adult. Epilepsia. 2023;64(6):e87–e92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36961094</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Monsour M, Croci DM, Agazzi S, Borlongan CV. Contemplating IL-6, a double-edged sword cytokine: which side to use for stroke pathology? CNS Neurosci Ther. 2023;29(2):493–497.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9873516</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36478506</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stredny CM, Case S, Sansevere AJ, Son M, Henderson L, Gorman MP. Interleukin-6 blockade with tocilizumab in anakinra-refractory febrile infection-related epilepsy syndrome (FIRES). Child Neurol Open. 2020;7:2329048X20979253.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7745547</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33403221</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Libbey JE, Doty DJ, Sim JT, Cusick MF, Round JL, Fujinami RS. The effects of diet on the severity of central nervous system disease: one part of lab-to-lab variability. Nutrition. 2016;32(7-8):877–883.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4877245</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27133811</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zierath DK, Davidson S, Manoukian J, Knox KM, White HS, Meeker S, Ericsson A, Barker-Haliski M. Diet composition and sterilization modifies intestinal microbiome diversity and burden of Theiler’s virus infection-induced acute seizures. Epilepsia. 2024. Mar 16. doi: 10.1111/epi.17946. Epub ahead of print. PMID: 38491947.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38491947</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tewari BP, Chaunsali L, Campbell SL, Patel DC, Goode AE, Sontheimer H. Perineuronal nets decrease membrane capacitance of peritumoral fast spiking interneurons in a model of epilepsy. Nat Commun. 2018;9(1):4724.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6226462</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30413686</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chaunsali L, Tewari BP, Sontheimer H. Perineuronal net dynamics in the pathophysiology of epilepsy. Epilepsy Curr. 2021;21(4):273–281.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8512927</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34690566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tewari BP, Chaunsali L, Prim CE, Sontheimer H. A glial perspective on the extracellular matrix and perineuronal net remodeling in the central nervous system. Front Cell Neurosci. 2022;16:1022754.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9630365</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36339816</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Tewari BP, Woo AM, Prim CE, et al.
Perineuronal nets support astrocytic ion and glutamate homeostasis at tripartite synapses. Res Sq. 2023. https://www.researchsquare.com/article/rs-2501039/v1 (accessed January 27, 2024)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patel DC, Swift N, Tewari BP, et al. Infection-induced epilepsy is caused by increased expression of chondroitin sulfate proteoglycans in hippocampus and amygdala. bioRxiv. 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Graus F, Escudero D, Oleaga L, et al. Syndrome and outcome of antibody-negative limbic encephalitis. Eur J Neurol. 2018;25(8):1011–1016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6037545</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29667271</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Graus F, Titulaer MJ, Balu R, et al. A clinical approach to diagnosis of autoimmune encephalitis. Lancet Neurol. 2016;15(4):391–404.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5066574</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26906964</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dalmau J, Gleichman AJ, Hughes EG, et al. Anti-NMDA-receptor encephalitis: case series and analysis of the effects of antibodies. Lancet Neurol. 2008;7(12):1091–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2607118</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18851928</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nersesjan V, McWilliam O, Krarup LH, Kondziella D. Autoimmune encephalitis related to cancer treatment with immune checkpoint inhibitors: a systematic review. Neurology. 2021;97(2):e191–e202.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33952651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maudes E, Landa J, Munoz-Lopetegi A, et al. Clinical significance of Kelch-like protein 11 antibodies. Neurol Neuroimmunol Neuroinflamm. 2020;7(3):e666.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7051195</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31953318</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niehusmann P, Mittelstaedt T, Bien CG, et al. Presence of human herpes virus 6 DNA exclusively in temporal lobe epilepsy brain tissue of patients with history of encephalitis. Epilepsia. 2010;51(12):2478–83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21204811</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vincent A, Bien CG, Irani SR, Waters P. Autoantibodies associated with diseases of the CNS: new developments and future challenges. Lancet Neurol. 2011;10(8):759–772.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21777830</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leypoldt F, Armangue T, Dalmau J. Autoimmune encephalopathies. Ann N Y Acad Sci. 2015;1338(1):94–114.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4363225</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25315420</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lancaster E. Autoantibody encephalitis: presentation, diagnosis, and management. J Clin Neurol. 2022;18(4):373–390.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9262450</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35796263</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuehn JC, Meschede C, Helmstaedter C, et al. Adult-onset temporal lobe epilepsy suspicious for autoimmune pathogenesis: autoantibody prevalence and clinical correlates. PLoS One. 2020;15(10):e0241289.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7595292</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33119692</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pitsch J, Kamalizade D, Braun A, et al. Drebrin autoantibodies in patients with seizures and suspected encephalitis. Ann Neurol. 2020;87(6):869–884.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32196746</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hirsch LJ, Gaspard N, van Baalen A, et al. Proposed consensus definitions for new-onset refractory status epilepticus (NORSE), febrile infection-related epilepsy syndrome (FIRES), and related conditions. Epilepsia. 2018;59(4):739–744.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29399791</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hanin A, Cespedes J, Dorgham K, et al. Cytokines in new-onset refractory status epilepticus predict outcomes. Ann Neurol. 2023;94(1):75–90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36871188</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cerovic M, Di Nunzio M, Craparotta I, Vezzani A. An in vitro model of drug-resistant seizures for selecting clinically effective antiseizure medications in febrile infection-related epilepsy syndrome. Front Neurol. 2023;14:1129138.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10074483</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37034097</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li H, Liu X, Wang R, et al. Blood-brain barrier damage and new onset refractory status epilepticus: an exploratory study using dynamic contrast-enhanced magnetic resonance imaging. Epilepsia. 2023;64(6):1594–1604.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36892496</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dale RC, Thomas T, Patel S, et al. CSF neopterin and quinolinic acid are biomarkers of neuroinflammation and neurotoxicity in FIRES and other infection-triggered encephalopathy syndromes. Ann Clin Transl Neurol. 2023;10(8):1417–1432.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10424664</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37340737</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wickstrom R, Taraschenko O, Dilena R, et al. International consensus recommendations for management of New Onset Refractory Status Epilepticus (NORSE) including Febrile Infection-Related Epilepsy Syndrome (FIRES): summary and clinical tools. Epilepsia. 2022;63(11):2827–2839.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9826478</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35951466</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taraschenko O, Pavuluri S, Schmidt CM, Pulluru YR, Gupta N. Seizure burden and neuropsychological outcomes of new-onset refractory status epilepticus: systematic review. Front Neurol. 2023;14:1095061.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9902772</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36761344</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galanopoulou AS, Ferastraoaru V, Correa DJ, et al. EEG findings in acutely ill patients investigated for SARS-CoV-2/COVID-19: a small case series preliminary report. Epilepsia Open. 2020;5(2):314–324.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7289172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32537529</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Varatharaj A, Thomas N, Ellul MA, et al. Neurological and neuropsychiatric complications of COVID-19 in 153 patients: a UK-wide surveillance study. Lancet Psychiatry. 2020;7(10):875–882.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7316461</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32593341</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Netland J, Meyerholz DK, Moore S, Cassell M, Perlman S. Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus infection causes neuronal death in the absence of encephalitis in mice transgenic for human ACE2. J Virol. 2008;82(15):7264–75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2493326</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18495771</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsu S, Correa DJ, Steinschneider M, Galanopoulou AS. Case control study of EEG abnormalities in hospitalized patients investigated for SARS-CoV-2/COVID-19 infection. In: American Epilepsy Society, Annual Meeting. Chicago, IL; 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kubota T, Gajera PK, Kuroda N. Meta-analysis of EEG findings in patients with COVID-19. Epilepsy Behav. 2021;115:107682.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7833461</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33342709</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin L, Al-Faraj A, Ayub N, et al. Electroencephalographic abnormalities are common in COVID-19 and are associated with outcomes. Ann Neurol. 2021;89(5):872–883.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8104061</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33704826</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eskandar EN, Altschul DJ, de la Garza Ramos R, et al. Neurologic syndromes predict higher in-hospital mortality in COVID-19. Neurology. 2021;96(11):e1527–e1538.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8032378</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33443111</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Legriel S, Badenes R, Engrand N, et al. Outcomes in patients with COVID-19 with acute encephalopathy and coma: an international prospective study. Neurology. 2023;100(22):e2247–e2258.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10259271</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37041081</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spudich S, Nath A. Nervous system consequences of COVID-19. Science. 2022;375(6578):267–269.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35050660</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matschke J, Lutgehetmann M, Hagel C, et al. Neuropathology of patients with COVID-19 in Germany: a post-mortem case series. Lancet Neurol. 2020;19(11):919–929.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7535629</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33031735</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee MH, Perl DP, Nair G, et al. Microvascular injury in the brains of patients with Covid-19. N Engl J Med. 2021;384(5):481–483.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7787217</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33378608</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song E, Bartley CM, Chow RD, et al. Divergent and self-reactive immune responses in the CNS of COVID-19 patients with neurological symptoms. Cell Rep Med. 2021;2(5):100288.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8091032</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33969321</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taquet M, Devinsky O, Cross JH, Harrison PJ, Sen A. Incidence of epilepsy and seizures over the first 6 months after a COVID-19 diagnosis: a retrospective cohort study. Neurology. 2023;100(8):e790–e799.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9984208</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36384658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu YZ, Jiang T, Jiang CL. Bioinformatic analysis identified common pathogenetic processes between epilepsy and COVID-19. Eur Rev Med Pharmacol Sci. 2023;27(24):11673–11690.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38164831</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>