<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39554986</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2190-572X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>14</Volume><Issue>12</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Dec</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>3 Biotech</Title><ISOAbbreviation>3 Biotech</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Plant resources for immunonutrients and immunomodulators to combat infectious respiratory viral diseases: a review.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>302</StartPage><MedlinePgn>302</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">302</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s13205-024-04143-y</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Boosting the immune system has become a crucial aspect in the global battle against the COVID-19 pandemic and other similar infections to protect oneself against symptoms, especially in the prevention of viral infections of the lower respiratory tract. The importance of conducting more studies to create successful herbal formulations as infection prevention measures is emphasized in this review, which looks at the function of immune-boosting nutrients, medicinal plants, and herbal treatments. We reviewed and analyzed 207 studies published from 1946 to the present using reputable databases like Google Scholar, PubMed, and NCBI. The review examined 115 plant species in total and identified 12 key nutrients, including vitamins A, D, C, omega-3 fatty acids, iron, and zinc, while noting that four plant families, Rosaceae, Asteraceae, Amaryllidaceae, and Acanthaceae, show potential against respiratory infections like influenza, RSV, and SARS-CoV. To lower the risk of infection, it is recommended to consume nutritious meals that have immune-modulating qualities. Information on the bioactive components of medicinal herbs, spices, and plants that have been effective in treating respiratory viral infections and related conditions is compiled in this review, which highlights phytoactive substances with antibacterial and antiviral activity as effective modulators to lower the risk of infections. Furthermore, it is highlighted that ancient knowledge systems, like Ayurveda and Naturopathy, should be integrated to help develop new herbal formulations. To improve immunity and lessen vulnerability to serious respiratory infections, the results highlight the need for including immune-modulating foods and plant-based medicines into everyday routines.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© King Abdulaziz City for Science and Technology 2024. Springer Nature or its licensor (e.g. a society or other partner) holds exclusive rights to this article under a publishing agreement with the author(s) or other rightsholder(s); author self-archiving of the accepted manuscript version of this article is solely governed by the terms of such publishing agreement and applicable law.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kota</LastName><ForeName>Sobha</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-9140-6396</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Chemical Engineering, RVR &amp; JC College of Engineering, Guntur, Andhra Pradesh 522 019 India.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.411114.0</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0000 9211 2181</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nelapati</LastName><ForeName>Anand Kumar</ForeName><Initials>AK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biotechnology, Vignan's Foundation for Science, Technology and Research, Vadlamudi, Guntur, Andhra Pradesh 522 213 India.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="ROR">https://ror.org/03tjsyq23</Identifier><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.454774.1</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Govada</LastName><ForeName>Vayunandana Rao</ForeName><Initials>VR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Chemical Engineering, RVR &amp; JC College of Engineering, Guntur, Andhra Pradesh 522 019 India.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.411114.0</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0000 9211 2181</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>16</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>3 Biotech</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101565857</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2190-5738</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Antiviral bio-active compounds</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Herbal remedies</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Immune modulation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Nutrition</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflict of interestThe authors declare that there are no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>31</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39554986</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11568085</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13205-024-04143-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">4143</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>AANP (The American Association of Naturopathic Physicians) (2020) Naturopathic recommendations regarding the 2019 novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV). https://cdn.ymaws.com/naturopathic.org/resource/resmgr/newsletter/natnow2020/AANP2019CoronavirusFINAL.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abedini A, Mahdavi A, Mirza Alizadeh A, Hejazi E, Hosseini H (2022) A review on dietary additive, food supplement and exercise effects on the prevention of COVID-19. Nutr Food Sci Res 9(1):1–14. 10.52547/nfsr.9.1.1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adiguna SP, Panggabean JA, Atikana A, Untari F, Izzati F, Bayu A, Rosyidah A, Rahmawati SI, Putra MY (2021) Antiviral activities of andrographolide and its derivatives: mechanism of action and delivery system. Pharmaceuticals 14(11):1102. 10.3390/ph14111102</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8619093</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34832884</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agostini ML, Andres EL, Sims AC, Graham RL, Sheahan TP, Lu X, Smith EC, Case JB, Feng JY, Jordan R, Ray AS, Cihlar T, Siegel D, Mackmam RL, Clarke MO, Baric RS, Denison MR (2018) Coronavirus susceptibility to the antiviral remdesivir (GS-5734) is mediated by the viral polymerase and the proofreading exoribonuclease. Mbio 9(2):e0221-18. 10.1128/mBio.00221-18</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5844999</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29511076</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmad A, Davies J, Randall S, Skinner G (1996) Antiviral properties of extract of Opuntia streptacantha. Antiviral Res 30(2–3):75–85. 10.1016/0166-3542(95)00839-X</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8783800</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alrasheid AA, Babiker MY, Awad TA (2021) Evaluation of certain medicinal plants compounds as new potential inhibitors of novel corona virus (COVID-19) using molecular docking analysis. In Silico Pharmacol 9(1):10. 10.1007/s40203-020-00073-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7787652</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33432283</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Zuhair H, El-Sayeh B, Ameen HA, Al-Shoora H (1996) Pharmacological studies of cardamom oil in animals. Pharmacol Res 34(1–2):79–82. 10.1006/phrs.1996.0067</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8981560</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arabi YM, Al-Omari A, Mandourah Y, Al-Hameed F, Sindi AA, Alraddadi B, Shalhoub S, Almotairi A, Al Khatib K, Abdulmomem A, Qushmaq I, Mady A, Solaiman O, Al-Aithan A-R, Ragab A, Al Mekhlafi GA, Al Harthy A, Kharaba A, Ahmadi MA, Sadat M, Mutairi HA, Qasim EA, Jose J, Nasim M, Al-Dawood A, Merson L, Fowler R, Hayden FG, Balkhy HH (2017) Critically ill patients with the Middle East respiratory syndrome: a multicenter retrospective cohort study. Critic Care Med 45(10):1683–1695. 10.1097/CCM.0000000000002621</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28787295</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arbeitskreis Blut, Untergruppe «BewertungBlutassoziierterKrankheitserreger» (2009) Influenza virus. Transfus Med Hemother 36 (1):32–39. 10.1159/000197314</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arun Kumar B, Fernandez A, Laila SP, Nair AS (2020) Molecular docking study of acyclovir and its derivatives as potent inhibitors in novel COVID-19. Int J Pharam Sci 11:4700–4705. 10.13040/IJPSR.0975-8232.11(9).4700-05</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashok Kumar K, Murugan M, Dhanya MK, Surya R, Kamaraj D (2020) Phytochemical variations among four distinct varieties of Indian cardamom Elettaria cardamomum (L.) Maton. Nat Prod Res 34(13):1919–1922. 10.1080/14786419.2018.1561687</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30663385</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Avicenna (1998) Al Qanun Fil Tibb [Hameed HA trans], 1st edn. Jamia Hamdard Printing Press, New Delhi</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barrett R, Kuzawa CW, McDade T, Armelagos GJ (1998) Emerging and re-emerging infectious diseases: the third epidemiologic transition. Annu Rev Anthropol 27(1):247–271. 10.1146/annurev.anthro.27.1.247</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baxter H, Puri B, Harborne JB, Hall A, Moss GP (1998) Phytochemical dictionary: a handbook of bioactive compounds from plants. CRC Press, London</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benjamini E, Coico R, Sunshine G (2000) Immunology: a short course, 4th edn. Wiley-Liss, New York</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ben-Shabat S, Yarmolinsky L, Porat D, Dahan A (2020) Antiviral effect of phytochemicals from medicinal plants: applications and drug delivery strategies. Drug Deliv Transl Res 10:354–367. 10.1007/s13346-019-00691-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7097340</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31788762</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhutta ZA, Black RE, Brown KH, Gardner JM, Gore S, Hidayat A, Khatun F, Martorell R, Ninh NX, Penny ME, Rosado JL, Roy SK, Ruel M, Sazawal S, Shankar A (1999) Prevention of diarrhea and pneumonia by zinc supplementation in children in developing countries: pooled analysis of randomized controlled trials. J Pediatr 135(6):689–697. 10.1016/S0022-3476(99)70086-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10586170</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bing F-H, Liu J, Li Z, Zhang GB, Liao YF, Li J, Dong CY (2009) Anti-influenza-virus activity of total alkaloids from Commelina communis L. Arch Virol 154(11):1837–1840. 10.1007/s00705-009-0503-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19774337</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bisht V, Negi J, Bhandari A, Sundriyal R (2011) Amomum subulatum roxb: traditional, phytochemical and biological activities—an overview. Afr J Agric Res 6(24):5386–5390. 10.5897/AJAR11.745</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blumenthal M, Brusse WR, Goldberg A, Gruenwald J, Hall T, Riggins CW, Rister RS (1998) The complete German commission e monographs therapeutic guide to herbal medicines. American Botanical Council, Austin, pp 136–138</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bongiorno PB, Fratellone PM, LoGiudice P (2008) Potential health benefits of garlic (Allium sativum): a narrative review. J Complement Integr Med. 10.2202/1553-3840.1084</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bouvier NM, Palese P (2008) The biology of influenza viruses. Vaccine 26:D49-53. 10.1016/j.vaccine.2008.07.039</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3074182</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19230160</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown AJ, Won JJ, Graham RL, Dinnon KH, Sims AC, Feng JY, Cihlar T, Denison MR, Baric RS, Sheahan TP (2019) Broad spectrum antiviral remdesivir inhibits human endemic and zoonotic delta coronaviruses with a highly divergent RNA dependent RNA polymerase. Antiviral Res 169:104541. 10.1016/j.antiviral.2019.104541</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6699884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31233808</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bueno CA, Barquero AA, Di Cónsoli H, Maier MS, Alché LE (2009) A natural tetranortriterpenoid with immunomodulating properties as a potential anti-HSV agent. Virus Res 141(1):47–54. 10.1016/j.virusres.2008.12.013</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7114431</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19162100</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buya AB, Beloqui A, Memvanga PB, Préat V (2020) Self-nano-emulsifying drug-delivery systems: from the development to the current applications and challenges in oral drug delivery. Pharmaceutics 12(12):1194. 10.3390/pharmaceutics12121194</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7764143</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33317067</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caly L, Druce JD, Catton MG, Jans DA, Wagstaff KM (2020) The FDA-approved drug ivermectin inhibits the replication of SARS-CoV-2 in vitro. Antiviral Res 178:104787. 10.1016/j.antiviral.2020.104787</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7129059</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32251768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>CCRH (Central Council for Research in Homoeopathy) (2020) Homoeopathic perspectives in COVID-19 corona virus infection. https://www.ccrhindia.nic.in/showimg.aspx?ID=15677</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CDC (Centers for Disease Control and Prevention) (2003) Severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) and coronavirus testing in—US. 52, 297–302</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CDC (Centers for Disease Control and Prevention) (2012) First global estimates of 2009 H1N1 pandemic mortality released by CDC-led collaboration. https://www.cdc.gov/flu/spotlights/pandemic-global-estimates.htm</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chakraborty DP, Barman BK, Bose PK (1965) On the constitution of murrayanine, a carbazole derivative isolated from Murrayakoenigii Spreng. Tetrahedron 21(2):681–685. 10.1016/S0040-4020(01)82240-7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chandel V, Raj S, Rathi B, Kumar D (2020) In silico identification of potent COVID-19 main protease inhibitors from FDA approved antiviral compounds and active phytochemicals through molecular docking: a drug repurposing approach. Chem Biol Lett 7(3):166–175. 10.20944/preprints202003.0349.v1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chauhan N, Vasava P, Khan SL, Siddiqui FA, Islam F, Chopra H, Emran TB (2022) Ethosomes: a novel drug carrier. Ann Med Surg (Lond) 8(82):104595. 10.1016/j.amsu.2022.104595</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9482122</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36124209</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen JL, Blanc P, Stoddart CA, Bogan M, Rozhon EJ, Parkinson N, Ye Z, Cooper R, Balick M, Nanakorn W, Kernan MR (1998) New iridoids from the medicinal plant Barleria prionitis with potent activity against respiratory syncytial virus. J Nat Prod 61(10):1295–1297. 10.1021/np980086y</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9784173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choudhury S, Ahmed R, Kanjilal PB, Leclercq PA (1998) Composition of the seed oil of Trachyspermum ammi (L.) sprague from northeast India. J Essent Oil Res 10(5):588–590. 10.1080/10412905.1998.9700979</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chulet R, Pradhan P (2009) A review on Rasayana. Phcog Rev 3(6):229–234</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coronado LM, Nadovich CT, Spadafora C (2014) Malarial hemozoin: from target to tool. Biochim Biophys Acta 1840(6):2032–2041. 10.1016/j.bbagen.2014.02.009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4049529</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24556123</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dao TT, Nguyen PH, Lee HS, Kim E, Park J, Lim SI, Oh WK (2011) Chalcones as novel influenza A (H1N1) neuraminidase inhibitors from Glycyrrhiza inflata. Bioorg Med Chem Lett 21(1):294–298. 10.1016/j.bmcl.2010.11.016</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21123068</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>David P, Oates RK, Macfarlane J (2004) Iron in human nutrition: an overview. J Nutr 134(1):156–162</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dey D (2016) Role of secondary metabolites in plant defense. Innov Farm 1(4):115–118</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diao W-R, Hu Q-P, Zhang H, Xu J-G (2014) Chemical composition, antibacterial activity and mechanism of action of essential oil from seeds of fennel (Foeniculum vulgare Mill.). Food Control 35(1):109–116. 10.1016/j.foodcont.2013.06.056</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duan Z-P, Jia Z-H, Zhang J, Liu S, Chen Y, Liang LC, Zhang CQ, Zhang Z, Sun Y, Zhang SQ, Wang YY, Wu YL (2011) Natural herbal medicine Lianhuaqingwen capsule anti-influenza A (H1N1) trial: a randomized, double blind, positive controlled clinical trial. Chin Med J (Engl) 124(18):2925–2933. 10.3760/cma.j.issn.0366-6999.2011.18.024</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22040504</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ehrhardt C, Hrincius ER, Korte V, Mazur I, Droebner K, Poetter A, Dreschers S, Schmolke M, Planz O, Ludwig S (2007) A polyphenol rich plant extract, CYSTUS052, exerts anti influenza virus activity in cell culture without toxic side effects or the tendency to induce viral resistance. Antiviral Res 76(1):38–47. 10.1016/j.antiviral.2007.05.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17572513</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elfiky AA (2020) Ribavirin, remdesivir, sofosbuvir, galidesivir, and tenofovir against SARS-CoV-2 RNA dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp): a molecular docking study. Life Sci 253:117592. 10.1016/j.lfs.2020.117592</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7102646</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32222463</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Hoshoudy AN (2020) Investigating the potential antiviral activity drugs against SARS-CoV-2 by molecular docking simulation. J Mol Liq 318:113968. 10.1016/j.molliq.2020.113968</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7399655</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32839634</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Sheikh AA (2008) Renal transport and drug interactions of immunosuppressants (Thesis). Radbound University, Nijmegen, Netherlands</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Endres S, Ghorbani R, Kelley VE, Georgilis K, Lonnemann G, Meer M, Cannon JG, Rogers TS, Klempner MS, Webe P (1989) The effect of dietary supplementation with n − 3 polyunsaturated fatty acids on the synthesis of interleukin-1 and tumor necrosis factor by mononuclear cells. N Engl J Med 320(5):265–271. 10.1056/NEJM198902023200501</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2783477</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ESCOP (European Scientific Cooperative on Phytotherapy) (1996) Monographs on the medicinal uses of plant drugs</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan BE, Chong VCL, Chan SSW, Lim GH, Lim KGE, Tan GB, Mucheli SS, Kuperan P, Ong KH (2020). Hematologic parameters in patients with COVID-19 infection. Am J Hematol 95(6):E131–E134. 10.1002/ajh.25774. Epub 2020 Mar 19. Erratum in: Am J Hematol. 2020 Nov;95(11):1442. 10.1002/ajh.25921. PMID: 32129508</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32129508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fawzi WW, Mbise RL, Hertzmark E, Fataki MR, Herrera MG, Ndossi G, Spiegelman D (1999) A randomized trial of vitamin A supplements in relation to mortality among human immunodeficiency virus-infected and uninfected children in Tanzania. Pediatr Infect Dis J 18(2):127–133. 10.1097/00006454-199902000-00009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10048684</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fiore C, Eisenhut M, Krausse R, Ragazzi E, Pellati D, Armanini D, Bielenberg J (2008) Antiviral effects of Glycyrrhiza species. Phytother Res 22(2):141–148. 10.1002/ptr.2295</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7167979</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17886224</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Foster HD, Hoffer A (2007) Hyperoxidation of the two catecholamines, dopamine and adrenaline: implications for the etiologies and treatment of encephalitis lethargica, Parkinson’s disease, multiple sclerosis, amyotrophic lateral sclerosis, and schizophrenia. In: Oxidative stress and neurodegenerative disorders, pp 369–382. 10.1016/B978-044452809-4/50157-5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gadek JE, DeMichele SJ, Karlstad MD, Pacht ER, Donahoe M, Albertson TE, Hoozen CV, Wennberg AK, Nelson JL, Noursalehi M (1999) Effect of enteral feeding with eicosapentaenoic acid, gamma-linolenic acid, and antioxidants in patients with acute respiratory distress syndrome. Enteral Nutrition in ARDS Study Group. Crit Care Med 27(8):1409–1420. 10.1097/00003246-199908000-00001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10470743</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>García de Tena J, El Hachem DA, Hernández Gutiérrez C, Izquierdo Alonso JL (2014) The role of vitamin D in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, asthma and other respiratory diseases. Arch Bronconeumol 50(5):179–184. 10.1016/j.arbres.2013.11.023</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24447429</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glatthaar-Saalmüller B, Sacher F, Esperester A (2001) Antiviral activity of an extract derived from roots of Eleutherococcus senticosus. Antiviral Res 50(3):223–228. 10.1016/s0166-3542(01)00143-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11397509</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Göbel H, Schmidt G, Soyka D (1994) Effect of peppermint and eucalyptus oil preparations on neurophysiological and experimental algesimetric headache parameters. Cephalalgia 14(3):228–234. 10.1046/j.1468-2982.1994.014003228.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7954745</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goleniowski ME, Bongiovanni GA, Palacio L, Nunez CO, Cantero JJ (2006) Medicinal plants from the “Sierra de Comechingones.” Argentina J Ethnopharmacol 107(3):324–341. 10.1016/j.jep.2006.07.026</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16949228</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gorbalenya AE, Baker SC, Baric RS, Groot RJD, Drosten C, Gulyaeva AA, Haagmans BL, Lauber C, Leontovich AM, Neuman BW, Penzar D, Perlman S, Poon LLM, Samborskiy DV, Sidorov IA, Sola I, Ziebuhr J (2020) The species severe acute respiratory syndrome-related coronavirus: classifying 2019-nCoV and naming it SARS-CoV-2. Nat Microbiol 5(4):536–544. 10.1038/s41564-020-0695-z</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7095448</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32123347</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gordon AC, Mouncey PR, Al-Beidh F, Rowan KM, Nichol AD, Arabi YM, Djillali A, Beane A, Derde LPG (2021) Interleukin-6 receptor antagonists in critically ill patients with Covid-19. N Engl J Med 384(16):1491–1502. 10.1056/NEJMoa2100433</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7953461</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33631065</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grienke U, Schmidtke M, von Grafenstein S, Kirchmair J, Liedl KR, Rollinger JM (2012) Influenza neuraminidase: a druggable target for natural products. Nat Prod Rep 29(1):11–36. 10.1039/c1np00053e</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22025274</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo D (2020) Old weapon for new enemy: drug repurposing for treatment of newly emerging viral diseases. Virol Sin. 10.1007/s12250-020-00204-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7090748</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32048130</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta SC, Sung B, Kim JH, Prasad S, Li S, Aggarwal BB (2013) Multitargeting by turmeric, the golden spice: from kitchen to clinic. Mol Nutr Food Res 57(9):1510–1528. 10.1002/mnfr.201100741</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22887802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gurib-Fakim A (2006) Medicinal plants: traditions of yesterday and drugs of tomorrow. Mol Aspects Med 27(1):1–93. 10.1016/j.mam.2005.07.008</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16105678</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gurung AB, Ali MA, Lee J, Farah MA, Al-Anazi KM (2020) Unravelling lead antiviral phytochemicals for the inhibition of SARS-CoV-2 Mpro enzyme through in silico approach. Life Sci 255:117831. 10.1016/j.lfs.2020.117831</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7243810</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32450166</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gyana RR, Sahoo S (2015) Role of iron in plant growth and metabolism. Rev Agric Sci 3:1–24. 10.7831/ras.3.1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haidari M, Ali M, Ward Casscells S, Madjid M (2009) Pomegranate (Punica granatum) purified polyphenol extract inhibits influenza virus and has a synergistic effect with oseltamivir. Phytomedicine 16(12):1127–1136. 10.1016/j.phymed.2009.06.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19586764</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harborne JB, Baxter H (1993) Phytochemical dictionnary and handbook of bioactive compounds from plants. Taylor and Francis, London</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hartel C, Puzik A, Gopel W, Temming P, Bucsky P, Schultz C (2007) Immunomodulatory effect of vitamin C on intracytoplasmic cytokine production in neonatal cord blood cells. Neonatol 91(1):54–60. 10.1159/000096972</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17344653</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hartmann T (2007) From waste products to ecochemicals: fifty years research of plant secondary metabolism. Phytochemistry 68(22–24):2831–2846. 10.1016/j.phytochem.2007.09.017</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17980895</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hays JN (2005) Epidemics and pandemics: their impacts on human history. Bloomsbury Publishing USA</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hiller K (1987) New results on the structure and biological activity of triterpenoid saponins. In: Biologically active natural products, pp 167–184</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ho T-Y, Wu S-L, Chen J-C, Li CC, Hsiang CY (2007) Emodin blocks the SARS coronavirus spike protein and angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 interaction. Antiviral Res 74(2):92–101. 10.1016/j.antiviral.2006.04.014</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7114332</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16730806</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hokari R, Nagai T, Yamada H (2012) In vivo anti-influenza virus activity of Japanese herbal (kampo) medicine, “shahakusan”, and its possible mode of action. Evid Based Complement Alternat Med 2012:794970. 10.1155/2012/794970</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3545285</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23346216</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horby PW, Pessoa-Amorim G, Peto L, Brightling CE, Sarkar R, Thomas K, Jeebun V, Ashish A, Tully R, Chadwick D, Sharafat M (2021) Tocilizumab in patients admitted to hospital with COVID-19 (RECOVERY): a randomised, controlled, open-label, platform trial. Lancet 397(10285):1637–1645. 10.1016/S0140-6736(21)00676-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8084355</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33933206</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsieh L-E, Lin C-N, Su B-L, Jan TR, Chen CM, Wang CH, Lin DS, Lin CT, Chueh LL (2010) Synergistic antiviral effect of Galanthus nivalis agglutinin and nelfinavir against feline coronavirus. Antiviral Res 88(1):25–30. 10.1016/j.antiviral.2010.06.010</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7114315</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20603153</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hudson J, Vimalanathan S (2011) Echinacea—a source of potent antivirals for respiratory virus infections. Pharmaceut 4(7):1019–1031. 10.3390/ph4071019</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hussain A, Kausar T, Sehar S, Sarwar A, Quddoos MY, Aslam J, Liaqat A, Siddique T, An QU, Kauser S, Rehman A (2023) A review on biochemical constituents of pumpkin and their role as pharma foods; a key strategy to improve health in post COVID 19 period. Food Prod Process and Nutr 5(1):22. 10.1186/s43014-023-00138-z</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iskandar MM, Lands LC, Sabally K, Azadi B, Meehan B, Mawji N, Skinner CD, Kubow S (2015) High hydrostatic pressure pretreatment of whey protein isolates improves their digestibility and antioxidant capacity. Foods 4(2):184–207. 10.3390/foods4020184</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5302329</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28231198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Islam MA, Haque MA, Rahman MA, Hossen F, Reza M, Barua A, Marzan AA, Das T, Kumar Baral S, He C, Ahmed F (2022) A review on measures to rejuvenate immune system: natural mode of protection against coronavirus infection. Front Immunol 13:837290. 10.3389/fimmu.2022.837290</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8965011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35371007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jilani TN, Jamil RT, Nguyen AD, Siddiqui AH (2024) H1N1 influenza. In: StatPearls Publishing, Treasure Island (FL)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30020613</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>John KMM, Ayyanar M, Jeeva S, Suresh M, Enkhtaivan G (2014) Kim DH (2014) Metabolic variations, antioxidant potential, and antiviral activity of different extracts of Eugenia singampattiana (an endangered medicinal plant used by Kani tribals, Tamil Nadu, India) leaf. Biomed Res Int 1:726145. 10.1155/2014/726145</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4123486</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25133179</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaïj-a-Kamb M, Amoros M, Girre L (1992) Search for new antiviral agents of plant origin. Pharm Acta Helv 67(5–6):130–147</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1438451</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kala CP, Dhyani PP, Sajwan BS (2006) Developing the medicinal plants sector in northern India: challenges and opportunities. J Ethnobiol Ethnomed 2:1–5. 10.1186/1746-4269-2-32</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalus U, Grigorov A, Kadecki O, Jansen JP, Kiesewetter H, Radtke H (2009) Cistus incanus (CYSTUS052) for treating patients with infection of the upper respiratory tract. A prospective, randomised, placebo-controlled clinical study. Antiviral Res 84(3):267–271. 10.1016/j.antiviral.2009.10.001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19828122</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaminogawa S, Nanno M (2004) Modulation of immune functions by foods. Evid Based Complement Alternat Med 1(3):241–250. 10.1093/ecam/neh042</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC538513</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15841257</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kan A, Özçelik B, Kartal M (2009) In vitro antiviral activities under cytotoxic doses against herpes simples type-1 and parainfluensa-3 viruses of Cicer arietinum L. (Chickpea). Afr J Pharm Pharmacol 3(12):627–631</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karagöz A, Arda N, Gören N, Nagata K, Kuru A (1999) Antiviral activity of Sanicula europaea L. extracts on multiplication of human parainfluenza virus type 2. Phytother Res 13(5):436–438. 10.1002/(sici)1099-1573(199908/09)13:5%3c436::aid-ptr459%3e3.0.co;2-q</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10441789</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kernan MR, Sendl A, Chen JL, Jolad SD, Blanc P, Murphy JT, Stoddart CA, Nanakorn W, Balick MJ, Rozhon EJ (1997) Two new lignans with activity against influenza virus from the medicinal plant Rhinacanthus nasutus. J Nat Prod 60(6):635–637. 10.1021/np960613i</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9214738</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kernan MR, Amarquaye A, Chen JL, Chan J, Sesin DF, Parkinson N, Ye ZJ, Barrett M, Bales C, Stoddart CA, Sloan B (1998) Antiviral phenylpropanoid glycosides from the medicinal plant Markhamia lutea. J Nat Prod 61(5):564–570. 10.1021/np9703914</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9599250</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khaerunnisa S, Kurniawan H, Awaluddin R, Suhartati S, Soetjipto S (2020) Potential inhibitor of COVID-19 main protease (Mpro) from several medicinal plant compounds by molecular docking study. Preprints 2020:2020030226. 10.20944/preprints202003.0226.v1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim BK, Cho AR, Park DJ (2016) Enhancing oral bioavailability using preparations of apigenin-loaded W/O/W emulsions: in vitro and in vivo evaluations. Food Chem 206(1):85–91. 10.1016/j.foodchem.2016.03.052</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27041302</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kitazato K, Wang Y, Kobayashi N (2007) Viral infectious disease and natural products with antiviral activity. Drug Discov Ther 1(1):14–22</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22504360</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kiyohara H, Ichino C, Kawamura Y, Nagai T, Sato N, Yamada H (2012a) Patchouli alcohol: in vitro direct anti-influenza virus sesquiterpene in Pogostemon cablin Benth. J Nat Med 66(1):55–61. 10.1007/s11418-011-0550-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21671149</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kiyohara H, Ichino C, Kawamura Y, Nagai T, Sato N, Yamada H, Salama MM, Abdel-Sattar E (2012b) In vitro anti-influenza virus activity of a cardiotonic glycoside from Adenium obesum (Forssk.). Phytomedicine 19(2):111–114. 10.1016/j.phymed.2011.07.004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21899996</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koch A, Sandor G (1969) Heart glycosides in poliovirus host cell interaction III. Chem Struct Activity Acta Microbiol 16:245–251</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4314335</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar S, Andy A (2012) Health promoting bioactive phytochemicals from Brassica. Int Food Res J 19(1):141</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kupferschmidt K, Cohen J (2020) Will novel virus go pandemic or be contained? Science 367(6478):610–611. 10.1126/science.367.6478.610</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32029604</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuru P (2014) Tamarindus indica and its health-related effects. Asian Pac J Trop Biomed 4(9):676–681. 10.12980/APJTB.4.2014APJTB-2014-0173</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Łagocka R, Dziedziejko V, Kłos P, Pawlik A (2021) Favipiravir in therapy of viral infections. J Clin Med 10(2):273. 10.3390/jcm10020273</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7828521</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33451007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lancet CR (1994) Pharmaceuticals from plants: great potential, few funds. Lancet 343:1513–1515</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7911864</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lattanzio V, Lattanzio VMT, Cardinali A (2006) Role of phenolics in the resistance mechanisms of plants against fungal pathogens and insects. In: Imperato F (ed) Phytochem adv res Research Signpost, vol 37, pp 23–67</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lattanzio V (2003) Advances in phytochemistry. Imperato, F. (ed)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lau KM, Lee KM, Koon CM, Cheung CS, Lau CP, Ho HM, Lee MY, Au SW, Cheng CH, Lau CB, Tsui SK, Wan DC, Waye MM, Wong KB, Wong CK, Lam CW, Leung PC, Fung KP (2008) Immunomodulatory and anti-SARS activities of Houttuynia cordata. J Ethnopharmacol 118(1):79–85. 10.1016/j.jep.2008.03.018</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7126383</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18479853</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee J-B, Miyake S, Umetsu R, Hayashi K, Chijimatsu T, Hayashi T (2012) Anti-influenza a virus effects of fructan from Welsh onion (Allium fistulosum L.). Food Chem 134(4):2164–2168. 10.1016/j.foodchem.2012.04.016</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7173106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23442670</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee N-K, Lee J-H, Lim S-M, Lee KA, Kim YB, Chang PS, Paik HD (2014) Short communication: antiviral activity of subcritical water extract of Brassica junceaagainst influenza virus A/H1N1 in nonfat milk. J Dairy Sci 97(9):5383–5386. 10.3168/jds.2014-8016</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25022686</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li YL, Ma SC, Yang YT, Ye SM, But PP (2002) Antiviral activities of flavonoids and organic acid from Trollius chinensis Bunge. J Ethnopharmacol 79(3):365–368. 10.1016/s0378-8741(01)00410-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11849843</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Ooi LSM, Wang H, But PP, Ooi VE (2004) Antiviral activities of medicinal herbs traditionally used in southern mainland China. Phytother Res 18(9):718–722. 10.1002/ptr.1518</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15478204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li S-Y, Chen C, Zhang H-Q, Guo HY, Wang H, Wang L, Zhang X, Hua SN, Yu J, Xiao PG, Li RS (2005a) Identification of natural compounds with antiviral activities against SARS-associated coronavirus. Antiviral Res 67(1):18–23. 10.1016/j.antiviral.2005.02.007</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7114104</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15885816</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, But PP, Ooi VE (2005b) Antiviral activity and mode of action of caffeoylquinic acids from Schefflera heptaphylla (L.) Frodin. Antiviral Res 68(1):1–9. 10.1016/j.antiviral.2005.06.004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16140400</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li J-Y, You Z, Wang Q, Zhou ZJ, Qiu Y, Luo R, Ge XY (2020) The epidemic of 2019-novel-coronavirus (2019-nCoV) pneumonia and insights for emerging infectious diseases in the future. Microbes Infect 22(2):80–85. 10.1016/j.micinf.2020.02.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7079563</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32087334</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin YM, Flavin MT, Schure R, Chen FC, Sidwell R, Barnard DI, Huffmann JH, Kern ER (1999) Antiviral activities of biflavonoids. Planta Med 65(02):120–125. 10.1055/s-1999-13971</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10193201</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin CW, Tsai FJ, Tsai CH, Lai CC, Wan L, Ho TY, Hsieh CC, Chao PD (2005) Anti-SARS coronavirus 3C-like protease effects of Isatis indigotica root and plant-derived phenolic compounds. Antiviral Res 68(1):36–42. 10.1016/j.antiviral.2005.07.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7114321</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16115693</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lisa Aston Philander (2011) An ethnobotany of Western Cape Rasta bush medicine. J Ethnopharmacol 138(2):578–594. 10.1016/j.jep.2011.10.004</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22004893</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu A-L, Liu B, Qin H-L, Lee SM, Wang YT, Du GH (2008) Anti-influenza virus activities of flavonoids from the medicinal plant Elsholtzia rugulosa. Planta Med 74(08):847–851. 10.1055/s-2008-1074558</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18553272</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Local Government Board (1893) Further report and papers on epidemic influenza, 1889–92: with an introduction by the medical officer of the Local Government Board. https://ia802600.us.archive.org/14/items/b21459393/b21459393.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma SC, But PP, Ooi VE, He YH, Lee SH, Lee SF, Lin RC (2001) Antiviral amentoflavone from Selaginella sinensis. Biol Pharm Bull 24(3):311–312. 10.1248/bpb.24.311</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11256492</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mager S, Sloan J (2003) Possible role of amino acids, peptides, and sugar transporter in protein removal and innate lung defense. Eur J Pharmacol 479(1–3):263–267. 10.1016/j.ejphar.2003.08.075</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14612156</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maheshwari ML, Singh BM, Gupta R, Chien M (1987) Essential oil of sacred basil (Ocimum sanctum). Indian Perfumer 31:137–145</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manske RF, Brossi A (1987) The alkaloids 15. Academic Press, London, pp 83–164</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCutcheon AR, Roberts TE, Gibbons E, Ellis SM, Babiuk LA, Hancock RE, Towers GH (1995) Antiviral screening of British Columbian medicinal plants. J Ethnopharmacol 49(2):101–110. 10.1016/0378-8741(95)90037-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7131204</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8847882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McMichael AJ (2004) Environmental and social influences on emerging infectious diseases: past, present and future. Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci 359(1447):1049–1058. 10.1098/rstb.2004.1480</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1693387</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15306389</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mifsud EJ, Hayden FG, Hurt AC (2019) Antivirals targeting the polymerase complex of influenza viruses. Antiviral Res 169:104545. 10.1016/j.antiviral.2019.104545</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31247246</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of AYUSH (Ayurvedic, Yoga and Naturopathy, Unani, Siddha and Homeopathy) (2020) Ayurveda’s immunity boosting measures for self-care during COVID 19 crisis. https://www.mohfw.gov.in/pdf/ImmunityBoostingAYUSHAdvisory.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mochida K (2008) Anti-influenza virus activity of Myrica rubra leaf ethanol extract evaluated using Madino-Darby canine kidney (MDCK) cells. Biosci Biotechnol Biochem 72(11):3018–3020. 10.1271/bbb.80330</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18997411</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohammadi N, Shaghaghi N (2020) Inhibitory effect of eight secondary metabolites from conventional medicinal plants on COVID_19 virus protease by molecular docking analysis. 10.26434/chemrxiv.11987475</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mølgaard P, Ravn H (1988) Evolutionary aspects of caffeoyl ester distribution in dicotyledons. Phytochemistry 27(8):2411–2421. 10.1016/0031-9422(88)87005-5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moradi M-T, Karimi A, Fotouhi F, Soleiman K, Ali T (2017) In vitro and in vivo effects of Peganum harmala L. seeds extract against influenza A virus. Avicenna J Phytomed 7(6):519–530</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5745536</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29299435</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morse JS, Lalonde T, Xu S, Liu WR (2020) Learning from the past: possible urgent prevention and treatment options for severe acute respiratory infections caused by 2019-nCoV. ChemBioChem 21(5):730–738. 10.1002/cbic.202000047</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7162020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32022370</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mouhid L, Corzo-Martínez M, Torres C, Vázquez L, Reglero G, Fornari T, Ramírez de Molina A (2017) Improving in vivo efficacy of bioactive molecules: an overview of potentially antitumor phytochemicals and currently available lipid-based delivery systems. J Oncol 2017:7351976. 10.1155/2017/7351976</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5438845</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28555156</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nagai T, Suzuki Y, Tomimori T, Yamada H (1995) Antiviral activity of plant flavonoid, 5,7,4′-trihydroxy-8-methoxyflavone, from the roots of Scutellaria baicalensis against influenza A (H3N2) and B viruses. Biol Pharm Bull 18(2):295–299. 10.1248/bpb.18.295</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7742801</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>NCT04252885 (2020) The efficacy of Lopinavir plus Ritonavir and Arbidol against novel corona virus infection (ELACOI). https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT04252885</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nesari T, Kadam S, Vyas M, Huddar VG, Prajapati PK, Rajagopala M, More A, Rajagopala SK, Bhatted SK, Yadav RK, Mahanta V, Mandal SK, Mahto RR, Kajaria D, Sherkhane R, Bavalatti N, Kundal P, Dharmarajan P, Bhojani M, Bhide B, Harti SK, Mahapatra AK, Tagade U, Ruknuddin G, Venkatramana Sharma AP, Rai S, Ghildiyal S, Yadav PR, Sandrepogu J, Deogade M, Pathak P, Kapoor A, Kumar A, Saini H, Tripathi R (2022) AYURAKSHA, a prophylactic Ayurvedic immunity boosting kit reducing positivity percentage of IgG COVID-19 among frontline Indian Delhi police personnel: a non-randomized controlled intervention trial. Front Public Health 10:920126. 10.3389/fpubh.2022.920126</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9424736</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36052011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nicholson LB (2016) The immune system. Essays Biochem 60(3):275–301. 10.1042/EBC20160017</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5091071</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27784777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noor S, Piscopo S, Gasmi A (2021) Nutrients interaction with the immune system. Arch Razi Inst 76(6):1579–1588. 10.22092/ari.2021.356098.1775</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9083862</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35546980</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O’Leary MJ, Coakley JH (1996) Nutrition and immunonutrition. Br J Anaesth 77(1):118–127. 10.1093/bja/77.1.118</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8703621</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ooi LSM, Sun SSM, Ooi VEC (2004) Purification and characterization of a new antiviral protein from the leaves of Pandanus amaryllifolius (Pandanaceae). Int J Biochem Cell Biol 36(8):1440–1446. 10.1016/j.biocel.2004.01.015</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15147723</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ooi LSM, Ho W-S, Ngai KLK, Tian L, Chan PK, Sun SS, Ooi VE (2010) Narcissus tazetta lectin shows strong inhibitory effects against respiratory syncytial virus, influenza A (H1N1, H3N2, H5N1) and B viruses. J Biosci 35(1):95–103. 10.1007/s12038-010-0012-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7091448</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20413914</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Packman EW, London SJ (1980) The utility of artificially induced cough as a clinical model for evaluating the antitussive effects of aromatics delivered by inunction. Eur J Respir Dis Suppl 110:101–109</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6938377</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paranagama PA, Wimalasena S, Jayatilake GS, Jayawardena AL, Senanayake UM, Mubarak AM (2001) A comparison of essential oil constituents of bark, leaf, root and fruit of cinnamon (Cinnamomum zeylanicum Blum) grown in Sri Lanka. J Natn Sci Found Sri Lanka 29(3–4):147. 10.4038/jnsfsr.v29i3-4.2613</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parimala Devi B, Manoharan K (2009) Anti viral medicinal plants: an ethnobotanical approach. J Phytol 1(6). https://updatepublishing.com/journal/index.php/jp/article/view/2053</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patil US, Jaydeokar AV, Bandawane DD (2012) Immunomodulators: a pharmacological review. Int J Pharm Sci 4(1):30–36</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patterson KD, Pyle GF (1991) The geography and mortality of the 1918 influenza pandemic. Bull Hist Med 65(1):4–21</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2021692</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pilcher KS, Soike KF, Smith VH, Trosper F, Folston B (1955) Inhibition of multiplication of Lee influenza virus by canavanine. Proc Soc Exp Biol Med 88(1):79–86. 10.3181/00379727-88-21498</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14357349</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Platonova EY, Shaposhnikov MV, Lee HY, Lee JH, Min KJ, Moskalev A (2021) Black chokeberry (Aronia melanocarpa) extracts in terms of geroprotector criteria. Trends Food Sci Technol 114:570–584. 10.1016/j.tifs.2021.06.020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pleschka S, Stein M, Schoop R, Hudson JB (2009) Anti-viral properties and mode of action of standardized Echinacea purpurea extract against highly pathogenic avian influenza virus (H5N1, H7N7) and swine-origin H1N1 (S-OIV). Virol J 6:197. 10.1186/1743-422X-6-197</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2785784</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19912623</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Porter CJ, Charman WN (2001) In vitro assessment of oral lipid-based formulations. Adv Drug Deliv Rev 50:S127-147. 10.1016/s0169-409x(01)00182-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11576699</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prasad S, Aggarwal BB (2011) Turmeric, the golden spice: from traditional medicine to modern medicine. In: Benzie IFF, Wachtel-Galor S (eds) Herbal medicine: biomolecular and clinical aspects, 2nd ed. CRC Press/Taylor &amp; Francis, Boca Raton</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22593922</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pryor EG (1975) The great plague of Hong Kong. J Hong Kong Branch R Asiat Soc 1975:61–70</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11614750</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qian J, Meng H, Xin L, Xia M, Shen H, Li G, Xie Y (2017) Self-nanoemulsifying drug delivery systems of myricetin: formulation development, characterization, and in vitro and in vivo evaluation. Colloids Surf B Biointerfaces 160:101–109. 10.1016/j.colsurfb.2017.09.020</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28917148</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rajbhandari M, Wegner U, Jülich M, Schoepke T, Mentel R (2001) Screening of Nepalese medicinal plants for antiviral activity. J Ethnopharmacol 74(3):251–255. 10.1016/s0378-8741(00)00374-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11274826</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rajbhandari M, Mentel R, Jha PK, Chaudhary RP, Bhattarai S, Gewali MB, Karmacharya N, Hipper M, Lindequist U (2007) Antiviral activity of some plants used in Nepalese traditional medicine. Evid Based Complement Alternat Med 6:517–522. 10.1093/ecam/nem156</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2781767</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18955262</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramos-Martínez E, López-Vancell MR, Fernández de Córdova-Aguirre JC, Rojas-Serrano J, Chavarría A, Velasco-Medina A, Velázquez-Sámano G (2018) Reduction of respiratory infections in asthma patients supplemented with vitamin D is related to increased serum IL-10 and IFNγ levels and cathelicidin expression. Cytokine 108:239–246. 10.1016/j.cyto.2018.01.001</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29402723</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richardson P, Griffin I, Tucker C, Smith D, Oechsle O, Phelan A, Rawling M, Savory E, Stebbing J (2020) Baricitinib as potential treatment for 2019-nCoV acute respiratory disease. Lancet 395(10223):e30–e31. 10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30304-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7137985</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32032529</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rossignol J-F (2014) Nitazoxanide: a first-in-class broad-spectrum antiviral agent. Antiviral Res 110:94–103. 10.1016/j.antiviral.2014.07.014</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7113776</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25108173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruuskanen O, Ogra PL (1993) Respiratory syncytial virus. Curr Probl Pediatr 23(2):50–79. 10.1016/0045-9380(93)90003-u.PMID:7681743;PMCID:PMC7131133</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7131133</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7681743</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryu YB, Jeong HJ, Kim JH, Kim YM, Park JY, Kim D, Naguyen TT, Park SJ, Chang JS, Park KH, Rho MC (2010a) Biflavonoids from Torreya nucifera displaying SARS-CoV 3CL(pro) inhibition. Bioorg Med Chem 18(22):7940–7947. 10.1016/j.bmc.2010.09.035</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7126309</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20934345</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryu YB, Park S-J, Kim YM, Lee JY, Seo WD, Chang JS, Park KH, Rho MC, Lee WS (2010b) SARS-CoV 3CL pro inhibitory effects of quinone-methide triterpenes from Tripterygium regelii. Bioorg Med Chem Lett 20(6):1873–1876. 10.1016/j.bmcl.2010.01.152</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7127101</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20167482</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadlon AE, Lamson DW (2010) Immune-modifying and antimicrobial effects of Eucalyptus oil and simple inhalation devices. Altern Med Rev 15(1):33–47</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20359267</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salomon R, Webster RG (2009) The influenza virus enigma. Cell 136(3):402–410. 10.1016/j.cell.2009.01.029</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2971533</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19203576</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Savo V, Giulia C, Maria GP, David R (2011) Folk phytotherapy of the Amalfi Coast (Campania, Southern Italy). J Ethnopharmacol 135(2):376–392. 10.1016/j.jep.2011.03.027</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21419835</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sawai R, Kuroda K, Shibata T, Gomyou R, Osawa K, Shimizu K (2008) Anti-influenza virus activity of Chaenomeles sinensis. J Ethnopharmacol 118(1):108–112. 10.1016/j.jep.2008.03.013</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18456441</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sazawal S, Black RE, Jalla S et al (1998) Zinc supplementation reduces the incidence of acute lower respiratory infections in infants and preschool children: a double-blind, controlled trial. Pediatrics 102(1):1–5. 10.1542/peds.102.1.1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9651405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Selby-Pham SNB, Miller RB, Howell K, Dunshea F, Bennett LE (2017) Physicochemical properties of dietary phytochemicals can predict their passive absorption in the human small intestine. Sci Rep 7(1):1931. 10.1038/s41598-017-01888-w</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5434065</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28512322</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Serkedjieva J (1996) A polyphenolic extract from Geranium sanguineum L. inhibits influenza virus protein expression. Phytother Res 10(5):441–443. 10.1002/(SICI)1099-1573(199608)10:5%3c441::AID-PTR867%3e3.0.CO;2-9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Serkedjieva J, Manolova N, Zgórniak-Nowosielska I, Zawilińska B, Grzybek J (1990) Antiviral activity of the infusion (SHS-174) from flowers of Sambucus nigra L., aerial parts of Hypericum perforatum L., and roots of Saponaria officinalis L. against influenza and herpes simplex viruses. Phytother Res 4(3):97–100. 10.1002/ptr.2650040305</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah B, Modi P, Sagar SR (2020) In silico studies on therapeutic agents for COVID-19: drug repurposing approach. Life Sci 252:117652. 10.1016/j.lfs.2020.117652</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7194845</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32278693</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shakoor H, Feehan J, Al Dhaheri AS, Ali HI, Platat C, Ismail LC, Apostolopoulos V, Stojanovska L (2020) Immune-boosting role of vitamins D, C, E, zinc, selenium and omega-3 fatty acids: Could they help against COVID-19? Maturitas 143:1–9. 10.1016/j.maturitas.2020.08.003</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7415215</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33308613</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma P, Kumar P, Sharma R, Gupta G, Chaudhary A (2017) Immunomodulators: role of medicinal plants in immune system. Natl J Physiol Pharm Pharmacol 7(6):552</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharp PM, Hahn BH (2011) Origins of HIV and the AIDS pandemic. Cold Spring Harb Perspect Med 1(1):a006841. 10.1101/cshperspect.a006841</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3234451</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22229120</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shin WJ, Lee KH, Park MH, Seong BL (2010) Broad-spectrum antiviral effect of Agrimonia pilosa extract on influenza viruses. Microbiol Immunol 54(1):11–19. 10.1111/j.1348-0421.2009.00173.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20055938</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siddiqui SA, Azmy Harahap I, Suthar P, Wu YS, Ghosh N, Castro-Muñoz R (2023) A comprehensive review of phytonutrients as a dietary therapy for obesity. Foods 12(19):3610. 10.3390/foods12193610</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10572887</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37835263</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh S, Agrawal SS (1991) Anti-asthmatic and anti-inflammatory activity of Ocimum sanctum. Int J Pharmacogn 29:306–310. 10.3109/13880209109082904</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh S, Majumdar DK, Yadav MR (1996) Chemical and pharmacological studies on fixed oil of Ocimum sanctum. Indian J Exp Biol 34(12):1212–1215</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9246913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Skwarek T (1979) Effects of herbal preparations on the propagation of influenza viruses. Acta Pol Pharm 36(5):1–7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">549452</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sokmen M, Angelova M, Krumova E, Pashova S, Ivancheva S, Sokmen A, Serkedjieva J (2005) In vitro antioxidant activity of polyphenol extracts with antiviral properties from Geranium sanguineum L. Life Sci 76(25):2981–2993. 10.1016/j.lfs.2004.11.020</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15820508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song J-M, Lee K-H, Seong B-L (2005) Antiviral effect of catechins in green tea on influenza virus. Antiviral Res 68(2):66–74. 10.1016/j.antiviral.2005.06.010</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16137775</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spreeuwenberg P, Kroneman M, Paget J (2018) Reassessing the global mortality burden of the 1918 influenza pandemic. Am J Epidemiol 187(12):2561–2567. 10.1093/aje/kwy191</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7314216</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30202996</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sriwilaijaroen N, Fukumoto S, Kumagai K, Hiramatsu H, Odagiri T, Tashiro M, Suzuki Y (2012) Antiviral effects of Psidium guajava Linn. (guava) tea on the growth of clinical isolated H1N1 viruses: its role in viral hemagglutination and neuraminidase inhibition. Antivir Res 94(2):139–146. 10.1016/j.antiviral.2012.02.013</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22453134</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stenseth NC (2008) Infectious diseases: plague through history, vol 321, pp 773–774. https://science.sciencemag.org/content/321/5890/773.full</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stephensen CB, Zunino SJ (2011) Nutrition and the immune system. In: Ross AC, Caballero B, Cousins RJ, Tucker KL (eds) Modern nutrition in health and disease, 11th edn. Wolters Kluwer Health, Philadelphia, pp 601–610</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Subramani SK, Gupta Y, Manish M, Prasad G (2020) Gymnema sylvestre a—potential inhibitor of COVID-19 main protease by MD simulation study. 10.26434/chemrxiv.12333251.v1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sumner J, Plotkin MJ (2000) The natural history of medicinal plants. Timber Press, Oxford, p 16</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sydiskis RJ, Owen DG, Lohr JL, Rosler KH, Blomster RN (1991) Inactivation of enveloped viruses by anthraquinones extracted from plants. Antimicrob Agents Chemother 35(12):2463–2466. 10.1128/AAC.35.12.2463</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC245413</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1810179</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tachibana Y, Kikuzaki H, Lajis NH, Nakatani N (2001) Antioxidative activity of carbazoles from Murrayakoenigii leaves. J Agric Food Chem 49(11):5589–5594. 10.1021/jf010621r</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11714364</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tian C, Asghar S, Wu Y, KambereAmerigos D, Chen Z, Zhang M (2017) N-acetyl-l-cysteine functionalized nanostructured lipid carrier for improving oral bioavailability of curcumin: preparation, in vitro and in vivo evaluations. Drug Deliv 24(1):1605–1616. 10.1080/10717544.2017.1391890</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8241171</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29063815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Umakanth K, Geetha RV, Smiline Girija AS, Lakshmi T (2020) Role of commonly used asian spices in boosting immunity against infectious agents. Eur J Mol Clin Med 7(1):452–458</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNAIDS (Joint United Nations Programme on HIV/AIDS) (2019) Global HIV and AIDS statistics-2019 fact sheet. https://www.unaids.org/en/resources/fact-sheet</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valcheva-Kuzmanova SV, Belcheva A (2006) Current knowledge of Aronia melanocarpa as a medicinal plant. Folia Med (Plovdiv) 48:11–17</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17408071</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vimalanathan S, Kang L, Amiguet VT, Livesey J, Arnason JT, Hudson J (2005) Echinacea purpurea. Aerial parts contain multiple antiviral compounds. Pharm Biol 43(9):740–745. 10.1080/13880200500406354</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vincent S, Arokiyaraj S, Saravanan M, Dhanraj M (2020) Molecular docking studies on the anti-viral effects of compounds from kabasura kudineer on SARS-CoV-2 3CLpro. Front Mol Biosci 7:613401. 10.3389/fmolb.2020.613401</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7785853</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33425994</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wachtel-Galor S (2011) Turmeric, the golden spice: from traditional medicine to modern medicine. Herbal medicine. CRC Press, Boca Raton, pp 285–310</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22593922</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang X, Li W, Li N, Li J (2008) Omega-3 fatty acids-supplemented parenteral nutrition decreases hyperinflammatory response and attenuates systemic disease sequelae in severe acute pancreatitis: a randomized and controlled study. J Parenter Enteral Nutr 32(2):236–241. 10.1177/0148607108316189</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18443134</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Warren TK, Wells J, Panchal RG, Stuthman KS, Garza NL, Van Tongeren SA, Dong L, Retterer CJ, Eaton BP, Pegoraro G, Honnold S, Bantia S, Kotian P, Chen X, Taubenheim BR, Welch LS, Minning DM, Babu YS, Sheridan WP, Bavari S (2014) Protection against filovirus diseases by a novel broad-spectrum nucleoside analogue BCX4430. Nature 508(7496):402–405. 10.1038/nature13027</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7095208</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24590073</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weber ND, Andersen DO, North JA, Murray BK, Lawson LD, Hughes BG (1992) In vitro virucidal effects of Allium sativum (garlic) extract and compounds. Planta Med 58(5):417–423. 10.1055/s-2006-961504</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1470664</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wen CC, Kuo YH, Jan JT, Liang PH, Wang SY, Liu HG, Lee CK, Chang ST, Kuo CJ, Lee SS, Hou CC, Hsiao PW, Chien SC, Shyur LF, Yang NS (2007) Specific plant terpenoids and lignoids possess potent antiviral activities against severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus. J Med Chem 50(17):4087–4095. 10.1021/jm070295s</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17663539</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO (World Health Organization) (2002) Monographs on selected medicinal plants. WHO, Geneva, p 2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO (World Health Organization) (2003) Summary of probable SARS cases with onset of illness from 1 November 2002 to 31 July 2003. https://www.who.int/csr/sars/country/table2004_04_21/en/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO (World Health Organization) (2019) Middle east respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV). https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/middle-east-respiratory-syndrome-coronavirus-(mers-cov)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO (World Health Organization) (2020) Middle east respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV)—The Kingdom of Saudi Arabia. https://www.who.int/csr/don/08-april-2020-mers-saudi-arabia/en/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO (World Health Organization) (2021) Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) pandemic. Accessed on May 29, 2021. https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus.2019?gclid=EAIaIQobChMInoXEvpnx8AIVmg4rCh0j0AAdEAAYASAAEgJqlfD_Bw</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wirotesangthong M, Nagai T, Yamada H, Amnuoypol S, Mungmee C (2009) Effects of Clinacanthus siamensis leaf extract on influenza virus infection. Microbiol Immunol 53(2):66–74. 10.1111/j.1348-0421.2008.00095.x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19291089</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WNF (World Naturopathic Federation) (2020) Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-2019). http://worldnaturopathicfederation.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/WNF_COVID_Feb15.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Won JN, Lee SY, Song DS, Poo H (2013) Antiviral activity of the plant extracts from thuja orientalis, aster spathulifolius, and pinus Thunbergii against influenza virus A/PR/8/34. J MicrobiolBiotechn 23(1):125–130. 10.4014/jmb.1210.10074</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23314378</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wutzler P, Kossow KD, Lode H, Ruf BR, Scholz H, Vogel GE (2004) Expert Group, German Association for the Control of Virus Diseases and Paul-Ehrlich Society of Germany. Antiviral treatment and prophylaxis of influenza in primary care: German recommendations. J Clin Virol 31(2):84–91. 10.1016/j.jcv.2004.05.009</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15364262</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamazaki Z, Tagaya I (1980) Antiviral effects of atropine and caffeine. J Gen Virol 50(2):429–431. 10.1099/0022-1317-50-2-429</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6257827</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yimer EM, Tuem KB, Karim A, Ur-Rehman N, Anwar F (2019) Nigella sativa L. (Black Cumin): a promising natural remedy for wide range of illnesses. Evid Based Complement Altern Med. 10.1155/2019/1528635</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6535880</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31214267</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yingsakmongkon S, Miyamoto D, Sriwilaijaroen N, Fujita K, Matsumoto K, Jampangem W, Hiramatsu H, Guo CT, Sawada T, Takahashi T, Hidari K, Suzuli T, Ito Y, Suzuki Y (2008) In vitro inhibition of human influenza A virus infection by fruit-juice concentrate of Japanese plum (Prunus mume SIEB. et ZUCC). Biol Pharm Bull 31(3):511–515. 10.1248/bpb.31.511</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18310920</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yishan Lu, Ao D, He X (2024) The rising SARS-CoV-2 JN.1 variant: evolution, infectivity, immune escape, and response strategies. MedComm 5(8):e675</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11286544</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39081516</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang H, Yang X, Zhao L, Jiao Y, Liu J, Zhai G (2016) In vitro and in vivo study of Baicalin-loaded mixed micelles for oral delivery. Drug Deliv 23(6):1933–1939. 10.3109/10717544.2015.1008705</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25693642</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhong J, Cui X, Shi Y, Gao Y, Cao H (2013) Antiviral activity of Jinchai capsule against influenza virus. J Tradit Chin Med 33(2):200–204. 10.1016/S0254-6272(13)60125-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7147227</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23789217</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>