<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39558305</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1471-2458</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>24</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>18</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC public health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Public Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Application of artificial intelligence in triage in emergencies and disasters: a systematic review.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>3203</StartPage><MedlinePgn>3203</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12889-024-20447-3</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION AND OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">Modern and intelligent triage systems are used today due to the growing trend of disasters and emergencies worldwide and the increase in the number of injured people facing the challenge of using traditional triage methods. The main objective of this study is to investigate the application of artificial intelligence and Technology in the triage of patients injured by disasters and emergencies and the challenges of the implementation of intelligent triage systems.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHOD" NlmCategory="METHODS">The present study is a systematic review and follows PRISMA guidelines. The protocol of this study was registered in PROSPERO with the code CRD42023471415. To find relevant studies, the databases PubMed, Scopus and Web of Science (ISI) were searched without a time limit until September 2024. The scientific search engine Google Scholar and the references of the final articles were read manually for the final review.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The search identified 2,630 articles, narrowing down to 19 high-quality studies on AI in triage, which improved patient care through optimized resource management and real-time data transmission. AI algorithms like OpenPose and YOLO enhanced efficiency in mass casualty incidents, while e-triage systems allowed for continuous vital sign monitoring and faster triaging. AI tools demonstrated high accuracy in diagnosing COVID-19 (94.57%). Implementing intelligent triage systems faced challenges such as trust issues, training needs, equipment shortages, and data privacy concerns.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Developing assessment systems using artificial intelligence enables timely treatment and better resuscitation services for people injured in disasters. For future studies, we recommend designing intelligent triage systems to remove the obstacles in triaging children and disabled people in disasters.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tahernejad</LastName><ForeName>Azadeh</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health in Disasters and Emergencies, School of Public Health and Safety, Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, 1983535511, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sahebi</LastName><ForeName>Ali</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Prehospital Medical Emergencies and Health in Disaster and Emergencies, School of Allied Medical Sciences, Ilam University of Medical Sciences, Ilam, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abadi</LastName><ForeName>Ali Salehi Sahl</ForeName><Initials>ASS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Occupational Health and Safety Engineering, School of Public Health and Safety, Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Safety Promotion and Injury Prevention Research Center, Research Institute for Health Sciences and Environment, Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Safari</LastName><ForeName>Mehdi</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0449-3688</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health in Disasters and Emergencies, School of Public Health and Safety, Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, 1983535511, Iran. safari.pe@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D000078182">Systematic Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Public Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100968562</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1471-2458</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014218" MajorTopicYN="Y">Triage</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001185" MajorTopicYN="Y">Artificial Intelligence</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004190" MajorTopicYN="Y">Disasters</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004630" MajorTopicYN="N">Emergencies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D054527" MajorTopicYN="N">Mass Casualty Incidents</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">AI</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Artificial intelligence</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Data mining</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Disasters</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Emergencies</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Machine learning</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Mass casualty</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Smart</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Systematic review</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Triage</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement><b>Declarations</b> <b>Ethics approval and consent to participate</b> The present study was approved by the Ethics Council of Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences (Ethical code: IR.SBMU.PHNS.REC.1401.151) <b>Consent for publication</b> Not applicable. <b>Competing interests</b> The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>59</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39558305</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12889-024-20447-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12889-024-20447-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Monte BEO, et al. Terminology of natural hazards and disasters: A review and the case of Brazil. Int J of Disaster Risk Reduct. 2021;52:101970.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijdrr.2020.101970</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mead L. Disaster risk reduction in an unstable world. International Institute for Sustainable Development. 2022. Retrieved from https://www.iisd.org/articles/disaster-risk-reduction . Accessed 24 Oct 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Medford-Davis LN, Kapur GB. Preparing for effective communications during disasters: lessons from a World Health Organization quality improvement project, in effective communication during disasters. Apple Academic Press; 2016. p. 29–44.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tahernejad A, et al. Predicting the Fit between the Respirator and Face based on facial anthropometric dimensions using neural-fuzzy method (used in crises). Journal of Health Sciences &amp; Surveillance System. 2020;8(4):168–72.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farahani RZ, et al. Mass casualty management in disaster scene: A systematic review of OR&amp;MS research in humanitarian operations. Eur J Oper Res. 2020;287(3):787–819.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ejor.2020.03.005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heller AR, et al. Diagnostic precision of triage algorithms for mass casualty incidents. English version Der Anaesthesist. 2019;68(1):15–24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28798972</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tahernejad A, et al. Musculoskeletal disorders in emergency medical services personnel: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Public Health. 2024;237:107–15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.puhe.2024.08.020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39366277</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bazyar J, Farrokhi M, Khankeh H. Triage systems in mass casualty incidents and disasters: a review study with a worldwide approach. Open access Macedonian journal of medical sciences. 2019;7(3):482–94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3889/oamjms.2019.119</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30834023</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6390156</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhalla MC, et al. Simple triage algorithm and rapid treatment and sort, assess, lifesaving, interventions, treatment, and transportation mass casualty triage methods for sensitivity, specificity, and predictive values. Am J Emerg Med. 2015;33(11):1687–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ajem.2015.08.021</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26349777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohammadi F, et al. Exploring the challenges to telephone triage in pre-hospital emergency care: a qualitative content analysis. BMC Health Serv Res. 2022;22(1):1–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12913-022-08585-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pairon A, Philips H, Verhoeven V. A scoping review on the use and usefulness of online symptom checkers and triage systems: How to proceed? Front Med. 2023;9:1040926.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmed.2022.1040926</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cannon M, et al. Development of a mass-gathering triage tool: an Australian perspective. Prehosp Disaster Med. 2017;32(1):101–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S1049023X16001242</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27928973</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tahernejad S, et al. Sleep disorders among healthcare workers during the COVID-19 pandemic: An umbrella review and meta-analysis. Nurs Practice Today. 2024;11:22–33.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hill MG, Sim M, Mills B. The quality of diagnosis and triage advice provided by free online symptom checkers and apps in Australia. Med J Aust. 2020;212(11):514–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5694/mja2.50600</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32391611</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pokorny DM, Kung AC, Gordon JL. Disaster Management. In: Pediatric Trauma Care: A Practical Guide. Springer; 2023. p. 47–59.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adebayo O, Bhuiyan ZA, Ahmed Z. Exploring the effectiveness of artificial intelligence, machine learning and deep learning in trauma triage: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Digital Health. 2023;9:20552076231205736.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/20552076231205736</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37822960</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10563501</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baker A, et al. A Comparison of artificial intelligence and human doctors for the purpose of triage and diagnosis. Front Artif Intell. 2020;3:543405.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moher D, et al. Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses: the PRISMA statement. Revista Espanola de Nutricion Humana y Dietetica. 2014;18(3):172–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.14306/renhyd.18.3.114</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sahebi A, et al. Personal protective equipment-associated headaches in health care workers during COVID-19: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Front Public Health. 2022;10: 942046.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2022.942046</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36311638</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9605797</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hong QN, et al. The Mixed Methods Appraisal Tool (MMAT) version 2018 for information professionals and researchers. Educ Inf. 2018;34(4):285–91.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Killeen JP, et al. A wireless first responder handheld device for rapid triage, patient assessment and documentation during mass casualty incidents. in AMIA annual symposium proceedings. American Medical Informatics Association; 2006. p. 429–433.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aoki N, et al. Predictive model for estimating risk of crush syndrome: a data mining approach. J Trauma Acute Care Surg. 2007;62(4):940–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/01.ta.0000229795.01720.1e</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao T, et al. The Advanced Health and Disaster Aid Network: A Light-Weight Wireless Medical System for Triage. IEEE Trans Biomed Circuits Syst. 2007;1(3):203–16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/TBCAS.2007.910901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greiner-Mai T, Donner A. Data management in mass casualty incidents: The e-Triage project. INFORMATIK 2010. Service Science–Neue Perspektiven für die Informatik. Band 2. 2010;2:192–8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adler C, et al. IT-supported management of mass casualty incidents: The e-Triage project. Proceedings of the 8th International ISCRAM Conference – Lisbon, Portugal. 2011;8:17562.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Craig JB, et al. Gleaning data from disaster: a hospital-based data mining method to studying all-hazard triage after a chemical disaster. Am J Disaster Med. 2013;8(2):97.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5055/ajdm.2013.0116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24352925</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4090778</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sakanushi K, et al. Electronic triage system for continuously monitoring casualties at disaster scenes. J Ambient Intell Humaniz Comput. 2013;4(5):547–58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12652-012-0130-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tian Y, et al. Design and development of a mobile-based system for supporting emergency triage decision making. J Med Syst. 2014;38(6):65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10916-014-0065-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24898115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cicero MX, et al. Do you see what I see? Insights from using google glass for disaster telemedicine triage. Prehosp Disaster Med. 2015;30(1):4–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S1049023X1400140X</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25571779</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim D, et al. A data-driven artificial intelligence model for remote triage in the prehospital environment. PLoS ONE. 2018;13(10):e0206006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0206006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30352077</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6198975</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Follmann A, et al. Technical support by smart glasses during a mass casualty incident: a randomized controlled simulation trial on technically assisted triage and telemedical app use in disaster medicine. J Med Internet Res. 2019;21(1): e11939.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/11939</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30609988</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6682285</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim D, et al. Automated remote decision-making algorithm as a primary triage system using machine learning techniques. Physiol Meas. 2021;42(2): 025006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1088/1361-6579/abe524</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33567409</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soltan AA, et al. Rapid triage for COVID-19 using routine clinical data for patients attending hospital: development and prospective validation of an artificial intelligence screening test. The Lancet Digital Health. 2021;3(2):e78–87.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2589-7500(20)30274-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33509388</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anschau F, et al. Smart Check–COVID-19 triage system: Evaluation of the impact on the screening time and identification of clinical manifestations of SARS-CoV-2 infection in a public health service. Int J Clin Pract. 2021;75(10): e14610.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/ijcp.14610</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34235816</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park JY. Real-time monitoring electronic triage tag system for improving survival rate in disaster-induced mass casualty incidents. Healthcare. 2021;9(7):877. MDPI.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Apiratwarakul K, et al. Smart Glasses: A New Tool for Assessing the Number of Patients in Mass-Casualty Incidents. Prehosp Disaster Med. 2022;37(4):480–4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S1049023X22000929</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35757837</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9280067</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu J, et al. Unmanned aerial vehicle based intelligent triage system in mass-casualty incidents using 5G and artificial intelligence. World J Emerg Med. 2023;14(4):273–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5847/wjem.j.1920-8642.2023.066</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37425090</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10323497</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Villafuerte N, et al. Artificial Intelligence in Virtual Telemedicine Triage: A Respiratory Infection Diagnosis Tool with Electronic Measuring Device. Future Internet. 2023;15(7):227.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/fi15070227</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khanna VV, et al. A machine learning and explainable artificial intelligence triage-prediction system for COVID-19. Decis Anal J. 2023;7:100246.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.dajour.2023.100246</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10163946</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>