<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39553297</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2196-5226</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>19</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>GMS hygiene and infection control</Title><ISOAbbreviation>GMS Hyg Infect Control</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A COVID-19 outbreak with a high attack rate among inpatients in a psychiatric hospital in Wenzhou, China.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>Doc43</StartPage><MedlinePgn>Doc43</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">Doc43</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3205/dgkh000498</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Since the emergence of COVID-19, China has taken strict prevention and control measures against the disease. At the end of 2022, when the government optimized and relaxed the COVID-19 prevention and control policy, a new wave of the epidemic appeared. This paper reports an outbreak of COVID-19 among inpatients in a psychiatric hospital in Wenzhou, China.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The case definition of COVID-19 was established. Throat swab specimens were collected and examined by RT-PCT. Questionnaires were distributed to hospitalized patients. Survey data were collected and analyzed.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Of 902 inpatients in our hospital, 762 became infected with COVID-19, an attack rate of 84.5%. The outbreak occurred from 10 December, 2022 to January 18, 2023. Twenty patients died, yielding a case fatality rate of 2.6%. Most of the dead were among elderly people with underlying diseases, and 19 of the deceased were over 65 years old.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Our investigation showed that the outbreak of COVID-19 among hospitalized patients had the characteristics of high incidence, strong infectivity, and rapid transmission. Infectious sources were introduced into the hospital from the community and spread within the hospital, resulting in an outbreak. In addition, special attention should be paid to elderly people with underlying diseases when treating patients with COVID-19 in the future.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Zhou et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Yiwei</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Business School, University of Shanghai for Science and Technology, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Intelligent Emergency Management, University of Shanghai for Science and Technology, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Smart Urban Mobility Institute, University of Shanghai for Science and Technology, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lin</LastName><ForeName>Xingbao</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Affiliated Kangning Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University, Zhejiang Provincial Clinical Research Center for Mental Disorders, Wenzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huang</LastName><ForeName>Yu</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Affiliated Kangning Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University, Zhejiang Provincial Clinical Research Center for Mental Disorders, Wenzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wu</LastName><ForeName>Chunhua</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Affiliated Kangning Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University, Zhejiang Provincial Clinical Research Center for Mental Disorders, Wenzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Jun</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wenzhou Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Wenzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huang</LastName><ForeName>Jieru</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Wenzhou Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Wenzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Zumu</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Affiliated Kangning Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University, Zhejiang Provincial Clinical Research Center for Mental Disorders, Wenzhou, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>02</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>GMS Hyg Infect Control</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101609519</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2196-5226</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="ger"><AbstractText Label="HINTERGRUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Seit dem Auftreten von COVID-19 hat China strenge Präventions- und Kontrollmaßnahmen gegen die Krankheit ergriffen. Ende 2022, als die Regierung die Präventions- und Kontrollmaßnahmen für COVID-19 optimierte und lockerte, trat eine neue Welle von Epidemien auf. Dieser Artikel berichtet über einen Ausbruch von COVID-19 bei stationären Patienten in einem psychiatrischen Krankenhaus in Wenzhou, China.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Die Falldefinition von COVID-19 wurde festgelegt. Es wurden Rachenabstriche entnommen und mittels RT-PCT untersucht. An die Krankenhauspatienten wurden Fragebögen verteilt. Die Erhebungsdaten wurden gesammelt und analysiert.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="ERGEBNISSE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Es wurden 920 Patienten stationär im Krankenhaus aufgenommen. Bei 762 Patienten trat COVID-19 auf, d.h. die Ansteckungsrate betrug 84,5%. Der Ausbruch erfolgte vom 10. Dezember 2022 bis zum 18. Januar 2023. Es ereigneten sich 20 Todesfälle mit einer Sterblichkeitsrate von 2,6%. Bei den meisten Verstorbenen handelte es sich um ältere Menschen mit Grunderkrankungen; 19 Verstorbene waren über 65 Jahre alt.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="SCHLUSSFOLGERUNG" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Unsere Untersuchung ergab, dass der Ausbruch von COVID-19 bei Krankenhauspatienten durch eine hohe Inzidenz, eine starke Infektiosität und eine schnelle Übertragung gekennzeichnet war. Die Erreger wurden aus der Bevölkerung in das Krankenhaus eingeschleppt und verbreiteten sich innerhalb des Krankenhauses, was zu einem Ausbruch der Krankheit führte. Im Rahmen des Ausbruchmanagements sollte bei der Behandlung von Patienten mit COVID-19 in Zukunft besonders auf ältere Menschen mit Grunderkrankungen geachtet werden.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 Zhou et al.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">cluster</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">outbreak</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">psychiatric hospital</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39553297</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11565407</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3205/dgkh000498</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">dgkh000498</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Kim SW. COVID-19 Outbreak in Daegu City, Korea and Response to COVID-19: How Have We Dealt and What Are the Lessons? J Korean Med Sci. 2022 Dec 26;37(50):e356. doi: 10.3346/jkms.2022.37.e356.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3346/jkms.2022.37.e356</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9792262</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36573388</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou Y, Xiang F, Ni C, Zhang X, Xie H, Zhu H, Zhou Z. Travel-associated outbreak of COVID-19 in a departmental store, Wenzhou, China. J Infect Dev Ctries. 2022 May 30;16(5):752–758. doi: 10.3855/jidc.15670.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3855/jidc.15670</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35656944</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suhs T, Gerlach D, Garfin J, Lorentz A, Firestone M, Sherden M, Hackman K, Gray T, Siebman S, Wienkes H, Vilen K, Wang X, Como-Sabetti K, Danila R, Smith K, Medus C. COVID-19 Outbreak Associated With a Fitness Center-Minnesota, September-November 2020. Clin Infect Dis. 2022 Apr 9;74(7):1265–1267. doi: 10.1093/cid/ciab653.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/ciab653</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8344575</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34297064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zoghbi M, Haddad C, Khansa W, Karam E, Chamoun A, Hachem D. COVID-19 outbreak in a psychiatric hospital: what makes it worse? Ann Gen Psychiatry. 2022 Jul 11;21(1):26. doi: 10.1186/s12991-022-00403-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12991-022-00403-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9277896</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35820935</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou ZM, Zhou HZ, Lin XD, Su ZC, Zhao LS, Chen X. Outbreak of COVID-19 in a family, Wenzhou, China. Epidemiol Infect. 2020 May 20;148:e103. doi: 10.1017/S0950268820001089.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0950268820001089</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7267103</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32430084</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor J, Carter RJ, Lehnertz N, Kazazian L, Sullivan M, Wang X, Garfin J, Diekman S, Plumb M, Bennet ME, Hale T, Vallabhaneni S, Namugenyi S, Carpenter D, Turner-Harper D, Booth M, Coursey EJ, Martin K, McMahon M, Beaudoin A, Lifson A, Holzbauer S, Reddy SC, Jernigan JA, Lynfield R Minnesota Long-Term Care COVID-19 Response Group. Serial Testing for SARS-CoV-2 and Virus Whole Genome Sequencing Inform Infection Risk at Two Skilled Nursing Facilities with COVID-19 Outbreaks - Minnesota, April-June 2020. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2020 Sep 18;69(37):1288–1295. doi: 10.15585/mmwr.mm6937a3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm6937a3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7498172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32966272</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boudhabhay I, Serris A, Servais A, Planas D, Hummel A, Guery B, Parize P, Aguilar C, Dao M, Rouzaud C, Ferriere E, Knebelmann B, Sakhi H, Leruez M, Joly D, Schwartz O, Lanternier F, Bruel T. COVID-19 outbreak in vaccinated patients from a haemodialysis unit: antibody titres as a marker of protection from infection. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2022 Jun 23;37(7):1357–1365. doi: 10.1093/ndt/gfac016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ndt/gfac016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8903345</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35104884</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Ewijk CE, Hazelhorst EI, Hahné SJM, Knol MJ. COVID-19 outbreak in an elderly care home: Very low vaccine effectiveness and late impact of booster vaccination campaign. Vaccine. 2022 Nov 2;40(46):6664–6669. doi: 10.1016/j.vaccine.2022.09.080.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2022.09.080</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9531647</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36216647</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. WHO COVID-19 Case definition: Updated in Public health surveillance for COVID-19. Jul 22, 2022.  [accessed 2023 Feb 25].  Available from:  https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/WHO-2019-nCoV-Surveillance_Case_Definition-2022-1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imamura T, Ko YK, Furuse Y, Imamura T, Jindai K, Miyahara R, Sando E, Yasuda I, Tsuchiya N Field Epidemiology Training Program, Japan (FETP-J), The National COVID-19 Cluster Response Taskforce; Saito M, Suzuki M, Oshitani H. Epidemiological Factors Associated with COVID-19 Clusters in Medical and Social Welfare Facilities. Jpn J Infect Dis. 2022 May 24;75(3):281–287. doi: 10.7883/yoken.JJID.2021.288.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7883/yoken.JJID.2021.288</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34719529</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Druss BG. Addressing the COVID-19 Pandemic in Populations With Serious Mental Illness. JAMA Psychiatry. 2020 Sep 1;77(9):891–892. doi: 10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2020.0894.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2020.0894</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32242888</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shinn AK, Viron M. Perspectives on the COVID-19 Pandemic and Individuals With Serious Mental Illness. J Clin Psychiatry. 2020 Apr 28;81(3):20com13412. doi: 10.4088/JCP.20com13412.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4088/JCP.20com13412</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32369691</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paruk S, Ngcobo NN, Karim E, Tomita A, Ramlall S. COVID-19 infection at a psychiatric hospital in KwaZulu-Natal, South Africa: Clinical service planning and challenges. S Afr J Psychiatr. 2022 Dec 7;28:1933. doi: 10.4102/sajpsychiatry.v28i0.1933.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4102/sajpsychiatry.v28i0.1933</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9772653</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36569809</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ng CYH, Lim NA, Bao LXY, Quek AML, Seet RCS. Mitigating SARS-CoV-2 Transmission in Hospitals: A Systematic Literature Review. Public Health Rev. 2022 Feb 23;43:1604572. doi: 10.3389/phrs.2022.1604572.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/phrs.2022.1604572</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8906284</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35296115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abbas M, Robalo Nunes T, Martischang R, Zingg W, Iten A, Pittet D, Harbarth S. Nosocomial transmission and outbreaks of coronavirus disease 2019: the need to protect both patients and healthcare workers. Antimicrob Resist Infect Control. 2021 Jan 6;10(1):7. doi: 10.1186/s13756-020-00875-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13756-020-00875-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7787623</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33407833</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghinai I, McPherson TD, Hunter JC, Kirking HL, Christiansen D, Joshi K, Rubin R, Morales-Estrada S, Black SR, Pacilli M, Fricchione MJ, Chugh RK, Walblay KA, Ahmed NS, Stoecker WC, Hasan NF, Burdsall DP, Reese HE, Wallace M, Wang C, Moeller D, Korpics J, Novosad SA, Benowitz I, Jacobs MW, Dasari VS, Patel MT, Kauerauf J, Charles EM, Ezike NO, Chu V, Midgley CM, Rolfes MA, Gerber SI, Lu X, Lindstrom S, Verani JR, Layden JE Illinois COVID-19 Investigation Team. First known person-to-person transmission of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) in the USA. Lancet. 2020 Apr 4;395(10230):1137–1144. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30607-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30607-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7158585</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32178768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamner L, Dubbel P, Capron I, Ross A, Jordan A, Lee J, Lynn J, Ball A, Narwal S, Russell S, Patrick D, Leibrand H. High SARS-CoV-2 Attack Rate Following Exposure at a Choir Practice - Skagit County, Washington, March 2020. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2020 May 15;69(19):606–610. doi: 10.15585/mmwr.mm6919e6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm6919e6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32407303</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Araf Y, Akter F, Tang YD, Fatemi R, Parvez MSA, Zheng C, Hossain MG. Omicron variant of SARS-CoV-2: Genomics, transmissibility, and responses to current COVID-19 vaccines. J Med Virol. 2022 May;94(5):1825–1832. doi: 10.1002/jmv.27588.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.27588</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9015557</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35023191</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan Y, Li X, Zhang L, Wan S, Zhang L, Zhou F. SARS-CoV-2 Omicron variant: recent progress and future perspectives. Signal Transduct Target Ther. 2022 Apr 28;7(1):141. doi: 10.1038/s41392-022-00997-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41392-022-00997-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9047469</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35484110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohsin M, Mahmud S. Omicron SARS-CoV-2 variant of concern: A review on its transmissibility, immune evasion, reinfection, and severity. Medicine (Baltimore) 2022 May 13;101(19):e29165. doi: 10.1097/MD.0000000000029165.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000029165</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9276130</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35583528</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Müller-Wieland D, Marx N, Dreher M, Fritzen K, Schnell O. COVID-19 and Cardiovascular Comorbidities. Exp Clin Endocrinol Diabetes. 2022 Mar;130(3):178–189. doi: 10.1055/a-1269-1405.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1055/a-1269-1405</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33157558</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shakor JK, Isa RA, Babakir-Mina M, Ali SI, Hama-Soor TA, Abdulla JE. Health related factors contributing to COVID-19 fatality rates in various communities across the world. J Infect Dev Ctries. 2021 Sep 30;15(9):1263–1272. doi: 10.3855/jidc.13876.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3855/jidc.13876</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34669594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>