<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39552917</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2045-1253</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>14</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Therapeutic advances in psychopharmacology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Ther Adv Psychopharmacol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Prevalence and risk factors of PTSD symptoms: a 3-month follow-up study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>20451253241298816</StartPage><MedlinePgn>20451253241298816</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">20451253241298816</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1177/20451253241298816</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">During the peak of the epidemic, hospitalized patients frequently encountered significant health risks and potentially life-threatening circumstances, including uncertainty regarding treatment and the potential for complications.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The present study aimed to explore the prevalence of post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) symptoms among hospitalized patients 3 months after discharge during the first peak of the epidemic, and the association of PTSD with disease-related characteristics.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DESIGN" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A single-center and full-sample follow-up study was conducted on COVID-19 patients from the Optical Valley Branch of Maternal and Child Hospital of Hubei Province, Wuhan, China. Data were collected during their hospitalization and 3 months after discharge.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">PTSD symptoms were evaluated by primary care post-traumatic stress disorder (PC-PTSD), a total score of 3 or above was considered as clinically significant PTSD symptoms. Demographic and disease-related characteristics were collected to identify related associations with PTSD symptoms.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A total of 903 patients completed the follow-up survey, yielding a response rate of 63.5%. A total of 212 (23.5%) of the patients were positive in PC-PTSD screening. Univariate regression analysis identified several factors correlated with PTSD symptoms, including female gender, younger age, a lower body mass index (BMI), preexisting sleep problems, bereavement due to COVID-19, a severe clinical diagnosis, the presence of three or more clinical symptoms at disease onset, and residual respiratory symptoms after discharge. Notably, in the multivariate regression analysis, experiencing three or more clinical symptoms at onset emerged as a robust predictor of PTSD symptoms (OR = 2.09, 95% CI: 1.48-2.95). An intriguing finding was that patients who underwent radiological assessment post-discharge reported a higher incidence of PTSD symptoms, whereas those who underwent re-testing for IgG or IgM antibodies exhibited a lower prevalence of PTSD symptoms.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Three months post-recovery, PTSD symptoms prevalence among COVID-19 patients was 23.5%. Those with three or more clinical symptoms at onset or residual respiratory symptoms post-discharge showed higher risk. These findings highlighted the long-term effect of COVID-19 on mental health, urging enhanced attention and interventions for survivors.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s), 2024.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shang</LastName><ForeName>Zhilei</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Lab for Post-traumatic Stress Disorder, Faculty of Psychology and Mental Health, Naval Medical University, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Emotion &amp; Cognition Lab, Faculty of Psychology and Mental Health, Naval Medical University, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pan</LastName><ForeName>Xiao</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Psychology, Changzheng Hospital, Naval Medical University, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cheng</LastName><ForeName>Suhui</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Lab for Post-traumatic Stress Disorder, Faculty of Psychology and Mental Health, Naval Medical University, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Emotion &amp; Cognition Lab, Faculty of Psychology and Mental Health, Naval Medical University, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yang</LastName><ForeName>Yuchen</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Sociology and Political Science, Shanghai University, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yan</LastName><ForeName>Wenjie</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Lab for Post-traumatic Stress Disorder, Faculty of Psychology and Mental Health, Naval Medical University, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Emotion &amp; Cognition Lab, Faculty of Psychology and Mental Health, Naval Medical University, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sun</LastName><ForeName>LiangLiang</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Endocrinology and Metabolism, Changzheng Hospital, Naval Medical University, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Optical Valley Branch of Maternal and Child Hospital of Hubei Province, Wuhan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huang</LastName><ForeName>Hai</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Optical Valley Branch of Maternal and Child Hospital of Hubei Province, Wuhan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine, Changzheng Hospital, Naval Medical University, Shanghai, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bai</LastName><ForeName>Yonghai</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Psychology, Changzheng Hospital, Naval Medical University, Shanghai 200003, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Optical Valley Branch of Maternal and Child Hospital of Hubei Province, Wuhan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xie</LastName><ForeName>Weifen</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Gastroenterology, Changzheng Hospital, Naval Medical University, Shanghai 200005, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Optical Valley Branch of Maternal and Child Hospital of Hubei Province, Wuhan, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Xu</LastName><ForeName>Shu</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6968-1674</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biostatistics, School of Global Public Health, New York University, 708 Broadway, 7th floor - Rm 761, New York, NY 10003, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>15</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Ther Adv Psychopharmacol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101555693</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2045-1253</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><OtherAbstract Type="plain-language-summary" Language="eng"><AbstractText>Prevalence and risk factors of PTSD symptoms: a three-month follow-up study Why was the study done?: PTSD (Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder) is a mental health condition that can develop after someone goes through or witnesses an extremely frightening, life-threatening event. It’s a type of ongoing mental distress that can show up later and last for a long time, significantly affecting a person’s quality of life. The study aimed to find out how many people who have gone through a public health emergency like COVID-19 develop PTSD symptoms within three months of recovery, and see if there’s a link between these symptoms and their illness. What did the researchers do? The research team did a single-center and full-sample follow-up study in COVID-19 patients who had recovered for three months. A tool called the PC-PTSD scale was used to check if they had PTSD symptoms. If their score was 3 or above, it meant they might have significant PTSD symptoms. The details about their illness were also collected to see if there’s a connection with PTSD symptoms. What did the researchers find? A total of 903 patients participated in the survey, with a participation rate of 63.5%. Among them, 212 patients (23.5%) had a positive result on the PC-PTSD test, indicating they might have PTSD symptoms. The study found that several factors were linked to PTSD symptoms, such as being female, younger age, having a low body weight, previous sleep issues, losing a loved one due to COVID-19, having a severe COVID-19 diagnosis, experiencing three or more symptoms at onset, and having residual respiratory issues after discharge. Specifically, those who had three or more symptoms at onset were more likely to develop PTSD. What do the findings mean? Within three months of COVID-19 recovery, 23.5% of patients may experience PTSD symptoms. Those who had three or more symptoms at onset or had residual respiratory issues after discharge were more likely to develop PTSD symptoms. This suggests that COVID-19 can have long-term psychological effects on patients.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s), 2024.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">PTSD</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">follow-up study</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">prevalence</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">public health emergency</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>58</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39552917</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11569496</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/20451253241298816</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1177_20451253241298816</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Mahase E. China coronavirus: WHO declares international emergency as death toll exceeds 200. BMJ-Brit Med J 2020; 368: m408.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32005727</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zandifar A, Karim H, Qorbani M, et al.. Mental health care for medical staff in Iran during the COVID-19 pandemic; different performance in Alborz Province. Iranian J Psychiatry 2020; 15: 243–247.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7603594</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33193773</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>APA. Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders-5th edition (DSM-5). Arlington, TX: American Psychiatric Association, 2013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiehui L, Caramanica ZK, Brackbill RM, et al.. Comorbidity amplifies the effects of post-9/11 posttraumatic stress disorder trajectories on health-related quality of life. Quality Life Res 2018; 27: 651–660.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5845593</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29260446</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Claudia C, Liliana D, Corrado M, et al.. Frequency of trauma exposure and post-traumatic stress disorder in Italy: analysis from the World Mental Health Survey Initiative. J. Psychiatr Res 2014; 59: 77–84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4313080</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25266475</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu T, Xu S, Liu W. A senior high school-based survey on the long-term impact of the Wenchuan earthquake on survivors’ quality of life: PTSD as a mediator. Psychiat Res 2018; 270: 310–316.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30290316</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hong X, Currier GW, Zhao X, et al.. Posttraumatic stress disorder in convalescent severe acute respiratory syndrome patients: a 4-year follow-up study. Gen Hosp Psychiat 2009; 31: 546–554.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7112559</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19892213</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee SM, Kang WS, Cho A, et al.. Psychological impact of the 2015 MERS outbreak on hospital workers and quarantined hemodialysis patients. Compr Psychiat 2018; 87: 123–127.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7094631</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30343247</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu N, Zhang F, Wei C, et al.. Prevalence and predictors of PTSS during COVID-19 outbreak in China hardest-hit areas: gender differences matter. Psychiat Res 2020; 287: 112921.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7102622</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32240896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan W, Shang Z, Wu L, et al.. The impact of isolation on comorbidity of PTSD symptoms and depression: evidence from PTRP-5-6 in China. BMC Public Health 2024; 24: 21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10762958</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38166952</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun L, Yi B, Pan X, et al.. PTSD symptoms and sleep quality of COVID-19 patients during hospitalization: an observational study from two centers. Nat Sci Sleep 2021; 13: 1519–1531.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8449687</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34548832</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sankar K, Gould MK, Prescott HC. Psychological morbidity after COVID-19 critical illness. Chest 2023; 163: 139–147.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9528063</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36202259</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tarsitani L, Vassalini P, Koukopoulos A, et al.. Post-traumatic stress disorder among COVID-19 survivors at 3-month follow-up after hospital discharge. J Gen Intern Med 2021; 36: 1702–1707.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8007055</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33782888</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Houben-Wilke S, Goërtz YM, Delbressine JM, et al.. The impact of long COVID-19 on mental health: observational 6-month follow-up study. Jmir Ment Health 2022; 9: e33704.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8914795</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35200155</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiao S, Luo D, Xiao Y. Survivors of COVID-19 are at high risk of posttraumatic stress disorder. Glob Health Res Pol 2020; 5: 29.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7273810</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32514428</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kessler RC, Chiu WT, Demler O, et al.. Prevalence, severity, and comorbidity of 12-month DSM-IV disorders in the national comorbidity survey replication. Arch General Psychiatry 2005; 62: 617–627.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2847357</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15939839</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mak IWC, Chu CM, Pan PC, et al.. Risk factors for chronic post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) in SARS survivors. Gen Hosp Psychiat 2010; 32: 590–598.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7132390</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21112450</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carmassi C, Dell Oste V, Barberi FM, et al.. Do somatic symptoms relate to PTSD and gender after earthquake exposure? A cross-sectional study on young adult survivors in Italy. CNS Spectrums 2021; 26: 268–274.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32248878</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pacella ML, Hruska B, Delahanty DL. The physical health consequences of PTSD and PTSD symptoms: a meta-analytic review. J Anxiety Disord 2013; 27: 33–46.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23247200</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu L, Guo X, Shang Z, et al.. China experience from COVID-19: mental health in mandatory quarantine zones urgently requires intervention. Psychol Trauma Theory Res Pract Policy 2020; 12: S3–S5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32538663</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dutheil F, Mondillon L, Navel V. PTSD as the second tsunami of the SARS-Cov-2 pandemic. Psychol Med 2021; 51: 1773–1774.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7198460</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32326997</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>von Elm E, Altman DG, Egger M, et al.. The strengthening the reporting of observational studies in epidemiology (STROBE) statement: guidelines for reporting observational studies. Ann Intern Med 2007; 147: 573–577.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17938396</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prins A, Ouimette P, Kimerling R, et al.. The primary care PTSD screen (PCPTSD): development and operating characteristics. Primary Care Psychiatry 2003; 9: 9–14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tiet QQ, Schutte KK, Leyva YE. Diagnostic accuracy of brief PTSD screening instruments in military veterans. J Subst Abuse Treat 2013; 45: 134–142.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23506779</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freedy JR, Steenkamp MM, Magruder KM, et al.. Post-traumatic stress disorder screening test performance in civilian primary care. Fam Pract 2010; 27: 615–624.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20622049</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cooper SA, Szymanski BR, Bohnert KM, et al.. Association between positive results on the primary care-posttraumatic stress disorder screen and suicide mortality among US veterans. JAMA Netw Open 2020; 3: e2015707.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7489804</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32880649</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo F, Han R, Luo T, et al.. Psychological distress was still serious among anesthesiologists under the post COVID-19 era. Psychol Res Behav Manag 2022; 15: 777–784.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8974417</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35368423</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng P, Jasinski N, Zheng W, et al.. Psychometric properties of the primary care PTSD screen for DSM-5: findings from family members of Chinese healthcare workers during the outbreak of COVID-19. Front Psychiatry 2021; 12: 695678.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8477025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34594246</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ju Y, Liu J, Ng R, et al.. Prevalence and predictors of post-traumatic stress disorder in patients with cured coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) one month post-discharge. Eur J Psychotraumato 2021; 12: 1915576.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8725742</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34992752</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bellan M, Soddu D, Balbo PE, et al.. Respiratory and psychophysical sequelae among patients with COVID-19 four months after hospital discharge. Jama Netw Open 2021; 4: e2036142.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7841464</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33502487</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>T’Ng K, Kenardy J, Hartanto A. Evaluating mental health outcomes in COVID-19 ICU survivors: a scoping review of measurement tools. J Clin Med 2024; 13: 3191.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11172430</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38892906</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hanley J, DeRoon-Cassini T, Brasel K. Efficiency of a four-item posttraumatic stress disorder screen in trauma patients. J. Trauma Acute Care 2013; 75: 722–727.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24064889</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu CH, Zhang E, Wong GTF, et al.. Factors associated with depression, anxiety, and PTSD symptomatology during the COVID-19 pandemic: clinical implications for U.S. young adult mental health. Psychiat Res 2020; 290: 113172.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7263263</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32512357</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Epidemiology Working Group For NCIP Epidemic Response CCFD. The epidemiological characteristics of an outbreak of 2019 novel coronavirus diseases (COVID-19) in China. Chin J Epidemiol 2020; 41: 145–151.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Franck M, Noel BM, Peter JB, et al.. Sex and gender: modifiers of health, disease, and medicine. Lancet 2020; 396: 565–582.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7440877</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32828189</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dagan Y, Yager J. Addressing loneliness in complex PTSD. J Nervous Mental Dis 2019; 207: 433–439.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31045977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen W, Wu S, Ling L, et al.. Impacts of social integration and loneliness on mental health of humanitarian migrants in Australia: evidence from a longitudinal study. Aust Nz J Publ Heal 2019; 43: 46–55.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30602072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zegel M, Tran JK, Vujanovic AA. Posttraumatic stress, alcohol use, and alcohol use motives among firefighters: the role of distress tolerance. Psychiat Res 2019; 282: 112633.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31708250</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin RL, Bauer BW, Ramsey KL, et al.. How distress tolerance mediates the relationship between posttraumatic stress disorder and the interpersonal theory of suicide constructs in a U.S. Military sample. Suicide Life-Threat Behav 2019; 49: 1318–1331.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30368865</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang W. Obesity and happiness. Zhejiang University of Finance &amp; Economics, 2019, p. 58.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lan C, Su C, Chou L, et al.. Association of body mass index with exercise cardiopulmonary responses in lung function-matched patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. Heart Lung 2012; 41: 374–381.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22421506</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takemoto E, Van Oss KR, Chamany S, et al.. Post-traumatic stress disorder and the association with overweight, obesity, and weight change among individuals exposed to the World Trade Center disaster, 2003–2016. Psychol Med 2021; 51(5): 2647–2656.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32375911</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roberts RE, Strawbridge WJ, Deleger S, et al.. Are the fat more jolly? Ann Behav Med 2002; 24: 169–180.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12173674</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robertson S, Davies M, Winefield H. Why weight for happiness? Correlates of BMI and SWB in Australia. Obes Res Clin Pract 2015; 9: 609–612.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26048722</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>