<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39557626</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1442-2018</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>26</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Dec</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Nursing &amp; health sciences</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Nurs Health Sci</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Development of COVID-19 Infection Prevention and Control Training Program Based on ADDIE Model for Clinical Nurses: A Pretest-Posttest Study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e13194</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e13194</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/nhs.13194</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Scientific and effective training is important to enhance the theoretical knowledge and practical skills of clinical nurses in coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) prevention and control (IPC), so as to improve the IPC capacity. The study aimed to design and implement a COVID-19 IPC training program for clinical nurses based on the ADDIE model, and to evaluate its clinical application effects. This was a pretest-posttest study in which 389 clinical nurses were recruited through convenience sampling. The IPC training program for clinical nurses was developed based on the five stages of ADDIE model. Data were analyzed using pared-sample t test, McNemar's test, and Wilcoxon test. After training, nurses' theoretical scores and operational scores except for hand hygiene were improved significantly (p &lt; 0.001). Compared to pre-training assessment, their job performances were also significantly improved (p &lt; 0.001). And they had higher satisfaction with the program post-training. Under the situation of COVID-19, training based on the ADDIE model can effectively improve the IPC ability of clinical nurses. Besides, it provides new ideas, methods, and approaches for future clinical IPC training.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liang</LastName><ForeName>Bing</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0048-9307</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Nursing, Jilin University, Jilin, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Jiaxin</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Nursing, Beijing Children's Hospital, Capital Medical University, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Qu</LastName><ForeName>Zhifei</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Nursing, Jilin University, Jilin, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jiang</LastName><ForeName>Nan</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cardiovascular Center, Jilin University First Hospital, Changchun, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Chen</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Central Sterile Supply Department, The Second Hospital of Jilin University, Changchun, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cheng</LastName><ForeName>Siming</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Jilin General Aviation Vocational and Technical College, Jilin, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Li</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4294-7089</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nursing Department, The Second Hospital of Jilin University, Changchun, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>JGJX2021C1</GrantID><Agency>Higher Education Research Project of Jilin Province</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>20200901012SF</GrantID><Agency>Science and Technology Development Plan of Jilin Province</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2021XYB191</GrantID><Agency>Teaching Reform Research Project of Jilin University</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2021SZ2Y02</GrantID><Agency>Jilin University Course Ideological and Political Demonstration Course construction project</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>SK2021126</GrantID><Agency>Course Ideological and Political Project of Jilin University</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Australia</Country><MedlineTA>Nurs Health Sci</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100891857</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1441-0745</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000451" MajorTopicYN="N">nursing</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011795" MajorTopicYN="N">Surveys and Questionnaires</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017053" MajorTopicYN="N">Infection Control</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016730" MajorTopicYN="N">Program Development</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ADDIE model</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID‐19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Kirkpatrick model</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">clinical nurses</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">infection prevention and control</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">training program</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>22</Hour><Minute>32</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39557626</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/nhs.13194</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>Abualenain, J. T., and M. M. Al‐Alawi. 2018. “Simulation‐Based Training in Ebola Personal Protective Equipment for Healthcare Workers: Experience From King Abdulaziz University Hospital in Saudi Arabia.” Journal of Infection and Public Health 11, no. 6: 796–800. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jiph.2018.05.002.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akshaya, K. M., H. D. Shewade, O. P. Aslesh, et al. 2017. ““Who Has to Do It at the End of the Day? Programme Officials or Hospital Authorities?” Airborne Infection Control at Drug Resistant Tuberculosis (DR‐TB) Centres of Karnataka, India: A Mixed‐Methods Study.” Antimicrobial Resistance and Infection Control 6: 111. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13756‐017‐0270‐4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allen, W. C. 2006. “Overview and Evolution of the ADDIE Training System.” Advances in Developing Human Resources 8: 430–441. https://doi.org/10.1177/1523422306292942.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aydin, A., A. Gursoy, and H. Karal. 2023. “Mobile Care App Development Process: Using the ADDIE Model to Manage Symptoms After Breast Cancer Surgery (Step 1).” Discover Oncology 14, no. 1: 63. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12672‐023‐00676‐5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhamra, N., K. Gupta, J. Lee, S. Al‐Hity, K. Jolly, and A. Darr. 2021. “Personal Protective Equipment: Knowledge of the Guidance.” British Journal of Nursing 30, no. 1: 16–22. https://doi.org/10.12968/bjon.2021.30.1.16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Braun, V., and V. Clarke. 2006. “Using Thematic Analysis in Psychology.” Qualitative Research in Psychology 3: 77–101. https://doi.org/10.1191/1478088706qp063oa.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caijuan, X., J. Jingfen, S. Jianping, et al. 2020. “Application of Refined Management in Prevention and Control of Coronavirus Disease 2019 Epidemic in Nonisolated Areas of a General Hospita.” Chinese Journal of Nursing 55, no. 3: 351–354.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cardinal, P., G. Barton, K. DesRosier, et al. 2020. “Mapping the Expert Mind: Integration Method for Revising the ACES Medical Simulation Curriculum.” Journal of Medical Education and Curricular Development 7: 2382120520913270. https://doi.org/10.1177/2382120520913270.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carmassi, C., C. Foghi, V. Dell'Oste, et al. 2020. “PTSD Symptoms in Healthcare Workers Facing the Three Coronavirus Outbreaks: What Can We Expect After the COVID‐19 Pandemic.” Psychiatry Research 292: 113312. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.psychres.2020.113312.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, Q., Z. Li, S. Tang, et al. 2022. “Development of a Blended Emergent Research Training Program for Clinical Nurses (Part 1).” BMC Nursing 21, no. 1: 2. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12912‐021‐00786‐x.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen, H. A., E. Kitai, I. Levy, and D. Ben‐Anitai. 2002. “Handwashing Patterns in Two Dermatology Clinics.” Dermatology 205, no. 4: 358–361.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Kock, J. H., H. A. Latham, S. J. Leslie, et al. 2021. “A Rapid Review of the Impact of COVID‐19 on the Mental Health of Healthcare Workers: Implications for Supporting Psychological Well‐Being.” BMC Public Health 21, no. 1: 104. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889‐020‐10070‐3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Earl, M. L., M. M. Jackson, and L. S. Rickman. 2001. “Improved Rates of Compliance With Hand Antisepsis Guidelines: A Three‐Phase Observational Study.” American Journal of Nursing 101, no. 3: 26–33. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0001‐2092(06)61693‐1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gail, C., K. W. Field, T. Simpson, and E. F. Bond. 2004. “Clinical Nurse Specialists and Nurse Practitioners: Complementary Roles for Infectious Disease and Infection Control.” American Journal of Infection Control 32, no. 4: 239–242. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajic.2003.06.002.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galanis, P., I. Vraka, D. Fragkou, A. Bilali, and D. Kaitelidou. 2021. “Nurses' Burnout and Associated Risk Factors During the COVID‐19 Pandemic: A Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis.” Journal of Advanced Nursing 77, no. 8: 3286–3302. https://doi.org/10.1111/jan.14839.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garg, K., A. Grewal, R. Mahajan, S. Kumari, and A. Mahajan. 2020. “A Cross‐Sectional Study on Knowledge, Attitude, and Practices of Donning and Doffing of Personal Protective Equipment: An Institutional Survey of Health‐Care Staff During the COVID‐19 Pandemic.” Anesthesia, Essays and Researches 14, no. 3: 370–375. https://doi.org/10.4103/aer.AER_53_20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guimarães, H. C. Q. C. P., S. B. Pena, L. Lopes Jde, C. T. Lopes, and A. L. Bottura Leite de Barros. 2016. “Experts for Validation Studies in Nursing: New Proposal and Selection Criteria.” International Journal of Nursing Knowledge 27, no. 3: 130–135. https://doi.org/10.1111/2047‐3095.12089.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halcomb, E., S. McInnes, A. Williams, et al. 2020. “Experiences of Primary Healthcare Nurses During the COVID‐19 Pandemic in Australia.” Journal of Nursing Scholarship 52, no. 5: 553–563. https://doi.org/10.1111/jnu.12589.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holmes, E. A., R. C. O'Connor, V. H. Perry, et al. 2020. “Multidisciplinary Research Priorities for the COVID‐19 Pandemic: A Call for Action for Mental Health Science.” Lancet Psychiatry 7, no. 6: 547–560. https://doi.org/10.1016/s2215‐0366(20)30168‐1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hossain, M. A., M. U. B. Rashid, M. A. S. Khan, S. Sayeed, M. A. Kader, and M. D. H. Hawlader. 2021. “Healthcare Workers' Knowledge, Attitude, and Practice Regarding Personal Protective Equipment for the Prevention of COVID‐19.” Journal of Multidisciplinary Healthcare 14: 229–238. https://doi.org/10.2147/jmdh.S293717.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Houghton, C., P. Meskell, H. Delaney, et al. 2020. “Barriers and Facilitators to Healthcare workers' Adherence With Infection Prevention and Control (IPC) Guidelines for Respiratory Infectious Diseases: A Rapid Qualitative Evidence Synthesis.” Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews 4, no. 4: Cd013582. https://doi.org/10.1002/14651858.Cd013582.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Islam, M. S., K. M. Rahman, Y. Sun, et al. 2020. “Current Knowledge of COVID‐19 and Infection Prevention and Control Strategies in Healthcare Settings: A Global Analysis.” Infection Control and Hospital Epidemiology 41, no. 10: 1196–1206. https://doi.org/10.1017/ice.2020.237.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kulatunga, G. G., R. B. Marasinghe, I. M. Karunathilake, and V. H. Dissanayake. 2013. “Development and Implementation of a Web‐Based Continuing Professional Development (CPD) Programme on Medical Genetics.” Journal of Telemedicine and Telecare 19, no. 7: 388–392. https://doi.org/10.1177/1357633x13506525.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>LaMarca, V. J., and J. M. LaMarca. 2024. “Using the ADDIE Model of Instructional Design to Create Programming for Comprehensive ABA Treatment.” Behavior Analysis in Practice 17, no. 2: 371–388. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40617‐024‐00908‐2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lavoie‐Tremblay, M., C. Gélinas, T. Aubé, et al. 2022. “Influence of Caring for COVID‐19 Patients on Nurse's Turnover, Work Satisfaction and Quality of Care.” Journal of Nursing Management 30, no. 1: 33–43. https://doi.org/10.1111/jonm.13462.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, D. F., C. X. Shi, F. Z. Shi, L. Zhao, R. Zhao, and W. Q. Kang. 2020. “Effects of Simulation Training on COVID‐19 Control Ability and Psychological States of Nurses in a Children's Hospital.” European Review for Medical and Pharmacological Sciences 24, no. 21: 11381–11385. https://doi.org/10.26355/eurrev_202011_23630.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lorente, L., M. Vera, and T. Peiró. 2021. “Nurses' Stressors and Psychological Distress During the COVID‐19 Pandemic: The Mediating Role of Coping and Resilience.” Journal of Advanced Nursing 77, no. 3: 1335–1344. https://doi.org/10.1111/jan.14695.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahnaz, E., B. Nasim, and O. Sonia. 2020. “Effect of a Structured Educational Package on Women's Sexual Function During Pregnancy.” International Journal of Gynaecology and Obstetrics 148, no. 2: 225–230. https://doi.org/10.1002/ijgo.13051.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malan, Z., B. Mash, and K. Everett‐Murphy. 2015. “Development of a Training Programme for Primary Care Providers to Counsel Patients With Risky Lifestyle Behaviours in South Africa.” African Journal of Primary Health Care &amp; Family Medicine 7, no. 1: 819. https://doi.org/10.4102/phcfm.v7i1.819.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munzer, B. W., B. S. Bassin, W. J. Peterson, et al. 2020. “In‐Situ Simulation Use for Rapid Implementation and Process Improvement of COVID‐19 Airway Management.” Western Journal of Emergency Medicine 21, no. 6: 99–106. https://doi.org/10.5811/westjem.2020.7.48159.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naidoo, N., A. J. Azar, A. H. Khamis, et al. 2021. “Design, Implementation, and Evaluation of a Distance Learning Framework to Adapt to the Changing Landscape of Anatomy Instruction in Medical Education During COVID‐19 Pandemic: A Proof‐of‐Concept Study.” Frontiers in Public Health 9: 726814. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpubh.2021.726814.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nalla, A. K., A. M. Casto, M. W. Huang, et al. 2020. “Comparative Performance of SARS‐CoV‐2 Detection Assays Using Seven Different Primer‐Probe Sets and One Assay Kit.” Journal of Clinical Microbiology 58, no. 6: e00557‐20. https://doi.org/10.1128/jcm.00557‐20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noh, J., E. G. Oh, S. S. Kim, Y. S. Jang, H. S. Chung, and O. Lee. 2020. “Development and Evaluation of a Multimodality Simulation Disaster Education and Training Program for Hospital Nurses.” International Journal of Nursing Practice 26, no. 3: e12810. https://doi.org/10.1111/ijn.12810.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O'Keeffe, D. A., D. Bradley, L. Evans, et al. 2016. “Ebola Emergency Preparedness: Simulation Training for Frontline Health Care Professionals.” MedEdPORTAL 12: 10433. https://doi.org/10.15766/mep_2374‐8265.10433.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ozdilek, Z., and E. Robeck. 2009. “Operational Priorities of Instructional Designers Analyzed Within the Steps of the Addie Instructional Design Model.” Procedia—Social and Behavioral Sciences 1: 2046–2050. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.sbspro.2009.01.359.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park, E. W., H. Lee, and E. K. Yun. 2019. “Development and Evaluation of a Quick Response Code‐Based Nursing Education Program for Operating and Recovery Room Nurses.” Computers, Informatics, Nursing 37, no. 11: 599–605. https://doi.org/10.1097/cin.0000000000000550.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng, W., D. Li‐li, Y. Ling‐li, Z. Ping, Z. Ying‐li, and Q. Min‐ke. 2019. “Evaluation of the Application Effects of Diversified Training Mode in the Prevention and Control of Nosocomial Infection Among Medical Staff.” Chinese Journal of Nosocomiology 29, no. 16: 2533–2536.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piché‐Renaud, P. P., H. E. Groves, T. Kitano, et al. 2021. “Healthcare Worker Perception of a Global Outbreak of Novel Coronavirus (COVID‐19) and Personal Protective Equipment: Survey of a Pediatric Tertiary‐Care Hospital.” Infection Control and Hospital Epidemiology 42, no. 3: 261–267. https://doi.org/10.1017/ice.2020.415.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piras, A., D. Rizzo, S. Uzzau, G. De Riu, S. Rubino, and F. Bussu. 2020. “Inappropriate Nasopharyngeal Sampling for SARS‐CoV‐2 Detection Is a Relevant Cause of False‐Negative Reports.” Otolaryngology and Head and Neck Surgery 163, no. 3: 459–461. https://doi.org/10.1177/0194599820931793.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rowlands, A. 2007. “Medical Social Work Practice and SARS in Singapore.” Social Work in Health Care 45, no. 3: 57–83. https://doi.org/10.1300/J010v45n03_04.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seitz, R. M., A. Q. Yaffee, E. Peacock, T. P. Moran, A. Pendley, and J. D. Rupp. 2021. “Self‐Reported Use of Personal Protective Equipment Among Emergency Department Nurses, Physicians and Advanced Practice Providers During the 2020 COVID‐19 Pandemic.” International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health 18, no. 13: 7076. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph18137076.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shrestha, A., A. Shrestha, T. Sonnenberg, and R. Shrestha. 2020. “COVID‐19 Emergency Department Protocols: Experience of Protocol Implementation Through In‐Situ Simulation.” Open Access Emergency Medicine 12: 293–303. https://doi.org/10.2147/oaem.S266702.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shrestha, L. B., and K. Pokharel. 2020. “Standard Operating Procedure for Specimen Collection, Packaging and Transport for Diagnosis of SARS‐COV‐2.” Journal of the Nepal Medical Association 58, no. 228: 627–629. https://doi.org/10.31729/jnma.5260.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smidt, A., S. Balandin, J. Sigafoos, and V. A. Reed. 2009. “The Kirkpatrick Model: A Useful Tool for Evaluating Training Outcomes.” Journal of Intellectual &amp; Developmental Disability 34, no. 3: 266–274. https://doi.org/10.1080/13668250903093125.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang, Y. W., J. E. Schmitz, D. H. Persing, and C. W. Stratton. 2020. “Laboratory Diagnosis of COVID‐19: Current Issues and Challenges.” Journal of Clinical Microbiology 58, no. 6: e00512‐20. https://doi.org/10.1128/jcm.00512‐20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tian, F., H. Li, S. Tian, J. Yang, J. Shao, and C. Tian. 2020. “Psychological Symptoms of Ordinary Chinese Citizens Based on SCL‐90 During the Level I Emergency Response to COVID‐19.” Psychiatry Research 288: 112992. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.psychres.2020.112992.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsioutis, C., G. Birgand, E. Bathoorn, et al. 2020. “Education and Training Programmes for Infection Prevention and Control Professionals: Mapping the Current Opportunities and Local Needs in European Countries.” Antimicrobial Resistance and Infection Control 9, no. 1: 183. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13756‐020‐00835‐1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, D., B. Hu, C. Hu, et al. 2020. “Clinical Characteristics of 138 Hospitalized Patients With 2019 Novel Coronavirus‐Infected Pneumonia in Wuhan, China.” JAMA 323, no. 11: 1061–1069. https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2020.1585.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ward, D. J. 2011. “The Role of Education in the Prevention and Control of Infection: A Review of the Literature.” Nurse Education Today 31, no. 1: 9–17. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.nedt.2010.03.007.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, T., X. Jia, H. Shi, et al. 2021. “Prevalence of Mental Health Problems During the COVID‐19 Pandemic: A Systematic Review and Meta‐Analysis.” Journal of Affective Disorders 281: 91–98. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jad.2020.11.117.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xinjuan, W., G. Na, C. Jing, et al. 2020. “Establishment and Implementation of Standardized Training Program on Prevention and Control of Coronavirus Disease 2019 in General Hospitals.” Chinese Journal of Nursing 55, no. 4: 500–503.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xueyan, H., Z. Yingyin, F. Ying, Y. Qi, and G. Fang. 2018. “Evaluation of Effects of Traditional Chinese Medicine Nursing Training Based on Kirkpatrick's Model.” Chinese Journal of Nursing 53, no. 1: 71–75.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu, L., W. Hui, C. Junhua, et al. 2020. “Emergency Management of Nursing Human Resources and Material Resources for Coronavirus Disease 2019.” Chinese Journal of Nursing 55, no. 3: 343–346.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, J., H. Chen, X. Wang, X. Huang, and D. Xie. 2024. “Application of Flipped Classroom Teaching Method Based on ADDIE Concept in Clinical Teaching for Neurology Residents.” BMC Medical Education 24, no. 1: 366. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12909‐024‐05343‐z.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng, R., Y. Zhou, M. Qiu, et al. 2021. “Prevalence and Associated Factors of Depression, Anxiety, and Stress Among Hubei Pediatric Nurses During COVID‐19 Pandemic.” Comprehensive Psychiatry 104: 152217. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.comppsych.2020.152217.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>