<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39553294</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2196-5226</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>19</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>GMS hygiene and infection control</Title><ISOAbbreviation>GMS Hyg Infect Control</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Can the use of iron phthalocyanine-derivative mouthrinses in COVID-19 patients provide systemic benefits? Research into this potential should be considered.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>Doc45</StartPage><MedlinePgn>Doc45</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">Doc45</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3205/dgkh000500</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="AIM" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The purpose of this brief report is to discuss the impact of an oral rinse and spray containing an iron phthalocyanine derivative as an additional therapy in hospitalized COVID-19 patients.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">In the first study by this group of authors published on this topic, the clinical status of 22 patients with COVID-19 who were hospitalized and receiving PDMS (phthalocyanine derivative mouth spray) was assessed using the Karnofsky scale (KS) for thtree days (D0, D2, and D4). In another study, the laboratory data (CBC, D-dimer, Ferritin, and C-reactive protein [CRP]) of 41 patients hospitalized with COVID-19 who took part in a randomized clinical trial with an MIPD (mouthwash with iron phthalocyanine derivative) were evaluated retrospectively on the first day of intervention (D1) and 48 hours later (D2). The present study used these data to determine a correlation between clinical symptoms and laboratory data.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">In individuals receiving PDMS and evaluated using the KS, a statistically significant intra-group difference (p=0.03, Friedman's test) was identified. The Durbin-Conover test found a significant difference between D0 and D2 (p=0.008). Laboratory data from only 9 patients in the experimental group and 13 patients in the control group were found in the retrospective analysis. There were no statistically significant confounders in the survival analysis using the Cox regression model. In the descriptive analysis, the intervention group's CRP was lower than that of the control group.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">PDMS demonstrated considerable clinical improvement in patients, whereas MIPD appears to lower CRP, an inflammatory marker, in descriptive analysis.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 da Fonseca Orcina et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>da Fonseca Orcina</LastName><ForeName>Bernardo</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Surgery, Stomatology, Pathology and Radiology, Bauru School of Dentistry, University of São Paulo, Bauru, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bertin</LastName><ForeName>Laura</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Surgery, Stomatology, Pathology and Radiology, Bauru School of Dentistry, University of São Paulo, Bauru, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Izu Nakamura Pietro</LastName><ForeName>Emilene Cristine</ForeName><Initials>EC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hospital Estadual de Bauru, Bauru, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pescinelli Garcia Kuroda</LastName><ForeName>Juliana</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hospital Estadual de Bauru, Bauru, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Marques da Costa Alves</LastName><ForeName>Lucas</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hospital Estadual de Bauru, Bauru, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vieira Vilhena</LastName><ForeName>Fabiano</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>TRIALS - Oral Health &amp; Technologies, Bauru,Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>da Silva Santos</LastName><ForeName>Paulo Sérgio</ForeName><Initials>PS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Surgery, Stomatology, Pathology and Radiology, Bauru School of Dentistry, University of São Paulo, Bauru, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>02</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>GMS Hyg Infect Control</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101609519</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2196-5226</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><OtherAbstract Type="Publisher" Language="ger"><AbstractText Label="ZIELSETZUNG" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">In diesem Kurzbericht werden die Auswirkungen einer Mundspülung und eines Sprays mit einem Eisenphthalocyanin-Derivat als Zusatztherapie bei hospitalisierten COVID-19-Patienten erörtert.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODEN" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">In der ersten Studie wurde der klinische Zustand von 22 Patienten mit COVID-19, die stationär aufgenommen wurden und PDMS (Phthalocyanin-Derivat-Mundspray) erhielten, vier Tage lang (D0, D2 und D4) anhand der Karnofsky-Skala bewertet. In einer weiteren Studie wurden bei 41 Patienten mit COVID-19 im Krankenhaus, die an einer randomisierten klinischen Studie mit einem MIPD (Mundspray mit Eisenphthalocyanin-Derivat) teilnahmen, die Labordaten (CBC, D-Dimer, Ferritin und C-reaktives Protein (CRP)) am ersten Tag der Intervention (D1) und 48 h später (D2) retrospektiv bewertet.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="ERGEBNISSE" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Bei den Personen mit KS, die PDMS erhielten, wurde mit Hilfe des Friedman-Tests ein statistischer Unterschied zwischen den Gruppen festgestellt (p=0,03). Der Durbin-Conover-Test ergab einen signifikanten Unterschied zwischen D0 und D2 (p=0,008). In der retrospektiven Analyse wurden nur Daten von 9 Patienten in der Experimentalgruppe und 13 Patienten in der Kontrollgruppe gefunden. Bei der Überlebensanalyse mit dem Cox-Regressionsmodell gab es keine statistisch signifikanten Störfaktoren. In der deskriptiven Analyse war das CRP in der Interventionsgruppe niedriger als in der Kontrollgruppe.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="SCHLUSSFOLGERUNGEN" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Die PDMS zeigte eine erhebliche klinische Verbesserung bei den Patienten, während die MIPD in einer deskriptiven Analyse den Entzündungsmarker CRP zu senken scheint.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024 da Fonseca Orcina et al.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">dentistry</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">hospitalization</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mouthwashes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">oral sprays</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">supporting COVID-19 therapy</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Dr. F. V. Vilhena has a patent. The other authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39553294</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11565403</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3205/dgkh000500</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">dgkh000500</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Deuel JW, Lauria E, Lovey T, Zweifel S, Meier MI, Züst R, Gültekin N, Stettbacher A, Schlagenhauf P. Persistence, prevalence, and polymorphism of sequelae after COVID-19 in unvaccinated, young adults of the Swiss Armed Forces: a longitudinal, cohort study (LoCoMo) Lancet Infect Dis. 2022 Dec;22(12):1694–1702. doi: 10.1016/S1473-3099(22)00449-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(22)00449-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9411260</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36030795</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nehme M, Vetter P, Chappuis F, Kaiser L, Guessous I CoviCare Study Team. Prevalence of Post-Coronavirus Disease Condition 12 Weeks After Omicron Infection Compared With Negative Controls and Association With Vaccination Status. Clin Infect Dis. 2023 May;76(9):1567–1575. doi: 10.1093/cid/ciac947.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/ciac947</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36519381</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoffmann M, Kleine-Weber H, Schroeder S, Krüger N, Herrler T, Erichsen S, Schiergens TS, Herrler G, Wu NH, Nitsche A, Müller MA, Drosten C, Pöhlmann S. SARS-CoV-2 Cell Entry Depends on ACE2 and TMPRSS2 and Is Blocked by a Clinically Proven Protease Inhibitor. Cell. 2020 Apr;181(2):271–280. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2020.02.052.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2020.02.052</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7102627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32142651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhong M, Lin B, Pathak JL, Gao H, Young AJ, Wang X, Liu C, Wu K, Liu M, Chen JM, Huang J, Lee LH, Qi CL, Ge L, Wang L. ACE2 and Furin Expressions in Oral Epithelial Cells Possibly Facilitate COVID-19 Infection via Respiratory and Fecal-Oral Routes. Front Med (Lausanne) 2020;7:580796. doi: 10.3389/fmed.2020.580796.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmed.2020.580796</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7758442</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33363183</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen L, Zhao J, Peng J, Li X, Deng X, Geng Z, Shen Z, Guo F, Zhang Q, Jin Y, Wang L, Wang S. Detection of SARS-CoV-2 in saliva and characterization of oral symptoms in COVID-19 patients. Cell Prolif. 2020 Dec;53(12):e12923. doi: 10.1111/cpr.12923.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/cpr.12923</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7645955</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33073910</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang N, Pérez P, Kato T, Mikami Y, Okuda K, Gilmore RC, Conde CD, Gasmi B, Stein S, Beach M, Pelayo E, Maldonado JO, Lafont BA, Jang SI, Nasir N, Padilla RJ, Murrah VA, Maile R, Lovell W, Wallet SM, Bowman NM, Meinig SL, Wolfgang MC, Choudhury SN, Novotny M, Aevermann BD, Scheuermann RH, Cannon G, Anderson CW, Lee RE, Marchesan JT, Bush M, Freire M, Kimple AJ, Herr DL, Rabin J, Grazioli A, Das S, French BN, Pranzatelli T, Chiorini JA, Kleiner DE, Pittaluga S, Hewitt SM, Burbelo PD, Chertow D NIH COVID-19 Autopsy Consortium; HCA Oral and Craniofacial Biological NetworkFrank K, Lee J, Boucher RC, Teichmann SA, Warner BM, Byrd KM. SARS-CoV-2 infection of the oral cavity and saliva. Nat Med. 2021 May;27(5):892–903. doi: 10.1038/s41591-021-01296-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41591-021-01296-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8240394</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33767405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matuck BF, Dolhnikoff M, Maia GVA, Isaac Sendyk D, Zarpellon A, Costa Gomes S, Duarte-Neto AN, Rebello Pinho JR, Gomes-Gouvêa MS, Sousa SCOM, Mauad T, Saldiva PHDN, Braz-Silva PH, da Silva LFF. Periodontal tissues are targets for Sars-Cov-2: a post-mortem study. J Oral Microbiol. 2020 Nov;13(1):1848135. doi: 10.1080/20002297.2020.1848135.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/20002297.2020.1848135</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7717160</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33391625</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Matuck BF, Dolhnikoff M, Duarte-Neto AN, Maia G, Gomes SC, Sendyk DI, Zarpellon A, de Andrade NP, Monteiro RA, Pinho JRR, Gomes-Gouvêa MS, Souza SC, Kanamura C, Mauad T, Saldiva PHN, Braz-Silva PH, Caldini EG, da Silva LFF. Salivary glands are a target for SARS-CoV-2: a source for saliva contamination. J Pathol. 2021 Jul;254(3):239–243. doi: 10.1002/path.5679.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/path.5679</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8250228</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33834497</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vilhena FV, Brito Reia VC, da Fonseca Orcina B, Santos CA, Zangrando M, Cardoso de Oliveira R, da Silva Santos PS. The use of antiviral Phthalocyanine mouthwash as a preventive measure against COVID-19. GMS Hyg Infect Control. 2021;16:Doc24. doi: 10.3205/dgkh000395.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3205/dgkh000395</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8299057</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34354903</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan American Health Organization; World Health Organization. Manejo Clínico da COVID-19. 27 de maio de 2020. Washington (DC): Pan American Health Organization; 2020.  [Last access 2023 Oct 03].  Available from:  https://www.paho.org/pt/taxonomy/term/13. Last access October 3, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orcina BF, Vilhena FV, Cardoso de Oliveira R, Marques da Costa Alves L, Araki K, Toma SH, Ragghianti Zangrando MS, da Silva Santos PS. A Phthalocyanine Derivate Mouthwash to Gargling/Rinsing as an Option to Reduce Clinical Symptoms of COVID-19: Case Series. Clin Cosmet Investig Dent. 2021;13:47–50. doi: 10.2147/CCIDE.S295423.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2147/CCIDE.S295423</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7899311</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33628060</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orcina BF, Santos PSS. Oral manifestation COVID-19 and the rapid resolution of symptoms post-phtalox treatment: A case series. Int J Odontostomat. 2021;15(1):67–70. doi: 10.4067/S0718-381X2021000100067.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4067/S0718-381X2021000100067</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vilhena FV, Orcina BDF, Lemos L, Less JCF, Pinto I, Santos PSDS. Elimination of SARS-CoV-2 in nasopharynx and oropharynx after use of an adjuvant gargling and rinsing protocol with an antiseptic mouthwash. Einstein (Sao Paulo) 2022;19:eCE6999. doi: 10.31744/einstein_journal/2021CE6999.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.31744/einstein_journal/2021CE6999</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8693883</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35019040</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orcina BDF, Pietro ECIN, Kuroda JPG, Alves LMDC, Zangrando MSR, Oliveira RC, Simão ANC, Vilhena FV, Santos PSDS. Oral Antiseptic Spray Containing Phthalocyanine Solution Reduced Saliva SARS-CoV-2 Viral Load: Case Series. Int Arch Otorhinolaryngol. 2022 Jul;26(3):e293–e295. doi: 10.1055/s-0042-1750202.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1055/s-0042-1750202</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9282974</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35846829</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>da Silva Santos PS, da Fonseca Orcina B, Machado RRG, Vilhena FV, da Costa Alves LM, Zangrando MSR, de Oliveira RC, Soares MQS, Simão ANC, Pietro ECIN, Kuroda JPG, de Almeida Benjamim IA, Araujo DB, Toma SH, Flor L, Araki K, Durigon EL. Beneficial effects of a mouthwash containing an antiviral phthalocyanine derivative on the length of hospital stay for COVID-19: randomised trial. Sci Rep. 2021 Oct;11(1):19937. doi: 10.1038/s41598-021-99013-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-99013-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8497631</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34620904</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (WHO) (2021) COVID-19 clinical management: living guidance.  [Cited 2021 May 13].  Available from:  https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/clinical-management-of-covid-19.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karnofsky DA, Burchenal JH. In: The Clinical Evaluation of Chemotherapeutic Agents in Cancer. MacLeod CM, editor. Columbia University Press; 1949. pp. 191–205.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moussaron A, Arnoux P, Vanderesse R, Sibille E, Chaimbault P, Frochot C. Lipophilic phthalocyanines for their potential interest in photodynamic therapy: Synthesis and photo-physical properties. Tetrahedron. 2013;69(47):10116–10122. doi: 10.1016/j.tet.2013.09.035.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tet.2013.09.035</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heugebaert TS, Roman BI, Stevens CV. Synthesis of isoindoles and related iso-condensed heteroaromatic pyrroles. Chem Soc Rev. 2012 Sep;41(17):5626–5640. doi: 10.1039/c2cs35093a.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/c2cs35093a</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22782188</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Encinar JA, Menendez JA. Potential Drugs Targeting Early Innate Immune Evasion of SARS-Coronavirus 2 via 2'-O-Methylation of Viral RNA. Viruses. 2020 May;12(5):525. doi: 10.3390/v12050525.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/v12050525</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7291090</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32397643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Romeo A, Iacovelli F, Falconi M. Targeting the SARS-CoV-2 spike glycoprotein prefusion conformation: virtual screening and molecular dynamics simulations applied to the identification of potential fusion inhibitors. Virus Res. 2020 Sep;286:198068. doi: 10.1016/j.virusres.2020.198068.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.virusres.2020.198068</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7301794</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32565126</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>