<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39553635</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2405-8440</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>10</Volume><Issue>21</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>15</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Heliyon</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Heliyon</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Prospects of <i>Carica papaya</i> in the treatment of human viral infections: A comprehensive and a systematic review.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e39635</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e39635</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e39635</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e39635</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Viruses cause various human diseases, some of which become pandemic outbreaks lack effective treatments and vaccines. This study gathered data on Carica papaya's antiviral effects against various human viruses, highlighting its potential as a natural treatment. Through <i>in-vitro</i>, <i>in-vivo</i>, and clinical study analysis, we illustrated the potential of Carica papaya in combating viral infections and its potential role in cure of common viral diseases.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHOD" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">ology: Research papers on antiviral activity of Carica papaya were identified by using specific keywords in PUBMED, Google Scholar, and ScienceDirect databases. Articles published between January 2015 and March 2024 were screened for inclusion. Eligible studies utilized Carica papaya leaves (powder or juice) or fruits to investigate their effects against human viral infections. Each selected study applied either qualitative or quantitative antiviral assays to assess the efficacy of Carica papaya in combating human viruses.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Fifteen studies went through assessment for antiviral properties of Carica papaya, 7 (46.67 %) of them displayed significant activity against the dengue virus, while 1 study (6.67 %) demonstrated moderate/less effectiveness against dengue serotype-2. Two studies (13.33 %) found no anti-dengue effects. Additionally, Carica papaya exhibited strong antiviral activity against SARS-CoV-2 in 2 studies (13.33 %). One study (6.67 %) showed inhibition of both dengue serotype-2 and chikungunya, and 1 study (6.67 %) each demonstrated inhibitory effects against human immunodeficiency virus and Zika virus infections.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The present study listed human diseases for which Carica papaya revealed significant antiviral effects against Dengue virus, Severe acute respiratory syndrome, Human immunodeficiency virus-I, Chikungunya virus and Zika virus suggesting its potential as a treatment candidate for all these viruses. However, the majority of the research involved <i>in-vitro</i> screening, with minimal <i>in-vivo</i> and clinical testing. Further <i>in-vivo</i> studies and clinical trials should be conducted to explore the potential of Carica papaya in the treatment of human viral infections.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Masooma</LastName><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Atta-ur-Rehman School of Applied Biosciences, National University of Sciences and Technology H-12 Islamabad, Islamabad Capital Territory, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Qaiser</LastName><ForeName>Ariba</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Atta-ur-Rehman School of Applied Biosciences, National University of Sciences and Technology H-12 Islamabad, Islamabad Capital Territory, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ali</LastName><ForeName>Dr Sajid</ForeName><Initials>DS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biotechnology Abdul Wali Khan University Mardan, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Manzoor</LastName><ForeName>Dr Sobia</ForeName><Initials>DS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Atta-ur-Rehman School of Applied Biosciences, National University of Sciences and Technology H-12 Islamabad, Islamabad Capital Territory, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Heliyon</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101672560</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2405-8440</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Anti dengue</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Antiviral agent</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Carica papaya extract</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Fruits</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Leaves</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Virus titer</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Viruses</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>8</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39553635</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11566848</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e39635</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2405-8440(24)15666-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Babalola B.A., Akinwande A.I., Gboyega A.E., Otunba A.A. Extraction, purification and characterization of papain cysteine-proteases from the leaves of Carica papaya. Sci Afr. 2023 Mar 1;19</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shinde A, Kolhe D, Hase DDP, Chavan DMJ. A brief introduction about carica papaya linn. World J Pharm Res.9(12).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Urgessa O.E., Itana D.D., Raga T.O. Extraction of papain from papaya (carica papaya L.) fruit latex and its application in transforming tannery raw trimming. Ethiop J Sci Sustain Dev. 2019 Sep 9;6(2):22–32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ayodipupo Babalola B., Ifeolu Akinwande A., Otunba A.A., Ebenezer Adebami G., Babalola O., Nwufo C. Therapeutic benefits of Carica papaya: a review on its pharmacological activities and characterization of papain. Arab. J. Chem. 2024 Jan 1;17(1)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fatima U., Shahid S. Pharmacological activities of carica papaya Linn. J. Basic Appl. Sci. 2018 Jun 22;14:210–216.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghaffarilaleh V., Fisher D., Henkel R. Carica papaya seed extract slows human sperm. J. Ethnopharmacol. 2019 Sep;241</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31128152</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>K A., M R.K., Pa S.B., Gowda S.K., Ajay A., Baby B. Ethanobotonical and biological activities of Carica papaya Linn: a review. Int J Pharm Drug Anal. 2020 Aug 15:1–5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adel A., S, Elnaggar M., Albohy A., A, Elrashedy A., Mostafa A., Kutkat O., et al. Evaluation of antiviral activity of Carica papaya leaves against SARS-CoV-2 assisted by metabolomic profiling. RSC Adv. 2022;12(51):32844–32852.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9667237</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36425179</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adel A., Elnaggar M.S., Al-Sayed E., Rabeh M.A. Secondary metabolites from carica papaya, and its biological activities: a comprehensive review. Arch Pharm Sci Ain Shams Univ. 2021 Dec 1;5(2):331–353.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shyr Z.A., Cheng Y.S., Lo D.C., Zheng W. Drug combination therapy for emerging viral diseases. Drug Discov. Today. 2021 Oct 1;26(10):2367–2376.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8139175</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34023496</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shin J.S., Jung E., Kim M., Baric R.S., Go Y.Y. Saracatinib inhibits Middle East respiratory syndrome-coronavirus replication in vitro. Viruses. 2018 Jun;10(6):283.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6024778</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29795047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mattio L.M., Catinella G., Pinto A., Dallavalle S. Natural and nature-inspired stilbenoids as antiviral agents. Eur. J. Med. Chem. 2020 Sep 15;202</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7335248</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32652408</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salehi B., Kumar N.V.A., Şener B., Sharifi-Rad M., Kılıç M., Mahady G.B., et al. Medicinal plants used in the treatment of human immunodeficiency virus. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 2018 May;19(5):1459.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5983620</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29757986</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jadaun P., Shah P., Harshithkumar R., Said M.S., Bhoite S.P., Bokuri S., et al. Antiviral and ROS scavenging potential of Carica papaya Linn and Psidium guajava leaves extract against HIV-1 infection. BMC Complement Med Ther. 2023 Mar 18;23(1):82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10024014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36934258</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haddad J.G., Carcauzon V., El Kalamouni O., Desprès P., Garcia C., Remize F., et al. Papaya fruit pulp and resulting lactic fermented pulp exert antiviral activity against Zika virus. Microorganisms. 2020 Aug 20;8(9):1257.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7565477</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32825246</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohd Abd Razak MR., Mohmad Misnan N., Md Jelas N.H., Norahmad N.A., Muhammad A., Ho T.C.D., et al. The effect of freeze-dried Carica papaya leaf juice treatment on NS1 and viremia levels in dengue fever mice model. BMC Complement Altern Med. 2018 Dec 5;18(1):320.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6282281</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30518360</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Norahmad N.A., Mohd Abd Razak M.R., Mohmad Misnan N., Md Jelas N.H., Sastu U.R., Muhammad A., et al. Effect of freeze-dried Carica papaya leaf juice on inflammatory cytokines production during dengue virus infection in AG129 mice. BMC Complement Altern Med. 2019 Feb 11;19(1):44.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6371484</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30744623</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohd Abd Razak M.R., Norahmad N.A., Md Jelas N.H., Afzan A., Mohmad Misnan N., Mat Ripen A., et al. Immunomodulatory activities of carica papaya L. Leaf juice in a non-lethal, symptomatic dengue mouse model. Pathogens. 2021 May;10(5):501.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8170887</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33919457</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amin I., Jahan N., Malkani N., Amin S., Nadeem S.I. Inhibitory activities of methanolic extracts of carica papaya, mentha piperita and Citrullus colocynthis against dengue viruses-2 viability: lahore garrison. Univ J Life Sci. 2023 Dec 20;7(4):515–529.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hariono M., Hidayat I., Djunarko I., Julianus J., Saqallah F.G., Khawory M.H., et al.  Carica papaya leaf extract inhibits SARS-CoV-2 main proteases but not human TMPRSS2: an in-vitro and in-silico study [internet] arXiv. 2022 http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.00273 [cited 2024 Jan 19]. Available from:</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma N., Mishra K.P., Chanda S., Bhardwaj V., Tanwar H., Ganju L., et al. Evaluation of anti-dengue activity of Carica papaya aqueous leaf extract and its role in platelet augmentation. Arch. Virol. 2019 Apr 1;164(4):1095–1110.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30790105</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joseph B., Sankarganesh P., Ichiyama K., Yamamoto N. In vitro study on cytotoxic effect and anti-DENV2 activity of Carica papaya L. leaf. Front. Life Sci. 2015 Jan 2;8(1):18–22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thao T.T.P., Dung N.T., Ninh P.T., Van Chien T., Anh H.N., Hau V.T.B., et al. Phytochemistry of the unpolar extract of Carica papaya leaves and its antidengue activity. Vietnam J Chem. 2022;60(6):777–783.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bere A.W., Mulati O., Kimotho J., Ng’ong’a F. Carica papaya leaf extract silver synthesized nanoparticles inhibit dengue type 2 viral replication in vitro. Pharmaceuticals. 2021 Aug;14(8):718.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8400503</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34451815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sathyapalan D.T., Padmanabhan A., Moni M., P-Prabhu B., Prasanna P., Balachandran S., et al. Efficacy &amp; safety of Carica papaya leaf extract (CPLE) in severe thrombocytopenia (≤30,000/μl) in adult dengue – results of a pilot study. PLoS One. 2020 Feb 19;15(2)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7029881</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32074143</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agfata F., Ma’rufah S., Saptawati L., Yuliasari Istifadah D., Mirawati T., et al. Screening of carica papaya L. And psidium guajava leaves fraction as antiviral drug to dengue virus. Teikyo Med. J. 2021 Feb 1;44:667–675.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patil P., Alagarasu K., Chowdhury D., Kakade M., Cherian S., Kaushik S., et al. In-vitro antiviral activity of Carica papaya formulations against dengue virus type 2 and chikungunya virus. Heliyon. 2022 Dec;8(12)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9723942</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36483307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abad M.J., Guerra J.A., Bermejo P., Irurzun A., Carrasco L. Search for antiviral activity in higher plant extracts. Phytother Res. 2000;14(8):604–607.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11113996</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adhikari B., Marasini B.P., Rayamajhee B., Bhattarai B.R., Lamichhane G., Khadayat K., et al. Potential roles of medicinal plants for the treatment of viral diseases focusing on COVID-19: a review. Phytother Res. 2021;35(3):1298–1312.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7675695</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33037698</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alayli F., Scholle F. Dengue virus NS1 enhances viral replication and pro-inflammatory cytokine production in human dendritic cells. Virology. 2016 Sep 1;496:227–236.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4969143</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27348054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Senthilvel P., Lavanya P., Kumar K.M., Swetha R., Anitha P., Bag S., et al. Flavonoid from Carica papaya inhibits NS2B-NS3 protease and prevents Dengue 2 viral assembly. Bioinformation. 2013;9(18):889–895.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3842573</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24307765</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bok Z.K., Balakrishnan M., Jong Y.X., Kong Y.R., Khaw K.Y., Ong Y.S. The plausible mechanisms of action of Carica papaya on Dengue infection: a comprehensive review. Prog Drug Discov Biomed Sci [Internet] 2020 Aug 6;3(1) https://journals.hh-publisher.com/index.php/pddbs/article/view/299 [cited 2024 Sep. 4] Available from:</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. V, R. M. S, B. R. H Role of Carica papaya leaf extract tablets/capsules on platelet counts in cases of dengue thrombocytopenia. Int J Adv Med. 2018 Jul 23;5(4):845.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hettige S. Salutary effects of carica papaya leaf extract in dengue fever patients – a pilot study. 2008;29(1)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jayasinghe C.D., Gunasekera D.S., De Silva N., Jayawardena K.K.M., Udagama P.V. Mature leaf concentrate of Sri Lankan wild type Carica papaya Linn. modulates nonfunctional and functional immune responses of rats. BMC Complement Altern Med. 2017 Apr 26;17(1):230.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5406937</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28446195</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haggag E., Elshamy A., Rabeh M., Gabr N., Salem M., Youssif K., et al. Antiviral potential of green synthesized silver nanoparticles of Lampranthus coccineus and Malephora lutea. Int J Nanomedicine. 2019 Aug;14:6217–6229.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6690046</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31496682</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hariyono P., Patramurti C., Candrasari D.S., Hariono M. An integrated virtual screening of compounds from Carica papaya leaves against multiple protein targets of SARS-Coronavirus-2. Results Chem. 2021 Jan 1;3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7889459</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33619449</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rashed K., Luo M.T., Zhang L.T., Zheng Y.T. Phytochemical screening of the polar extracts of Carica papaya Linn. and the evaluation of their anti- HIV-1 activity. 2013;1:49–53.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yogiraj V, Goyal PK, Chauhan CS, Vyas B. Carica papaya Linn: an overview. Int. J. Herb. Med. 2014;2:01–08.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keramagi A.R., Skariyachan S. Prediction of binding potential of natural leads against the prioritized drug targets of chikungunya and dengue viruses by computational screening. 3 Biotech. 2018 May 26;8(6):274.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5971020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29868312</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roy A., Lim L., Song J. Identification of quercetin from fruits to immediately fight Zika [Internet] 2016. http://biorxiv.org/lookup/doi/10.1101/074559 [cited 2024 Jun 5]. Available from:</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/074559</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banjan B, Krishnan D, Koshy AJ, Soman S, Leelamma A, Raju R, et al. In-silico screening and identification of potential drug-like compounds for dengue-associated thrombocytopenia from Carica papaya leaf extracts. J. Biomol. Struct. Dyn. 2024 Jul 23;42(11):5963–5981.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37394810</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>