<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39557769</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1573-4927</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>18</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Biochemical genetics</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Biochem Genet</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Identification of Novel Genomic Variants in COVID-19 Patients Using Whole-Exome Sequencing: Exploring the Plausible Targets of Functional Genomics.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s10528-024-10970-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Covid-19 caused by SARS-CoV-2 virus has emerged as an immense burden and an unparalleled global health challenge in recorded human history. The clinical characteristics and risk factors of COVID-19 exhibit considerable variability, leading to a spectrum of clinical severity. Moreover, the likelihood of exposure to the virus may differ based on comorbidity status as comorbid illnesses have mechanisms that can considerably increase mortality by reducing the body's ability to withstand injury. The mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR) pathway is essential for orchestrating innate immune cell defense, including cytokine production and is dysregulated in severe Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) individuals. Through genome-wide, association studies, numerous genetic variants in the human host have been identified that have a significant impact on the immune response to SARS-CoV-2. To identify potentially significant genetic variants in Covid-19 patients that could affect the risk, severity, and clinical outcome of the infection, this study has used whole-exome sequencing (WES) on the 16 COVID-19 patients with varying comorbidities and severity of the disease including fatal outcomes. Among them, 8 patients made a full recovery and were discharged, while 8 patients unfortunately did not survive due to the severity of the illness and majority of them were males. The study identified 10,204 variants in the patients. From 1120 variants, which were chosen for novel variant analysis using mutation, function prediction tools to identify deleterious variants that could affect normal gene function, 116 variants of 57 genes were found to be deleterious. These variants were further classified as likely pathogenic and variants of uncertain significance. The data showed that among the likely pathogenic variants five genes were identified in connection to immune response whereas two were related to respiratory system. The common variants associated with the covid-19 phenotype showed the top 10 significant genes identified in this study such as ERCC2, FBXO5, HTR3D, FAIM, DNAH17, MTOR, IGHMBP2, ZNF530, QSER1, and FOXRED2 with variant rs1057079 of the MTOR gene representing the highest odds ratio (1.7, p = 8.7e-04). The mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR) pathway variant rs1057079 was reported with high odds ratio, may orchestrate innate immune cell defense, including cytokine production, and is dysregulated. This study concluded that the mTOR signaling gene variant (rs1057079) is associated with different degrees of covid-19 severity and is essential for orchestrating innate immune cell defense including cytokine production. Inhibiting mTOR and its corresponding deleterious immune responses with medicinal approaches may provide a novel avenue for treating severe COVID-19 illness. Besides the PPI network exhibited a significantly high local clustering coefficient of 0.424 (p = 0.000536), suggesting the presence of tightly knit functional modules. These findings enhance our comprehension of the intricate interactions between genetic factors and COVID-19 disease.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer Science+Business Media, LLC, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mir</LastName><ForeName>Rashid</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Laboratory Technology Faculty of Applied Medical Sciences, Prince Fahad Bin Sultan Chair for Biomedical Research, University of Tabuk, 71491, Tabuk, Saudi Arabia. rashid@ut.edu.sa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Altemani</LastName><ForeName>Faisal A</ForeName><Initials>FA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Laboratory Technology Faculty of Applied Medical Sciences, Prince Fahad Bin Sultan Chair for Biomedical Research, University of Tabuk, 71491, Tabuk, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Algehainy</LastName><ForeName>Naseh A</ForeName><Initials>NA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Laboratory Technology Faculty of Applied Medical Sciences, Prince Fahad Bin Sultan Chair for Biomedical Research, University of Tabuk, 71491, Tabuk, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alanazi</LastName><ForeName>Mohammad A</ForeName><Initials>MA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Laboratory Technology Faculty of Applied Medical Sciences, Prince Fahad Bin Sultan Chair for Biomedical Research, University of Tabuk, 71491, Tabuk, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Elfaki</LastName><ForeName>Imadeldin</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biochemistry, Faculty of Science, University of Tabuk, 71491, Tabuk, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alsayed</LastName><ForeName>Badr A</ForeName><Initials>BA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, University of Tabuk, 71491, Tabuk, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mir</LastName><ForeName>Mohammad Muzaffar</ForeName><Initials>MM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Biochemistry, College of Medicine, University of Bisha, 61922, Bisha, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mustafa</LastName><ForeName>Syed Khalid</ForeName><Initials>SK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Chemistry, Faculty of Science, University of Tabuk, 71491, Tabuk, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Moawadh</LastName><ForeName>Mamdoh S</ForeName><Initials>MS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Laboratory Technology Faculty of Applied Medical Sciences, Prince Fahad Bin Sultan Chair for Biomedical Research, University of Tabuk, 71491, Tabuk, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tayeb</LastName><ForeName>Faris J</ForeName><Initials>FJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Laboratory Technology Faculty of Applied Medical Sciences, Prince Fahad Bin Sultan Chair for Biomedical Research, University of Tabuk, 71491, Tabuk, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alfailfi</LastName><ForeName>Jaber</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Child Health, College of Medicine, University of Bisha, 61922, Bisha, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alatawi</LastName><ForeName>Sael M</ForeName><Initials>SM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Laboratory Technology Faculty of Applied Medical Sciences, Prince Fahad Bin Sultan Chair for Biomedical Research, University of Tabuk, 71491, Tabuk, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alhiwety</LastName><ForeName>Mohammed Saad</ForeName><Initials>MS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>NEOM Hospital, Sharma, Tabuk, Saudi Arabia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ullah</LastName><ForeName>Mohammad Fahad</ForeName><Initials>MF</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Laboratory Technology, Faculty of Applied Medical Sciences, University of Tabuk, King Faisel Road, 7149, Tabuk, Saudi Arabia. m.ullah@ut.edu.sa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Biochem Genet</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0126611</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0006-2928</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Covid-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Functional genomics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pathogenic variants</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">The mechanistic target of rapamycin (mTOR)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Whole-exome sequencing</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement><b>Declarations</b> <b>Competing Interest</b> The authors declare no competing interests. <b>Ethical Approval</b> The study was approved by the institutional ethics committees at the University of Bisha (Ref. no. UBCOM/H-06-BH-087(05/25)). All the subjects provided written informed consent before their participation in the study.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>17</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39557769</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10528-024-10970-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s10528-024-10970-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Alsaedi SB, Mineta K, Gao X et al (2023) Computational network analysis of host genetic risk variants of severe COVID-19. Hum Genomics 17:17</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36859360</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9977643</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40246-023-00454-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bian J, Li Z (2021) Angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2): SARS-CoV-2 receptor and RAS modulator. Acta Pharm Sin b 11(1):1–12</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33072500</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.apsb.2020.10.006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bigdelou B, Sepand MR, Najafikhoshnoo S, Negrete JAT, Sharaf M, Ho JQ, Sullivan I, Chauhan P, Etter M, Shekarian T, Liang O, Hutter G, Esfandiarpour R, Zanganeh S (2022) COVID-19 and preexisting comorbidities: risks, synergies, and clinical outcomes. Front Immunol 13:890517</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35711466</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9196863</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2022.890517</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bohnekamp J, Böselt I, Saalbach A, Tönjes A, Kovacs P, Biebermann H, Manvelyan HM, Polte T, Gasperikova D, Lkhagvasuren S, Baier L, Stumvoll M, Römpler H, Schöneberg T (2010) Involvement of the chemokine-like receptor GPR33 in innate immunity. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 396(2):272–277</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20399748</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2954049</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2010.04.077</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burger AL, Kaufmann CC, Jäger B, Pogran E, Ahmed A, Wojta J, Farhan S, Huber K (2021) Direct cardiovascular complications and indirect collateral damage during the COVID-19 pandemic: a review. Wien Klin Wochenschr 133:1289–1297</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34671829</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8527966</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00508-021-01956-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campuzano O, Sanchez-Molero O, Mademont-Soler I, Riuró H, Allegue C, Coll M, Pérez-Serra A, Mates J, Picó F, Iglesias A et al (2015) Rare Titin (TTN) variants in diseases associated with sudden cardiac death. Int J Mol Sci 16(10):25773–25787</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26516846</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4632826</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijms161025773</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Casanova J-L, Su HC, Abel L, Aiuti A, Almuhsen S, Arias AA et al (2020) A global effort to define the human genetics of protective immunity to SARS-CoV-2 infection. Cell 181(6):1194–1199</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32405102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7218368</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2020.05.016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chin CH, Chen SH, Wu HH, Ho CW, Ko MT, Lin CY (2014) cytoHubba: identifying hub objects and sub-networks from complex interactome. BMC Syst Biol 8(Suppl 4):S11. https://doi.org/10.1186/1752-0509-8-S4-S11</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1752-0509-8-S4-S11</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25521941</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4290687</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clark A et al (2020) Global, regional, and national estimates of the population at increased risk of severe COVID-19 due to underlying health conditions in 2020: a modelling study. Lancet Glob Health 8:e1003–e1017</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32553130</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7295519</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2214-109X(20)30264-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deng M, Lu Z, Zheng J, Wan X, Chen X, Hirayasu K et al (2014) A motif in LILRB2 critical for Angptl2 binding and activation. Blood 124:924–935</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24899623</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4126332</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1182/blood-2014-01-549162</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Devi-Marulkar P, Moraes-Cabe C, Campagne P, Corre B, Meghraoui-Kheddar A, Bondet V, Llibre A, Duffy D, Maillart E, Papeix C, Pellegrini S, Michel F (2021) Altered immune phenotypes and HLA-DQB1 gene variation in multiple sclerosis patients failing interferon β treatment. Front Immunol 12:628375</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34113337</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8185344</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2021.628375</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Docherty AB, Harrison EM, Green CA, Hardwick HE, Pius R, Norman L, Holden KA, Read JM, Dondelinger F, Carson G, Merson L, Lee J, Plotkin D, Sigfrid L, Halpin S, Jackson C, Gamble C, Horby PW, Nguyenvan-Tam JS, Ho A, Russell CD, Dunning J, Openshaw PJ, Baillie JK, Semple MG, ISARIC4C investigators (2020) Features of 20133 UK patients in hospital with covid-19 using the ISARIC WHO clinical characterization protocol: prospective observational cohort study. BMJ 369:1985</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.m1985</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elssaig EH, Alnour TMS, Ullah MF, Ahmed-Abakur EH (2022) Omicron SARS-CoV-2 Variants in an In Silico Genomic Comparison Study with the Original Wuhan Strain and WHO-Recognized Variants of Concern. Pol J Microbiol 71(4):577–587</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36537060</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9944972</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.33073/pjm-2022-053</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fuchs FD, Whelton PK (2020) High blood pressure and cardiovascular disease. Hypertension 75(2):285–292</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31865786</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.119.14240</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghosh R, Harrison SM, Rehm HL, Plon SE, Biesecker LG, ClinGen Sequence Variant Interpretation Working Group (2018) Updated recommendation for the benign stand-alone ACMG/AMP criterion. Hum Mutat 39(11):1525–1530</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30311383</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">6188666</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/humu.23642</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Griffith DM, Sharma G, Holliday CS, Enyia OK, Valliere M, Semlow AR et al (2020) Men and COVID-19: a biopsychosocial approach to understanding sex differences in mortality and recommendations for practice and policy interventions. Prev Chronic Dis 17:E63</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32678061</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7380297</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5888/pcd17.200247</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Henry BM, Lippi G (2020) Chronic kidney disease is associated with severe coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) infection. Int Urol Nephrol 52(6):1193–1194</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32222883</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7103107</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11255-020-02451-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hirayasu K, Arase H (2015) Functional and genetic diversity of leukocyte immunoglobulin-like receptor and implication for disease associations. J Hum Genet 60(11):703–708</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26040207</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/jhg.2015.64</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>https://www.who.int/publications/m/item/covid-19-epidemiological-update---29-september-2023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu J, Ng PC (2013) SIFT Indel: predictions for the functional effects of amino acid insertions/deletions in proteins. PLoS ONE 8(10):e77940</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24194902</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3806772</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0077940</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kang SJ, Jung SI (2020) Age-related morbidity and mortality among patients with COVID-19. Infect Chemother 52(2):154–164</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32537961</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7335648</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3947/ic.2020.52.2.154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karam BS, Morris RS, Bramante CT, Puskarich M, Zolfaghari EJ, Lotfi-Emran S, Ingraham NE, Charles A, Odde DJ, Tignanelli CJ (2021) mTOR inhibition in COVID-19: a commentary and review of efficacy in RNA viruses. J Med Virol 93(4):1843–1846</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33314219</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmv.26728</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kilbourne ED (2006) Influenza pandemics of the 20th century. Emerg Infect Dis 12(1):9–14</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16494710</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3291411</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3201/eid1201.051254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kondĕlková K, Vokurková D, Krejsek J, Borská L, Fiala Z, Ctirad A (2010) Regulatory T cells (TREG) and their roles in immune system with respect to immunopathological disorders. Acta Medica (Hradec Kralove) 53(2):73–77</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20672742</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.14712/18059694.2016.63</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Le Sage V, Cinti A, Amorim R, Mouland AJ (2016) Adapting the stress response: viral subversion of the mTOR signaling pathway. Viruses 8(6):152</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27231932</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4926172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/v8060152</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>LeWinter MM, Granzier HL (2013) Titin is a major human disease gene. Circulation 127(8):938–944</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23439446</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">3594684</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.112.139717</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lichterfeld M, Kavanagh DG, Williams KL, Moza B, Mui SK, Miura T et al (2007) A viral CTL escape mutation leading to immunoglobulin-like transcript 4-mediated functional inhibition of myelomonocytic cells. J Exp Med 204:2813–2824</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18025130</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">2118510</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1084/jem.20061865</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu C, Zhao Y, Okwan-Duodu D, Basho R, Cui X (2020) COVID-19 in cancer patients: risk, clinical features, and management. Cancer Biol Med 17(3):519–527</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32944387</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7476081</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.20892/j.issn.2095-3941.2020.0289</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Z, Liang Q, Ren Y, Guo C, Ge X, Wang L, Cheng Q, Luo P, Zhang Y, Han X (2023) Immunosenescence: molecular mechanisms and diseases. Signal Transduct Target Ther 8(1):200</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37179335</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10182360</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41392-023-01451-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu C, Hu X, Wang G et al (2010) Why do essential proteins tend to be clustered in the yeast interactome network? Mol Biosyst 6(5):871–877. https://doi.org/10.1039/b921069e</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/b921069e</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20567773</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maggi L, Bonanno S, Altamura C, Desaphy JF (2021) Ion channel gene mutations causing skeletal muscle disorders: pathomechanisms and opportunities for therapy. Cells 10(6):1521</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34208776</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8234207</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/cells10061521</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin AR, Williams E, Foulger RE, Leigh S, Daugherty LC, Niblock O et al (2019) PanelApp crowdsources expert knowledge to establish consensus diagnostic gene panels. Nat Genet 51:1560–1565</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31676867</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41588-019-0528-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McLaren W, Gil L, Hunt SE, Riat HS, Ritchie GR, Thormann A, Flicek P, Cunningham F (2016) The ensembl variant effect predictor. Genome Biol 17(1):122</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27268795</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">4893825</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13059-016-0974-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mentzer AJ, O’Connor D, Bibi S, Chelysheva I, Clutterbuck EA, Demissie T et al (2023) Human leukocyte antigen alleles associate with COVID-19 vaccine immunogenicity and risk of breakthrough infection. Nat Med 29(1):147–157</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36228659</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41591-022-02078-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paninka RM, Mazzotti DR, Kizys MM, Vidi AC, Rodrigues H, Silva SP, Kunii IS, Furuzawa GK, Arcisio-Miranda M, Dias-da-Silva MR (2016) Whole genome and exome sequencing realignment supports the assignment of KCNJ12, KCNJ17, and KCNJ18 paralogous genes in thyrotoxic periodic paralysis locus: functional characterization of two polymorphic Kir2.6 isoforms. Mol Genet Genom 291:1535–1544</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00438-016-1185-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petersen BS, Fredrich B, Hoeppner MP et al (2017) Opportunities and challenges of whole-genome and -exome sequencing. BMC Genet 18(1):14</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28193154</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5307692</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12863-017-0479-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petrilli CM, Jones SA, Yang J, Rajagopalan H, O’Donnell L, Chernyak Y et al (2020) Factors associated with hospital admission and critical illness among 5279 people with coronavirus disease 2019 in New York City: prospective cohort study. BMJ 369:m1966</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32444366</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7243801</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.m1966</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richardson S, Hirsch JS, Narasimhan M, Crawford JM, McGinn T, Davidson KW et al (2020) Presenting characteristics, comorbidities, and outcomes among 5700 patients hospitalized with COVID-19 in the New York City area. JAMA 323(20):2052–2059</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32320003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7177629</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.6775</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Russell CD, Lone NI, Baillie JK (2023) Comorbidities, multimorbidity and COVID-19. Nat Med 29(2):334–343</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36797482</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41591-022-02156-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salah HM, Mehta JL (2021) Hypothesis: sex-related differences in ACE2 activity may contribute to higher mortality in men versus women with COVID-19. J Cardiovasc Pharmacol Ther 26(2):114–118</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33078623</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1074248420967792</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schöneberg T, Liebscher I (2021) Mutations in G protein-coupled receptors: mechanisms, pathophysiology and potential therapeutic approaches. Pharmacol Rev 73(1):89–119</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33219147</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1124/pharmrev.120.000011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shannon P, Markiel A, Ozier O et al (2003) Cytoscape: a software environment for integrated models of biomolecular interaction networks. Genome Res 13(11):2498–2504. https://doi.org/10.1101/gr.1239303</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/gr.1239303</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14597658</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">403769</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh R, Saluja P, Madan A (2022) COVID-19: a gender-biased pandemic. J Oral Maxillofac Pathol 26(4):555–557</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37082045</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10112087</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/jomfp.jomfp_210_22</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Siordia JA Jr (2020) Epidemiology and clinical features of COVID-19: a review of current literature. J Clin Virol 127:104357</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32305884</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7195311</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jcv.2020.104357</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Szklarczyk D, Franceschini A, Kuhn M et al (2011) The STRING database in 2011: functional interaction networks of proteins globally integrated and scored. Nucleic Acids Res 39:D561–D568. https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkq973</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/nar/gkq973</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21045058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uddin M, Mustafa F, Rizvi TA, Loney T, Suwaidi HA, Al-Marzouqi AHH, Eldin AK, Alsabeeha N, Adrian TE, Stefanini C, Nowotny N, Alsheikh-Ali A, Senok AC (2020) SARS-CoV-2/COVID-19: viral genomics, epidemiology, vaccines, and therapeutic interventions. Viruses 12(5):526</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32397688</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7290442</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/v12050526</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ullah MF, Alnour TMS, Elssaig EH, Ahmed-Abakur EH (2021) Characterization of altered genomic landscape of SARS-CoV-2 variants isolated in Saudi Arabia in a comparative in silico study. Saudi J Biol Sci 28(12):6803–6807</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34866979</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8626222</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.sjbs.2021.07.054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uribarri A, Núñez-Gil IJ, Aparisi A, Becerra-Muñoz VM, Feltes G, Trabattoni D et al (2020) Impact of renal function on admission in COVID-19 patients: an analysis of the international HOPE COVID-19 (health outcome predictive evaluation for COVID 19) Registry. J Nephrol 33(4):737–745</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32602006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7322375</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40620-020-00790-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vandewalle J, Bauters M, Van Esch H, Belet S, Verbeeck J, Fieremans N et al (2013) The mitochondrial solute carrier SLC25A5 at Xq24 is a novel candidate gene for non-syndromic intellectual disability. Human Genet 132:1177–1185</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00439-013-1322-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vidal-Perez R, Brandão M, Pazdernik M, Kresoja KP, Carpenito M, Maeda S, Casado-Arroyo R, Muscoli S, Pöss J, Fontes-Carvalho R, Vazquez-Rodriguez JM (2022) Cardiovascular disease and COVID-19, a deadly combination: a review about direct and indirect impact of a pandemic. World J Clin Cases 10(27):9556–9572</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36186196</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9516905</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.12998/wjcc.v10.i27.9556</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Virolainen SJ, VonHandorf A, Viel KCMF, Weirauch MT, Kottyan LC (2023) Gene-environment interactions and their impact on human health. Genes Immun 24(1):1–11</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36585519</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41435-022-00192-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Q, Dhindsa RS, Carss K, Harper AR, Nag A, Tachmazidou I, et al; AstraZeneca Genomics Initiative;Wasilewski S, Smith KR, March R, Platt A, Haefliger C, Petrovski S. Rare variant contribution to human disease in 281,104 UK Biobank exomes. Nature. 2021 ;597(7877):527–532.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yanez ND, Weiss NS, Romand JA, Treggiari MM (2020) COVID-19 mortality risk for older men and women. BMC Public Health 20(1):1742</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33213391</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7675386</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12889-020-09826-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang J, Mai S, Chen HM, Kang K, Li XC, Chen SH, Pan PY (2017) Leukocyte immunoglobulin-like receptors in human diseases: an overview of their distribution, function, and potential application for immunotherapies. J Leukoc Biol 102(2):351–360</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28351852</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">5505746</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1189/jlb.5MR1216-534R</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou B, Lin W, Long Y, Yang Y, Zhang H, Wu K, Chu Q (2022) Notch signaling pathway: architecture, disease, and therapeutics. Signal Transduct Target Ther 7(1):95</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35332121</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8948217</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41392-022-00934-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu D, Zhao R, Yuan H, Xie Y, Jiang Y, Xu K, Zhang T, Chen X, Suo C (2023) Host genetic factors, comorbidities and the risk of severe COVID-19. J Epidemiol Glob Health 13(2):279–291</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37160831</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">10169198</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s44197-023-00106-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>