<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39553036</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2168-8184</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cureus</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cureus</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Key Determinants of SARS-CoV-2 Testing Among Symptomatic Individuals During the Second Wave in Uttar Pradesh, India: An Analysis From Two Districts.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e71784</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e71784</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e71784</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7759/cureus.71784</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The COVID-19 epidemic caused significant disruptions worldwide, particularly in healthcare systems. India's second wave, driven by the Delta variant in 2021, severely affected healthcare capacity, leading to resource shortages and healthcare service disruptions. In this context, understanding the factors influencing SARS-CoV-2 testing is crucial for improving public health responses. This study investigates testing determinants in Uttar Pradesh, India, using Andersen's Behavioral Model of Health Services Use.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODOLOGY" NlmCategory="METHODS">We chose Lucknow and Sitapur districts in Uttar Pradesh based on the number of SARS-CoV-2 tests conducted per million people during the second wave of the epidemic. We conducted a cross-sectional study and surveyed 675 consenting respondents aged 18 and above from both districts. These respondents reported experiencing at least three COVID-19 symptoms between March and June 2021 (the second wave in the state). The survey was conducted face-to-face using a structured questionnaire on an electronic device. We used multiple correspondence analysis (MCA) to identify underlying factors, which were then utilized in a logistic regression model to assess their impact on SARS-CoV-2 testing.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS"> The testing rate in Lucknow (281, 84.6%) was higher than in Sitapur (117, 34.1%) (<i>P</i> &lt; 0.001). Urban residents had a higher likelihood of being tested (188, 75.8%) than rural residents (210, 49.2%) (<i>P</i> &lt; 0.001). Males (213, 63.0%) were more frequently tested than females (185, 54.9%) (<i>P</i> = 0.032). Postgraduates had the highest testing rate (49, 89.1%) compared to those without formal education (73, 44.8%) (<i>P</i> &lt; 0.001). Individuals in regular jobs were more likely to be tested (171, 67.1%) compared to homemakers (128, 51.2%) and laborers (72, 57.1%) (<i>P</i> = 0.004). Smaller households (&lt;5 members) had higher testing rates (146, 69.9%) than larger ones (252, 54.1%) (<i>P</i> &lt; 0.001). Those living closer to a facility were more frequently tested (90, 64.3%) compared to those farther away (61, 34.1%) (<i>P</i> &lt; 0.001). Additionally, individuals with access to public transport had higher testing rates (294, 62.0%) compared to those without (104, 51.7%) (<i>P</i> = 0.013). Higher-income groups were more likely to be tested (14, 93.3%) than low-income individuals (39, 36.8%) (<i>P</i> &lt; 0.001). Psychological factors such as ease of testing (285, 72.5%) vs. (71, 38.6%) and perceived likelihood of needing testing (312, 90.7%) vs. (78, 25.1%) were strong predictors (both <i>P</i> &lt; 0.001). Logistic regression identified urban residency and education as key determinants (odds ratio [OR] = 2.00, <i>P</i> &lt; 0.001).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">This study identifies key sociodemographic, logistical, and psychological factors influencing SARS-CoV-2 testing during the second wave of COVID-19 in Uttar Pradesh, India. Addressing disparities in healthcare infrastructure, improving health literacy, and reducing psychological barriers are essential to enhancing public health responses in future pandemics. Expanding healthcare access in rural areas and targeted public health campaigns could help bridge the gap in testing utilization. Further research is needed to explore these factors longitudinally and in different regional contexts.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024, Pandey et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pandey</LastName><ForeName>Raghukul R</ForeName><Initials>RR</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, King George's Medical University, Lucknow, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Agarwal</LastName><ForeName>Monika</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Community Medicine and Public Health, King George's Medical University, Lucknow, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wahl</LastName><ForeName>Brian</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Yale School of Public Health, Yale University, New Haven, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Garg</LastName><ForeName>Tushar</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Global Health Campus, Stop TB Partnership, Geneva, CHE.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jain</LastName><ForeName>Amita</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, King George's Medical University, Lucknow, IND.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cureus</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101596737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2168-8184</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">andersen's behavioral model</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">covid-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">healthcare access</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">logistic regression</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">multiple correspondence analysis (mca)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">psychological barriers</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sars-cov-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">testing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">uttar pradesh</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. UP Institutional Ethics Committee of King George’s Medical University issued approval 119th ECM II B-Ph.D/P1. Animal subjects: All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>59</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39553036</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11569817</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7759/cureus.71784</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>WHO Director-General’s Opening Remarks at the Media Briefing on COVID-19 - 11 March 2020.  [
Sep;
2024 
];https://www.who.int/director-general/speeches/detail/who-director-general-s-opening-remarks-at-the-media-briefing-on-covid-19---11-march-2020 2020 3:19–10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Critical supply shortages - the need for ventilators and personal protective equipment during the Covid-19 pandemic. Ranney ML, Griffeth V, Jha AK. N Engl J Med. 2020;382:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32212516</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Italian health system and the COVID-19 challenge. Armocida B, Formenti B, Ussai S, Palestra F, Missoni E. Lancet Public Health. 2020;5:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7104094</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32220653</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delta variant triggers new phase in the pandemic. Kupferschmidt K, Wadman M. Science. 2021;372:1375–1376.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Press Information Bureau, Government of India, Ministry of Health and Family Welfare.  [
Sep;
2024 
];https://pib.gov.in/Pressreleaseshare.aspx?PRID=1787361 2022 3:1787361.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>India's COVID-19 emergency. The Lancet. Lancet. 2021;397:1683.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Revisiting the behavioral model and access to medical care: does it matter? Andersen RM. J Health Soc Behav. 1995;36:1–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7738325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Socioeconomic and demographic effects on SARS-CoV-2 testing: evidence from the state of Uttar Pradesh, India. Pandey RR, Agarwal M, Wahl BP, Garg T, Jain A. Cureus. 2024;16:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11144016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38826941</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Disparities in the population at risk of severe illness from COVID-19 by race/ethnicity and income. Raifman MA, Raifman JR. Am J Prev Med. 2020;59:137–139.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7183932</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32430225</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Why inequality could spread COVID-19. Ahmed F, Ahmed N, Pissarides C, Stiglitz J. Lancet Public Health. 2020;5:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7270465</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32247329</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Multiple correspondence analysis and the multilogit bilinear model. Fithian W, Josse J. J Multivariate Anal. 2017;157:87–102.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Population projections for India and state.  [
Sep;
2024 
];https://nhm.gov.in/New_Updates_2018/Report_Population_Projection_2019.pdf 2019 4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uttar Pradesh ke Swasthya Kendra.  [
Sep;
2024 
];https://uphealthfacility.in/ 2022 4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Surveillance Platform UP Covid-19.  [
Sep;
2024 
];https://upcovid19tracks.in/ 2021 4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Directorate of Economics And Statistics, Government of Uttar Pradesh.  [
Sep;
2024 
];https://updes.up.nic.in/ 2024 8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Census Tables. https://censusindia.gov.in/census.website/data/census-tables# 2024;of:2023–2031.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sample size guidelines for logistic regression from observational studies with large population: emphasis on the accuracy between statistics and parameters based on real life clinical data. Bujang MA, Sa’at N, Sidik TM, Joo LC. Malays J Med Sci. 2018;25:122–130.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6422534</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30914854</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The double burden of malnutrition in India: Trends and inequalities (2006-2016) Nguyen PH, Scott S, Headey D, Singh N, Tran LM, Menon P, Ruel MT. PLoS One. 2021;16:0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7906302</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33630964</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Office of Registrar General and Census Commissioner, India, Ministry of Home Affairs, Government of India .  [
Mar;
2023 
]. 2011. https://censusindia.gov.in/nada/index.php/catalog/6348 and 6345 https://censusindia.gov.in/nada/index.php/catalog/6348 and 6345</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A procedure for objective respondent selection within a household. Kish L. J Amer Sociol Assoc. 1949;44:380–387.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Multiple correspondence analysis as a tool for analysis of large health surveys in African settings. Ayele D, Zewotir T, Mwambi H. Afr Health Sci. 2014;14:1036–1045.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4386317</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25873942</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Changes in access to health services during the COVID-19 pandemic: a scoping review. Pujolar G, Oliver-Anglès A, Vargas I, Vázquez ML. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19:1749.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8834942</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35162772</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>A vulnerability index for the management of and response to the COVID-19 epidemic in India: an ecological study. Acharya R, Porwal A. Lancet Glob Health. 2020;8:0–51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7365640</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32682459</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Low health literacy and health outcomes: an updated systematic review. Berkman ND, Sheridan SL, Donahue KE, Halpern DJ, Crotty K. Ann Intern Med. 2011;155:97–107.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21768583</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patient-centred access to health care: conceptualising access at the interface of health systems and populations. Levesque JF, Harris MF, Russell G. Int J Equity Health. 2013;12:18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3610159</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23496984</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stigma and discrimination during COVID-19 pandemic. Bhanot D, Singh T, Verma SK, Sharad S. Front Public Health. 2020;8:577018.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7874150</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33585379</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Regional disparity of covid-19 infections: an investigation using state-level Indian data. Basu P, Mazumder R. Indian Econ Rev. 2021;56:215–232.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8158080</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34075257</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Health literacy as a public health goal: a challenge for contemporary health education and communication strategies into the 21st century. Nutbeam D. Health Promotion Int. 2000;15:259–267.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The psychological impact of quarantine and how to reduce it: rapid review of the evidence. Brooks SK, Webster RK, Smith LE, Woodland L, Wessely S, Greenberg N, Rubin GJ. Lancet. 2020;395:912–920.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7158942</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32112714</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>How do we balance tensions between COVID-19 public health responses and stigma mitigation? Learning from HIV research. Logie CH, Turan JM. AIDS Behav. 2020;24:2003–2006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7137404</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32266502</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>