<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39558201</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1471-2458</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>24</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>18</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC public health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Public Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A modeling study on SARS-CoV-2 transmissions in primary and middle schools in Illinois.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>3197</StartPage><MedlinePgn>3197</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12889-024-20623-5</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">The global pandemic caused by the SARS-CoV-2 virus led to a statewide lockdown in Illinois starting in March 2020. To ensure students' and employees' safety for school reopening, protective measures, such as a statewide mask mandate and weekly testing, were in place in Illinois from Spring 2021 to Spring 2022. The study objective is to 1) estimate the in-school and external transmission of SARS-CoV-2 in elementary and middle schools under mask mandate and weekly surveillance and 2) estimate the impacts of protective measures such as testing and mask proportion and testing frequency on SARS-CoV-2 transmission.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A stochastic compartmental model was built to simulate the SARS-CoV-2 transmission within and between the student and employee groups in primary and middle schools participating in the weekly testing program and to evaluate the effectiveness of these protective measures. This stochastic model was modified from a susceptible-infected-recovered framework and calibrated to SARS-CoV-2 surveillance data in 116 primary and middle school districts from Spring 2021 to March 2022. This model calibration was assessed using the surveillance data from the rest of the spring semester in 2022.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Overall, the external transmission rates in students and employees were significantly greater than those within schools, and the external transmission rates in middle school students and school employees were greater than those in primary school students. Our sensitivity analysis showed that transmission rates within student groups could significantly influence overall infection rates in vaccinated and unvaccinated students in large school districts. Under the protective measures implemented in the studied period in Illinois, an increased proportion of students and employees participating in the weekly testing can decrease infections. However, community-level measures of self-reported mask adherence among adults were not significantly associated with the infections during the study period, when a universal mask policy was in place for the state.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Although increased testing proportion and/or frequency can reduce the SARS-CoV-2 infections, the costs of testing can increase with the testing volume. Further studies on the cost-effectiveness between the testing volume and cases reduction or learning disturbance can aid in policy development to reduce transmission effectively.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huang</LastName><ForeName>Conghui</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathobiology, College of Veterinary Medicine, University of Illinois at Urbana Champaign, Urbana, IL, USA. chuang65@illinois.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Smith</LastName><ForeName>Rebecca Lee</ForeName><Initials>RL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pathobiology, College of Veterinary Medicine, University of Illinois at Urbana Champaign, Urbana, IL, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Carle-Illinois College of Medicine, University of Illinois at Urbana Champaign, Urbana, IL, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Genomic Biology, University of Illinois at Urbana Champaign, Urbana, IL, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Public Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100968562</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1471-2458</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000635" MajorTopicYN="N">transmission</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007087" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Illinois</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012574" MajorTopicYN="Y">Schools</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008397" MajorTopicYN="Y">Masks</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000293" MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescent</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013334" MajorTopicYN="N">Students</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000523" MajorTopicYN="N">psychology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086742" MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19 Testing</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013269" MajorTopicYN="N">Stochastic Processes</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Compartment model</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Primary and middle schools</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2 transmission</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Within-school transmission</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement><b>Declarations</b> <b>Ethics approval and consent to participate</b> All analyses were declared to be exempt by University of Illinois Institutional Review Boards (protocol #22843). The requirement for ethical approval and informed consent was waived by the University of Illinois Institutional Review Boards (protocol #22843) because of the retrospective nature of the study. <b>Consent for publication</b> Not applicable. <b>Competing interests</b> The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>54</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39558201</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12889-024-20623-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12889-024-20623-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. CDC Museum COVID-19 Timeline. 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Francom GM, Lee SJ, Pinkney H. Technologies, challenges and needs of K-12 teachers in the transition to distance learning during the COVID-19 pandemic. TechTrends. 2021;65:589–601.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11528-021-00625-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34223560</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8233184</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. COVID-19 Vaccinations in the United States,County. CDC. 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doron S, Ingalls RR, Beauchamp A, Boehm JS, Boucher HW, Chow LH, et al. Weekly SARS-CoV-2 screening of asymptomatic kindergarten to grade 12 students and staff helps inform strategies for safer in-person learning. Cell Rep Med. 2021;2:100452.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.xcrm.2021.100452</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34723225</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8549440</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ueki H, Furusawa Y, Iwatsuki-Horimoto K, Imai M, Kabata H, Nishimura H, et al. Effectiveness of face masks in preventing airborne transmission of SARS-CoV-2. mSphere. 2020;5:10–128. https://doi.org/10.1128/msphere.00637-20 .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/msphere.00637-20</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang CC, Prather KA, Sznitman J, Jimenez JL, Lakdawala SS, Tufekci Z, et al. Airborne transmission of respiratory viruses. Science. 2021;373:eabd9149.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.abd9149</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34446582</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8721651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Whiley H, Keerthirathne TP, Nisar MA, White MAF, Ross KE. Viral filtration efficiency of fabric masks compared with surgical and N95 masks. Pathogens. 2020;9:762.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/pathogens9090762</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32957638</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7559551</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boutzoukas AE, Zimmerman KO, Benjamin DK Jr, DeMuri GP, Kalu IC, Smith MJ, et al. Secondary transmission of COVID-19 in K–12 Schools: findings from 2 States. Pediatrics. 2022;149(Supplement_2):e2021054268K.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1542/peds.2021-054268K</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34737171</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jehn M, McCullough JM, Dale AP, Gue M, Eller B, Cullen T, et al. Association between K-12 school mask policies and school-associated COVID-19 Outbreaks - Maricopa and Pima Counties, Arizona, July-August 2021. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2021;70:1372–3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7039e1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34591830</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8486387</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Illinois State Board of Education. Public school calendar inquiry. 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Census Bureau. County Population Totals and Components of Change: 2020–2022. US Dep Commer.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Department of Education. Institute of Education Sciences, National Center for Education Statistics. The Elementary/Secondary Information System. 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. COVID-19 Case Surveillance Restricted Data Access. COVID-19 Response. 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Nationwide COVID-19 Infection-Induced Antibody Seroprevalence (Commercial laboratories). US Dep Health Hum Serv. 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salomon JA, Reinhart A, Bilinski A, Chua EJ, La Motte-Kerr W, Rönn MM, et al. The US COVID-19 Trends and Impact Survey: Continuous real-time measurement of COVID-19 symptoms, risks, protective behaviors, testing, and vaccination. Proc Natl Acad Sci. 2021;118:e2111454118.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.2111454118</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34903656</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8713763</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bilinski A, Ciaranello A, Fitzpatrick MC, Giardina J, Shah M, Salomon JA, et al. Estimated transmission outcomes and costs of SARS-CoV-2 diagnostic testing, screening, and surveillance strategies among a simulated population of primary school students. JAMA Pediatr. 2022;176:679–89.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamapediatrics.2022.1326</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35442396</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9021988</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kissler Stephen M, Fauver Joseph R, Mack C, Tai Caroline G, BrebanMallery I, Watkins Anne E, et al. Viral dynamics of SARS-CoV-2 variants in vaccinated and unvaccinated persons. N Engl J Med. 2021;385:2489–91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMc2102507</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34941024</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hart WS, Miller E, Andrews NJ, Waight P, Maini PK, Funk S, et al. Generation time of the alpha and delta SARS-CoV-2 variants: an epidemiological analysis. Lancet Infect Dis. 2022;22:603–10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(22)00001-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35176230</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8843191</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andrejko KL, Pry JM, Myers JF, Fukui N, DeGuzman JL, Openshaw J, et al. effectiveness of face mask or respirator use in indoor public settings for prevention of SARS-CoV-2 infection - California, February-December 2021. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2022;71:212–6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7106e1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35143470</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8830622</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. COVID-19 Vaccine effectiveness update. Dep Health Hum Serv. 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Różański M, Walczak-Drzewiecka A, Witaszewska J, Wójcik E, Guziński A, Zimoń B, et al. RT-qPCR-based tests for SARS-CoV-2 detection in pooled saliva samples for massive population screening to monitor epidemics. Sci Rep. 2022;12:8082.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-12179-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35577836</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9109753</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Emma B. Hodcroft. CoVariants: SARS-CoV-2 Mutations and Variants of Interest. 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wickham H, François R, Henry L, Müller K. dplyr: A Grammar of Data Manipulation. 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wickham H, Averick M, Bryan J, Chang W, McGowan LD, François R, et al. Welcome to the tidyverse. J Open Source Softw. 2019;4:1686.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21105/joss.01686</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wickham H. Reshaping data with the reshape package. J Stat Softw. 2007;21:1–20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18637/jss.v021.i12</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Loo MPJ. The stringdist package for approximate string matching. R J. 2014;6:111–22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.32614/RJ-2014-011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grolemund G, Wickham H. Dates and times made easy with lubridate. J Stat Softw. 2011;40:1–25.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18637/jss.v040.i03</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niemi J. MMWRweek: Convert Dates to MMWR Day, Week, and Year. 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robinson D. fuzzyjoin: Join Tables Together on Inexact Matching. 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carnell R. lhs: Latin Hypercube Samples. 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stevenson M, from Telmo Nunes ESWC, Heuer C, Marshall J, Sanchez J, Thornton R, et al. epiR: Tools for the Analysis of Epidemiological Data. 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wickham H. ggplot2: Elegant Graphics for Data Analysis. New York: Springer-Verlag; 2016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-24277-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Puhach O, Adea K, Hulo N, Sattonnet P, Genecand C, Iten A, et al. Infectious viral load in unvaccinated and vaccinated individuals infected with ancestral, Delta or Omicron SARS-CoV-2. Nat Med. 2022;28:1491–500.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41591-022-01816-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35395151</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu W, Li X, Dozier M, He Y, Kirolos A, Lang Z, et al. What is the evidence for transmission of COVID-19 by children in schools? A living systematic review. J Glob Health. 2020;10:021104.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7189/jogh.10.021104</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33437465</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7774027</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nemoto N, Dhillon S, Fink S, Holman EJ, Cope AK, Dinh T-H, et al. Evaluation of test to stay strategy on secondary and tertiary transmission of SARS-CoV-2 in K-12 schools - Lake County, Illinois, August 9-October 29, 2021. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2021;70:1778–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm705152e2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34968375</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8736270</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boutzoukas AE, Zimmerman KO, Inkelas M, Brookhart MA, Benjamin DK Sr, Butteris S, et al. School masking policies and secondary SARS-CoV-2 transmission. Pediatrics. 2022;149:e2022056687.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1542/peds.2022-056687</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35260896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Volpp KG, Kraut BH, Ghosh S, Neatherlin J. Minimal SARS-CoV-2 transmission after implementation of a comprehensive mitigation strategy at a school - New Jersey, August 20-November 27, 2020. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2021;70:377–81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7011a2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33735161</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7976619</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Budzyn SE, Panaggio MJ, Parks SE, Papazian M, Magid J, Eng M, et al. Pediatric COVID-19 cases in counties with and without school mask requirements - United States, July 1-September 4, 2021. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2021;70:1377–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7039e3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34591829</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8486393</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sombetzki M, Lücker P, Ehmke M, Bock S, Littmann M, Reisinger EC, et al. Impact of changes in infection control measures on the dynamics of COVID-19 infections in schools and pre-schools. Front Public Health. 2021;9:780039.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2021.780039</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34988054</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8720754</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hershow RB, Wu K, Lewis NM, Milne AT, Currie D, Smith AR, et al. Low SARS-CoV-2 transmission in elementary schools - Salt Lake County, Utah, December 3, 2020-January 31, 2021. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2021;70:442–8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7012e3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33764967</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7993560</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boutzoukas AE, Zimmerman KO, Benjamin DK Jr, Chick KJ, Curtiss J, Høeg TB. Quarantine elimination for K–12 students with mask-on-mask exposure to SARS-CoV-2. Pediatrics. 2022;149(Supplement_2):e2021054268L.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1542/peds.2021-054268L</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34737181</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doyle T, Kendrick K, Troelstrup T, Gumke M, Edwards J, Chapman S, et al. COVID-19 in primary and secondary school settings during the first semester of school reopening - Florida, August-December 2020. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2021;70:437–41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm7012e2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33764962</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7993553</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zimmerman KO, Brookhart MA, Kalu IC, Boutzoukas AE, McGann KA, Smith MJ, et al. Community SARS-CoV-2 surge and within-school transmission. Pediatrics. 2021;148:e2021052686.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1542/peds.2021-052686</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34321339</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>España G, Cavany S, Oidtman R, Barbera C, Costello A, Lerch A, et al. Impacts of K-12 school reopening on the COVID-19 epidemic in Indiana. USA Epidemics. 2021;37:100487.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.epidem.2021.100487</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34425301</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wada K, Okabe N, Shobugawa Y. Infection and transmission of COVID-19 among students and teachers in schools in Japan after the reopening in June 2020. BMJ Paediatr Open. 2020;4:e000854.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjpo-2020-000854</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34192181</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meuris C, Kremer C, Geerinck A, Locquet M, Bruyère O, Defêche J, et al. Transmission of SARS-CoV-2 after COVID-19 screening and mitigation measures for primary school children attending school in Liège. Belgium JAMA Netw Open. 2021;4:e2128757–e2128757.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.28757</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34636913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leng T, Hill EM, Thompson RN, Tildesley MJ, Keeling MJ, Dyson L. Assessing the impact of lateral flow testing strategies on within-school SARS-CoV-2 transmission and absences: a modelling study. PLOS Comput Biol. 2022;18:e1010158.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1010158</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35622860</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9182264</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wiens KE, Smith CP, Badillo-Goicoechea E, Grantz KH, Grabowski MK, Azman AS, et al. In-person schooling and associated COVID-19 risk in the United States over spring semester 2021. Sci Adv. 2022;8:eabm9128.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/sciadv.abm9128</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35442740</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9020776</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adjodah D, Dinakar K, Chinazzi M, Fraiberger SP, Pentland A, Bates S, et al. Association between COVID-19 outcomes and mask mandates, adherence, and attitudes. PLoS ONE. 2021;16:e0252315.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0252315</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34161332</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8221503</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chandra A, Høeg TB. Lack of correlation between school mask mandates and paediatric COVID-19 cases in a large cohort. J Infect. 2022;85:671–5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2022.09.019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36183909</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9539411</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McElfish PA, Willis DE, Shah SK, Reece S, Andersen JA, Schootman M, et al. Parents’ and guardians’ intentions to vaccinate children against COVID-19. Vaccines. 2022;10:361.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/vaccines10030361</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35334993</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8949105</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woodland L, Mowbray F, Smith LE, Webster RK, Amlôt R, Rubin GJ. What influences whether parents recognise COVID-19 symptoms, request a test and self-isolate: a qualitative study. PLoS ONE. 2022;17:e0263537.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0263537</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35196349</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">8865653</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruiz JB, Bell RA. Parental COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy in the United States. Public Health Rep. 2022;137:1162–9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/00333549221114346</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35915993</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">9574308</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>