<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39555713</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2198-3844</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>18</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Advanced science (Weinheim, Baden-Wurttemberg, Germany)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Adv Sci (Weinh)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>High Quality-Factor All-Dielectric Metacavity for Label-Free Biosensing.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e2410125</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e2410125</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/advs.202410125</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>High sensitivity and high quality-factor are crucial for achieving outstanding sensing performance in photonic biosensors. However, strong optical field confinement and high light-biomolecule interactions on photonic surfaces are usually contradictory and challenging to satisfy simultaneously. Here, a distinctive configuration for addressing this issue is reported: embedding a nanophotonic metasurface inside a micro vertical cavity as a meta-channel (metacavity) biosensor. The analyte solution serves as the cavity medium, thereby maximizing the light-analyte interaction. Simulation validation is conducted to optimize the metacavity with high structural robustness and remarkable optical and sensing properties. Large-scale low-cost metacavity biosensors are realized by combining anodic aluminum oxide template technique and wafer bonding. Experimentally, the metacavity biosensor demonstrates a notable quality-factor (maximum 4140) and high bulk refractometric sensitivity (450 nm RIU<sup>-1</sup>), resulting in an unprecedented figure-of-merit (1670 RIU<sup>-1</sup>). Moreover, the metacavity biosensor achieves high surface sensitivity, together with a detection-limit of 119 viral copies mL<sup>-1</sup> for label-free severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) pseudovirus sensing, revealing remarkable performance in both bulk and surface sensing.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024 The Author(s). Advanced Science published by Wiley‐VCH GmbH.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zheng</LastName><ForeName>Yuqiao</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, Zhejiang, 310058, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>CenBRAIN Neurotech Center of Excellence, School of Engineering, Westlake University, Hangzhou, Zhejiang, 310030, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sun</LastName><ForeName>Jiacheng</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of 3D Micro/Nano Fabrication and Characterization of Zhejiang, School of Engineering, Westlake University, Hangzhou, Zhejiang, 310030, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ma</LastName><ForeName>Yaqing</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Advanced Solid-state Semiconductor Lab, School of Engineering, Westlake University, Hangzhou, Zhejiang, 310024, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Hongyong</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>CenBRAIN Neurotech Center of Excellence, School of Engineering, Westlake University, Hangzhou, Zhejiang, 310030, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cui</LastName><ForeName>Zhen</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory for Quantum Materials of Zhejiang Province, Department of Physics, School of Science, Westlake University, Hangzhou, Zhejiang, 310030, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Paschos</LastName><ForeName>Giannis G</ForeName><Initials>GG</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory for Quantum Materials of Zhejiang Province, Department of Physics, School of Science, Westlake University, Hangzhou, Zhejiang, 310030, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Song</LastName><ForeName>Xixi</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>CenBRAIN Neurotech Center of Excellence, School of Engineering, Westlake University, Hangzhou, Zhejiang, 310030, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tao</LastName><ForeName>Ying</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>CenBRAIN Neurotech Center of Excellence, School of Engineering, Westlake University, Hangzhou, Zhejiang, 310030, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Savvidis</LastName><ForeName>Pavlos</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory for Quantum Materials of Zhejiang Province, Department of Physics, School of Science, Westlake University, Hangzhou, Zhejiang, 310030, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kong</LastName><ForeName>Wei</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Advanced Solid-state Semiconductor Lab, School of Engineering, Westlake University, Hangzhou, Zhejiang, 310024, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wen</LastName><ForeName>Liaoyong</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Key Laboratory of 3D Micro/Nano Fabrication and Characterization of Zhejiang, School of Engineering, Westlake University, Hangzhou, Zhejiang, 310030, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bian</LastName><ForeName>Sumin</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>CenBRAIN Neurotech Center of Excellence, School of Engineering, Westlake University, Hangzhou, Zhejiang, 310030, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sawan</LastName><ForeName>Mohamad</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4137-7272</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>CenBRAIN Neurotech Center of Excellence, School of Engineering, Westlake University, Hangzhou, Zhejiang, 310030, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Westlake University, Startup funds</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>82104122</GrantID><Agency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>WU2022C040</GrantID><Agency>Research Center for Industries of the Future of Westlake University</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>52373238,52003225</GrantID><Agency>the Natural Science Foundation of China</Agency><Country /></Grant><Grant><GrantID>10300000H062201</GrantID><Agency>Special Support Plan for Photoelectric Chips Research at Westlake University</Agency><Country /></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Adv Sci (Weinh)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101664569</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2198-3844</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">biosensor</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">high quality‐factor</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">metasurface</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">microcavity</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">virus detection</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>34</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39555713</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/advs.202410125</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>H. Altug, S. H. Oh, S. A. Maier, J. Homola, Nat. Nanotechnol. 2022, 17, 5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Soler, A. Belushkin, A. Cavallini, C. Kebbi‐Beghdadi, G. Greub, H. Altug, Biosens. Bioelectron. 2017, 94, 560.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. V. Sreekanth, Y. Alapan, M. ElKabbash, E. Ilker, M. Hinczewski, U. A. Gurkan, A. De Luca, G. Strangi, Nat. Mater. 2016, 15, 621.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Q. Zheng, X. X. Song, Z. Fredj, S. M. Bian, M. Sawan, Anal. Chim. Acta 2023, 1244, 340860.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R. Singh, Z. Wang, C. Marques, R. Min, B. Y. Zhang, S. Kumar, Biosens. Bioelectron. 2023, 236, 115424.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. X. Cai, C. P. Zhang, C. W. Liang, S. Y. Min, X. Cheng, W. D. Li, Adv. Opt. Mater. 2019, 7, 1900516.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Danilov, G. Tselikov, F. Wu, V. G. Kravets, I. Ozerov, F. Bedu, A. N. Grigorenko, A. V. Kabashin, Biosens. Bioelectron. 2018, 104, 102.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. S. Bin‐Alam, O. Reshef, Y. Mamchur, M. Z. Alam, G. Carlow, J. Upham, B. T. Sullivan, J. M. Ménard, M. J. Huttunen, R. W. Boyd, K. Dolgaleva, Nat. Commun. 2021, 12, 974.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Q. Zhang, P. X. Li, Z. Y. Gu, S. D. Liu, Z. J. Suan, Photon. Res. 2024, 12, 598.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. D. Yang, J. Yao, J. Rho, X. B. Yin, X. Zhang, Nat. Photonics 2012, 6, 450.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. B. Khurgin, Nat. Nanotechnol. 2015, 10, 2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Luo, Y. Zhou, X. Y. Zhao, Z. H. Guo, Y. X. Li, Q. Wang, J. J. Liu, W. Luo, Y. Z. Shi, A. Q. Liu, X. Wu, ACS Nano 2024, 18, 6477.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. C. Wang, J. C. Sun, J. Y. Li, L. Wang, Z. S. Li, X. R. Zheng, L. Y. Wen, Adv. Sci. 2023, 10, 2206236.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Zhou, Z. H. Guo, X. Y. Zhao, F. L. Wang, Z. Y. Yu, Y. Z. Chen, Z. R. Liu, S. Y. Zhang, S. L. Sun, X. Wu, Adv. Opt. Mater. 2022, 10, 2200965.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Shen, K. He, Q. S. Zou, S. Xing, J. Y. Huang, M. C. Zheng, X. Y. She, C. J. Jin, Adv. Funct. Mater. 2022, 32, 2108741.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. A. Yanik, A. E. Cetin, M. Huang, A. Artar, S. H. Mousavi, A. Khanikaev, J. H. Connor, G. Shvets, H. Altug, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 2011, 108, 11784.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Watanabe, M. Iwanaga, Nanophotonics 2023, 12, 99.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. C. Liu, T. B. Guo, Q. Tan, Z. P. Hu, Y. W. Sun, H. X. Fan, Z. Zhang, Y. Jin, S. L. He, Nano Lett. 2023, 23, 10441.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Zhou, M. Luo, X. Y. Zhao, Y. X. Li, Q. Wang, Z. R. Liu, J. H. Guo, Z. H. Guo, J. J. Liu, X. Wu, Nanophotonics 2023, 12, 1295.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. M. Yang, I. I. Kravchenko, D. P. Briggs, J. Valentine, Nat. Commun. 2014, 5, 5753.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>F. Yesilkoy, E. R. Arvelo, Y. Jahani, M. K. Liu, A. Tittl, V. Cevher, Y. Kivshar, H. Altug, Nat. Photonics 2019, 13, 390.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Wang, J. Kühne, T. Karamanos, C. Rockstuhl, S. A. Maier, A. Tittl, Adv. Funct. Mater. 2021, 31, 2104652.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Jahani, E. R. Arvelo, F. Yesilkoy, K. Koshelev, C. Cianciaruso, M. De Palma, Y. Kivshar, H. Altug, Nat Commun. 2021, 12, 3246.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. Watanabe, H. Y. Wu, J. Xavier, L. T. Joshi, F. Vollmer, Small 2022, 18, 2107597.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Ge, P. Liu, Q. Chen, M. R. Qu, L. J. Xu, H. Liang, X. Zhang, Z. Huang, Y. P. Wen, L. Wang, Biosens. Bioelectron. 2023, 237, 115454.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. P. Niu, J. F. Jiang, K. Liu, X. Zhou, S. Wang, T. H. Xu, T. Wang, Y. L. Li, Q. Yang, T. G. Liu, Biosens. Bioelectron. 2024, 248, 115970.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. C. Yu, S. J. Tang, W. J. Liv, Y. L. Xu, Q. H. Gong, Y. L. Chen, Y. F. Xiao, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 2022, 119, e2108678119.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. J. Tang, P. H. Dannenberg, A. C. Liapis, N. Martino, Y. Zhuo, Y. F. Xiao, S. H. Yun, Light. Sci. Appl. 2021, 10, 43.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>E. Ozgur, K. E. Roberts, E. O. Ozgur, A. N. Gin, J. R. Bankhead, Z. K. Wang, J. Su, Anal. Chem. 2019, 91, 11872.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Su, A. F. G. Goldberg, B. M. Stoltz, Light. Sci. Appl. 2016, 5, e16001.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. C. Yu, Y. Y. Zhi, S. J. Tang, B. B. Li, Q. H. Gong, C. W. Qiu, Y. F. Xiao, Light. Sci. Appl. 2018, 7, 18003.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Z. Shi, Y. F. Wu, L. K. Chin, Z. Y. Li, J. Q. Liu, M. K. Chen, S. B. Wang, Y. Zhang, P. Y. Liu, X. H. Zhou, H. Cai, W. Z. Jin, Y. F. Yu, R. Z. Yu, W. Huang, P. H. Yap, L. M. Xiao, W. Ser, T. T. B. Nguyen, Y. T. Lin, P. C. Wu, J. Y. Liao, F. Wang, C. T. Chan, Y. Kivshar, D. P. Tsai, A. Q. Liu, Laser. Photonics. Rev. 2022, 16, 2100197.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. M. Shaltout, J. Kim, A. Boltasseva, V. M. Shalaev, A. V. Kildishev, Nat. Commun. 2018, 9, 2673.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Z. Y. Yuan, S. H. Huang, Z. Qiao, P. C. Wu, Y. C. Chen, Optica 2023, 10, 269.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Ossiander, M. L. Meretska, S. Rourke, C. Spägele, X. Yin, I.‐C. Benea‐Chelmus, F. Capasso, Nat. Commun. 2023, 14, 1114.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P. Xie, Y. H. Deng, L. X. Zeng, Z. C. Liang, S. Y. Shen, Q. Ding, H. Zhang, Z. K. Zhou, W. Wang, Phys. Rev. 2022, B 106, 165408.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>V. Kravtsov, E. Khestanova, F. A. Benimetskiy, T. Ivanova, A. K. Samusev, I. S. Sinev, D. Pidgayko, A. M. Mozharov, I. S. Mukhin, M. S. Lozhkin, Y. V. Kapitonov, A. S. Brichkin, V. D. Kulakovskii, I. A. Shelykh, A. I. Tartakovskii, P. M. Walker, M. S. Skolnick, D. N. Krizhanovskii, I. V. Iorsh, Light. Sci. Appl. 2020, 9, 56.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>N. J. Engelsen, A. Beccari, T. J. Kippenberg, Nat. Nanotechnol. 2024, 19, 725.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. S. Jung, C. T. Campbell, T. M. Chinowsky, M. N. Mar, S. S. Yee, Langmuir 1998, 14, 5636.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. Y. Sun, J. C. Sun, Z. C. Wang, L. Wang, F. Qiu, L. Y. Wen, Nano Lett. 2022, 22, 9982.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>L. Y. Wen, R. Xu, Y. Mi, Y. Lei, Nat. Nanotechnol. 2017, 12, 244.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D. Conteduca, I. Barth, G. Pitruzzello, C. P. Reardon, E. R. Martins, T. F. Krauss, Nat. Commun. 2021, 12, 3293.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. X. Song, Y. Tao, S. M. Bian, M. Sawan, J. Pharm. Anal. 2024, 14, 100995.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. M. Bian, M. Shang, Y. Tao, P. B. Wang, Y. K. Xu, Y. Wang, Z. D. Shen, M. Sawan, Vaccines 2024, 12, 352.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Hentzien, B. Autran, L. Piroth, Y. Yazdanpanah, A. Calmy, Lancet. Infect. Dis. 2022, 22, 1278.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K. H. Hur, K. Park, Y. Lim, Y. S. Jeong, H. Sung, M. N. Kim, Front. Med. 2020, 7, 521.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>A. Ramgolam, Lancet. Infect. Dis. 2023, 23, 1004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>M. Meng, S. Zhang, X. Dong, W. Q. Sun, Y. F. Deng, W. Z. Li, R. R. Li, D. Annane, Z. X. Wu, D. C. Chen, Immun. Inflamm. Dis. 2022, 10, e597.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>X. X. Song, Z. Fredj, Y. Q. Zheng, H. Y. Zhang, G. G. Rong, S. M. Bian, M. Sawan, J. Pharm. Anal. 2023, 13, 1252.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. E. Park, A. Georgescu, D. Huh, Science 2019, 364, 960.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. N. Bhatia, D. E. Ingber, Nat. Biotechnol. 2014, 32, 760.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Y. Zhao, S. Landau, S. Okhovatian, C. Liu, R. X. Z. Lu, B. F. L. Lai, Q. Wu, J. Kieda, K. Cheung, S. Rajasekar, K. Jozani, B. Zhang, M. Radisic, Nat. Rev. Bioeng. 2024, 2, 588.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H. Zhou, D. X. Li, Z. H. Ren, C. Xu, L. F. Wang, C. K. Lee, Sci. Adv. 2024, 10, eado3179.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. Q. Li, J. Ye, C. Chen, Y. Li, N. Verellen, V. V. Moshchalkov, L. Lagae, P. Van Dorpe, ACS Photonics 2015, 2, 425.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>J. D. Lu, T. Van Stappen, D. Spasic, F. Delport, S. Vermeire, A. Gils, J. Lammertyn, Biosens. Bioelectron. 2016, 79, 173.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>