<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39554782</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2054-2577</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>11</Volume><Issue>6</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Dec</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Neuro-oncology practice</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Neurooncol Pract</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Challenges and opportunities in newly diagnosed glioblastoma in the United Kingdom: A Delphi panel.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>740</StartPage><EndPage>752</EndPage><MedlinePgn>740-752</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1093/nop/npae058</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Glioblastoma is the deadliest primary malignant brain tumor in adults with limited treatment options and an average survival time of 12-18 months in the United Kingdom. In addition, glioblastoma has a highly detrimental impact on physical, cognitive, and emotional well-being, leaving substantial unmet needs for patients and caregivers. This study aimed to identify unmet needs in people with newly diagnosed glioblastoma and opportunities to mitigate them.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Utilizing Delphi methodology, an initial roundtable discussion with patient advocacy experts from 5 brain tumor organizations in the United Kingdom informed the development of 2 rounds of surveys across 9 domains (diagnosis, treatment, integrated care, support beyond treatment, quality of life, access to new treatments, access to trials, measures to ease the burden, and impact of COVID-19). Consensus was predefined as ≥70% agreement.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">A total of 17 Delphi panelists (glioblastoma patients, caregivers, and patient representatives) completed the first round of questionnaires and 26 completed the second. Consensus was reached on 16/21 questions (76.2%) and 7/9 domains. Panelists reached a consensus on key questions including the high frequency of diagnosis via emergency departments, the lack of effective personalized treatments and holistic care, the high caregiver burden, the lack of awareness and availability of access to clinical trials, and the negative impact of COVID-19 on glioblastoma care.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">Significant unmet needs exist for newly diagnosed glioblastoma patients in the United Kingdom, highlighting the demand for increased research funding, comprehensive patient care, caregiver support, enhanced awareness and access to clinical trials, and new treatments.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s) 2024. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Neuro-Oncology and the European Association of Neuro-Oncology.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bulbeck</LastName><ForeName>Helen</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6775-5251</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Brainstrust-The Brain Cancer People, Cowes, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Noble</LastName><ForeName>Karen</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0006-9059-0922</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Brain Tumour Research, Milton Keynes, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Oliver</LastName><ForeName>Kathy</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-8317-2881</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The International Brain Tumour Alliance (IBTA), Tadworth, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Skinner</LastName><ForeName>Tina Mitchell</ForeName><Initials>TM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Brain Tumour Support, Thornbury, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Neurooncol Pract</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101640528</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2054-2577</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Delphi panel</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">UK</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">access to clinical trials</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">newly diagnosed glioblastoma</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">unmet need</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>H.B.: Participated as a patient advocate on a panel in the European Society for Medical Oncology (ESMO) Congress 2023. No organizational conflicts of interest to declare. K.N.: No personal conflicts of interest to declare. Regarding her organization, in October 2023, it was confirmed that Novocure will be the headline sponsor of the Brain Tumour Research Wear a Hat Day fundraising event in 2024 including financial support. At the time of the project initiation and patient surveys, Brain Tumour Research had nothing to declare. K.O.: No personal conflicts of interest to declare. For transparency, her organization’s funding sources for 2022 and 2023 are as follows: The IBTA received grant and sponsorship funding from the following companies and organizations: Bayer, Bristol Myers Squibb, Elekta, GW Pharma/Jazz Pharmaceuticals, Medac, Novartis, Novocure, Northwest Biotherapeutics, Pfizer, Photonamic, the Sontag Foundation, STOPhersentumoren, Daiichi Sankyo, GT Medical Technologies, Menarini Stemline, Regeneron, Roche, Seagen, and Servier. Additionally, the IBTA received honoraria for speaking and other roles (ie, advisory board membership) and/or reimbursement of expenses (ie, travel and accommodation) from the European Cancer Organisation, European Society for Medical Oncology Congress 2023, Sanofi, Novocure, Seagen, Bristol Myers Squibb, Novartis, and Eisai. T.M.S.: No conflicts of interest to declare at both personal and organizational levels.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>17</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>59</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>28</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39554782</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11567735</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/nop/npae058</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">npae058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>
Brain Tumour Research. What Is Glioblastoma Multiforme? https://www.braintumourresearch.org/info-support/types-of-brain-tumour/glioblastoma-multiforme. Accessed April 12, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wen PY, Weller M, Lee EQ, et al.. Glioblastoma in adults: a Society for Neuro-Oncology (SNO) and European Society of Neuro-Oncology (EANO) consensus review on current management and future directions. Neuro-Oncology. 2020;22(8):1073–1113.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7594557</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32328653</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Louis DN, Perry A, Wesseling P, et al.. The 2021 WHO classification of tumors of the central nervous system: a summary. Neuro Oncol. 2021;23(8):1231–1251.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8328013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34185076</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boele FW, Given CW, Given BA, et al.. Family caregivers’ level of mastery predicts survival of patients with glioblastoma: A preliminary report. Cancer. 2017;123(5):832–840.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5319890</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27787881</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma R, Taphoorn MJB, Plaha P.. Advances in the management of glioblastoma. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry. 2021;92(10):1103–1111.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34162730</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roa W, Brasher PM, Bauman G, et al.. Abbreviated course of radiation therapy in older patients with glioblastoma multiforme: a prospective randomized clinical trial. J Clin Oncol. 2004;22(9):1583–1588.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15051755</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Institute for Health and Care Excellence. Brain Tumours (Primary) and Brain Metastases in Over 16s (NG99). Manchester, UK: National Institute for Health and Care Excellence; 2018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brodbelt A, Greenberg D, Winters T, et al.; (UK) National Cancer Information Network Brain Tumour Group. Glioblastoma in England: 2007–2011. Eur J Cancer. 2015;51(4):533–542.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25661102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sutton K, Moore J, Armes J, Briggs E.. Perceptions and experiences of the subjective well-being of people with glioblastoma: a longitudinal phenomenological study. Neurooncol Pract. 2022;10(1):79–88.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9837778</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36654773</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nasa P, Jain R, Juneja D.. Delphi methodology in healthcare research: how to decide its appropriateness. World J Methodol. 2021;11(4):116–129.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8299905</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34322364</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iqbal S, Pipon-Young L.. Methods—the Delphi method—a guide from Susanne Iqbal and Laura Pipon-Young. Psychologist. 2009;22(7):598.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murray MJ, Bartels U, Nishikawa R, et al.. Consensus on the management of intracranial germ-cell tumours. Lancet Oncol. 2015;16(9):e470–e477.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26370356</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walker DA, Liu J, Kieran M, et al.; CPN Paris 2011 Conference Consensus Group. A multi-disciplinary consensus statement concerning surgical approaches to low-grade, high-grade astrocytomas and diffuse intrinsic pontine gliomas in childhood (CPN Paris 2011) using the Delphi method. Neuro Oncol. 2013;15(4):462–468.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3607269</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23502427</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Geisler J, Karihtala P, Tuxen M, et al.; Delphi Panellist Group. Current treatment landscape of HR+/HER2− advanced breast cancer in the Nordics: a modified Delphi study. Acta Oncol. 2023;62(12):1680–1688.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37713138</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
National Health Service. National Cancer Patient Experience Survey; 2022. https://www.ncpes.co.uk/latest-national-results/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
European Reference Network on Rare Adult Solid Cancers. Rare Cancer of the Brain and Spinal Cord. https://euracan.eu/rare-adult-solid-cancers/brain-and-spinal-cord/. Accessed April 12, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walter FM, Penfold C, Joannides A, et al.. Missed opportunities for diagnosing brain tumours in primary care: a qualitative study of patient experiences. Br J Gen Pract. 2019;69(681):e224–e235.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6428480</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30858332</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McKinnon C, Nandhabalan M, Murray SA, Plaha P.. Glioblastoma: clinical presentation, diagnosis, and management. BMJ. 2021;374(8300):n1560.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34261630</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Theeler BJ, Gilbert MR.. Advances in the treatment of newly diagnosed glioblastoma. BMC Med. 2015;13(1):293.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4673777</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26646075</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halkett GK, Lobb EA, Shaw T, et al.. Distress and psychological morbidity do not reduce over time in carers of patients with high-grade glioma. Support Care Cancer. 2017;25(3):887–893.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27841006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Long A, Halkett GKB, Lobb EA, et al.. Carers of patients with high-grade glioma report high levels of distress, unmet needs, and psychological morbidity during patient chemoradiotherapy. Neurooncol Pract.. 2016;3(2):105–112.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6668264</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31386072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schaefer I, Heneka N, Luckett T, et al.. Quality of online self-management resources for adults living with primary brain cancer, and their carers: a systematic environmental scan. BMC Palliat Care. 2021;20(1):22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7827995</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33485331</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
National Institute for Health and Care Excellence. Shared Decision Making. National Institute for Health and Care; Excellence. https://www.nice.org.uk/about/what-we-do/our-programmes/nice-guidance/nice-guidelines/shared-decision-making. Accessed April 12, 2024.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Retzer A, Sivell S, Scott H, et al.. Development of a core outcome set and identification of patient-reportable outcomes for primary brain tumour trials: protocol for the COBra study. BMJ Open. 2022;12(9):e057712.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9528585</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36180121</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>All-Party Parliamentary Group. Pathway to a Cure—Breaking Down the Barriers; 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee EQ, Chukwueke UN, Hervey-Jumper SL, et al.. Barriers to accrual and enrollment in brain tumor trials. Neuro Oncol. 2019;21(9):1100–1117.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7594546</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31175826</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bagley SJ, Kothari S, Rahman R, et al.. Glioblastoma clinical trials: current landscape and opportunities for improvement. Clin Cancer Res. 2021;28(4):594–602.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9044253</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34561269</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong AR, Sun V, George K, et al.. Barriers to participation in therapeutic clinical trials as perceived by community oncologists. JCO Oncol Pract. 2020;16(9):e849–e858.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7489483</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32240068</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Voisin MR, Oliver K, Farrimond S, et al.. Brain tumors and COVID-19: the patient and caregiver experience. Neurooncol Adv. 2020;2(1):vdaa104.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7499687</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32989433</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Price SJ, Joannides A, Plaha P, et al.; COVID-CNSMDT study group. Impact of COVID-19 pandemic on surgical neuro-oncology multi-disciplinary team decision making: a national survey (COVID-CNSMDT Study). BMJ Open. 2020;10(8):e040898.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7430412</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32801210</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>