<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39556155</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1573-6571</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>18</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of religion and health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Relig Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Pilgrimage to Luján in Argentina with Special Consideration to Argentines of Polish Descent During and After the COVID-19 Pandemic: The Spiritual Aspect.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s10943-024-02186-2</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Luján is considered the religious heart of Argentina, attracting pilgrims from all over the world. Among the pilgrimages across the world, there is also a Polish pilgrimage organized every year by Polish communities in Buenos Aires for the Polish Argentines. The purpose of this article is to examine the changes in the number of pilgrims, administered sacraments and celebrated masses in Luján from 2019 to 2023. The research shows that after a sharp decline in the number of pilgrims from 5 million in 2019 to 1 million in 2020 due to the COVID-19 pandemic, there has been a resurgence in pilgrimages, with over 6 million pilgrims worldwide in 2023. The article analyses empirical data collected through in-depth interviews with 25 Argentines of Polish descent (n = 25). Its purpose is to examine how the motives and intentions of these individuals for making a pilgrimage to Luján have changed before, during, and after the COVID-19 pandemic, as well as significance of the pilgrimage for each of them. The research clearly demonstrates that the pandemic has strengthened the faith of Polish pilgrims living in Argentina, who now view pilgrimages to Luján and entrusting their intentions to the Virgin Mary as a personal obligation.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© 2024. The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer Science+Business Media, LLC, part of Springer Nature.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ziółkowska-Weiss</LastName><ForeName>Kamila</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6575-5314</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Law and Economics, University of the National Education Commission, Ul. Podchorążych 2 (Room 537), 30-084, Kraków, Poland. kamila.ziolkowska-weiss@uken.krakow.pl.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Relig Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>2985199R</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-4197</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Argentina</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Buenos Aires</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Catholic Church</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Luján</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pilgrim</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pilgrimage</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Polonia</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement><b>Declarations</b> <b>Conflict of interest</b> The author declares no conflict of interest. <b>Consent for Publication</b> The author affirm that human research participants provided informed consent for publication. <b>Ethics Confirmation</b> I would like to confirm that no tests on human beings, animals, or tissues have been conducted for the purposes of the article. The article on " Pilgrimage to Luján in Argentina with special consideration to Argentines of Polish descent during and after the COVID-19 pandemic—the spiritual aspect” for the Journal of Religion and Health journal presents the research results obtained on the basis of the answers of respondents collected by means of the interview. Each person who was doing an interview at the beginning, was given the following information: "I hereby would like to kindly ask you to provide your responses based on your feelings, knowledge, and experience. The results will be used exclusively for scientific purposes in the form of a summary”. The study was performed in line with the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki, and according to local legislation and national guidelines on research involving human subjects, ethical approval was not required.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>31</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>31</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39556155</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10943-024-02186-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s10943-024-02186-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Bandeira, O., &amp; Carranza, B. (2020). Reactions to the pandemic in Latin America and Brazil: Are religions essential services? International Journal of Latin American Religions, 4, 170–193. https://doi.org/10.1007/s41603-020-00116-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s41603-020-00116-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7575139</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Béliveau, V. G. (2021). Catholicism in day-to-day life in argentina during a pandemic year: Blurring the institutional boundaries. International Journal of Latin American Religions, 5, 246–264. https://doi.org/10.1007/s41603-021-00136-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s41603-021-00136-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bertrand, J. R. (1999). Geografía y peregrinaciones. Coloquio Internacional Geografía de las Religiones. Santa Fe.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bożewicz., M. (2022). Zmiana religijności Polaków po pandemii. Warsaw: Public Opinion Research Center.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cadell, S., Gauthier, G., Labra, O., &amp; Ouellet-Plamondon, C. (2021). Predictive factors of spiritual quality of life during the COVID-19 pandemic: A multivariate analysis. Journal of Religion and Health, 60, 1475–1493. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10943-021-01233-6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10943-021-01233-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33759072</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7987239</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carballo, C. (2011). Territorios de religiosidad peregrina en la Argentina: mapas en movimiento. Actas de las XIIIº Jornadas de Interescuelas de Historia, San Fernando dell Valle de Catamarca: UNCa.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cloete, A. L. (2016). Mediated religion: Implications for religious authority. Verbum Et Ecclesia, 37(1), 1–6. https://doi.org/10.4102/ve.v37i1.1544</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4102/ve.v37i1.1544</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen, E. (1992). Pilgrimage and tourism: Convergence and divergence. In: A. Morinis (Ed.), Sacred Journeys. The Anthropology of Pilgrimage, 47–61. https://doi.org/10.1016/0160-7383(92)90105-X</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>da Silveira, E. S. (2020). Catholi covid-19 or Quo Vadis Catholica Ecclesia: The pandemic seen in the catholic institutional. International Journal of Latin American Religions, 4, 259–287. https://doi.org/10.1007/s41603-020-00114-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s41603-020-00114-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7500718</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dutra, C. C. D., &amp; Rocha, H. S. (2021). Religious support as a contribution to face the effects of social isolation in mental health during the pandemic of COVID-19. Journal of Religion and Health, 60, 99–111. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10943-020-01140-2</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10943-020-01140-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33405093</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7786321</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duran, J. G. (2012). La Basilica Nacional de Luján. el proyecto de su construccion (1887–1890). Teología, XLIX, 109, 65–96. https://repositorio.uca.edu.ar/handle/123456789/7583</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernández, N. S. (2020). De la parroquia a la Basílica: Sentidos, experiencias, militantes y devotos/as en torno a la Peregrinación Juvenil a Luján. Unidad Sociológica, 17(1), 23–32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flores, F. C. (2014). Espacialidades peregrinas y discursos territoriales en un ritual de entronización en la Basílica de Luján. XI Congreso Argentino de Antropología Social, Rosario. https://www.aacademica.org/000-081/286</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flores, F. C. (2015). Espacialidades peregrinas: El caso de la peragrinacion juvenil a pie a Lujan. Espaco e Cultura, 37, 116–136.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galli, C. M., Dotro, G., &amp; Mitchell, M. (2004). Seguimos caminando: aproximación socio-histórica teológica y pastoral de la peregrinación juvenil a Luján. Buenos Aires, Agape.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galli, C. M. (2011). Dios vive en la Ciudad: hacia una nueva pastoral urbana a la luz de Aparecida y del proyecto misionero de Francisco. Buenos Aires. https://repositorio.uca.edu.ar/bitstream/123456789/11207/2/dios.vive-ciudad-carlos-galli.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamilton, J. B., Best, N. C., Barney, T. A., Worthy, V. C., &amp; Phillips, N. R. (2021). Using spirituality to cope with COVID-19: The experiences of African American breast cancer survivors. Journal of Cancer Education, 37, 1422–1428. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13187-021-01974-8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s13187-021-01974-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33595772</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7886845</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hill, T. D., Gonzalez, K., &amp; Burdette, A. M. (2020). The blood of christ compels them: State religiosity and state population mobility during the coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic. Journal of Religion and Health, 59, 2229–2242. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10943-020-01058-9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10943-020-01058-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32596753</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7321650</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Institute of the Catholic Church Statistics, (2021). 4, 24, (iskk.pl)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackowski, A. (2003). Święta przestrzeń świata: podstawy geografii religii. Wydawnictwo Uniwersytetu Jagiellońskiego</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackowski, A. (1998). Pielgrzymki = turystyka pielgrzymkowa= turystyka religijna? Rozważania terminologiczne. Turyzm, 8 (1). http://hdl.handle.net/11089/27919</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaczmarek, Z. (1985). Duszpasterstwo polonijne, EK, t. I, Lublin.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kotler, P., Bowen, J., James, C. M., Moreno, R. R., &amp; Paz, M. D. R. (2003). Marketing para turismo. New York: McGraw-Hill.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levin, J. (2020). The faith community and the SARS-CoV-2 outbreak: Part of the problem or part of the solution? Journal of Religion and Health, 59, 2215–2228. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10943-020-01048-x</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10943-020-01048-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32488827</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7265665</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Magnus, A. (2013). A Luján (una novela peregrina). Buenos Aires: Interzona</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Main Statistical Office. (2019). 29</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitchell, M. (2004). Los orígenes de la Peregrinación Juvenil a Luján, Seguimos Caminando, Buenos Aires.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mróz, F. (2021). The impact of COVID-19 on pilgrimages and religious tourism in Europe during the first six months of the pandemic. Journal of Religion and Health, 60, 625–645. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10943-021-01201-0</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10943-021-01201-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33611686</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7896876</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Notermans, C. (ed.). (2016). Gender, nation and religion in european pilgrimage, Routledge</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oliver, M. P. (2021). Una caminata provinciana: digresión y peregrinación en A Luján (una novela peregrina) de Ariel Magnus, América sin Nombre, 25, 203–209. https://doi.org/10.14198/AMESN.2021.25.17</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ostrowski, M. (2002). Peregrinación o turismo religioso. III Congreso Europeo de Santuarios y Peregrinajes. Catalunya.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>https://mercaba.org/FICHAS/Evangelizacion/peregrinacion_o_turismo_religios</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papadopoulos, I., Lazzarino, R., Wright, S., Logan, P. E., &amp; Koulouglioti, C. (2021). Spiritual support during COVID-19 in England: A scoping study of online sources. Journal of Religion and Health, 19, 1–22. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10943-021-01254-1</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10943-021-01254-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Porcal, G. (2006). Turismo cultural, turismo religioso y peregrinaciones en Navarra. Las Javieradas como caso de estudio. Cuadernos De Turismo, 18, 103–134.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rebic, A. (1999). Documento de la Santa Sede sobre el Peregrinaje del 2000.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>http://www.medjugorje.hr/es/fenomeno-de-medjugorje/encuentros-/conferencias/neum1999#adalbert-rebic</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robles S. J. (2001). Turismo religioso. Alternativa de apoyo a la preservación del patrimonio y desarrollo. Biblio 3W. https://www.ub.edu/geocrit/b3w-316.htm</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roszak, P. (2019). Sacred and space in post-secular pilgrimage: The Camino de Santiago and relational model of the sacred. International Journal of Religious Tourism and Pilgrimage, 7(5), 33–40. https://doi.org/10.21427/v5r3-j416</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21427/v5r3-j416</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roszak, P. (2022). Contemporary trends in the theological understanding of Christian pilgrimage. International Journal of Religious Tourism and Pilgrimage, 10(3), 116–127. https://doi.org/10.21427/fa9w-9e96</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.21427/fa9w-9e96</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roszak, P. (2023). From tourist to pilgrim: Theological and pastoral challenges in the context of the Camino de Santiago. Pastoral Psychology, 72, 647–657. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11089-023-01099-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11089-023-01099-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Różycki, P. (2009). Perspektywy rozwoju turystyki pielgrzymkowej, religijnej i kulturowej na terenie Polski i w Europie. Turystyka Kulturowa, 12, 47–56. https://doi.org/10.62875/tk.v12i0.423</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.62875/tk.v12i0.423</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarasola, V. C. M. (2003). Shrine of our lady of Lujan (Argentyna). Vincentiana, 47, 5–6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Secall, R. E. (2009). Turismo y religión. Aproximación a la historia del turismo religioso. https://www.academia.edu/27653416/Turismo_y_religión_Aproximación_a_la_historia_del_turismo_religioso</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sereczynska, B., Oviedo, L., Roszak, P., Saarelainen, S. M. K., Inkilä, H., Albaladejo, J. T., &amp; Anthony, F. V. (2021). Religious capital as a central factor in coping with the Covid-19: Clues from an international survey. European Journal of Science and Theology, 17(2), 43–56.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shapiro, E., Levine, L., &amp; Kay, A. (2021). A Jerusalem Synagogue coping during the coronavirus pandemic: Challenges and opportunities. Journal of Religion and Health, 60, 81–98. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10943-020-01131-3</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10943-020-01131-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33389438</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">7778493</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sztabiński, P. B. (1997). Ankieterzy i ich respondenci, od kogo zależą wyniki badań ankietowych. Wydawnictwo IFiS PAN, Warszawa.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor, P. (2004). Goddess on the Rise, Pilgrimage and Popular Religion in Vietnam. Uniwersytet Hawajki Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Timothy, D. J., &amp; Olsen, D. H. (2006). Tourism, religion and spiritual journeys. Routledge, New York, USA.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tong, A., Sainsbury, P., &amp; Craig, J. (2007). Consolidated criteria for reporting qualitative research (COREQ): A 32-item checklist for interviewees and focus groups. International Journal for Quality in Health Care, 19(6), 349–357. https://doi.org/10.1093/intqhc/mzm042</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/intqhc/mzm042</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17872937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Twaróg, J. (2017). Schematyzm duchowieństwa polskiego w Argentynie. Księża diecezjalni, ojcowie i bracia zakonni, siostry zakonne, Buenos Aires.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tykarski, S. (2022). Czas pandemii – spojrzenie na funkcjonowanie polskich rodzin: Raport z badań. Teologia i Człowiek, 60(4), 159–174. https://doi.org/10.12775/ticz.2022.030</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.12775/ticz.2022.030</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNWTO, 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Urry J. (1996). Olhar do turista – lazer e viagens nas sociedades contemporâneas. São Paulo.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wróbel, A. H. (2002). Historia duszpasterstwa polskiego w Argentynie w latach 1897–1997, Buenos Aires: CESLA.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wróbel, A. H. (2020). Duszpasterstwo wśród emigracji polskiej w Argentynie w latach 1945–1997 i jego rola w środowiskach polonijnych, Archiwum OO. Bernardynów w Martin Coronado.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ziółkowska-Weiss, K. (2023). The Polish Catholic Church in Martin Coronado, Buenos Aires, and its role in the life of the Argentinian Polish Community during the COVID-19 pandemic. Journal of Religion and Health, 62, 585–607. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10943-022-01701-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10943-022-01701-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36482139</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>