<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39552637</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1758-8340</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>16</Volume><PubDate><Year>2024</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Therapeutic advances in medical oncology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Ther Adv Med Oncol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Case report: successful treatment of primary intradural extramedullary extraskeletal Ewing sarcoma in adult patient with intralesional surgery, chemotherapy, and proton beam therapy of the cerebrospinal axis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>17588359241297868</StartPage><MedlinePgn>17588359241297868</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">17588359241297868</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1177/17588359241297868</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Ewing sarcoma is a rare malignant neoplasm that primarily affects bone in children. Extraskeletal location is less common, while intradural extramedullary Ewing sarcoma (IEES) in adults is a casuistic phenomenon. Due to its rarity, a standardized treatment strategy for IEES has not been established. The clinical use of proton beam therapy (PBT) for craniospinal irradiation (CSI) in the treatment of IEES has not been reported in the literature. A 41-year-old previously healthy man presented with disabling gluteal and lower extremity pain, decreased sensation, and progressive paraparesis without sphincter dysfunction. Imaging showed intradural extramedullary spinal lesions. The patient underwent urgent surgery. Histology and immunohistochemistry suggested a poorly differentiated neuroendocrine tumor. Negative chromogranin staining and a high Ki67 index prompted further investigation. Next-generation sequencing later confirmed an <i>EWSR1/FLI1</i> translocation, leading to the diagnosis of extraskeletal Ewing sarcoma. The patient received standardized chemotherapy with marked clinical improvement. PBT CSI was initiated but was interrupted due to COVID-19 and other complications. At 20 months follow-up, no recurrence was observed, and the patient reported an active life. Despite intra-spinal spread and multiple complications, intensive chemotherapy combined with PBT CSI led to a favorable outcome. CSI rather than focal radiotherapy should be considered for patients with IEES limited to the cerebrospinal axis. PBT may be used as an alternative to photon radiotherapy to better spare organs at risk.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>© The Author(s), 2024.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ziomek</LastName><ForeName>Mateusz</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Soft Tissue/Bone Sarcoma and Melanoma, Maria Skłodowska-Curie National Research Institute of Oncology, Warsaw, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Placzke</LastName><ForeName>Joanna</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Soft Tissue/Bone Sarcoma and Melanoma, Maria Skłodowska-Curie National Research Institute of Oncology, Warsaw, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Urbanek</LastName><ForeName>Konrad</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiotherapy, Maria Skłodowska-Curie National Research Institute of Oncology, Kraków Branch, Kraków, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Skóra</LastName><ForeName>Tomasz</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiotherapy, Maria Skłodowska-Curie National Research Institute of Oncology, Kraków Branch, Kraków, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rutkowski</LastName><ForeName>Piotr</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Soft Tissue/Bone Sarcoma and Melanoma, Maria Skłodowska-Curie National Research Institute of Oncology, Warsaw, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Spałek</LastName><ForeName>Mateusz Jacek</ForeName><Initials>MJ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3960-7673</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Soft Tissue/Bone Sarcoma and Melanoma, Maria Skłodowska-Curie National Research Institute of Oncology, Roentgena 5, Warsaw 02-781, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Radiotherapy I, Maria Skłodowska-Curie National Research Institute of Oncology, Warsaw, Poland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D002363">Case Reports</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>16</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Ther Adv Med Oncol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101510808</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1758-8340</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Ewing sarcoma</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">case report</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">extramedullary</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">extraskeletal</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">proton beam therapy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">radiotherapy</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>7</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>54</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39552637</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11569501</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/17588359241297868</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1177_17588359241297868</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Balamuth NJ, Womer RB. Ewing’s sarcoma. Lancet Oncol 2010; 11: 184–192.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20152770</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Applebaum MA, Goldsby R, Neuhaus J, et al.. Clinical features and outcomes in patients with Ewing sarcoma and regional lymph node involvement. Pediatr Blood Cancer 2012; 59: 617–620.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3310932</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22184129</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van den Berg H, Heinen RC, van der Pal HJ, et al.. Extra-osseous Ewing sarcoma. Pediatr Hematol Oncol 2009; 26: 175–185.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19437320</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cash T, McIlvaine E, Krailo MD, et al.. Comparison of clinical features and outcomes in patients with extraskeletal versus skeletal localized ewing sarcoma: a report from the Children’s Oncology Group. Pediatr Blood Cancer 2016; 63: 1771–1779.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4995129</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27297500</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Applebaum MA, Worch J, Matthay KK, et al.. Clinical features and outcomes in patients with extraskeletal Ewing sarcoma. Cancer 2011; 117: 3027–3032.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3135782</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21692057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lynch AD, Gani F, Meyer CF, et al.. Extraskeletal versus skeletal Ewing Sarcoma in the adult population: controversies in care. Surg Oncol 2018; 27: 373–379.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30217290</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abboud A, Masrouha K, Saliba M, et al.. Extraskeletal Ewing sarcoma: diagnosis, management and prognosis. Oncol Lett 2021; 21: 354.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7967932</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33747211</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bernstein M, Kovar H, Paulussen M, et al.. Ewing’s sarcoma family of tumors: current management. Oncologist 2006; 11: 503–519.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16720851</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shihadeh OM, Khan MM, Salih H, et al.. Primary Ewing sarcoma of the cervical spine: a case report and literature review. Cureus 2023; 15: e42687.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10464919</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37649939</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Weiss SW, Goldblum JR, Folpe AL.
Enzinger and Weiss’s soft tissue tumors. Elsevier Health Sciences, 2007. https://books.google.be/books?hl=pl&amp;lr=&amp;id=8zIuQzik8WAC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA5&amp;dq=Enzinger+and+Weiss%E2%80%99s+soft+tissue+tumors.+Elsevier+Health+Sciences&amp;ots=ekvXQbKhUB&amp;sig=bEO5aIQpw2XS9e1vGEGD3goxdeA#v=onepage&amp;q=Enzinger%20and%20Weiss%E2%80%99s%20soft%20tissue%20tumors.%20Elsevier%20Health%20Sciences&amp;f=false</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Javery O, Krajewski K, O’Regan K, et al.. A to Z of extraskeletal Ewing sarcoma family of tumors in adults: imaging features of primary disease, metastatic patterns, and treatment responses. AJR Am J Roentgenol 2011; 197: W1015–W1022.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22109315</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubin BP, Antonescu CR, Gannon FH, et al.. Protocol for the examination of specimens from patients with tumors of bone. Arch Pathol Lab Med 2010; 134: e1–e7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20367293</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Casali PG, Bielack S, Abecassis N, et al.. Bone sarcomas: ESMO-PaedCan-EURACAN Clinical Practice Guidelines for diagnosis, treatment and follow-up. Ann Oncol 2018; 29: iv79–iv95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30285218</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dunst J, Schuck A. Role of radiotherapy in Ewing tumors. Pediatr Blood Cancer 2004; 42: 465–470.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15049022</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaspar N, Hawkins DS, Dirksen U, et al.. Ewing sarcoma: current management and future approaches through collaboration. J Clin Oncol 2015; 33: 3036–3046.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26304893</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Izubuchi Y, Nakajima H, Honjoh K, et al.. Primary intradural extramedullary Ewing sarcoma: a case report and literature review. Oncol Lett 2020; 20: 2347–2355.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7401003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32782552</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yan Y, Xu T, Chen J, et al.. Intraspinal Ewing’s sarcoma/primitive neuroectodermal tumors. J Clin Neurosci 2011; 18: 601–606.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21414790</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stabouli S, Sdougka M, Tsitspoulos P, et al.. Primary atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor of the spine in an infant. Hippokratia 2010; 14: 286–288.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3031327</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21311641</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hadar AK, Mns B, Ramdhan A, et al.. Large primary Intradural extramedullary spinal tumors: a case report. Int J Surg Case Rep 2023; 111: 108825.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10514415</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37716052</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biswas B, Shukla NK, Deo SVS, et al.. Evaluation of outcome and prognostic factors in extraosseous Ewing sarcoma. Pediatr Blood Cancer 2014; 61: 1925–1931.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25132242</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shannon Orr W, Denbo JW, Billups CA, et al.. Analysis of prognostic factors in extraosseous Ewing sarcoma family of tumors: review of St. Jude Children’s Research Hospital experience. Ann Surg Oncol 2012; 19: 3816–3822.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22739653</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brinkhuis M, Wijnaendts LCD, van der Linden JC, et al.. Peripheral primitive neuroectodermal tumour and extra-osseous Ewing’s sarcoma; a histological, immunohistochemical and DNA flow cytometric study. Vichows Arch 1995; 425: 611–616.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7697218</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee JA, Kim DH, Lim JS, et al.. Soft-tissue Ewing sarcoma in a low-incidence population: comparison to skeletal Ewing sarcoma for clinical characteristics and treatment outcome. Jpn J Clin Oncol 2010; 40: 1060–1067.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20513751</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kunwald M, Straszek CL, Bjarkam CR, et al.. Intradural extramedullary Ewing sarcoma in an adolescent female. Adolesc Health Med Ther 2022; 13: 39–43.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8859542</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35210896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu VM, Goyal A, Alvi MA, et al.. Primary intradural Ewing’s sarcoma of the spine: a systematic review of the literature. Clin Neurol Neurosurg 2019; 177: 12–19.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30579048</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Riley DS, Barber MS, Kienle GS, et al.. CARE guidelines for case reports: explanation and elaboration document. J Clin Epidemiol 2017; 89: 218–235.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28529185</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gagnier JJ, Kienle G, Altman DG, et al.. The CARE guidelines: consensus-based clinical case reporting guideline development. J Med Case Rep 2013; 7: 223.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3844611</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24228906</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Slotkin EK, Tap WD. Towards a new era in the treatment of Ewing sarcoma. Lancet 2022; 400: 1488–1489.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36522196</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arena JD, Sinha S, Wathen C, et al.. Primary intradural extraosseous Ewing’s sarcoma of the L3 nerve root: illustrative case. J Neurosurg Case Lessons 2024; 7: CASE23459.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10791552</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38224583</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Romero D. Craniospinal irradiation improves leptomeningeal metastasis control. Nat Rev Clin Oncol 2022; 19: 567.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35882997</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gurjar OP, Arya R, Goyal H, et al.. Craniospinal irradiation in medulloblastoma using high energy medical linear accelerator: an innovative approach to planning technique. J Biomed Phys Eng 2019; 9: 151–160.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6538910</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31214520</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsang DS, Murphy ES, Ezell SE, et al.. Craniospinal irradiation for treatment of metastatic pediatric low-grade glioma. J Neurooncol 2017; 134: 317–324.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8719438</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28623604</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu KX, Easwaran TP, Phuong C, et al.. Multi-institutional investigation of dose-escalated photon radiotherapy for intracranial ependymoma. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 2022; 114: e480–e481.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chihak MA, Ahmed SK, Lachance DH, et al.. Patterns of failure and optimal radiotherapy target volumes in primary intradural extramedullary Ewing sarcoma. Acta Oncol 2016; 55: 1057–1061.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5742858</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27050758</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmid MP, Harrabi S, Herfarth K, et al.. Particle therapy in adult patients with pelvic Ewing sarcoma-tumor and treatment characteristics and early clinical outcomes. Cancers (Basel) 2022; 14: 6045.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9775362</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36551530</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamaoka M, Akiyama M, Yokokawa Y, et al.. Multidisciplinary therapy including proton beam radiotherapy for a Ewing sarcoma family tumor of maxillary sinus in a 4-year-old girl. Head Neck 2013; 35: E386–E390.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23606421</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uezono H, Indelicato DJ, Rotondo RL, et al.. Treatment outcomes after proton therapy for Ewing sarcoma of the pelvis. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 2020; 107: 974–981.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32437922</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frisch S, Timmermann B. The evolving role of proton beam therapy for sarcomas. Clin Oncol (R Coll Radiol) 2017; 29: 500–506.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28506520</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kharod SM, Indelicato DJ, Rotondo RL, et al.. Outcomes following proton therapy for Ewing sarcoma of the cranium and skull base. Pediatr Blood Cancer 2020; 67:e28080.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31736243</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lundkvist J, Ekman M, Ericsson SR, et al.. Proton therapy of cancer: potential clinical advantages and cost-effectiveness. Acta Oncol 2005; 44: 850–861.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16332592</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yuh GE, Loredo LN, Yonemoto LT, et al.. Reducing toxicity from craniospinal irradiation: using proton beams to treat medulloblastoma in young children. Cancer J 2004; 10: 386.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15701271</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang R, Howell RM, Giebeler A, et al.. Comparison of risk of radiogenic second cancer following photon and proton craniospinal irradiation for a pediatric medulloblastoma patient. Phys Med Biol 2013; 58: 807.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3615542</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23322160</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stokkevåg CH, Engeseth G-M, Ytre-Hauge KS, et al.. Estimated risk of radiation-induced cancer following paediatric cranio-spinal irradiation with electron, photon and proton therapy. Acta Oncol 2014; 53: 1048–1057.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25017376</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Husak AI, Bridge P. Proton therapy in craniospinal irradiation: a systematic review. J Radiother Pract 2016; 15: 196–202.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taddei PJ, Mirkovic D, Fontenot JD, et al.. Stray radiation dose and second cancer risk for a pediatric patient receiving craniospinal irradiation with proton beams. Phys Med Biol 2009; 54: 2259.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4142507</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19305045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown AP, Barney CL, Grosshans DR, et al.. Proton beam craniospinal irradiation reduces acute toxicity for adults with medulloblastoma. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys 2013; 86: 277–284.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3954470</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23433794</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barney CL, Brown AP, Grosshans DR, et al.. Technique, outcomes, and acute toxicities in adults treated with proton beam craniospinal irradiation. Neuro Oncol 2014; 16: 303–309.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3895378</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24311638</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nutman A, Postovsky S, Zaidman I, et al.. Primary intraspinal primitive neuroectodermal tumor treated with autologous stem cell transplantation: case report and review of the literature. Pediatr Hematol Oncol 2007; 24: 53–61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17130114</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>