<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39557342</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1879-0984</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>16</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of virological methods</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Virol Methods</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Optimisation of a multiplexed, high throughput assay to measure neutralising antibodies against SARS-CoV-2 variants.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>115073</StartPage><MedlinePgn>115073</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.jviromet.2024.115073</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0166-0934(24)00198-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>A multiplexed, lentivirus-based pseudovirus neutralisation assay (pVNT) was developed for high-throughput measurement of neutralising antibodies (nAbs) against three distinct SARS-CoV-2 spike variants. Intra-assay variability was minimised by optimising the plate layout and determining an optimal percentage transduction for the pseudovirus inoculum. Comparison of EC<sub>50</sub> titres between single and multiplexed pVNT assays showed no significant differences, indicating reliability of the multiplexed assay. Evaluation of convalescent human sera confirmed assay robustness, with consistent EC<sub>50</sub> titres for variant pseudoviruses relative to the ancestral strain observed across single and multiplexed assays. This multiplexed pVNT provides a reliable tool for assessing nAb responses against SARS-CoV-2 variants and could be used to accelerate preclinical vaccine assessment in preparation for the next coronavirus pandemic.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2024. Published by Elsevier B.V.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ashley</LastName><ForeName>Caroline L</ForeName><Initials>CL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sydney Infectious Diseases Institute (Sydney ID), Faculty of Medicine and Health, The University of Sydney, Camperdown, NSW, 2006, Australia; School of Medical Sciences, Faculty of Medicine and Health, The University of Sydney, Camperdown NSW, 2006, Australia; Charles Perkin Centre, The University of Sydney, Camperdown NSW, 2006, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bloul</LastName><ForeName>Malik</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sydney Infectious Diseases Institute (Sydney ID), Faculty of Medicine and Health, The University of Sydney, Camperdown, NSW, 2006, Australia; School of Medical Sciences, Faculty of Medicine and Health, The University of Sydney, Camperdown NSW, 2006, Australia; Charles Perkin Centre, The University of Sydney, Camperdown NSW, 2006, Australia. Electronic address: malik.i.bloul@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alca</LastName><ForeName>Sibel</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sydney Infectious Diseases Institute (Sydney ID), Faculty of Medicine and Health, The University of Sydney, Camperdown, NSW, 2006, Australia; School of Medical Sciences, Faculty of Medicine and Health, The University of Sydney, Camperdown NSW, 2006, Australia; Charles Perkin Centre, The University of Sydney, Camperdown NSW, 2006, Australia. Electronic address: sibel.alca@sydney.edu.au.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Smith</LastName><ForeName>Lachlan</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sydney Infectious Diseases Institute (Sydney ID), Faculty of Medicine and Health, The University of Sydney, Camperdown, NSW, 2006, Australia; School of Medical Sciences, Faculty of Medicine and Health, The University of Sydney, Camperdown NSW, 2006, Australia; Charles Perkin Centre, The University of Sydney, Camperdown NSW, 2006, Australia. Electronic address: lachlan.smith1@sydney.edu.au.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jin</LastName><ForeName>Wang</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Kirby Institute, University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW, 2052, Australia. Electronic address: jwang@kirby.unsw.edu.au.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Khoury</LastName><ForeName>David</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Kirby Institute, University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW, 2052, Australia. Electronic address: dkhoury@kirby.unsw.edu.au.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Counoupas</LastName><ForeName>Claudio</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sydney Infectious Diseases Institute (Sydney ID), Faculty of Medicine and Health, The University of Sydney, Camperdown, NSW, 2006, Australia; School of Medical Sciences, Faculty of Medicine and Health, The University of Sydney, Camperdown NSW, 2006, Australia; Charles Perkin Centre, The University of Sydney, Camperdown NSW, 2006, Australia; Centre for Infection and Immunity, Centenary Institute, The University of Sydney, Camperdown NSW, 2006, Australia. Electronic address: claudio.counoupas@sydney.edu.au.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Davenport</LastName><ForeName>Miles</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Kirby Institute, University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW, 2052, Australia. Electronic address: M.Davenport@unsw.edu.au.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Triccas</LastName><ForeName>James A</ForeName><Initials>JA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sydney Infectious Diseases Institute (Sydney ID), Faculty of Medicine and Health, The University of Sydney, Camperdown, NSW, 2006, Australia; School of Medical Sciences, Faculty of Medicine and Health, The University of Sydney, Camperdown NSW, 2006, Australia; Charles Perkin Centre, The University of Sydney, Camperdown NSW, 2006, Australia; Centre for Infection and Immunity, Centenary Institute, The University of Sydney, Camperdown NSW, 2006, Australia. Electronic address: jamie.triccas@sydney.edu.au.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Steain</LastName><ForeName>Megan</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sydney Infectious Diseases Institute (Sydney ID), Faculty of Medicine and Health, The University of Sydney, Camperdown, NSW, 2006, Australia; School of Medical Sciences, Faculty of Medicine and Health, The University of Sydney, Camperdown NSW, 2006, Australia; Charles Perkin Centre, The University of Sydney, Camperdown NSW, 2006, Australia. Electronic address: megan.steain@sydney.edu.au.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>16</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>J Virol Methods</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8005839</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0166-0934</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Neutralising antibodies</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">multiplex neutralisation assay</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vaccine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">variants</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of Competing Interest The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>26</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39557342</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jviromet.2024.115073</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0166-0934(24)00198-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle>